<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ability of drugs to cross the BBB depends on their physicochemical characteristics, such as lipophilicity, 3D structure, and so on
 <italic>.</italic> Given that most of the drugs are unable to cross the BBB, a large number of substances may need to be tested in order to identify the ones that could translocate through the barrier. However, many of the current experimental approaches are low throughput and impractical for screening large sets of substances. Moreover, existing computational approaches can be computationally expensive or may neglect the physical mechanisms of the underlying translocation processes. Here, we have shown that the SMD simulation based on all-atom models may be a fast, reliable, and computationally inexpensive approach to determine the relative permeability of the BBB to various substances. To achieve this, simple model membranes were used. Our approach based on SMD was able to provide good agreement with the experimental results in terms of the relative permeability of the compounds. In particular, we have clearly shown that compounds with lower logBB are highly correlated with larger values of nonequilibrium work required to pull a compound through the bilayer, with correlation coefficient values close to unity. Moreover, the maximum force has also shown a remarkable correlation with the experimental logBB values. The correlation between the simulation and experimental data is consistent and parameters such as the forcefield, the number of independent trajectories, and orientation of compounds (Figure S3 in the 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jcim.9b00834/suppl_file/ci9b00834_si_001.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Supporting Information</ext-link>), the number of compounds, the membrane model and composition, and the pulling velocity, do not affect our conclusions. We have also monitored the formation of hydrogen bonds between the compounds and both the lipids and the water molecules, where a weaker correlation between simulation and experiment was observed. Overall, the presence of a large number of hydrogen bonds was associated with experimentally low permeability of the BBB. Analysis of the van der Waals and electrostatic interactions between the compounds and the lipid bilayer have indicated a higher correlation between logBB/logPS and electrostatic interactions rather than between logBB/logPS and van der Waals interactions. Because all ligands of our study were in neutral form, the effect of the charge of the compounds
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>
 </sup> on the membrane permeability can be further considered in future studies. Overall, we anticipate that our method opens new opportunities for estimating the relative permeability of the BBB to various compounds and future studies may involve more complex membranes and coarse-grained models, including models for the BBB.
</p>
