<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Blood samples were collected from 51 children (≤6 years old) who recruited to the present study (
 <xref rid="tI-mmr-17-02-2402" ref-type="table">Table I</xref>). Written informed consent was obtained from the guardians of each participant and the present study was approved by the Ethical Committee of Guangzhou Women and Children's Medical Center [(2013)077; Guangdong, China] based on the Japanese Ministry of Health and Welfare criteria, and the American Heart Association (
 <xref rid="b6-mmr-17-02-2402" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="b11-mmr-17-02-2402" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). A total of 17 age- and sex-matched samples obtained from normal children, served as the controls; individuals were physically examined in Guangzhou Women and Children's Medical Center. The other 34 samples (17 CAA and 17 CAD) were obtained from patients who were diagnosed and excluded of other possible diseases by ≥2 pediatric cardiologists. Blood samples were separated by centrifugation at 1,000 × g for 10 min at 4°C and aliquots of serum were collected and stored at −80°C. Serum samples were processed to remove albumin and immunoglobulin G (IgG) using a ProteoPrep Blue Albumin and IgG Depletion kit (Sigma-Aldrich; Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany). The concentrations of these proteins were determined using a Bradford protein assay kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories Inc., Hercules, CA, USA). These protein samples were randomly combined into 17 comparison groups, each of which included 1 control sample, 1 CAA sample and 1 CAD sample. Of the 17 comparison groups, 5 were randomly chosen and pooled together according to each type of sample; 3 pooled samples of the control, CAA and CAD groups were produced, and were subsequently analyzed by iTRAQ (Sciex, Framingham, MA, USA) experiments (
 <xref rid="tI-mmr-17-02-2402" ref-type="table">Table IA</xref>). The other 12 groups out of the total 17 were analyzed via western blotting. Information regarding the groups and diagnosis is presented in 
 <xref rid="tI-mmr-17-02-2402" ref-type="table">Table IB</xref>.
</p>
