<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phospholipase, another metabolic enzyme of mycoplasmas, primarily plays a pathogenic function by destroying the integrity of the host cell membrane or by facilitating mycoplasma invasion. Phospholipase activity is identified in multiple mycoplasmas including 
 <italic>M. fermentans</italic> (phospholipase C, PLC), 
 <italic>M. penetrans</italic> (PLC and PLA
 <sub>1</sub>), 
 <italic>M. hyorhinis</italic> (PLA and glycerophosphodiesterase), 
 <italic>U. diversum</italic> (PLC), 
 <italic>U. urealyticum</italic> (PLA
 <sub>1</sub>, PLA
 <sub>2</sub> and PLC), and 
 <italic>U. parvum</italic> (PLA
 <sub>1</sub>, PLA
 <sub>2</sub> and PLC) [
 <xref rid="cit0138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0198" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0236" ref-type="bibr">236</xref>]. Of these, 
 <italic>M. penetrans</italic> PLA
 <sub>1</sub> may trigger specific signal cascades in the host cell, thereby affecting HIV replication [
 <xref rid="cit0236" ref-type="bibr">236</xref>]. 
 <italic>M. hyorhinis</italic> PLA and glycerophosphodiesterase participate in invading host eukaryotic cells, and PLA is also involved in the perturbation of the host membrane [
 <xref rid="cit0198" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>]. Interestingly, although PLD activity is not found in 
 <italic>M. hyorhinis</italic>, two PLD conserved motifs exit in the cardiolipin synthase, which may be associated with the antagonistic effect of erythrocytes against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> β-hemolytic activity [
 <xref rid="cit0237" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>]. 
 <italic>U. urealyticum</italic> and 
 <italic>U. parvum</italic> exhibit PLA
 <sub>1</sub>, PLA
 <sub>2</sub>, and PLC activities; however, the corresponding coding genes have not been identified, and only a few PLD domain-containing proteins have been found in this bacterium; hence, their function needs further clarification. Similarly, 
 <italic>U. diversum</italic> PLC also contributes to cell invasion [
 <xref rid="cit0103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Additionally, like 
 <italic>U. urealyticum</italic>, several mycoplasmas, including 
 <italic>M. pulmonis</italic>, have been reported to present PLC activity, yet it remains controversial whether this activity may ascribe to serum protein contamination rather than the PLC itself [
 <xref rid="cit0234" ref-type="bibr">234</xref>].
</p>
