<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">We identified a total of 101, 114 and 116 differentially expressed miRNAs with known functions in the H1 vs H3, H1 vs H8 and H3 vs H8 in a pairwise fashion, respectively (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) in ovaries of Hu sheep. The key miRNAs identified include oar-let seven families (a–d, f, g and i). The oar-let seven family is one of the first discovered miRNA groups, and its family members are highly conserved in sequences across animal species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. The oar-let seven family were predominantly downregulated in H1 vs H3 compared to H1 vs H8 and H3 and H8 groups (up-regulated). These changes observed at the miRNA expression level could control different pathways. Also, miRNAs have been estimated to regulate more than one-third of protein-encoding mRNAs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. Studies have shown that many non-coding RNAs such as miRNAs are involved in the regulation of ovarian development, influencing the reproductive ability of animals, and are closely related to ovarian tissue-related diseases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. The 5 top most differentially expressed miRNAs identified in the present study included oar-miR-148a, oar-miR-21, oar-let-7b, oar-let-7a and oar-let-7b and were also highly expressed in the ovaries of goats in earlier studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>, pigs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, mice
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>, cattle
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup> and other animal species Li, et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. These miRNAs indicate their involvement in ovary development by modulating the mRNAs as an important regulator of reproductive processes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. However, their fundamental roles in modulating mRNAs need further functional validation.
</p>
