<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genes of melioidosis patients associated with death include 
 <italic>IL1R2, IRAK3, IL18RAP, MGAM, LPL, HGMB2, S100A9, GAS7, NFKBIA, TLR2, TLR4, MAPK14, GPR27, HIF1A,</italic> and 
 <italic>ITGAM.</italic> Many of these genes or their proteins have been reported in related studies. Elevation of 
 <italic>IL1R2</italic> expression and soluble 
 <italic>IL1R2</italic> concentrations are correlated with severity of 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infections [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Increased expression levels of the 
 <italic>IRAK3</italic> gene are correlated with the development of acute lung injury in patients with severe sepsis [
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In melioidosis, Wiersinga et al. reported up-regulation of 
 <italic>IRAK3</italic> is related to attenuated capacity of monocytes to respond to 
 <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> stimulation and this coincided with mortality [
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In parallel to our study, a recent study reported that extracellular S100A8 and S100A9 (S100A8/A9), a Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> sensor in cytoskeleton rearrangement and arachidonic acid metabolism, are the key mediators of sepsis secreted from neutrophils and monocytes during inflammation [
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The S100A9 serve as damage associated molecular patterns and induce pro-inflammatory cytokine expression and secretion via toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) activation [
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Increasing evidence supports that 
 <italic>NFKBIA</italic>-mediated inflammation is linked to susceptibility to infectious and inflammatory diseases [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24–26</xref>]. A report demonstrated an up-regulation of 
 <italic>NFKBIA</italic> expression in mouse macrophages in response to 
 <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> infection [
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and our data confirmed that increased 
 <italic>NFKBIA</italic> expression is associated with fatality in melioidosis patients.
</p>
