<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The description of hemolysis of erythrocytes was originally discovered when the 
 <italic>Pleuropneumonia bovum</italic> strains were growing in the presence of blood [
 <xref rid="cit0186" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>]. Subsequently, the catalase and horseradish peroxidase experiments confirmed that the mechanism of hemolysis was caused by mycoplasma-produced H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> or organic peroxide. Indeed, many mycoplasmas, such as 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae, M. homins, M. bovis, M. agalactiae</italic>, Mmm SC, 
 <italic>M. dispar, M. bovirhinis</italic>, Mccp, 
 <italic>M. gallisepticum, M. canis</italic>, and 
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic> can metabolize glycerol as carbon source to synthesize ATP, and ultimately produce H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> as virulence determinants [
 <xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0165" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0179" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0187" ref-type="bibr">187–196</xref>]. The glycerol metabolism mechanism of mycoplasma is becoming clearer. Generally, when glucose is present as the preferred carbon source, the expression of glycerol metabolism-related genes is suppressed [
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0197" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. Only when glycerol or its derivatives, such as glycerophosphocholine (GPC), is available, glycerol metabolism-related genes are expressed. Glycerol is usually absorbed by the glycerol import system GtsABC or the facilitator factor GlpF, and then phosphorylated by glycerol kinase (GlpK) to glycerol 3-phosphate (G3P). GPC is taken up by glycerophosphocholine importer (GlpU) [
 <xref rid="cit0179" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>], and then degraded by glycerophophodiesterases (GlpQ) to G3P [
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Next, G3P is oxidized by L-α-glycerophosphate oxidase (GlpO or GlpD) and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> is released as a byproduct [
 <xref rid="cit0179" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>]. H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> plays a role in lipid peroxidation, cell damage and death, erythrocyte lysis, and ciliary action inhibition [
 <xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
