<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The accuracy of the NP size determination from the CN analysis is always limited by the quite significant uncertainty of the CN values, especially in the case of the analysis of 
 <italic>in situ</italic> and 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS data, which typically have lower signal-to-noise ratio. An alternative insight into the particle size can be obtained from the interpretation of interatomic distances. Note that due to surface tension effects, interatomic distances in NP near-surface layers tend to be shorter than those in the bulk material.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref162">162</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref274">274</xref>
 </sup> Because of the increasingly large surface-to-volume ratio in small NPs, this results in a reduction of the sample-averaged interatomic distances that can be detected by XAS.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref275">275</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref277">277</xref>
 </sup> Hence, accurately estimated interatomic distances can be used to determine particle sizes. Frenkel et al. used this approach for the determination of particle sizes in thiol-stabilized Au NPs from Au L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge EXAFS data and demonstrated a good agreement between the particle sizes, as estimated from the CN analysis, and those obtained from interatomic distance analysis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref278">278</xref>
 </sup> More recently, a linear relationship between the Au–Au bond contraction and the first shell coordination numbers was confirmed by Behafarid et al. for size-controlled Au NPs encapsulated in PS-P2PVP micelles (
 <xref rid="fig14" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>
 </xref>a).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref259">259</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, the trend obtained based on the XAS data analysis was found to be in agreement with the results of DFT simulations for ligand-free NPs, highlighting the importance of theoretical modeling in the interpretation of the particle size/bond contraction relationship. Finally, it should be noted that similarly to the CN analysis, the interatomic distances can only provide insight into NP sizes in the case of very small particles (&lt;2–3 nm) and are most informative for particles of subnanometer size. For example, Timoshenko et al. used interatomic distances extracted by neural networks from Cu K-edge XANES data to confirm the presence of ultrasmall NPs under a reactive atmosphere in samples containing size-selected Cu clusters, in agreement with the findings extracted from the analysis of NN-yielded CNs (
 <xref rid="fig14" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig14" ref-type="fig">14</xref>
 </xref>b).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>
 </sup> Significant contraction of the interatomic distances was observed for Cu clusters with subnanometer size, while for larger particles, the interatomic distances were found to be close to the bulk value.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref277">277</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
