<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">We performed whole blood RNA-Seq in women with CI and compared the transcriptomic profile to that of normal controls. Our results identified upregulation of genes associated with neutrophil activation and neutrophil-mediated immunity in the CI group compared to in the control group. The uterine cervix is positioned between the vagina, with a rich vaginal microorganism environment, and the presumed sterile intrauterine space. Thus, the uterine cervix is implicated as a mechanical barrier against ascending infection by maintaining closure until delivery and an immunological barrier containing immune cells (dendritic cells, neutrophils, and macrophages) and molecular components, including pattern recognition receptors, Toll-like receptors, receptor for advanced glycation end products, cytokines and chemokines, damage-associated molecular patterns, and antimicrobial peptides [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Therefore, in women with a disrupted cervical barrier, such as advanced cervical dilation, the risk of intra-amniotic microbial invasion is increased. The upregulated neutrophil immunity-associated genes in women with CI showing clinical manifestations, such as cervical dilation, identified in the present study, presumably protects the fetus by preventing ascending infection. Neutrophils are specialized innate phagocytic cells that are densely packed with granules, which are divided as primary (azurophil), secondary (specific), gelatinase, and secretory granules, and contain several proteins with broad antibacterial action [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The granules are heterogenous with respect to their structure, content, and function, and readily released to participate in the host responses to infection or inflammation. In this study, we identified a broad spectrum of neutrophil-related genes expressed at significantly higher levels in women with CI than in controls. Alpha defensins, expressed in azurophil granules, are antimicrobial peptides with remarkable antibacterial, antifungal, and antiviral activities against a wide variety of microorganisms, suggesting their role in innate immunity; they also play important roles in modulating the immune response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. A previous study reported that maternal plasma defensin levels were increased in women who developed histologic chorioamnionitis after preterm premature rupture of membrane [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Therefore, the upregulated DEFA3 expression in the maternal blood of the CI group observed in this study may be explained by the intra-amniotic inflammation that is found in 80% of patients with CI [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].
</p>
