<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">Further, we observed that genes associated with myeloid leukocyte activation and neutrophil-mediated immunity were upregulated in the CI group compared to in the control group, supporting that systemic and intra-uterine inflammation occurs in women with CI. Intra-uterine inflammation may be associated with CI, and its severity is associated with every PTB in women with CI [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Our results showed a higher neutrophil count in the CI-preterm group than in the CI-term group, indicating more severe inflammation. Since alpha defensin is produced by neutrophils, it was expected that the concentration of alpha defensin 3 would be higher in the CI-preterm group than in the CI-term group. However, our results showed that the concentration of alpha defensin 3 tended to be higher in the CI-term group. This trend was also observed in the RNA-Seq and qRT-PCR results. DEFA3 expression was higher in the CI-term group than in the CI-preterm group. We speculate the following as the explanation for these results. Although alpha defensins are stored in the azurophil granules of neutrophils, granules normally undergo restricted secretion and are released into the extracellular milieu through degranulation of activated neutrophils. In addition, alpha defensin can be released following apoptosis, necrosis, or neutrophil extracellular trap (NET)-osis of neutrophils [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Thus, the expression level of alpha defensin is not proportional to the number of neutrophils, but it can be considered to be more related to the degree of activation of neutrophils. For a deeper knowledge on this, further studies, such as examination of neutrophil degranulation markers or serial measurement of defensin levels, are needed. Reduced alpha defensin expression reportedly compromises mucosal host defenses of the ileal mucosa and is associated with the initiation of Crohn’s disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Moreover, alpha defensins can control inflammation by inhibiting biosynthesis of proinflammatory cytokines by macrophages [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In a similar context, our findings showed that the upregulated expression of various host defense-related genes, such as DEFA3, was associated with favorable pregnancy outcomes in women with CI. However, since a high expression of defensin reflects a strong inflammatory response and serves as a double-edged sword through which the host defense mechanism acts, more studies are needed on the effect of DEFA3 gene expression on pregnancy prognosis.
</p>
