<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50">To our knowledge, this is the first RNA-Seq study of whole blood in women with CI. To date, there are few high-throughput studies on CI, likely because isolated CI is a relatively rare condition, and there are no objective diagnostic criteria, making it difficult to determine the subject inclusion and obtaining cervical tissue during pregnancy for analysis. In this study, women with a short cervix on ultrasonography were excluded, and only those with cervical dilation were included. The presence of symptoms, such as uterine contractions or vaginal bleeding, was closely observed in the CI group, and patients with any suspected symptoms were excluded from the study group. Moreover, although the pathophysiology or etiology of CI could not be investigated using cervical tissues, our study revealed a systemic unique transcriptomic profile for cervical barrier disruption and differential gene expression according to pregnancy outcomes. Our study had some limitations. First, the sample size was small, particularly in the control group. However, we carefully matched the maternal and gestational ages of women in the CI and control groups, and homogenous gene expression of normal controls enabled us to overcome the limitations of the small sample size. In addition, although the serum alpha defensin 3 concentration in the CI-term group tended to be higher than that in the CI-preterm group, the difference between the two groups was not significant. Thus, studies with a larger sample size are needed to determine the usefulness of serum alpha defensin 3 as a predictive biomarker of pregnancy outcomes. Further, in recent studies, higher levels of beta defensin were observed in the amniotic fluid of patients with spontaneous preterm labor with intraamniotic inflammation than in women without inflammation, and higher vaginal beta defensin levels were also observed to lower the risk of preterm birth [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Although we found that alpha defensin showed a significant difference between the CI and normal groups, further studies on the expression of other antimicrobial peptides and their effect on pregnancy prognosis are needed to broaden understanding of the pathophysiology of preterm parturition.
</p>
