<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
 <label>Figure 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Increased oxidative phosphorylation in Kawasaki disease with coronary artery lesion (KD-CAL+) sera-treated human coronary artery endothelial cells (HCAECs). 
   <bold>(A)</bold> HCAECs were treated with deoxyglucose (50 μg/ml) and oligomycin (10 mM) for 12 h. Intracellular ATP content was determined by chemiluminescence apparatus. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> HCAECs were treated with medium containing 15% sera from healthy controls (HCs; 
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), Kawasaki disease without coronary artery lesion (KD-CAL–; 
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), and KD-CAL+ (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6) for 4 h. Intracellular ATP content was determined by chemiluminescence apparatus. 
   <bold>(C)</bold> HCAECs were treated with medium containing 15% serum from HC (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), KD-CAL– (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), and KD-CAL+ (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6) for 4 h. Mitochondrial Complex I activity was determined in 340 nm with a microplate reader. 
   <bold>(D)</bold> HCAECs were treated with medium containing 15% sera from HC (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), KD-CAL– (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), and KD-CAL+ (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6) for 4 h. Mitochondrial gene copy number was measured by qPCR. 
   <bold>(E,F)</bold> HCAECs were treated with medium containing 15% sera from HC (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), KD-CAL– (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), and KD-CAL+ (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6) for 4 h. Mitochondrial membrane potential was determined by JC-1 (monomers green, aggregates red) analyzed by confocal microscopy. 
   <bold>(F)</bold> Statistical analysis of relative fluorescence intensity (red/green). All samples were normalized to HCAECs with CAL serum treatment or control. The bar graphs are mean ± SEM. 
   <sup>*</sup>
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 and 
   <sup>**</sup>
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 compared with the indicated group.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fped-09-618267-g0004" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
