<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Presently, defining a translational role for our topical formulation in human patients is beyond the scope of this study’s findings, but is certainly a future goal. Further experimental refinements are required in pursuit of that goal: at this time, the study’s limitations include the unpredictability of animal behavior and reaction to testing, and thus how it affected topical application of our experimental drug. All of the animals underwent their intervention at the same time, some even from the same litter, such that the effects of hair cycling and age differences were largely controlled. However, the issue of differing results with small shifts in the timing of these experiments (6 vs. 8 weeks), as described above, could also be more effectively controlled. In addition, we did not isolate the layers of the skin in some of our experiments, and thus the changes in HA content and HAS expression in response to topical 4-MU cannot be directly attributed to either the dermis or the epidermis. Further optimization of the topical 4-MU formulation would include differential, layer-specific targeting. A critical look at the components of the formulation may also be warranted, as it is known that EtOH can have a dose-dependent desiccant effect, possibly disruptive to the protective lipid matrix layer of the skin (Kownatzki 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Kwak et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). As we observed a notable sex-based difference in the in HA and HAS expression, both with and without 4-MU treatment, it would be critical to isolate the effects of sex hormones on HA and 4-MU in future experiments, which would be powered adequately to study sex as a biological variable. Moreover, upcoming experiments should involve determining molecular weight of HA in these skin samples, as the molecular weight of HA is currently considered a critical factor in its downstream effects (Garantziotis and Savani 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).
</p>
