<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another technologically important reaction is the hydrogen evolution reaction, which takes place at the cathode during the electrochemical water splitting. Pt catalysts are most commonly used for this reaction due to the optimal hydrogen binding energy.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref638">638</xref>
 </sup> However, the high cost of Pt limits its large-scale application. One approach to address this problem is to improve Pt utilization efficiency by using ultradispersed catalysts. For example, in a recent study, a catalyst featuring singly dispersed Pt sites in a porous carbon matrix was found to exhibit good HER activity. Analysis of EXAFS features coupled to wavelet transform confirmed the presence of isolated Pt sites, while the changes in the Pt L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge WL revealed the charge transfer between Pt and the support, which based on DFT simulations was found to be important for ensuring the high HER activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref150">150</xref>
 </sup> Alternative approaches for reducing HER catalyst costs rely on using non-Pt-based catalysts. In particular, various phosphides, sulfides, carbides, nitrides and borides have been proposed.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>
 </sup> XAS was found to be helpful in revealing the actual structure of these multielement catalysts, for example, the partially oxidized structure of a Co sulfide catalyst,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref114">114</xref>
 </sup> and the structures of Mo carbides, nitrides, and sulfides.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref639">639</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref641">641</xref>
 </sup> XAS measurements were helpful also to establish the oxidation states of Cr, Cu, and Ni in a recently proposed multisite CrO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>/Cu–Ni catalyst, which was found to be promising for HER in neutral media.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref638">638</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
