<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the last years, the electrochemical N
 <sub>2</sub> reduction reaction (NRR) for ammonia synthesis at ambient conditions has also attracted attention. The idea behind the intensive new research efforts on this extremely challenging electrochemical process is the possibility to replace or at least to complement the Haber-Bosch process that currently is used for industrial NH
 <sub>3</sub> production since the latter requires high pressures (200–350 atm), high temperatures (300–550 °C), and high-purity hydrogen that is currently produced from fossil fuels.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref642">642</xref>
 </sup> However, the inertness of the N
 <sub>2</sub> molecule and a competition with the kinetically favored HER limit the efficiency of NRR, requiring further improvements in the choice of catalyst and non-aqueous electrolyte.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref643">643</xref>
 </sup> Among others, transition metal-based single atom catalysts have been considered such as Au-based,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref644">644</xref>
 </sup> Ru-based,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref645">645</xref>
 </sup> Ni-based,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref646">646</xref>
 </sup> Fe-based,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref647">647</xref>
 </sup> and Co-based
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref648">648</xref>
 </sup> TMNC materials. In all these examples, XANES and EXAFS analysis of the as-prepared samples confirmed the presence of M-N
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> motifs that are believed to be important for NRR activity. In some cases, 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS investigations were also performed, confirming the stability of these moieties under catalyst working conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref649">649</xref>
 </sup> However, further 
 <italic>operando</italic> studies are needed to understand the roles of different species in NRR. More importantly, and as featured in a recent publication,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref650">650</xref>
 </sup> the majority of the ammonia yields reported to date for a variety of catalyst structures/compositions (other than a Li-based system
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref651">651</xref>
 </sup>) could not be reproduced when measured under stringent experimental protocols to avoid the detection of other residual ammonia sources. Therefore, this is an open field where significant work will still be needed in the years to come not only to increase the production of ammonia but even more importantly, to ensure that the data collected correspond to ammonia really produced via the NRR process.
</p>
