<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par51">Several transcriptome surveys were conducted to identify 
 <italic>P. notatum</italic> apomixis-associated genes. Firstly, transcripts expressed in sexual and apomictic florets were compared by using differential display, allowing the identification of a pioneer apomixis candidate gene homologous to the maize kinesin-like motor protein KIN-14P [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Then, Laspina et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] identified 65 transcripts differentially expressed in spikelets of apomictic and sexual genotypes at premeiosis/meiosis, several of which mapped in silico to a rice chromosome 2 region that had previously been associated with apospory by comparative mapping [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Moreover, endosperm RNA representation comparisons 3–24 h after pollination revealed more than 100 differentially expressed transcripts (DETs) in seeds that differed from the expected 2 m:1p genome contribution ratio, formed when apomictic plants were used as female parents in crosses (the endosperm involved 4 m:1p, 8 m:1p or 8 m:3p contribution ratios, depending on the cross) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Besides, transcripts related to endosperm development were identified in apomictic and sexual ovaries of 
 <italic>Paspalum notatum</italic> 48 h after pollination, a stage prior to post-zygotic collapse [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. These DETs were mainly associated with genes related to transcription, signal transduction, growth/division, protein destination and storage, as well as regulation of gene expression. Interestingly, several differential sequences identified at the onset of endosperm development showed high similarity with proteins expressed in response to changes in the levels of extracellular ATP [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Besides, the Roche 454/FLX + long-read technology was used to produce apomictic and sexual reference floral transcriptomes on an equitable mix of RNA extracted from spikelets at different developmental states from premeiosis to anthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Recently, De Oliveira et al. (2020) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] reported a global gene expression analysis using Illumina Hi-Seq technology on RNA isolated from leaf and floral tissues of 2x sexual, 4x sexual and 4x apomictic genotypes. Interestingly, 89 DETs expressed in apomictic or sexual plants mapped at the chromosome regions of rice syntenic to the Paspalum apomixis controlling locus (ACL) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].
</p>
