<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HK-2 cells were digested by trypsin and centrifuged at 1,000 rpm for 5 min. Supernatant was discarded and the cells were washed twice with pre-cooled phosphate buffered saline (PBS). The PBS was then discarded, and the petri dish was added with an appropriate volume of RIPA buffer (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) containing protease inhibitors and gently shaken to let the solution completely cover the bottom of the petri dish. After that, the dish was placed on ice for a few minutes. The cells were scraped from the bottom of the dish using a cell scraper, and the cell lysates were transferred into an EP tube using a pipette. The cell lysis and transfer of cell lysates were operated on ice. The EP tube was placed on ice for 15 min. The lysates were centrifuged at 32,000 rpm for 15 min at 4 °C. Supernatant was carefully pipetted into a new EP tube and centrifuged to acquire protein samples. GAPDH acted as the internal reference. The concentration of each protein sample was measured using a BCA kit (Beyotime) to ensure the same loading amount of each sample. The BCA working reagent was made by mixing Reagent A and Reagent B at a ratio of 50:1. The newly prepared BCA working reagent was stable at room temperature for 24 h. Concentration of the standards was set to 0, 0.05, 0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4, and 0.5 mg/ml. The 96-well plate was added with an appropriate volume of protein samples, and each well was added with 200 μL of BCA working reagent. The protein samples were incubated at 37 °C for 30 min. The absorbance value was measured at 562 nm by a microplate reader. Concentration of the protein samples was calculated according to the standard curve. After the measurement of concentration, proteins of corresponding volumes were mixed with loading buffer (Beyotime) and denatured in boiling water for 3 min. The proteins were separated by 10% SDS-PAGE which was run at 80 V until bromophenol blue came into the gel and then continued at 120 V for 1–2 h. The transfer of proteins was conducted in an ice bath at 300 mA for 60 min. After that, the membrane was rinsed for 1–2 min and then soaked in blocking buffer at room temperature for 60 min or at 4 °C overnight. The proteins were incubated with primary antibodies of GAPDH (rabbit anti-human, 1:1000, Cell Signaling, Boston, USA), Bax (rabbit anti-human, 1:2000, Abcam, Cambridge, UK), Bcl-2 (rabbit anti-human, 1:800, Abcam), cleaved caspase-3 (rabbit anti-human, 1:1000, Abcam) and AQP2 (rat anti-human, 1:500, Santa Cruz, TX, USA) on a shaking bed for 1 h. The membrane was washed for 3 × 10 min and then transferred to horseradish peroxidase-marked secondary antibody solution (goat anti-rabbit IgG, 1:10,000 or goat anti-rat IgG, 1:500) (Thermo Fisher Scientific, MA, USA) to incubate the proteins at room temperature for 1 h. After that, the membrane was subjected to another round of washing, and added with color-developing solution. Protein expression was detected by a chemiluminescence imaging system (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA).</p>
