<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The discussion in the previous paragraphs was limited to the cases where the metals that form the bimetallic material are substantially different in terms of their atomic number, so that they can be distinguished by EXAFS. In practice, many catalytically relevant alloy systems are formed by metals that are neighbors in the Periodic Table, limiting the amount of information that can be extracted from the CNs analysis. In this situation, to distinguish between different segregation/alloying motifs, one can rely on other structural parameters that can provide indirect insight. For example, due to the difference in sizes of the constituent atoms, the alloying may result in enhanced structural disorder and corresponding Debye–Waller factors. However, especially informative can be the analysis of the interatomic distances. According to Vegard’s law, the lattice constant of a bimetallic alloy is expected to be in between those of the constituent pure metals and should change linearly with composition. This provides a possibility to distinguish between well-ordered alloys and segregated systems even for bimetallics consisting of atoms that are neighbors in the Periodic Table. For example, such a reasoning was employed to confirm the alloying of Pt with Au in ultradilute Pt–Au nanoalloys, which exhibited high electrocatalytic activity for the formic acid oxidation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref316">316</xref>
 </sup> The dependency of Pd–Au, Pd–Pd, Au–Pd, and Au–Au bond lengths in random alloy PdAu NPs on the Pd concentration, as extracted from advanced analysis of EXAFS data,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref241">241</xref>
 </sup> is shown in 
 <xref rid="fig18" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig18" ref-type="fig">18</xref>
 </xref>b. The approximately linear relationship between the bond distance and the Pd concentration follows the Vegard’s law. However, a more detailed look reveals some differences between the Au–Au and Pd–Pd bond-lengths, which, according to Vegard’s law, should be the same. The observed difference was attributed to the difference in size of the Au and Pd atoms, together with the asymmetry of the interaction potential, which makes it easier to expand the Pd–Pd distance than to compress the Au–Au distance.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref241">241</xref>
 </sup> A similar effect was also observed for CuAu alloys.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref314">314</xref>
 </sup> This is just one example that demonstrates that caution is needed when the Vegard’s law is applied to understand the structural motifs in the catalyst because interatomic distances are not only affected by the composition. For example, the surface segregation of atoms of one type may also result in compressed interatomic distances due to a surface tension effect,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref162">162</xref>
 </sup> as observed, for example, for ultradilute PdAu alloys.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref241">241</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
