<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The epithelial sodium channel (ENaC)/Degenerin (DEG) ion channel superfamily are selective for Na
 <sup>+</sup>, showing preference over K
 <sup>+</sup> of 100-fold for ENaC and 10-fold for ASIC subunits [
 <xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–5</xref>]. An additional characteristic of the ENaC/DEG superfamily is sensitivity to the reversible channel blocker, amiloride [
 <xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In mammals, there are nine ENaC/DEG genes, four encode ENaC subunits (α/β/γ/δ-ENaC) and five encode ASIC subunits (ASIC1-5). Although the nomenclature has been standardized for the ASIC family (
 <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), ASIC5 is still often referred to as Bile Acid-Sensitive Ion Channel (BASIC), due to it not being modulated by extracellular acid [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and displaying a low amino acid homogeneity of ~30% with other ASIC subunits (by contrast, ASIC1-4 share at least 50% amino homogeneity, 
 <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7–11</xref>]. Due to alternative splicing, the four main ASIC genes produce six ASIC subunits: ASIC1a, ASIC1b, ASIC2a, ASIC2b, ASIC3 and ASIC4 and studies using x-ray crystallography [
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and atomic force microscopy [
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] have demonstrated that ASICs form trimers, subunits combining to form homomeric or heteromeric ion channels. To date, a total of 18 ASIC structures are available in the Protein Data Bank (PDB), but all of these are of 
 <italic>Gallus gallus</italic> (chicken) ASIC1a (cASIC1a). Therefore, it should be remembered that all structural information discussed on ASIC3 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>), both here and in the wider literature, is largely based on the structure of cASIC1a. Like BASIC, not all ASIC subunits form proton-sensitive homotrimers, ASIC2b and ASIC4 both being proton-insensitive [
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], but able to modulate the properties of other ASICs in heteromeric configurations [
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Of all ASIC subunit configurations, those containing ASIC3 are the most sensitive to protons [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], as well as producing a characteristic biphasic response: an initial transient inward current followed by a smaller magnitude-sustained phase, features that make ASIC3 of particular interest in the context of pain [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Human ASIC3 (hASIC3) was first located on chromosome 7q35 (6.4 cRad telomeric) in the late 1990s [
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and there have been limited subsequent studies of hASIC3, and thus, this review will encompass the broader mammalian publications from rat (rASIC3) and mouse (mASIC3) orthologues which share an 84% amino acid identity to hASIC3. 
</p>
