<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hybrid Na–air batteries are built up with two different electrolytes namely, organic and aqueous electrolytes. Sodium‐based salts such as NaCF
 <sub>3</sub>SO
 <sub>3</sub>, NaClO
 <sub>4</sub>, etc., are dissolved in organic solvents such as tetra ethylene glycol dimethyl ether (TEGDME) and EC/DMC and used as anolyte. The organic electrolytes are involved in the formation of SEI at anode which should allow deposition and stripping of Na
 <sup>+</sup> ions. SEI forms mainly due to the decomposition of organic electrolytes at lower potential on anode and electrolyte interface.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">49</xref> SEI is crucial for the protection of anode as it restricts transfer of electron from anode to electrolyte only allows the passage of Na
 <sup>+</sup> ions to and from the anode. Thus, an ideal SEI should be electronic insulator and ionic conductor.[qv: 49b] Moreover, SEI should be stable so it also could prevent the dendritic growth of Na. There is no any focused study for SEI formation using different combination of organic solvents with different Na salt which can provide understanding about suitable anolyte. On the other hand, in most of studies, aqueous NaOH and KOH are usually used as catholyte. Due to the usage of aqueous electrolytes, the hybrid Na–air batteries have essential advantage over nonaqueous Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> batteries thanks to the highly soluble discharge products (sodium hydroxide) which does not deposit into the pores of air electrodes, thus, enabling high performance hybrid Na–air battery. In addition to NaOH and KOH, Kang et al. modified the cell structure and used an acidic electrolyte instead of alkali electrolyte as catholyte.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">44</xref> The acidic electrolyte also helped to improve the cell potential (3.94 V) and thus the specific energy (4418 Wh kg
 <sup>−1</sup>) as well. The charge–discharge reactions of acidic electrolyte‐based hybrid Na–air battery can be governed by following steps:
</p>
