<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The increased deposition of fatty acids in adipose and other tissues is considered a hallmark of obesity. In the past few years, it has been established that fatty acids cross the plasma membrane via a protein-mediated mechanism involving one or more fatty acid-handling proteins, including a family of fatty acid transporters [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In the present study, we identified several differentially expressed genes involved in fatty acid transport and metabolism in SAT versus VAT in response to CD feeding. Slc27a3 is a membrane protein known for its critical role in fatty acid uptake by endothelial cells [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, the role of Slc27a3 in obesity, if any, remains unclear. We note that studies have reported elevated 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> expression in skeletal and cardiac muscle from mice fed a high-fat diet [
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and in H9c2 cardiomyocytes exposed to high glucose [
 <xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and although the expression status of 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> in adipose tissue is not well documented, Bouwman (2013) reported a significant downregulation of 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> in human abdominal adipose tissue biopsies in response to a 5-week, calorie restriction weight-loss programme [
 <xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The authors speculated that the reduction in adipose tissue fatty acid import may, in part, explain the benefits of weight loss in reducing metabolic risk. This study, together with ours, suggests a potential role for Slc27a3 in visceral fat accumulation. While further mechanistic investigation is required, we propose that the upregulation of 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> in VAT, as observed in our study, may represent an early adaptation event in response to CD feeding, triggering enhanced fatty acid uptake in order to compensate for the increased availability of circulating dietary triglycerides. The observation that this gene was not regulated by CD in SAT is in agreement with other studies showing depot-specific differences in fatty acid influx in obese humans with metabolic syndrome or T2D [
 <xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32–34</xref>].
</p>
