<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>In silico</italic> analysis of the 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> gene sequence revealed putative transcription factor binding sites for NKX2-1, E2F1, WT1 I and GCF in the region harbouring the six CpG sites investigated in this study. These transcription factors have previously been suggested to play a role in energy expenditure [
 <xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], glucose homeostasis [
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], adipogenesis [
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], insulin secretion [
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], lipolysis and β-oxidation [
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], control of cell growth [
 <xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and response to hypocaloric dietary intervention [
 <xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Importantly, the consensus binding site for GCF spans the region harbouring CpG5, which was shown to be hypomethylated in response to CD-feeding in our study. GCF has previously been shown to bind to the GC-rich sequences within the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR), β-actin and calcium-dependent protease gene promoters and consequently alter their transcriptional activity [
 <xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Similarly, we propose that CD-induced hypomethylation of 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> leads to epigenetic activation of the gene, possibly through increased GCF binding at this region. Future studies should experimentally determine whether GCF binds and regulates 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> transcriptional activity through CpG5 and whether this regulation is altered upon DNA methylation changes induced by CD-feeding. It would also be interesting to determine whether 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> is transcriptionally activated by WT1, which has been associated with visceral white adipose tissue identity [
 <xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Addressing these questions would require a combination of mechanistic studies including luciferase reporter gene assays as well as 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> binding assays such as electrophoretic mobility shift assays (EMSA) and chromatin immunoprecipitation assays, respectively.
</p>
