<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some limitations to this study exist. Due to the cross-sectional study design, we could not determine whether the DNA methylation and/or gene expression signatures identified in this study played a causal role in the different expansion properties observed in VAT and SAT in response to CD, and thus future longitudinal studies are warranted to investigate this. Moreover, the initial PCR array experiments in our study revealed significant downregulation of 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> in SAT from CD-fed rats compared to controls, however this was conflicting with our Taqman qRT-PCR data. This may be due to differences in the sample size used for the PCR arrays (n = 8) compared to the qRT-PCR experiments (n = 10) or alternatively, as a result of the different methods employed to quantify gene expression (i.e. SYBR Green dye for the PCR arrays and TaqMan fluorescent probes for qRT-PCR). It is important to note that SYBR Green dye is non-specific and can generate false positive signals if non-specific products or primer-dimers are present in the assay [
 <xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Thus, PCR array results should be interpreted with caution and validated using alternative gene quantification methods. It is well-established that VAT expansion is accompanied by infiltration of macrophages [
 <xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Since adipose tissue and immune cells have distinct DNA methylation and gene expression profiles, the infiltration of macrophages could have contributed to the observed differential DNA methylation and gene expression patterns in VAT. Future studies should exclude these potentially confounding effects by quantifying crown-like structure formation within VAT and correcting for these using statistical models as described by Zwamborn et al [
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. We were unable to determine whole-body SAT mass in CD versus STD-fed rats and thus future studies should include the measurement of total fat mass using dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA). We were also unable to determine 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> protein levels in response to CD and STD feeding in the current study and this forms part of future work. Lastly, the molecular function of Slc27a3 in fatty acid uptake and metabolism in VAT during the progression of obesity remains to be elucidated. Gene knockout adipocyte cell culture models may shed light on this and forms part of future studies.
</p>
