<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several metabolic pathways including purine and pyrimidine metabolism, nitrogen processes, and terpenoid backbone were downregulated in virus-infected plants (1 dpi and 4 dpi combined).Purine catabolism is a vital housekeeping function of the plants for growth, development, nitrogen remobilization, and induction of defense-related hormone signaling [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Allantoin is a nitrogen-rich compound and an essential intermediate in purine catabolism that typically accumulates in stressed plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Allantoin induces jasmonic acid (JA) [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], the defense signaling phytohormone that results in systemic resistance against viruses [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. In this study, downregulation of allantoin and nitrogen compounds could have resulted from suppression of purine catabolic processes. These successive suppressions may have decreased JA signaling resulting in plant susceptibility to virus infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Based on retrieved vsiRNAs from sRNA analysis in our study, there were few sequences of 3’ end of RNA2 encoding 2b protein of CMV. Because viral 2b protein inhibits cleavage activity of Argonaute [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], increased levels of this protein allow the virus to counter both plant defense through JA signaling repression and facilitates long distance movement of the virus. Purine and pyrimidine together as part of nucleotide metabolism of host are essential for virus replication. Downregulation of these two compounds could be an antiviral mechanism that deprives virus of nucleotides required for virus replication machinery [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Terpenoids are secondary metabolites with the anti-herbivory and defensive roles in plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Downregulation of DEG involved in terpenoid backbone biosynthesis was related to a chloroplastic terpenoid pathway (MEP) (
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>); this restricts biosynthesis of downstream terpenoid compounds and impairs the terpenoid-related defensive roles [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].
</p>
