<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Upregulated DEGs were involved in lipid and nitrogen metabolism, translation, hormone signaling, protein and terpenoid biosynthesis. Nitrogen is one of the primary limiting factors for plant growth, and its assimilation is required for biosynthesis of amino acids glutamate, glutamine, asparagine, and aspartate [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. CMV infection in tobacco leaves led to overexpression of two enzymes implicated in primary assimilation of nitrogen, glutamate dehydrogenase (GDH) and cytosolic glutamine synthetase (GS1) [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. In our study, accumulation of nitrogen compounds likely led to induction of amino acid biosynthesis, thus resulting in elevated levels of translation process and protein formation; the finding is also consistent with the study on 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> that reported impact of elevated level of nitrogen on increasing protein content [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Endoplasmic reticulum (ER), the replication site for viruses in the 
 <italic>Bromoviridae</italic> family, is the site for formation of viral factories, vesicles that are required for virus replication [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. In quinoa, following induction of DEGs in nitrogen and protein biosynthesis, amino acid transport to ER was also increased. Because amino acid transport is correlated to abundance of nitrogen in plant cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], elevated processes of protein retention in ER and translation might be due to viral demand for the protein biosynthesis required for its replication and assembly. Also, increased level of lipid metabolism might be the result of recruiting host cellular factors to synthesize glycerophospholipids, which is the main component of membraneous viral factories [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Phytohormones have several regulatory roles in plant development, growth, host-pathogen interaction, and plant defense mechanism [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Salicylic acid (SA) is one of the major defense-related hormones and plays a positive regulatory role against plant viruses. The SA interaction with brassinosteroid (BR) or ethylene (ET), as two other phytohormones, results in either synergistic or antagonistic immune responses. Because BR induces ET biosynthesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] and ET precedes the SA signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], the upregulation of both BR and ET DEGs in this study, that was concurrent with overexpression of SA-related DEGs, could have been a synergistic defense response against virus. Enzymatic reactions of synthases, reductases, kinases, etc. in the terpenoid backbone biosynthesis concatenates isoprene units to produce various classes of terpenoids. Monoterpenoids are biosynthesized through MEP pathway, whereas sesquiterpenes are produced in a cytosolic pathway (mevalonate [MVA]) [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Overexpression of DEGs pertaining to sesquiterpenes (
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) in quinoa might have resulted from increased activity of MVA pathway, which probably compensates the suppressed sources of chloroplastic-derived isoprene units. Although, MEP pathway was downregulated, induction of monoterpenoid DEGs might be from elevated isoprene blocks originated from MVA pathway. The cross-talk of MEP and MVA pathways have been reported in northern red oak as a response to ozone [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>].
</p>
