<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Analysis on the effect of CMV infection over time on separate quinoa varieties resulted in identification of DEGs that modulated variety-specific biological pathways, such as plant-pathogen interaction (PPI), DNA replication, mismatch and nucleotide excision repair, homologous recombination, and hormone signaling. The DEGs for PPI include defense-related mechanisms that involve reactive oxygen species (ROS) and result in hypersensitive response, cell programmed death, and induction of genes that are related to defense against viruses. All these responses modulate levels of defense hormones such as SA, JA, and ET [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. In ‘Jessie’, a variety with CMV-induced local lesions, downregulation of PPI was concomitant with suppression of DEGs of ROS and defense hormones (SA, JA, ET), which implies that these defense responses were suppressed over time (upregulated at 1 dpi during the active defense response and then downregulated at 4 dpi). Although the fact that a local lesion variety has downregulated defense system seems counter-intuitive, plant reaction to viral inoculation occurs rapidly and processes that require upregulation can be completed in early stages of infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. In ‘Red Head’, the variety with CMV-induced systemic symptoms, both PPI and ROS were upregulated, which implies elevation of these two stress responsive mechanisms over time. Therefore, in contrast to ‘Red Head’ (susceptible host) that had a consistent induced defense response, ‘Jessie’ (resistant host) had induction of defensive pathways at early stage of infection and then suppression of those defensive pathways at late stage of infection. Replication and repair processes of host genome is a critical and substantial antiviral mechanism [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. In tobacco infected with TMV, upregulation of plant DNA homologous recombination resulted in persistent induction of DNA rearrangement and leucine-rich repeat (LRR) gene expression, which led to persistent and broad-spectrum resistance to TMV infection in tobacco [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. In ‘QQ74’, a variety with few CMV-induced local lesions, PPI over time was overexpressed. This finding could be due to upregulation of DNA replication, mismatch and nucleotide excision repair, and homologous recombination that provided prolonged and persistent defense responses such as PPI even at 4 dpi. The DEGs involved in hormone signaling were altered in ‘Jessie’ and ‘Red Head’ but not ‘QQ74’. Reprogramming of auxin biosynthesis and/or signaling through altering its function and subcellular localization by several plant viruses including CMV has been shown to be beneficial for virus movement and replication, as well as enhanced infection and disease symptoms [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Elevated levels of auxin repressed the hypersensitive response (HR) resulting from SA signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. In this study, ‘Jessie’ and ‘Red Head’ displayed induction of genes of auxin signaling over time in CMV infection, suggesting suppression of systemic resistance in both varieties via disruption of SA-mediated defense responses. It has been reported that in cucumber infected with CMV, ET is a determinant for viral-induced symptoms [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. In ‘Red Head’, overexpression of ET-related genes at 4 dpi could be responsible for appearance of CMV-induced systemic symptoms. Abscisic acid (ABA), a phytohormone involved in developmental processes, such as seed germination, fruit ripening, and responses to abiotic stresses [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], is antagonist to SA/JA-dependent defense pathway, ROS production and HR, and therefore represses systemic resistance against viruses [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Furthermore, ABA induces callus deposition in plasmodesmata, which limits virus intercellular movement, and also elevates AGO1 activity implicated in gene silencing [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. In this study, in ‘Red Head’, induction of ABA responding genes at 4 dpi may have played a dual role against CMV infection: 1) utilization of ABA by virus to negate host systemic resistance, and 2) induction of ABA by host to repress virus through limiting viral movement or silencing viral genes via RNAi machinery. In tobacco, cytokinin (CK) accumulation led to enhanced viral resistance through SA-mediated defense responses [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. In ‘Jessie’ and ‘Red Head’, downregulation of CK-related genes over time was likely related to suppression of systemic resistance through SA signaling pathway. In ‘Jessie’ this might be a host strategy to bring hormonal levels to pre-infection levels, because the virus has already been deactivated in the adjacent cells due to appeared local lesions [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Conversely, in ‘Red Head’, suppression of CK-related genes was probably governed by CMV, because of the systemic infection of the virus that led to continuous modulation of defense hormone signaling over time.
</p>
