<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ten out of eleven known miRNA families identified in this study were also reported at least once elsewhere from 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>quinoa</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]; miR395 was reported only from this study. This indicated conserved structure of the detected miRNAs between this study and the others, and reliability of our 
 <italic>in silico</italic> miRNA analyses. Identification of known and novel miRNAs in quinoa [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>] and prediction of their target genes has already been reported [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]; however, screening of DEmiRNAs in quinoa between CMV- and mock-inoculated samples had not yet been investigated until this study. DE analysis detected a total of 13 DEmiRNAs from quinoa varieties, which overall targeted 126 candidate genes (
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0244364.s017">S6 Table</xref>). As miRNA targets 3’ UTR of the target genes for degradation by RISC [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>], there are several lines of evidence confirming that there is a strong negative correlation between miRNA expression and regulation of their targeted mRNA [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. In ‘Jessie’, downregulation of novel miRNA “NW_018743850.1_23708” derepressed expression of ABA receptor genes, which are known to modulate ABA levels in plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Increased ABA may result in diverse defense responses: 1) elevated callose deposition in plasmodesmata to confine and eliminate the virus, and/or 2) a viral strategy to inhibit host systemic resistance via disruption of SA/JA signaling pathway. The role of miR399 in relationship with lipid metabolism have been reported in maize [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. In ‘Jessie’, suppression of miR399 and miR166, and induction of novel miRNA “NW_018744092.1_28071”, might lead to upregulation of target genes involved in lipid biosynthesis, and one may infer that the virus regulated three miRNAs to modulate host lipid biosynthesis for its own multiplication. Another role of miR399 is to regulate ubiquitin-conjugating E2 enzyme that target proteins for degradation [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. In ‘Jessie’, downregulation of miR399 may induce: 1) expression of ubiquitin enzyme that increases degradation of viral proteins, and 2) endocytosis, which is a host mechanism to remove ligands, nutrients, lipids and proteins from the cell.
</p>
