<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The complexity in siRNA classification during host-virus interaction at genome-wide levels needs development of particular analysis. Using ShortStack facilitated identification of siRNAs based upon 1) software development according to plant genomes, and 2) prediction of 
 <italic>de novo</italic> regions over the genome with accumulated siRNAs named “clusters”. In the 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>-root knot nematode interaction, abundance of 23 and 24 siRNAs is higher in galled samples than in controls and was attributed as a gall characteristic [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In this study, however, significant higher accumulation of 24nt siRNA clusters among varieties (‘Red Head’, bitter variety had more siRNA than other two varieties), may suggest that varied abundance of siRNA clusters in quinoa was a variety-specific incidence. Since hc-siRNA were the most abundant cleaved size among quinoa siRNA clusters and are associated with silencing of gene and intergenic repeats through DNA methylation and histone modification, differential expression analysis focused only on hc-siRNAs. Similar to miRNAs that have negative correlation with expression of their targets, siRNA expression also influences their targets inversely [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Thus, differentially expressed clusters of hc-siRNAs in quinoa either in overall or variety-specific modes impact their putative genomic regions including genes, TFBSs, and TEs in a negative manner. Based on target analyses of differentially expressed hc-siRNA in quinoa, intergenic areas and repetitive elements were more regulated than coding sequences; this is consistent with the fact that hc-siRNA mostly target promoter regions [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The differentially expressed hc-siRNAs identified in this study may be good resistance candidates during virus infection, however, further functional studies should be conducted to verify their expression via RNA-directed DNA methylation, and their potential role in quinoa-virus interaction.
</p>
