<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During CMV infection in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, DCL4 produced 21nt vsiRNA that has been implicated in viral gene silencing. DCL4 mutants had a higher abundance of 22nt vsiRNA, indicating recruitment of DCL2 to compensate DCL4 impairment [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Both DCL4 and DCL2 may also be involved in vsiRNA biogenesis in quinoa since 21 and 22 nt are the predominant sizes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0244364.g004">Fig 4</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0244364.s005">S5 Fig</xref>). More vsiRNAs mapped to RNA3 than RNA1 or RNA2 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0244364.g005">Fig 5</xref>), perhaps due to the fact that RNA3 is the most abundant RNA in infected cells. RNA3 also has shorter sequence length and higher replication rate than RNA1 and RNA2 [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Since DCL2 and DCL4 preferentially cleave GC-rich template regions [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>] and GC content of CMV RNAs is similar (RNA1: 46.5%; RNA2: 45.9%; and RNA3: 46.9%), this eliminated GC content as the reason for uneven distribution of vsiRNAs across CMV genome. In CMV-infected 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and 
 <italic>Nicotiana</italic>, RDR1 has the primary role in vsiRNA formation with a 5’ selection bias for three viral genomic RNAs. In RDR1 mutants there was an increased production of vsiRNAs from the 3’ half of the genomic RNAs, particularly in RNA3, which appeared to be RDR6-dependent [
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244364.ref107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Thus, in our study, variability of 5’ bases (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0244364.g004">Fig 4B</xref>) and higher number of vsiRNAs mapped to RNA3 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0244364.g005">Fig 5</xref>) may have been due to suppressed activity of RDR1 and co-expression of RDR6 during vsiRNA formation.
</p>
