<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Placing monomer units in an orderly fashion into a macromolecule may facilitate self-healing because upon mechanical damage, neighboring polymer chains return to their original conformations due to enhanced van der Waals interactions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. This approach is advantageous because it eliminates chemical and physical alterations and enables multiple recovery of thermoplastic polymers upon mechanical damage, thus expanding their functionality and sustainability. Obtaining materials with a longer life span also requires consideration of external environments to which polymers are exposed, for example, water. Hydrophobic nature of the majority of polymers though suggests that the presence of hydrophilic water should not impact self-healing properties. For that reason, to achieve water-induced self-healing, multilayered polyelectrolytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup> and redox-switchable supramolecular
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup> were proposed or sugar moieties
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> incorporated into polymer networks. Considering that the hydrophobic effect is critical in many diverse phenomena, from the cleaning of laundry to emulsion synthesis or the assembly of proteins into functional complexes, theoretical studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup> have taught us that this typically multifaced effect depends on whether hydrophobic molecules are individually isolated or reassembled into larger hydrophobic structures. For example, water molecules can readily participate in four H bonds with a single methane molecule, but in larger hydrophobic aggregates, such as polymers, hydration of water is significantly diminished
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. Here, we show that if a polymer is physically damaged resulting in a chain separation, water molecules may disrupt vdW interactions and participate in self-H-bonding, thus affecting self-healing. When mechanical load is removed, unfavorable polymer–water interactions within hydrophobic domains will lead to the expulsion of water from the system and rapid regeneration of polymer–polymer interactions due to enhanced interchain cohesive energies, thus leading to potentially faster self-repair.
</p>
