<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">Seed is the reproductive and the primary nutrient storage organ in many crop plants, and its developmental success or failure directly determines the final crop yield and seed quality, as well as whether genetic information can be successfully transmitted to the next generation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Crop seed development is terribly a complex biological process that involves many gene regulatory pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. An increasing body of evidence shows that miRNAs participate in the regulation of seed development in crop plants. To date, thousands miRNAs have been identified in the development of seed in multiple crop plants including rice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], maize [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], wheat [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], barley [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], soybean [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], peanut [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], 
 <italic>Brassica napus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], narrow-leafed lupin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], and common buckwheat [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] by using a high-throughput sequencing approach. These studies found that the expression of various miRNAs is extremely dynamic during seed development and some miRNAs are specifically expressed in seed, implying that miRNAs have very vital regulatory roles in seed development. In fact, a few miRNAs have been functionally demonstrated to play crucial regulatory roles in the seed development of model crop rice and a few other crops by negatively regulating their target genes expression. For example, miR159, miR160, miR397, miR398, and miR408 positively regulate rice grain size [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], while miR1432, miR156, miR167, miR396c, miR396e, miR396f, and miR530 have opposite roles in regulating the grain size [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Notably, the conserved role of miR408 and miR160 in regulating seed size was also found in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tobacco, and cotton, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. In addition to the role in seed size, miRNAs were also demonstrated to regulate nutrient accumulation in developing seed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. For instance, miR160 positively regulate starch accumulation in rice seed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. EgmiR5179 and csa-miR167A regulate the oil and linolenic acid biosynthesis in oil palm and 
 <italic>Camelina sativa</italic> seeds, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].
</p>
