<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">Tartary buckwheat (
 <italic>Fagopyrum tataricum</italic>) is an annual medicinal and edible crop, belonging to the eudicot family Polygonaceae [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. It is widely cultivated in Asia and Eastern Europe, especially in the mountainous areas of Southwest China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Tartary buckwheat seed is a good source of nutrients including starch, protein, dietary fiber, fatty acid (linoleic acid), and various minerals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Importantly, Tartary buckwheat seed also contains rich flavonoids especially rutin, which have been proved to be effective in preventing liver injury and especially inflammatory liver injury [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Therefore, it is of great significance to understand the molecular mechanism of Tartary buckwheat seed development, which will be helpful in high-yield and quality breeding of Tartary buckwheat [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. To date, several transcriptome analyses have been reported that examine the molecular mechanism of Tartary buckwheat seed development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. However, to our knowledge, no one has studied miRNAs in Tartary buckwheat, and miRNAs whether and how to regulate the development of Tartary buckwheat seed is largely unclear. In this study, we first examined the conserved evolution of miRNA biosynthesis in Tartary buckwheat compared to other plants through homology identification and phylogenetic analysis of miRNA biosynthesis genes. Then, we identified the known and novel miRNAs in the developing seed of Tartary buckwheat and predicted their target genes. Finally, we performed integration analysis between miRNA and mRNA expression to insight into the miRNA-mediated molecular mechanisms of Tartary buckwheat seed development and identified key miRNA-mRNA interaction pairs for Tartary buckwheat seed development. Our results provide valuable information for enhancing the understanding of the miRNA-mediated regulatory mechanism of Tartary buckwheat seed development and aid in the Tartary buckwheat seed improvement.
</p>
