<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Soil acidification with an increased Aluminum (Al) toxicity level is a major reason for forest dieback [
 <xref rid="B15-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Based on previous reports, there are two main mechanisms, viz. the exclusion mechanism and tolerance mechanism, proposed for Al stress resistance in plants. The exclusion mechanism mainly minimizes the occurrence of harmful interaction in the apoplast by hindering the entry of Al into the cytosol [
 <xref rid="B56-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The symbiotic role of ectomycorrhizal fungi in 
 <italic>Pinus</italic> species is also well known to naturally cope with the different biotic and abiotic stresses and increase immune response towards Al toxicity [
 <xref rid="B5-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. 
 <italic>S. luteus</italic>, an ectomycorrhizal fungus, is well-known for its growth habit in adverse soil conditions, i.e., saline soils, drought, and metal toxicity [
 <xref rid="B27-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. 
 <italic>S. luteus</italic> has been previously described to actively stimulate resistance towards high concentrations of Al by facilitating plant growth through reduced reactive oxygen species and accumulation of antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B66-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. This study aimed at uncovering the role of 
 <italic>S. luteus</italic> in developing resistance towards Al toxicity in 
 <italic>P. massoniana</italic> at the proteome level. 
</p>
