<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As a result of differential expression analysis, we identified 12 core Al responsive proteins viz. chaperonin CPN60-2, Cu-Zn-superoxide dismutase precursor, drought response protein, phosphoglycerate kinase 1, and 8 unknown proteins. Abiotic stress causes enhanced protein misfolding. However, chaperones are reputed for their function in assisting protein folding under stress conditions [
 <xref rid="B72-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Efficient protein repair systems and protein stability enable organisms to survive in stress conditions [
 <xref rid="B75-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. A study by Aremu et al. [
 <xref rid="B76-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] described the substantial effects of chaperons on protein folding, as an adaptive strategy under Al stress. Thus, we speculated that chaperonin CPN60-2 is an important Al-responsive protein in masson pine. Another core Al-responsive protein, phosphoglycerate kinase-1, has been reported with its significant impact on plant and regulation of metabolic processes under different abiotic stress conditions [
 <xref rid="B77-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Furthermore, Cu-Zn-superoxide dismutase precursor (CSD) gene is regulated under oxidative stress conditions [
 <xref rid="B79-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] due to the downregulation of miRNA. CSD protein was up-regulated under induced Al stress conditions in this study. The antioxidant system controls oxidative cellular damage under abiotic stress conditions, specifically under Al-stress conditions [
 <xref rid="B81-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Many studies have emphasized the positive regulation of oxidative stress by Al-induced genes in different plants [
 <xref rid="B81-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>].
</p>
