<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Proteomics insights into induced Al stress under SL-inoculation identified 198 specific differentially expressed proteins (DEPs). GO term classified these proteins as BP: response to stress stimulus, polyamine metabolic process, cellulose catabolic process, MF: metal ion binding, chlorophyll-binding, metabolic process, and hydrolase activity, CC: photosystem I &amp; II, and integral component of membrane. In Plants, the first steps of tolerance under stress conditions are the ability to promptly sense the stress and trigger appropriate biological responses [
 <xref rid="B85-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Furthermore, stress signals and intercellular communication are vital to withstand the stress and activate the stress-related genes [
 <xref rid="B85-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. The identified DEPs include some well-known abiotic stress-responsive proteins such as chlorophyll a-b binding protein, laccase, endoglucanase, and spermidine synthase [
 <xref rid="B87-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Differential regulation of chlorophyll a-b binding protein (
 <italic>TRINITY_DN46586_c4_g5</italic>) under LB-04 vs. LB-0 suggests its significant role in developing resistance in SL-inoculated 
 <italic>Pinus</italic> against Al stress. Another protein, endoglucanase (
 <italic>TRINITY_DN51146_c0_g2</italic>), was also up-regulated under LB-04 vs. LB-0. Endoglucanase promotes cell wall development via carbohydrate binding and cellulase activity [
 <xref rid="B91-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Remodeling of the cell wall in response to stress has been extensively studied [
 <xref rid="B93-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. The cell wall provides structural integrity, supports cell division and acts as the first defense line against stressful conditions such as Al stress [
 <xref rid="B97-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Putative spermidine synthase protein was also identified as specific DEPs in LB-04 vs. LB0. Sang et al. [
 <xref rid="B99-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] reported a positive effect of exogenous spermidine in tomato seedlings under abiotic stress conditions. Another report by Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="B100-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>] also suggested the involvement of spermidine in the tolerance towards abiotic stress conditions. Furthermore, NADH dehydrogenase [
 <xref rid="B101-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], glutathione-S-transferase [
 <xref rid="B103-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>], LRR receptor-like protein kinase [
 <xref rid="B105-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>], aspartic proteinase [
 <xref rid="B106-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>], soluble starch synthase 1 [
 <xref rid="B108-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>], T-complex protein [
 <xref rid="B73-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], purple acid phosphatase 1 [
 <xref rid="B110-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>], NHL repeat [
 <xref rid="B112-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>], glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase [
 <xref rid="B113-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>], SCF ubiquitin ligase [
 <xref rid="B115-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>], ankyrin repeat domain-containing protein 2B [
 <xref rid="B116-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>], and HYL1 [
 <xref rid="B117-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>] were also identified as specific DEPs in response to Al stress under SL-inoculation in this study. These proteins have been reported for their direct or indirect regulatory roles in plant responses towards biotic and abiotic stress conditions, including Al stress. Interestingly, the expression of some of the DEPs identified in this study (i.e., chlorophyll a-b binding protein, glucanase, purple acid phosphatase) has been found regulated by methyl-jasmonate treatment in rice [
 <xref rid="B118-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Likewise, Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B119-life-11-00177" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>] described jasmonate and aluminum crosstalk in tomato. Hence, Al sensing under 
 <italic>S. luteus</italic> inoculation in masson pine might induce the activation of JA pathway. Further study is required to understand the relationship between Al stress and jasmonic acid pathways under SL inoculation in masson pine.
</p>
