<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this work, three variants of AlSiMg cast alloys are assessed, namely permanent mould-cast Al7Si0.3Mg [
 <xref rid="B214-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>], high-pressure die-cast Al10Si0.3Mg [
 <xref rid="B131-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>] and additively manufactured (laser-beam melted, LBM) Al10Si0.3Mg [
 <xref rid="B131-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f069">Figure 69</xref> compares these three cast alloy variants in terms of their DSC cooling curves (A, B) and the resulting precipitation enthalpies and hardness after ageing (C, D). In the same way as for AlMgSi wrought alloys, two main reaction intervals are observed that are strongly overlapped. A broad HTR stretching over more than 100 K with a peak around 450 to 510 °C dominates over the entire cooling rate range considered. It can also be seen that DSC detects a nearly instantaneous onset of precipitation with the start of cooling i.e., nearly no undercooling is required for the reaction to start. Although a detailed experimental analysis of the nature of quench-induced precipitates has not been performed for these cast alloys, it can be assumed that precipitation of Si is important [
 <xref rid="B47-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], i.e., during relatively slow cooling, part of the dissolved Si will diffuse to the existing eutectic Si [
 <xref rid="B47-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. This explains the instantaneous start of precipitation with the onset of cooling, as no separate nucleation is required: Si phase formation can proceed via growth of the existing Si particles. The latter assumption fits perfectly with the findings of instantaneous growth of undissolved β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si in AlMgSi alloys [
 <xref rid="B148-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. In addition to Si, the formation of β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si is also likely to occur at high temperatures during slow cooling of AlSiMg cast alloys. Ref. [
 <xref rid="B47-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] reports on the nucleation of β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si phase particles on eutectic Si particles at slower rates, and the formation of β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si phase particles within the Al matrix at slightly faster cooling rates. It is likely that the formation of both Si and β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si contributes to the HTRs. β’-phase particles have also been assumed to precipitate during cooling [
 <xref rid="B47-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. It is likely that these semi-coherent precursor precipitates form during the LTRs, which have a peak at about 350 °C in the cast alloy variants.
</p>
