<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The genes encoding AAF are usually organized in one operon that encodes four distinct proteins (schematically depicted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1(a</xref>)). The gene 
 <italic>aggD</italic> encodes a chaperone protein, 
 <italic>aggC</italic> encodes an usher protein, whereas the structural genes 
 <italic>aggA</italic> and 
 <italic>aggB</italic> encode the major and the minor fimbrial subunit, respectively [
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], with AggB sitting at the tip of a polymer body formed by AggA subunits [
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. AAF are assembled using the chaperone-usher (CU) pathway, similar to various other types of fimbriae in Gram-negative bacteria [
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. We have recently performed a comparative characterization of virulence relevant properties of the Stx2-encoding phage-cured EHEC O104:H4 with other prototypical EAEC, including the very close relative EAEC 55989. Overall, EHEC O104:H4 displayed similar phenotypic characteristics to the other EAEC, with the notable exception that significantly more bacteria were found to be attached to cultured epithelial cells [
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, it was not clear, if the increased numbers of bacteria attached to cultured epithelial cells were due to other factors that are specifically encoded in EHEC O104:H4, differences in regulation and-/or expression of the AAF fimbriae, or if this phenotype could be attributed directly to different AAF/I properties. In order to phenotypically characterize AAF/III in comparison with AAF/I, we heterologously expressed AAF/I and AAF/III in AAF-negative EAEC 55989 derivative (EAEC 55989 
 <italic>agg</italic>3
 <sup>−</sup>) as well as AAF/IV and AAF/V, which are more distantly and more closely related to AAF/III than AAF/I, respectively. Expression of the AAF subtypes on the bacterial cell surface was confirmed by Western blot analysis and electron microscopy (EM). This further showed that the expression of all four AAF clusters resulted in autoaggregation and sedimentation of the aggregates in liquid culture, albeit at different kinetics. When incubated together, mixed aggregates were formed, but AAF-negative variants were not included, indicating that all tested AAF subtypes do not interact with other EAEC surface structures. Moreover, AAF-promoted biofilm formation by the different AAF subtypes was found to be temperature-dependent and correlated inversely with the observed autoaggregation phenotype. Finally, we show that AAF/I expressing EAEC strain 55989 
 <italic>agg</italic>3
 <sup>−</sup> formed larger bacterial clusters on HEp-2 cells, similar to what we have previously shown for the outbreak strain EHEC O104:H4 [
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
