<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">Our transcriptome analyses revealed that many transmembrane proteins are differentially expressed in the two granulosa cell subpopulations. For example, Claudin 1 (
 <italic>CLDN1</italic>) is stably expressed in Gp cells of F5 and F1 follicles (G5p:18.49, G1p: 18.76), whereas its level is much lower in Gd cells of F1 follicles (G5d:1.61, G1d:0.3). CLDN1 are small (20–27 kDa) transmembrane proteins. As one of the most important components of tight junctions, it may form a part of the paracellular barrier to control the flow of molecules in the intercellular space between epithelium cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. The high abundance of this gene in Gp cells supports the notion put forward by past studies that the existence of tight junction between Gp cells may help to prevent the incorporation of yellow yolk
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. In our study, another transmembrane protein, epithelial cell adhesion molecule (
 <italic>EpCAM</italic>), which is a transmembrane glycoprotein mediating Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-independent homotypic cell–cell adhesion in epithelial cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>, showed a higher abundance in Gp cells (G5p:29.02, G1p: 21.74) (G5d:7.54, G1d:0.56). EpCAM is involved in cell signaling, migration, proliferation and differentiation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, EpCAM shows the oncogenic potential via its capacity to upregulate c-myc, e-fabp, and cyclins A &amp; E
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. In line with the expression profile of the genes 
 <italic>CLDN1</italic> and 
 <italic>EPCAM</italic>, ADAMTS family members (
 <italic>ADAMTS9</italic>,
 <italic> ADAMTS15</italic>,
 <italic> ADAMTSL3</italic>) also showed similar differential expression profiles with a higher abundance in Gp cells. ADAMTS family members were reported to play important roles in connective tissue organization, coagulation and extracellular matrix remodeling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. In our study, ADAMTS family members 3 (
 <italic>ADAMTS3</italic>) showed the differential expression with a higher expression level in Gd cells. 
 <italic>TGFBI</italic> encodes an RGD-containing protein that binds to collagens which helps to modulate cell adhesion and serve as a ligand recognition sequence for several integrins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>, also showed a higher expression abundance in Gd cells. The gene encoding fibromodulin (
 <italic>FMOD</italic>), which participates in the assembly of the collagen fibers of the extracellular matrix and extracellular organization
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>, also showed differential expression in Gd and Gp cells. 
 <italic>CD151</italic>, as a cell surface glycoprotein which collaborate with integrins to regulate cell development, activation, growth and motility, showed a higher expression abundance in Gd cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. The differential expression of these genes in Gd and Gp cells strongly suggests that cell–cell junctions and extracellular matrix organization vary between Gd and Gp cells.
</p>
