<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">In this study, we also found that genes encoding zona pellucida (ZP) proteins are differentially expressed in Gp and Gd cells. The ZPs are glycoproteins and are deposited in the inner perivitelline membrane layer (PVL) between granulosa cells and oocyte, forming a three-dimensional network which play roles in oocyte protection and sperm recognition and binding
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. As shown in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, ZP3 showed a high abundance in the 4 groups (F5p: 14,379.31, F5d: 14,816.1, F1p: 82,661.9, F1d: 111,496.28). The high abundance of ZP3 concentrated in G1d cells concurs with a past report that lower protein content was detected in Gp cells by flow cytometry
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. As the most abundant protein in PVL, ZP3 may provide the structural support during ovulation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. In our study, ZP3 expression differs significantly between G1p and G1d cells. This finding suggests that ZP3 may contribute to PVL architectural diversification. In mammals, ZP3 is synthesized by oocytes and suggested to bind to sperm head in O-glycan-dependent manner, thus implicated in sperm recognition
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. Unlike mammalian oocytes, chicken oocytes are huge and their surface area may reach 35 cm
 <sup>2</sup>. Since the chicken germinal vesicle (GV) and 99% ooplasm concentrate to form a very small plaque called the GD, the accurate penetration of PVL by sperms and subsequent contact with the GD to fertilize the oocyte should be an event with a higher difficulty than in mammals. We speculated that ZP3 may be expressed at a concentration gradient to guide sperms via the PVL so as to reach the GD region. Like ZP3, ZP2 is also highly expressed in Gp cells (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). This finding is in line with previous reports that ZP2 concentrates in Gp cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. Given that ZP2 plays a role in secondary binding of sperm during fertilization in mice
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>, it is likely that ZP2 (G1p:8.62, G1d:0.22) (G5p:28.81, G5d:2.68) may play a critical role in sperm recognition and binding during fertilization in chicken as well.
</p>
