<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Generally, it is well known that following cell-specific stimulation, the resulting gene expression profiles measured using gene arrays are inadequate to predict protein expression and subsequent functional outcomes on a genomic scale, since interrelationships between mRNA and protein levels vary greatly due to post-transcriptional mechanisms, as well as post-translational modifications. Influencing factors such as the mRNA transcription rate, stability, translational regulation, along with protein activity and degradation serve as limiting factors and controlling elements in a given cell at the physiological level when interpreting the after effects of that cell-specific stimulus [
 <xref rid="B60-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. However, in our study, comparison of the expression profiles of certain genes and their corresponding protein abundance levels showed similar patterns following stimulation with AC EFs. Accordingly, enriched pathways and processes following analysis of the gene and antibody array data using the STRING database also showed consistent enrichment of similar biological processes and signaling pathways, further highlighting the balanced, steady state of the epithelial cells during AC EF stimulation [
 <xref rid="B62-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Additionally, antibody array data showed enrichment of various interconnecting signaling events due to the involvement of similar molecules in multiple pathways, which was not observed during gene array data analysis. Since electric stimulation is considered as a master regulator of regeneration-associated cellular networks [
 <xref rid="B27-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], stimulation with AC EFs also switches on several intracellular pathways, and thus can be implemented, upon further testing and validation at shorter time points, as a potential therapeutic approach for corneal tissue regeneration. 
</p>
