<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The quality of small RNA fractions was assessed using Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer with Small RNA Kit chip (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) and measured with Qubit RNA HS Assay Kits (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). One µg of total RNA was used to sequencing library construction with an Ion Total RNA-Seq Kit v2 (Thermo Fisher Scientific), according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Ion Xpress™ RNA-Seq Barcode Kit, which allows for multiplexed sequencing, was used for hybridization and ligation of RNA adapters. RNA reverse transcription and subsequent cDNA purification and library size selection were performed using Nucleic Acid Binding Beads. cDNA was PCR-amplified, followed by DNA purification and size selection. Amount and size distribution of the amplified DNA was determined using Bioanalyzer 2100 using a High Sensitivity DNA Kit (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA). The length of miRNA ligation products in barcoded libraries ranged between 94 and 114 bp. Template preparation for clonal amplification of up to four miRNA libraries at a concentration of 18 pM, and loading of the PI chip, were performed using Ion Chef instrument, with Ion PI™ Hi-Q™ Chef Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). An Ion Proton sequencer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) was used for sequencing. Unmapped bam files were converted into fastq files with a bamToFastq script from bedtools. Read mapping to known human miRNAs (according to miRBase release 22) and reads quantification were performed using miRDeep2.14. Data normalization and differential expression analysis were performed using DESeq2. Filtration for low-expression miRNAs and miRNAs genes with less than five sequencing reads in at least half of the samples were excluded. Fold change of expression (FC) calculated as ratio of the normalized read-count value in 
 <italic>USP8</italic>-mutated and 
 <italic>USP8</italic>-wt tumors was used as a measure of expression difference. Differentially expressed miRNAs were defined as those with |FC| &gt; 2 and adjusted 
 <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05.
</p>
