<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>TOL_1625 encodes a long-chain fatty acid transporter which is a member of the FadL family of proteins. Members of this family are responsible for the passive transport of hydrophobic compounds across the bacterial outer membrane (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">van den Berg et al., 2004</xref>). The first member of the FadL family was isolated from 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and characterized as a long chain fatty acid transporter (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Black et al., 1987</xref>). FadL shares some structural similarities with the first known bacterial alkane importer, AlkL, which is part of the 
 <italic>alkBFGHJKL</italic> operon in 
 <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> GPo1 (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">van Beilen et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Grant et al., 2014</xref>). They both possess a lateral transfer mechanism with high affinity substrate binding causing conformational changes in the N terminus that opens a channel for passive substrate diffusion, allowing the entry of hydrophobic molecules into the outer membrane through the opening in the barrel wall (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">van den Berg, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Grant et al., 2014</xref>). FadL homologs are present in many Gram-negative bacteria which are involved in the biodegradation of xenobiotics (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">van den Berg et al., 2004</xref>). These compounds face the same bacterial cell entry problems as long-chain fatty acids. This suggests hydrophobic compounds enter the cells by a mechanism like that employed for long chain fatty acids by FadL (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">van den Berg et al., 2004</xref>). This theory has been supported by biochemical data on other members of the FadL family including XylN, the xylene transporter from 
 <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic>, and TbuX, the toluene transporter from 
 <italic>Ralstonia pickettii</italic> PK01 (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Kahng et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Kasai et al., 2001</xref>). FadL homologs have also been detected in other OHCB, such as 
 <italic>A. dieselolei</italic> B-5, which has three outer-membrane proteins belonging to the FadL family shown to be involved in the selective transport of 
 <italic>n</italic>-alkanes (C
 <sub>8</sub>-C
 <sub>36</sub>) (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Lai et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Shao, 2014</xref>).
</p>
