<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Proteins that must reach the outer membrane need to be transported from the ribosome where they are synthesized to the inner membrane, where they have to be differentiated from inner-membrane proteins, then transported across the inner membrane into the periplasm, transported through the periplasm and finally assemble into the outer membrane (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Reusch, 2012</xref>). TOL_3187 is a member of the MMPL family. Members of this family are inner membrane multisubstrate efflux pumps, which belong to the RND (resistance-nodulation-cell-division) permease superfamily of transmembrane transporters (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Székely and Cole, 2016</xref>). They transport a range of different substrates including trehalose monomycolate, siderophores, phtiocerol dimycocerosate, sulfolipid-1, acylated trehaloses and mycolate ester wax (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Jain and Cox, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Seeliger et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Varela et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Pacheco et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">Wells et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Belardinelli et al., 2014</xref>). Substrate transport is driven by the proton motive force (PMF) of the transmembrane electrochemical proton gradient (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Chim et al., 2015</xref>). MMPL are not restricted to mycobacteria and have been found in related 
 <italic>Streptomyces</italic> and 
 <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Deshayes et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Letek et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Cano-Prieto et al., 2015</xref>). SCOOP analysis showed there is a relationship between the MMPL family and the SecDF family. The functional importance of SecDF in protein translocation across the inner membrane was previously shown 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> with SecD and SecF-deficient 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains severely defective in protein export (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Pogliano and Beckwith, 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Nouwen et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Hand et al., 2006</xref>). This demonstrated bacterial SecD and SecF are required for efficient protein translocation across the inner membrane. The relationship with the SecDF family suggests MMPL may also be involved in export of outer membrane proteins across the inner membrane.
</p>
