<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on analyses of the 685 proteins that were quantified in all eight samples, 40 proteins were identified that were significantly (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) up-regulated and 47 proteins were down-regulated in nuclei from D1 versus D2 MSNs. PCA carried out on all 685 quantified proteins separated the four D1 and four D2 samples into two mostly discrete clusters. Although we caution that with multiple test correction there were no significant differences in expression between proteins from D1 versus D2 nuclei, the observed differential expression of 87 proteins was highlighted further by hierarchical clustering analyses of these proteins. These analyses separated all eight samples into D1 and D2 clusters containing the 40 proteins that are up-regulated and the 47 proteins that are down-regulated in D1 versus D2 nuclei. To further characterize these two groups of differentially expressed proteins, each group of proteins was separately subjected to annotation enrichment analyses. Although the most significantly enriched cellular components (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) in the D1 nuclear fraction were the nucleus, nucleoplasm, and plasma membrane; the most significantly enriched components in the D2 fraction were the endoplasmic reticulum, nucleoplasm, and nucleus. The appearance of endoplasmic reticulum proteins in the D2 nuclear fraction may result from the membranes of the endoplasmic reticulum being continuous with that of the outer nuclear membrane. The finding that D2 dopamine receptor binding is one of the molecular functions that was significantly (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) enriched in the D2 nuclear fraction provides confirmation of the identity of the cell type of this nuclear fraction. Pathway enrichment analyses that were based on these 87 differentially expressed proteins suggested their association with addiction and neurological disorders. Hence, the phospholipase D signaling pathway, which has been linked to cocaine addiction and Alzheimer disease, was up-regulated in D2 cell type samples; while the calcium signaling pathway, which has been associated with both addiction and neurological disorders, was up-regulated in D1 cell type [
 <xref rid="B38-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. 
</p>
