<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Reproduction, one of the major factors significantly affecting profitability of sheep production, is a complicated physiological process and determined by the integrated hypothalamic-pituitary-ovarian axis in breeding season [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Reproductive traits like litter size directly determine benefit of sheep production, are controlled by poly-gene at the micro level. How to undertake at molecular level to improve reproduction, thereby serving macro production is a hotspot in recent years. 
 <italic>BMPRIB</italic>, 
 <italic>BMP15</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and 
 <italic>GDF9</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] are major fecundity genes which significantly influence sheep prolificacy. 
 <italic>FecB</italic> is a mutation in 
 <italic>BMPRIB</italic> occurring in base 746 from A to G, one copy of this mutation significantly increases ovulation rate in sheep about 1.5 and two copies by 3.0 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. To date, this mutation has been detected in diverse sheep species such as Booroola Merino sheep (Australia) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], Small Tail Han (STH) and Hu sheep (China) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Wherein STH sheep is a famous native breed with year-round estrus and high fecundity, being officially recognized as one of the polytocous breeds in China. The average litter size and lambing rate of STH sheep are 2.61, 286.5%, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. There are three genotypes based on effects of 
 <italic>FecB</italic> mutation in STH sheep, namely 
 <italic>FecB</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>BB</italic>
 </sup> (with two-copy 
 <italic>FecB</italic> mutation), 
 <italic>FecB</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>B</italic>+
 </sup> (with one-copy 
 <italic>FecB</italic> mutation) and 
 <italic>FecB</italic>
 <sup>++</sup> (with no 
 <italic>FecB</italic> mutation), which is closely correlated with litter size of ewes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Therefore, this breed can be used as a classic model for study molecular mechanism of 
 <italic>FecB</italic> gene regulation of reproductive traits in sheep.
</p>
