<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Long noncoding RNA (lncRNA) is polymerase II transcript with length longer than 200 nucleotides that lacks the protein coding ability, its expression has high tissue specificity and distributes in cytoplasm or nucleus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. LncRNA is proposed to be the largest transcript class in mammalian transcriptome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], less than 2% of mammalian genome actually code for protein, 70–90% is transcribed in some context as lncRNA, originally thought to be ‘transcriptional noise’ in genome. Subsequently, studies have gradually shown that lncRNA exerts important roles in various biological processes such as cell proliferation, apoptosis and differentiation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], signal transduction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], immune regulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In terms of reproduction, there have many reports on lncRNA. For example, Miao et al. (2017) compared transcripts in ovaries of low fecundity ewes and high fecundity ewes, found that differentially expressed (DE) lncRNA significantly enriched in the oxytocin signaling pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Then, Feng et al. (2018) identified 5 lncRNAs and 76 mRNAs in ovaries of Hu sheep with high and low prolificacy, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Yang et al. (2020) analyzed lncRNA and mRNA in male sheep pituitary and found that 5 candidate lncRNAs and their targeted genes enriched in growth and reproduction related pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Su et al. (2020) screened differential lncRNA through high-throughput sequencing, concluded that 
 <italic>XLOC-2222497</italic> and its target 
 <italic>AKR1C1</italic> could interact with progesterone in porcine endometrium for controlling pregnancy maintenance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. These studies indicated the presence and role of lncRNA in reproductive tissues. It is known that the sheep pineal gland as an important reproductive-related gland, that is closely related to hormone and signal transduction. However, studies on function of sheep lncRNA in this organ are limited.
</p>
