<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the nonmetallic catalysts for ORR, transition metal chalcogenides have been widely studied. For instance, Ru-based chalcogenide materials demonstrated good performance for ORR in direct methanol fuel cells (DMFC) when compared to Pt catalysts.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref158">158</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref506">506</xref>
 </sup> In particular, Ru–Se–Mo,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref507">507</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref510">510</xref>
 </sup> Ru–S,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref158">158</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref508">508</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref509">509</xref>
 </sup> Ru–Se,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref158">158</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref508">508</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref509">509</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref511">511</xref>
 </sup> and Ru–Te
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref158">158</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref508">508</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref510">510</xref>
 </sup> have been investigated. The EXAFS data discussed in these references demonstrated the presence of metallic Ru–Ru bonds; thus, the actual structure of the investigated catalysts can be described as a chalcogenide-decorated metallic Ru. In all cases, Ru–O bonds were also observed. However, these bonds were attributed to adsorbed oxygen species rather than the formation of oxides.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref508">508</xref>
 </sup> By performing 
 <italic>in situ</italic> XAS measurements at the Rh K-edge and the K-edges of the chalcogenide elements, it was concluded that only Ru species respond to the changes in the applied potential, suggesting that those are likely the active species. More specifically, a significant increase in Rh–O contribution was observed via 
 <italic>in situ</italic> EXAFS with increasing applied potential, and simultaneous reduction of the Rh–Rh coordination number and the corresponding bond length.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref158">158</xref>
 </sup> This effect is very pronounced in pure Ru electrodes, where the formation of oxides was observed at higher potentials.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref510">510</xref>
 </sup> The presence of the chalcogenides in Ru
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>Se
 <sub>
  <italic>y</italic>
 </sub> and Ru
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>Se
 <sub>
  <italic>y</italic>
 </sub>Mo
 <sub>
  <italic>z</italic>
 </sub> catalysts, however, suppresses the oxidation of the electrode and the formation of the inactive RuO
 <sub>2</sub> phase, ensuring better catalytic activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref510">510</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref511">511</xref>
 </sup> Stronger Ru–O interactions (suggested by a larger Ru–O coordination number or shorter Ru–O bond length) were observed in Ru–S
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref508">508</xref>
 </sup> and Ru–Te
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref510">510</xref>
 </sup> catalysts, explaining the lower activity of these catalysts.
</p>
