<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While promising for ORR, Ru-based materials are still expensive. Among various precious-metal-free catalysts for ORR, manganese-based oxides have attracted attention due to the high tunability of their structure and properties. At the same time, this diversity of possible structural motifs and valence states complicates the understanding of the actual active species and working mechanism of MnO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>-based catalysts. Commonly, the ORR activity of MnO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>-based materials is attributed to the cyclic redox reaction between Mn
 <sup>4+</sup> species to Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> species, where ORR occurs by oxidizing the Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> species continuously produced by the reduction of Mn
 <sup>4+</sup> species.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref512">512</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref515">515</xref>
 </sup> As a result, the coexistence and the ratio of Mn
 <sup>4+</sup> and Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> species seem to be the key for ensuring high ORR activity. Because of the high sensitivity of XANES to the Mn valence state, 
 <italic>in situ</italic> measurements at the Mn K-edge have been used to gain insight into the working mechanism of MnO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>-based catalysts. For example, the reduction of a MnO
 <sub>2</sub>-rich catalyst under ORR conditions was demonstrated through the linear combination analysis of Mn K-edge XANES data. High ORR activity was associated with a high MnO
 <sub>2</sub> content in the material.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref514">514</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref515">515</xref>
 </sup> The importance of coexisting Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> and Mn
 <sup>4+</sup> species was confirmed also by Park et al., where the intercalation of layered Mn oxides with graphene oxide resulted in a reduced (closer to 3+) oxidation state of Mn-based catalysts and improved ORR activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref516">516</xref>
 </sup> The importance of fine-tuning the Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> and Mn
 <sup>4+</sup> ratio was emphasized in Mn K-edge XANES studies of mullite-type SmMn
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>5-δ</sub> NPs prepared by laser irradiation of a SmMn
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>5</sub> micropowder suspension. Here, XANES data revealed that the concentration of oxygen vacancies and the ratio of Mn species in different oxidation states could be controlled by changing the laser energy. The maximal ORR activity was observed for an average Mn valence of ∼3.36.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref517">517</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, the formation of disordered Mn
 <sup>2+</sup>/Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> mixed oxides in electrodeposited MnO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> catalysts under ORR conditions was reported by Gorlin et al. based on the positions of the Mn K-edge XANES features and the Mn–O interatomic distances extracted from EXAFS data.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref513">513</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref518">518</xref>
 </sup> Recently, even higher ORR activities have been reported in Co
 <sub>1.5</sub>Mn
 <sub>1.5</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> catalysts,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref519">519</xref>
 </sup> where the reduction of Mn species from the +3/+4 state to +2/+3 state (as well as that of Co species from +3 to +2 state) has been suggested with increasing reaction time. (
 <xref rid="fig36" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig36" ref-type="fig">36</xref>
 </xref>). See also 
 <xref rid="sec6.3.6" ref-type="other">Section 
  <xref rid="sec6.3.6" ref-type="other">6.3.6</xref>
 </xref> for the discussion of Mn-based materials for bifunctional catalysts that combine activity for ORR and OER reactions.
</p>
