<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study also revealed that the majority of differentially used PAS between species are located in 3' UTRs. We showed that, across species, increased intronic PAS usage is associated with a modest increased mRNA expression levels, while increased 3' UTR PAS usage is correlated with a modest decrease in mRNA expression. In a previous study, we found that human alternative polyadenylation quantitative trait loci (apaQTL) alleles associated with increased intronic PAS usage were correlated with 
 <italic>decreased</italic> mRNA expression levels (
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Mittleman et al., 2020</xref>). This is not the first molecular phenotype wherein a within-species study revealed alternative regulatory models compared to an inter-species analysis. For example, Pai et al. reported tissue-specific differential methylation to be almost exclusively inversely correlated with gene expression patterns between human and chimpanzee (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Enard et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Pai et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Weber et al., 2007</xref>), whereas Banovich et al. discovered genetic variation associated with DNA methylation variation that was both directly and inversely correlated with expression quantitative trait loci (eQTLs). At this time, we cannot provide evidence for a mechanistic explanation for these contradictory observations. We hypothesize the following: Transcripts terminating in introns are likely subject to nonstop decay (NSD). By studying APA variation within humans, we probably captured the effects of intronic termination. Across species, however, increased intronic PAS may simply track the overall expression level of the gene. Specifically, increased usage of intronic PAS may result in truncated isoforms that do not contain 3' UTR 
 <italic>cis</italic> regulatory elements that would normally signal mRNA decay. If these truncated isoforms are no longer targets of mRNA decay, this could cause some of these genes to appear upregulated. We hypothesize that the within-species effects related to NSD were likely overshadowed by inter-species differences, which typically have much larger effect sizes than differences observed within a population (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Housman and Gilad, 2020</xref>).
</p>
