<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?OLF?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arch Toxicol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arch Toxicol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Archives of Toxicology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0340-5761</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-0738</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7961173</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3011</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00204-021-03011-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Toxicogenomics and Omics Technologies</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcriptional profiling of the response to the trichloroethylene metabolite <italic>S</italic>-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine revealed activation of the eIF2&#x003b1;/ATF4 integrated stress response in two in vitro placental models</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8637-1731</contrib-id><name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>Elana R.</given-names></name><address><email>elkinela@umich.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9605-6337</contrib-id><name><surname>Bakulski</surname><given-names>Kelly M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5882-4569</contrib-id><name><surname>Colacino</surname><given-names>Justin A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5334-972X</contrib-id><name><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>Dave</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kilburn</surname><given-names>Brian A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5904-9325</contrib-id><name><surname>Armant</surname><given-names>D. Randall</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5993-2799</contrib-id><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>Rita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.214458.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000086837370</institution-id><institution>Department of Environmental Health Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Michigan, </institution></institution-wrap>1415 Washington Heights, Ann Arbor, MI 48109-2029 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.214458.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000086837370</institution-id><institution>Department of Epidemiology, </institution><institution>University of Michigan, </institution></institution-wrap>Ann Arbor, MI USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.214458.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000086837370</institution-id><institution>Department of Nutritional Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Michigan, </institution></institution-wrap>Ann Arbor, MI USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.254444.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1456 7807</institution-id><institution>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, </institution><institution>Wayne State University School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Detroit, MI USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.254444.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1456 7807</institution-id><institution>Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology, </institution><institution>Wayne State University School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>Detroit, MI USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2021</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Trichloroethylene (TCE) is an industrial solvent and widespread environmental contaminant. Although TCE exposure is prevalent, epidemiological studies of TCE exposure associations with adverse birth outcomes are inconclusive. Prior studies show that the TCE metabolite <italic>S</italic>-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine (DCVC) exhibits toxicity in a placental cell line. In the current study, genome-wide gene expression and gene set enrichment analyses were used to identify novel genes and pathway alterations in the HTR-8/SVneo human trophoblast cell line and human placental villous explants treated with DCVC at concentrations relevant to human exposures. In the cells, concentration- and time-dependent effects were observed, as evidenced by the magnitude of altered gene expression after treatment with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC versus 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M, and 12-h versus 6-h of treatment. Comparing the two models for the transcriptional response to 12-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment, no differentially expressed genes reached significance in villous explants, whereas 301 differentially expressed genes were detected in HTR-8/SVneo cells compared with non-treated controls (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;LogFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]). GSEA revealed five upregulated enriched pathways in common between explants and cells (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Moreover, all 12-h DCVC treatment groups from both models contained upregulated pathways enriched for genes regulated by the ATF4 transcription factor. The overrepresentation of ATF4 regulation of differentially expressed genes indicated activation of the integrated stress response (ISR), a condition triggered by multiple stress stimuli, including the unfolded protein response. DCVC-induced ISR activation was confirmed by elevated eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation, ATF4 protein concentrations, and decreased global protein synthesis in HTR-8/SVneo cells. This study identifies a mechanism of DCVC-induced cytotoxicity by revealing the involvement of a specific stress signaling pathway.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1007/s00204-021-03011-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Trichloroethylene</kwd><kwd>S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-l-cysteine (DCVC)</kwd><kwd>Placenta</kwd><kwd>Integrated stress response</kwd><kwd>ATF4</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000066</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>P42 ES017198</award-id><award-id>P30 ES017885</award-id><award-id>P30 ES020957</award-id><award-id>R01 ES025574</award-id><award-id>R01 ES025531</award-id><award-id>R01 ES028802</award-id><award-id>T32 ES007062</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>Elana R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakulski</surname><given-names>Kelly M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colacino</surname><given-names>Justin A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>Rita</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000062</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R01 DK107535</award-id><award-id>T32 DK071212</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>Elana R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>Dave</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000049</institution-id><institution>National Institute on Aging</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R01 AG055406</award-id><award-id>P30 AG053760</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Bakulski</surname><given-names>Kelly M.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100011415</institution-id><institution>Office of the Vice President for Research, Wayne State University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Trichloroethylene (TCE) is a volatile organic compound that belongs to a class of chlorinated hydrocarbons with potent solvent properties. Throughout the twentieth century, the chemical was widely used as a dry cleaning solvent and vapor metal degreaser with little attention paid to disposal methods (Chiu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2013</xref>; Waters et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">1977</xref>). Despite substantial efforts in recent decades to clean up and prevent further TCE environmental contamination, legacy pollution of soil and groundwater remains, as evidenced by TCE detection in thousands of hazardous waste sites across the United States (U.S. EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2019a</xref>; U.S. EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">2019b</xref>). Due to ongoing usage and persistent environmental contamination, occupational and community-based TCE exposure in humans is widespread.</p><p id="Par3">TCE exposure during pregnancy is associated with adverse birth outcomes, including multiple measures of restricted (or reduced) fetal growth (Forand et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2012</xref>; Ruckart et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2014</xref>). In rats, TCE treatment during mid-gestation decreases fetal weight and elevates oxidative stress biomarkers in the placenta (Loch-Caruso et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2019</xref>). Despite links between TCE exposure and elevated risks of adverse birth outcomes in humans and rats, the underlying toxicological mechanisms of these associations have scarcely been explored, as previously reviewed by Elkin et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2020c</xref>). The placenta, the multifaceted organ that supports the fetus during pregnancy, is at risk of TCE-induced toxic injury because it is capable of metabolizing TCE to its reactive metabolites (Burton and Fowden <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2015</xref>), and is likely in direct contact with the chemical and its metabolites circulating in maternal blood (Laham <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">1970</xref>). Indeed, one study reported TCE blood concentration levels of approximately 2&#x000a0;mg/L in females volunteers exposed to 100&#x000a0;ppm TCE for 4&#x000a0;h via inhalation (Fisher et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1998</xref>).
</p><p id="Par4">Placental development during the first trimester is especially vulnerable to xenobiotic insult because the first trimester encompasses a critical window for establishing adequate maternal blood supply to the placental bed. Fetal origin extravillous trophoblasts are specialized placental cells that play a critical role in placentation. During the first trimester, these cells acquire an invasive phenotype and migrate into the maternal decidua from the chorionic villi. Once in the decidua, the cells facilitate remodeling of the spiral arteries necessary for increased maternal blood supply to the placenta (Burton and Jauniaux <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2015</xref>; Pijnenborg et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">1981</xref>). Furthermore, as the pregnancy progresses to the second and third trimesters, the extravillous trophoblasts form cell columns at the tips of chorionic villi that anchor the villi to the maternal basal plate and stabilize them in the intervillous space (Kaufmann and Castellucci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1997</xref>). Dysfunctional trophoblasts may jeopardize the maternal blood supply to the placenta and result in abnormal placental development. Moreover, placental insufficiency, a condition caused in part by inadequate spiral artery remodeling, may contribute to intrauterine growth restriction (Burton and Jauniaux <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2015</xref>), preterm birth (Morgan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2014</xref>) and pre-eclampsia (Brosens et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1972</xref>; Steegers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2010</xref>).</p><p id="Par5">The TCE glutathione conjugation-derived metabolite <italic>S</italic>-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine (DCVC) induces cytotoxicity in HTR-8/SVneo, a placental cell line that models first-trimester extravillous trophoblasts (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020a</xref>; Hassan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2016</xref>). However, prior mechanistic studies of DCVC-induced cytotoxicity in placental cells have focused on specific molecular signaling pathways and biological responses, including reactive oxygen species generation, lipid peroxidation, inflammatory responses, mitochondrial dysfunction and apoptotic signaling (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Hassan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2016</xref>). Application of comprehensive discovery approaches such as genome-wide gene expression profiling allows for the unbiased characterization of toxicity mechanisms without relying on individual pre-selected pathways and/or processes.</p><p id="Par6">In the current study, high throughput RNA sequencing was used to quantify genome-wide DCVC-induced differential gene expression in two different first trimester placental models in vitro. The HTR-8/SVneo cells, with an extravillous trophoblast phenotype, were used to evaluate transcriptional responses in this specific critical cell type. Villous explants from first trimester placentae were used to evaluate transcriptional responses in intact villi tissue with multiple interacting cell types, including extravillous trophoblasts. Both of these placental models have been used extensively to study placental biology and pathophysiology (Huckle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2017</xref>; Orendi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2011</xref>) and to study the effect of xenobiotics on the placenta (Kovo and Golan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2008</xref>). Subsequently, gene set enrichment testing was used to identify biological pathways and/or processes targeted by DCVC and re-evaluate previously identified pathways. The most notable pathway identified was the endoplasmic reticulum unfolded protein response (UPR), a cellular response designed to rid cells of accumulated misfolded proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). Upon further characterization of genes enriched in this pathway, the specific involvement of the integrated stress response (ISR), a condition triggered by the UPR and other stress stimuli, was revealed (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>). Because the ISR is characterized by eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation, causing protein synthesis restriction and selective activation of transcription factor 4 (ATF4)-mediated upregulation of amino acid biosynthesis and transport genes (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>), additional experiments were conducted to confirm ISR activation by measuring global protein synthesis, phosphorylation levels of eIF2&#x003b1; and protein concentrations of ATF4 as key regulators of ISR activation. Lastly, cell cycle progression and proliferation were determined in the cell model to evaluate functional consequences of DCVC treatment and ensure no acute cellular toxicity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="Par7">The overall experimental design is outlined in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The effects of DCVC on gene expression were determined in placental villous explants and HTR-8/SVneo cells using RNA sequencing and gene set enrichment analysis. Follow-up experiments were conducted to verify the affected genes and pathways in HTR-8/SVneo cells.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Overall experimental design. HTR-8/SVneo cells and villous explant tissues were exposed to 0, 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 6 or 12&#x000a0;h. RNA sequencing and gene set enrichment analysis were performed to identify novel genes and pathways affected by DCVC treatment. Follow-up experiments were conducted to verify the affected genes and pathways in HTR-8/SVneo cells</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Tissue and cell culture reagents</title><p id="Par8">Cell and tissue culture reagents including RP mine and without phenol red, advanced DMEM/F-12 culture medium, 10,000 U/mL penicillin and 10,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL streptomycin (P/S) mixed solution, Antibiotic&#x02013;Antimycotic (Anti-Anti) mixed solution and fetal bovine serum (FBS) were purchased from Gibco, a division of Thermo Fisher Scientific (Waltham, MA, USA). Phosphate buffered saline (PBS) and 0.25% trypsin were purchased from Invitrogen Life Technologies (Carlsbad, CA, USA).</p><p id="Par9">The TCE metabolite <italic>S</italic>-(1, 2-dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine (DCVC) was synthesized as a powder by the University of Michigan Medicinal Chemistry Core according to published procedures (McKinney et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">1959</xref>). Purity of 98.7% was measured using high-performance liquid chromatography analysis. A stock solution of 1&#x000a0;mM DCVC was prepared by dissolving DCVC powder in PBS. The chemical structure was confirmed periodically by nuclear magnetic resonance analysis MI 1640 culture medium with <sc>l</sc>-glutamine performed at the University of Michigan Biochemical Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Core. The DCVC stock solution was stored in aliquots at&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="Par10">HTR-8/SVneo cells, a gift from Dr. Charles H. Graham (Queen&#x02019;s University, Kingston, Ontario, Canada), were cultured as previously described (Graham et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1993</xref>; Hassan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2016</xref>; Tetz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2013</xref>). Briefly, cells were cultured between passages 78&#x02013;84 in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% P/S at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> humidified incubator. Cells were cultured in RPMI 1640 growth medium with 10% FBS and 1% P/S prior to and during experiments to ensure optimal cell growth as previously described by Graham et al. (Graham et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1993</xref>). Cells were grown to 70&#x02013;90% confluence at least 24&#x000a0;h after plating prior to use in any experiments. For gene expression experiments, cells were seeded at a density of 800,000 cells per well in 6-well cell culture plates. 24 h later, cells were treated with RPMI 1640 complete medium alone (control) or complete medium plus DCVC diluted to a final concentration of 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M for 6 or 12&#x000a0;h. Four independent biological replicate experiments were performed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Cell line validation</title><p id="Par11">Microsatellite genotyping via fragment analysis was performed using AmpFLSTR Identifiler Plus PCR Amplification Kit run on an 3730XL Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems; Waltham, MA, USA). DNA for 8 tetranucleotide repeat loci and the Amelogenin sex determination marker were identified. The short tandem repeat profile generated for our cells was compared to the short tandem repeat profile for cells identified as HTR-8/SVneo (ATCC<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> CRL-3271&#x02122;) by ATCC<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (2015) (Manassas, VA, USA). The short tandem repeat profile was an exact match: CSF1PO: 12, D13S317: 9,12, D16S539: 13D5S818: 12, D7S820: 12, TH01: 6,9.3, vWA: 13,18, TPOX: 8, Amelogenin sex determination marker: X (ATCC 2015).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Explant tissue procurement and culture</title><p id="Par12">First-trimester placental tissues (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5; 4 male and 1 female) ranging in gestational age from 8.4 to 11&#x000a0;weeks (mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98&#x000a0;weeks) were acquired as discarded tissues at the time of termination at a Michigan family planning clinic with Institutional Review Board approval (Wayne State University IRB# 013515MP4E) and written informed consent obtained by collaborating Wayne State University physicians. Tissues were transported to the laboratory in ice-cold PBS. Chorionic villi were dissected under a microscope into approximately 20&#x000a0;mg (wet) segments and cultured in DMEM/F12 supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% Anti-Anti. The villous segments were floated one per well in clear 24-well cell culture plates and allowed to acclimate in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> humidified incubator for 24&#x000a0;h, as previously described (Bolnick et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2017</xref>). For gene expression experiments, the culture medium was removed and explants were treated with fresh DMEM/F12 complete medium alone (control) or complete medium plus DCVC diluted to a final concentration of 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M, and then cultured for an additional 12&#x000a0;h. Five independent biological replicate experiments were performed using placentae from 5 different donors on different days. Each experiment was conducted with a placenta from a different donor, and villous explants from the same placenta were assigned randomly to the non-treated control and DCVC-exposed groups.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cell and tissue toxicant treatment</title><p id="Par13">Prior to each experiment, a DCVC stock solution aliquot was thawed in a 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C water bath and then diluted in DMEM/F12 supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% Anti-Anti (villous explants) or RPMI 1640 supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% P/S (HTR-8/SVneo) to final concentrations of 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC. PBS alone was used as the 0&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC negative control. These concentrations of DCVC were chosen because we previously demonstrated that they did not induce cytotoxicity at the time points used in the current study (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Hassan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2016</xref>). Moreover, these concentrations are comparable to the average concentration of the DCVC precursor <italic>S</italic>-(1,2-dichlorovinyl) glutathione (DCVG), 13.4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M, measured in the serum of female volunteers exposed to 100&#x000a0;ppm of the parent compound, TCE, by inhalation for 4&#x000a0;h (Lash et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">1999</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Cell cycle phase determination</title><p id="Par14">HTR-8/SVneo cells were seeded at a density of 400,000 cells per well in a 6-well plate and allowed to adhere for 24&#x000a0;h prior to treatment. Cells were treated for 12&#x000a0;h with medium alone (control) or DCVC (10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M). The percentage of cells in each well in G<sub>1</sub>/G<sub>0</sub>, S, and G<sub>2</sub>/M phases were measured using the Cell Cycle Phase Determination Kit (Cayman Chemical; Ann Arbor, MI, USA) and flow cytometry, performed according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. This assay uses propidium iodide (PI) to label DNA. Briefly, after exposure, cells were treated with 0.25% trypsin&#x02013;EDTA and incubated for 2&#x000a0;min to detach adherent cells from the substrate. After incubation, trypsin was deactivated with FBS-containing medium, and the suspended cells were transferred to 5-ml round-bottom fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) tubes. Cells were washed twice with 1&#x000a0;ml of assay buffer, resuspended in 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of cell fixative assay buffer solution, and chilled for 2&#x000a0;h at &#x02212; 20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. After fixation, cells were washed and resuspended in 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l PI staining solution, incubated for 30&#x000a0;min at room temperature, and transported to the University of Michigan Flow Cytometry Core for analysis. Cell phases were quantified using a LSRFortessa Flow Cytometer (BD Biosciences; San Jose, CA, USA). Quantification and dye-based visualization were performed using BD FACSDiva Software (BD Sciences). Cell aggregates and cellular debris were excluded using the forward scatter (FSC) and side scatter (SSC) modes and the analysis was performed using 10,000 events per sample. PI was detected using the 488&#x000a0;nm laser.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Cell proliferation measurement</title><p id="Par15">HTR-8/SVneo cells were seeded at a density of 10,000 cells per well in a 96-well plate and allowed to adhere for 24&#x000a0;h. Cells were then treated with medium alone (control) or DCVC (10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) in quintuplicate for 6 or 12&#x000a0;h. CyQUANT<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Cell Proliferation Assay (Invitrogen) was used to quantify cell proliferation. The stain specifically binds to cellular DNA, and the fluorescence is proportional to the number of cells. The assay was performed according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Briefly, dye binding solution was prepared by diluting CyQUANT<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> reagent in Hank&#x02019;s Balanced Salt Solution (HBSS). After exposure to DCVC, the growth medium was removed and CyQUANT<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> dye binding solution was added to each well. Cells were incubated for 1&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. After incubation, fluorescence was measured (excitation: 485&#x000a0;nm; emission 530&#x000a0;nm) using a SpectraMax M2e Multi-Mode Microplate Reader (Molecular Devices).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>RNA isolation</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>HTR-8/SVneo cells</title><p id="Par16">After exposure, cells were scraped and lysed with RLT lysis buffer containing beta-mercaptoethanol. Cell lysates were homogenized using QIA shredders (Qiagen), and mRNA was extracted using the RNeasy Plus Mini Kit (Qiagen) following the manufacture&#x02019;s recommended protocol. RNA concentrations were determined with a Nanodrop 1000 Spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific) and stored at &#x02212; 80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. RNA was transported on dry ice to the University of Michigan Advanced Genomics Core for further processing. Four independent experiments were performed. Each treatment group within a given experiment was performed in triplicate. RNA from triplicates were pooled according to the treatment group within the experiment. In total, RNA was analyzed from 24 cell samples: 4 replicates at 2 time points and 3 treatment groups.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Placental villous explants</title><p id="Par17">After the treatment period, each explant was transferred to a 1.5-mL microcentrifuge tube, lysed in QIAzol reagent and homogenized in a TissueLyser LT (Qiagen) for 5&#x000a0;min at 50&#x000a0;Hz, using one 3.2&#x000a0;mm stainless steel bead per tube. mRNA was extracted using the miRNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommended protocol. RNA was eluted in RNase-free water. RNA concentrations were determined with a Nanodrop 1000 Spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific) and stored at &#x02212; 80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. RNA was transported on dry ice to the University of Michigan Advanced Genomics Core for further processing. Each treatment group within a given experiment (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5) was performed in triplicate (3 separate villous explants from the same placenta). RNA from triplicates were pooled according to the treatment group within the experiment. In total, RNA was analyzed from 10 explant samples (5 placentas and with 2 treatment groups).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>RNA sequencing</title><p id="Par18">At the University of Michigan Advanced Genomics Core, mRNA concentrations and quality were evaluated using a Bioanalyzer instrument (Agilent; Santa Clara, CA, USA). Stranded sequencing libraries for RNA isolated from HTR-8/SVneo cells were prepared with the TruSeq Stranded mRNA Library Prep Kit (lllumina; San Diego, CA, USA). Libraries were sequenced (on one lane) using single-end 50 cycle reads on a HiSeq 4000 sequencer (lllumina). The average total number of reads per sample for HTR-8/SVneo cells was 26,515,09. Stranded sequencing libraries for RNA isolated from villous explants were prepared with the KAPA Stranded RNA-Seq Kit with RiboErase (Roche; Basel, Switzerland). Libraries were multiplexed (on two lanes) and sequenced using single-end 50 cycle reads on a HiSeq 4000 sequencer (lllumina). The average total number of reads per sample was 13,368,165.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>RNA sequencing data analyses</title><p id="Par19">The Flux high-performance computer cluster at the University of Michigan was used for computational analysis. Sequencing read quality was assessed using FastQC (Andrews <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>). Reads were aligned to the human genome using STAR (Dobin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2013</xref>), with the options &#x0201c;outFilterMultimapNmax 10&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;sjdbScore 2&#x0201d;. Aligned reads were assigned to GRCh37 genes using featureCounts (Liao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2014</xref>). HTR-8/SVneo had 85.38% uniquely mapped reads. Villous explants had 82.46% uniquely mapped reads. Prior to differential gene expression testing, genes with mean read counts-per-million less than four (HTR-8/SVneo) or five (explants) across all samples were filtered out and excluded from the analysis to reduce dispersion due to low expression levels. After filtering, 12,855 (HTR-8/SVneo) or 13,972 (explants) genes were included in the analyses. Data were normalized using the trimmed mean of M values (TMM) method (Robinson and Oshlack <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2010</xref>). Differential gene expression testing was performed using the edgeR package (version 3.1) for R statistical computing (Robinson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2010</xref>). Quasi-likelihood general linear modeling was used for differential gene expression testing (Lun et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2016</xref>). For HTR-8/SVneo cells, comparisons were made within each time point between 0 (control) and 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, respectively, adjusting for experiment day as a covariate using the glmQLFit function in edgeR. For villous explants, comparisons were made between 0 (control) and 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, adjusting for a placental donor as a covariate. The log<sub>2</sub>fold change/fold change values reported for each gene were calculated from normalized (TMM method) gene expression counts averaged from each matching treatment/exposure replicate and directly compared to the average normalized gene expression counts of time-matched controls. Genes were considered differentially expressed between non-treated and treated samples with an adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 using the Benjamini&#x02013;Hochberg false discovery rate (FDR) method (Benjamini and Hochberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1995</xref>). DCVC-induced upregulation&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3-fold or downregulation&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;&#x02212; 1.3-fold are denoted throughout the results section. These fold-change (FC) values equate to log<sub>2</sub> fold-change (logFC)&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 (upregulation) or&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;&#x02212; 0.35 (downregulation). We selected a relatively inclusive log<sub>2</sub> fold change threshold to facilitate discussion of our genome-wide discovery results. This selection was a balance of prioritizing genes with larger comparative gene expression changes, while still conducting a thorough evaluation of differential gene expression. Moreover, we conducted sensitive analyses to demonstrate that using a more conservative logFC cutoff does not change the overall conclusions of the paper (Suppl. Table 7).</p><p id="Par20">Multidimensional scaling (MDS) plots constructed from RNA expression data were used to observe how samples, treated or non-treated from each respective experiment, clustered on relevant covariates including treatment, treatment duration and experimental day (HTR-8/SVneo cells), or treatment, sex, gestational week, and donor placenta (explants). Student&#x02019;s t-test (for two groups) or one-way ANOVA (for three or more groups) were used to test for associations between covariates and MDS dimension 1 or 2.</p><sec id="Sec15"><title>Correlation and linear regression testing</title><p id="Par21">To compare the effects of DCVC across time (6 vs. 12&#x000a0;h), dose (10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M vs. 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC), or model system (villous explants vs. HTR-8/SVneo), differential gene expression patterns were tested for correlation. Across all genes tested, Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficients were calculated and linear regression models were fitted. Comparisons were tested within each time point between non-treated controls and 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC using logFC values for 12,855 genes. Likewise, comparisons were tested between non-treated controls and each DCVC concentration for 6 or 12&#x000a0;h of exposure, also using log FC values for 12,855 genes. Lastly, comparisons were tested between placental villous explants and HTR-8/SVneo cells each exposed to 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h using logFC values for 11,912 commonly expressed genes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Gene set enrichment analyses</title><p id="Par22">To identify biological pathways and processes impacted by DCVC treatment, gene set enrichment analyses were performed using GSEA software (Mootha et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2003</xref>; Subramanian et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2005</xref>). For each gene set within a specified Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB, RRID: SCR_016863, version 7.0) curated collection, we used GSEA pre-ranked analyses to compute permutation-based tests that calculate a Normalized Enrichment Score (NES) and statistical FDR (Benjamini and Hochberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1995</xref>; Liberzon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2011</xref>). Additionally, the GSEA analyses returned a list of enriched genes for each gene set based on differential gene expression. The enriched gene list for a gene set was derived from all genes annotated to that gene set. Here, the hallmark gene set collection was used in the analyses because it represents well-defined biological pathways, processes and states with strong gene expression concordance and reduced redundancy often seen within other collections (Liberzon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2015</xref>). To conduct separate analyses for HTR-8/SVneo cells and placental villous explants, 12,855 (HTR-8/SVneo) or 13,972 (villous explants) genes included in the differential gene expression tests, respectively, were pre-ranked according to the logFC value for each gene. All genes (regardless of FDR or log<sub>2</sub>fold change values) thus, cutoffs do not impact the enriched pathways. We used 1000 permutations to test for enrichment within each of the hallmark gene sets. Because our genes were ranked based on logFC values, the magnitude of the NES above or below 0 corresponds directly with DCVC-induced up-regulation or down-regulation, respectively, of an enriched pathway or process. Gene sets representing an FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were considered significantly enriched (positive or negative).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Evaluation of temporal patterns in regulation of gene expression in HTR-8/SVneo</title><p id="Par23">Differentially expressed genes with a logFC magnitude difference&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 were grouped together by treatment based on temporal expression patterns (upregulated, downregulated or no change) for the two treatment durations (6 and 12&#x000a0;h). There were a total of 8 groups within each DCVC concentration: consistent responders (up&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;up and down&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;down) temporary responders (up&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;down, and down&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;up) early responders (down&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;no change and up&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;no change), late responders (no change&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;up and no change&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;down. Groups that contained&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;100 genes were tested for enrichment on the Enrichr platform (RRID: SCR_001575) (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2013</xref>; Kuleshov et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2016</xref>) for transcription factors (TRRUST) (Han et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2018</xref>) and histone modifications (ENCODE-2015) (Davis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2018</xref>; Encode Project Consortium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Enrichment testing and visualization of ATF4 gene targets from HTR-8/SVneo RNA sequencing analysis</title><p id="Par24">Because ATF4-driven transcriptional activity is a key indicator of ISR activation, ATF4 gene targets, were tested for overrepresentation among DCVC-induced differentially expressed genes. Individual ATF4 gene targets were identified from a mouse model ChIP-seq analysis and included in our study (Han et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>). Two additional ATF4 gene targets, <italic>PMAIP1 and PSPH</italic>, were also included (Sharma et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2018</xref>; Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2018</xref>; Zhao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">2014</xref>). Genes regulated by ATF4 (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;383) were tested for enrichment in DCVC-treated HTR-8/SVneo genes with significant differential expression (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;LogFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]). ATF4 mouse target genes were converted to human homologues using the biomaRt package (Durinck et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2009</xref>). ATF4 target gene enrichment tests were performed using the phyper function (hypergeometric test) (R Core Team <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2019</xref>). To visualize significantly enriched individual differential gene expression for ATF4 targets from the RNA sequencing analyses, a heatmap displaying the logFC levels of treated compared to control samples, along with a hierarchical clustering diagram were generated using the heatmap.2 function in the gplots package (Warnes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Western blotting analyses</title><p id="Par25">HTR-8/SVneo cells were seeded at a density of 400,000 cells per well in a clear 6-well culture plate and allowed to adhere for 24&#x000a0;h. Cells were treated with medium alone (control) or DCVC (20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M) for 12&#x000a0;h. Cells were lysed in RIPA lysis buffer containing both protease and phosphatase inhibitors or protease inhibitors alone and then centrifuged at 14,000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Lysates were heated with loading buffer at 85&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;min. Samples were loaded into commercially available Novex 4&#x02013;20% Tris&#x02013;Glycine Mini Gel cassettes (Invitrogen) and proteins were separated by polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis run at 140&#x000a0;V for 1.5&#x000a0;h. SeeBlue Plus2 pre-stained protein standard (Invitrogen) was used as a reference for protein molecular weight. After separation, proteins were transferred to nitrocellulose membranes at 75&#x000a0;V for 4&#x000a0;h at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Membranes were first blotted with Revert Total Protein Stain (Li-Cor Biosciences) and washed with Revert wash. Membranes were then blotted at room temperature using ATF4 (molecular weight 49; catalog no. 11815; Cell Signaling Technologies; RRID: AB_2616025), and eukaryotic initiation factor 2 alpha subunit -phosphorylated (p-eIF2&#x003b1;) or non-phosphorylated (eIF2&#x003b1;) [molecular weight 38; catalog nos. 3597 or 9722; Cell Signaling Technologies; Research Resource Identifier (RRID): AB_ 390740 and AB_ 2230924]. Antibody complexes were detected by Alexa Fluor anti-mouse and anti-rabbit fluorescent-conjugated antibodies (Invitrogen) and visualized using an Odyssey CLx image scanner (Li-Cor Biosciences; Lincoln, NE, USA). Blots were quantified using LI-COR<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Image Studio software (version 5.2) and normalized to Revert Total Protein Stain (Li-Cor Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Measurement of protein synthesis</title><p id="Par26">HTR-8/SVneo cells were seeded at a density of 10,000 cells per well in a black clear-bottomed 96-well plate and allowed to acclimate for 24&#x000a0;h. Cells were treated with medium alone (control) or DCVC (10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M) for 6 or 12&#x000a0;h. Protein synthesis was measured with a Protein Synthesis Assay Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific) according to the manufacture&#x02019;s recommended protocols. This assay utilizes cell-permeable O-propargyl-puromycin (OPP), which halts the translation of polypeptide chains by incorporating into the C-terminus. Briefly, cells were incubated with OPP solution for 2&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, fixed, and incubated with FAM-Azide solution (FAM-Azide, copper sulfate and ascorbic acid) for 30&#x000a0;min in the dark at room temperature. After incubation, protein synthesis was measured fluorescently (excitation: 485&#x000a0;nm; emission 535&#x000a0;nm) using a SpectraMax M2e Multi-Mode Microplate Reader (Molecular Devices; Sunnyvale, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Statistical analysis for non-RNA sequencing experiments</title><p id="Par27">Western blotting, protein synthesis measurement, cell cycle determination, and proliferation experiments were performed independently and repeated a minimum of three times. When applicable, technical replicates were averaged within each experiment and these values were analyzed using one-way or two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey&#x02019;s post-hoc test for comparison of means. GraphPad Prism software version 7 was used for statistical analysis (GraphPad Software Inc.; San Diego, CA, USA). Data are expressed as means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;stand error of the means (SEM). <italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;number of independent experiments. <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec23"><title>Effect of DCVC on cellular proliferation and cell cycle progression in HTR-8/SVneo cells</title><p id="Par28">We evaluated key biological processes as indicators of acute cytotoxicity after exposure to 0&#x02013;20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for up to 12&#x000a0;h in the HTR-8/SVneo cell line. We previously reported that 12-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment did not cause cell death in the same cell line (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2020b</xref>). Here, we extended those findings by showing that the maximal 12-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment did not cause significant expression changes in genes that regulate apoptosis (Suppl. Table 1). Moreover, there were no significant DCVC-induced changes in cell cycle progression (Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;1), proliferation (Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;2) or the majority of genes that regulate these cellular functions (Suppl. Table 2). These results suggest that the concentrations and time durations used in this study did not cause overt toxicity in the cell model, likely due to biological resilience at these stages.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Effects of DCVC on placental HTR-8/SVneo gene expression</title><p id="Par29">In order to evaluate the effects of DCVC on the first trimester placental extravillous trophoblasts, RNA sequencing analyses were performed on HTR-8/SVneo cells to measure differential gene expression between treated cells and controls. Average LogFC of expression levels for comparisons between all treated versus control samples are displayed in a heatmap in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Genes were ordered based on hierarchical clustering. In MDS diagrams depicting all samples plotted on relevant covariates, clustering by treatment duration and replicate were observed (Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;3). The replicate covariate (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.84&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;04</sup>) was associated with MDS dimension 1, while treatment duration (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.03&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;11</sup>) was associated with MDS dimension 2.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Top logFC expression levels for comparisons between treated versus control samples. HTR-8/SVneo cells were treated with 0 (control), 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 6 or 12&#x000a0;h. Heatmap depicts expression levels for the 40 genes with the largest magnitude logFC (up and downregulated) from each of the following comparisons: control vs. 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC (6&#x000a0;h), control vs. 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC (6&#x000a0;h), control vs. 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC (12&#x000a0;h) and control vs. 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC (12&#x000a0;h)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec25"><title>Concentration-dependent differential gene expression after 6-h DCVC treatment</title><p id="Par30">Comparison of altered gene expression in cells exposed to 10 versus 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 6&#x000a0;h was conducted by calculating pairwise correlation coefficients of logFC estimates. Differential changes in gene expression relative to control were strongly correlated for cells exposed to 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC versus 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC after a 6-h treatment [<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.51, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;15</sup>] (Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;4a). Furthermore, for genes that met the FDR criterion for significant differential gene expression (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and had a logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3], 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment-induced larger magnitude altered gene expression compared with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, indicating a concentration-dependent response (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Effects of 6-h DCVC treatment on HTR-8/SVneo gene expression. HTR-8/SVneo cells were treated with 0 (control), 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 6&#x000a0;h. Differential gene expression was analyzed with the edgeR package for R using quasi-likelihood general linear modeling. <italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 independent experiments. <bold>a</bold> Spaghetti plot depicting concentration-dependent expression levels for genes meeting FDR and logFC criteria. Blue dots represent individual genes differentially expressed (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC. Lines connecting blue dots to green dots represent the same respective genes with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M expression levels. <bold>b</bold> Venn diagram depicting overlap in differentially expressed genes (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) at 6&#x000a0;h, between 0 (control) vs.10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M and 0 vs. 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC. Volcano plots comparing differential gene expression between non-treated (controls) cells and 6-h DCVC-treated cells are depicted for: <bold>c</bold> 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC and <bold>d</bold> 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC. Genes were considered differentially expressed with FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Genes fulfilling the following criteria are denoted by color: FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 only (light pink), logFC magnitude&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] only (dark pink), and FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC magnitude&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] (red). Upregulated and downregulated gene sets from the MSigDB hallmark collection were identified through GSEA as enriched after treatment with <bold>e</bold> 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC or <bold>f</bold> 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC. Relevant characteristics of enriched gene sets are reported as: FDR, biological pathway categories and normalized enrichment score (NES). Gene sets are ordered according to magnitude of NES and were considered enriched with an FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">Both 10 and 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment in cells for 6&#x000a0;h caused differential gene expression with some overlap. For example, the only gene that met both criteria (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) for significant differential gene expression with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M, 5&#x02032;-aminolevulinate synthase 1 (<italic>ALAS1)</italic> (0.37 logFC [1.3 FC], FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.15&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;03</sup>)<italic>,</italic> was also differentially expressed with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M (0.37 logFC [1.3 FC], FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.51&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;04</sup>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). The 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment group yielded an additional 276 genes that had a logFC magnitude difference&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] but did not meet the FDR criterion (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c, Suppl. Table 3). Consequently, 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M treatment for 6&#x000a0;h demonstrated the smallest transcriptional response out of all the comparisons made for HTR-8/SVneo cells. Whereas 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment for 6&#x000a0;h yielded 7 differentially expressed genes that met FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 criterion only, an additional 354 genes had a logFC magnitude difference&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] only. Moreover, a total of 12 genes met both criteria (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d, Suppl. Table 3). Among the genes that met both criteria, the highest magnitude differentially expressed genes between 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M-treated and controls were oxidative stress-induced growth inhibitor <italic>(OSGIN1)</italic> (0.91 logFC [1.9 FC], FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.036), tripartite motif-containing 16-like <italic>(TRIM16L)</italic> (0.63 logFC [1.5 FC], FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.036) and glutathione-specific gamma-glutamylcyclotransferase 1 (<italic>CHAC1</italic>) (0.62 logFC [1.5 FC], FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.015) (Suppl. Table 3). Overall, these results indicate an increase in the number of genes differentially expressed with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, compared to 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M treatment.</p><p id="Par32">Genes differentially expressed by 6-h DCVC treatment were also enriched in pathways, as identified by GSEA. Although 6&#x000a0;h DCVC treatment yielded no pathways that were upregulated with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, two pathways were downregulated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>e). Treatment with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC upregulated one pathway and downregulated six pathways (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>f). Of the six downregulated pathways, four were involved in embryonic development, the most common category. Representative pathways in this category include epithelial-mesenchymal transition (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212; 1.97, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.001) and myogenesis (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212; 1.79, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.004). Other categories represented among downregulated pathways included immune response (2) proliferation (1) and cellular organization (1). The overall pattern of pathways affected by DCVC treatment for 6&#x000a0;h consisted primarily of the downregulation of pathways associated with embryonic development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Concentration-dependent differential gene expression after 12&#x000a0;h DCVC treatment</title><p id="Par33">In order to evaluate patterns in gene expression caused by 12-h DCVC treatment, correlation of expression levels across DCVC treatment concentrations (10 versus 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M), were evaluated. Changes in gene expression levels (relative to control) were strongly correlated for cells exposed to 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M versus 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC after a 12-h treatment [<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.67, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;15</sup>] (Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;4b). Furthermore, for genes that met the FDR criterion for significant differential gene expression (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and had a logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3], 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment-induced larger magnitude altered gene expression compared with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, further indicating a concentration-dependent response (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Effects of 12-h DCVC treatment on HTR-8/SVneo gene expression. HTR-8/SVneo cells were treated with 0 (control), 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h. Differential gene expression was analyzed with the edgeR package for R using quasi-likelihood general linear modeling. <italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 independent experiments. <bold>a</bold> Spaghetti plot depicting concentration-dependent expression levels for genes meeting FDR and logFC criteria. Blue dots represent individual genes differentially expressed (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M treatment. Lines connecting blue dots to green dots represent the same respective genes with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M expression levels. <bold>b</bold> Venn diagram depicting overlap in differentially expressed genes (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) at 12&#x000a0;h, between 0 (control) vs.10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M and 0 vs. 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC. Volcano plots comparing differential gene expression between non-treated (controls) cells and 12-h DCVC-treated cells are depicted for: <bold>c</bold> 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC and <bold>d</bold> 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC. Genes were considered differentially expressed with FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Genes fulfilling the following criteria are denoted by color: FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 only (light pink), logFC magnitude&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] only (dark pink), and FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC magnitude&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] (red). Upregulated and downregulated gene sets from the MSigDB hallmark collection were identified through GSEA as enriched after treatment with <bold>e</bold> 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC or <bold>f</bold> 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC. Relevant characteristics of enriched gene sets are reported as FDR, pathway categories and normalized enrichment score (NES). Gene sets are ordered according to magnitude of NES and were considered enriched with an FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Gene sets with an asterisk indicate they that the pathways contained ISR/ATF4-regulated enriched genes (detailed information found in suppl. table 6)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig4a_HTML" id="MO4"/><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig4b_HTML" id="MO40"/></fig></p><p id="Par34">Similar to 6-h results, both 10 and 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment for 12&#x000a0;h caused significant differential gene expression with substantial overlap. For example, the 15 genes that met both criteria (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) for significant differential gene expression with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, were also differentially expressed with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). Additionally, 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment yielded 17 differentially expressed genes that met FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 criterion only, and 373 genes had a logFC magnitude difference&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] only (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c, Suppl. Table 4). Compared to 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M, 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment increased the number of genes with altered expression, yielding 526 differentially expressed genes that met FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 criterion only, 436 genes with a logFC magnitude difference&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] only, and 301 genes that met both criteria (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d, Suppl. Table 4). Among the genes that met both criteria, 113 were upregulated and 188 were downregulated. The three genes with the largest magnitude logFC included, inhibin subunit beta (<italic>INHBE)</italic> (3.71 logFC [13 FC], FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.00&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;04</sup>), <italic>CHAC1</italic> (2.55 logFC [5.9 FC], FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.25&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;09</sup>) and sodium- and chloride-dependent glycine transporter 1 (<italic>SLC6A9</italic>) (1.81 logFC [3.0 FC], FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.46&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;04</sup>) (Suppl. Table 4). Although more downregulated genes met both FDR and logFC criteria, the upregulated genes had larger magnitude differential gene expression.</p><p id="Par35">Multiple enriched biological and molecular signaling pathways connected to differential gene expression were upregulated by 12-h DCVC treatment. Ten micromolar treatment upregulated 2 pathways (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e). Twenty micromolar treatments upregulated 9 pathways, 5 of which were involved in response to stress stimuli (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f). Representative pathways included unfolded protein response (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.36, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.001) and mTORC1 signaling (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.16, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.001). Moreover, 12&#x02013;79% of individual genes enriched within each of these pathway gene sets were targets of the ATF4 gene, which codes for a key transcription factor associated with ISR, a branch of the UPR. (Suppl. Table 6). In addition to the response to stress stimuli, upregulated pathways also involve metabolic processes (4), immune processes (2) and proliferation (1).</p><p id="Par36">Likewise, DCVC treatment for 12&#x000a0;h downregulated numerous biological and molecular signaling pathways. With 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, 6 pathways were downregulated, half of which were associated with the most common category, embryonic development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e). Twenty micromolar DCVC treatment downregulated 13 pathways (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f). Similar to 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC, the majority of these pathways (7) were associated with embryonic development. Representative pathways included epithelial&#x02013;mesenchymal transition (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212; 2.12, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), myogenesis (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212; 1.66, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.021) and hedgehog signaling (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212; 1.61, Other categories represented among the pathways downregulated with 12-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment included proliferation (3), cellular organization (2) and response to stress stimuli (2). Summarizing the overall pattern of pathways affected by DCVC treatment, pathways involved in cellular response to stress stimuli were upregulated and pathways related to embryonic development were downregulated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Time-dependent differential gene expression after 10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment</title><p id="Par37">In addition to concentration-dependent DCVC effects, altered gene expression associated with treatment duration was investigated. Comparison of gene expression changes in cells exposed for 6 versus 12&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC was evaluated by calculating pairwise correlation coefficients of logFC estimates. The overall differential gene expression levels (relative to control) were moderately correlated by time for both 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment [<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.14, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;15</sup>] (Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;5a) and 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment [<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.24, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;15</sup>] (Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;5b). Moreover, differentially expressed genes with a logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] and FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 after 12-h treatment, had larger expression changes than 6-h treatment, indicating time-dependent responses for both concentrations tested (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a, c). For 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M treatment, the only gene significantly differentially expressed (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) with 6-h DCVC treatment, <italic>ALAS1</italic>, was also differentially expressed with 12-h treatment along with 14 additional genes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). Likewise, among the 12 genes differentially expressed after 6-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment, 10 genes were also differentially expressed after 12-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). Moreover, there were 2 genes exclusively differentially expressed with 6-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M treatment and 289 genes with 12-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M treatment.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Time-dependent differential gene expression after DCVC treatment in HTR-8 SVneo cells. Comparison of differential gene expression across DCVC treatment durations (6 versus 12&#x000a0;h) was evaluating by calculating pairwise correlation coefficients of logFC estimates (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;15</sup>). Spaghetti plot depicting time-dependent expression levels for differential expressed genes meeting FDR and logFC criteria (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) for <bold>a</bold> 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC and C) 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment. Tan dots represent individual genes differentially expressed (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) with 12-h treatment. Lines connecting yellow dots to tan dots represent the same respective genes with 6-h expression levels. Venn diagrams depicting overlap in differentially expressed genes (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35[FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) between 6 and 12&#x000a0;h DCVC treatment for: <bold>b</bold> 0 (control) vs.10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC and <bold>d</bold> 0 (control) vs. 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par38">Time-dependent differential gene expression was further investigated by evaluating temporal patterns in the regulation of gene expression. When grouped by chronological expression patterns, the majority of genes with a logFC magnitude&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3], fit into one of the four different groups consisting of early and late responders: that is, differential expression (up or downregulated) at one time point and unchanged expression at the other time point. Each of these groups contained&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;100 genes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). These results indicate a pattern of nonlinearity in gene expression over time. Furthermore, the no change&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;upregulated groups were enriched for the ATF4 transcription factor for both 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M (enriched odds ratio: 26, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.51&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>) and 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC (enriched odds ratio: 23, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.84&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>). Additionally, the no change&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;downregulated group for 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M was enriched for two transcription factors and one histone modification that regulate gene expression during embryonic development: transcription factors PAX6 (enriched odds ratio: 8, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.28&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;2</sup>) and SMAD3 (enriched odds ratio: 7, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.54&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;2</sup>), and histone tri-methylation site H3K27me3 (enriched odds ratio: 23, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.18&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;10</sup>). The other 4 groups consisting of temporary and consistent responders-genes with expression logFC magnitude&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3], at both 6 and 12&#x000a0;h (up and/or down-regulated)&#x02014;each contained&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;50 genes with no enrichment for specific regulation of gene expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Temporal patterns in regulation of gene expression in HTR-8/SVneo cells. Differentially expressed genes with logFC magnitude&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3], regardless of FDR, were grouped together by treatment based on chronological expression patterns (upregulation, downregulated or no change) for the two treatment durations (6 and 12&#x000a0;h). There were a total of 8 groups for: <bold>a</bold> 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC and <bold>b</bold> 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC consistent responders (up&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;up and down&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;down), temporary responders (up&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;down, and down&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;up), early responders (down&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;no change and up&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;no change), and late responders (no change&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;up and no change&#x02009;&#x02192;&#x02009;down). Groups that contained&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;100 genes were tested for enrichment on the Enrichr platform for transcription factors (TF) and histone modifications (HM). The enrichment odds ratio is abbreviated EOR. TF and HM were considered to be significantly enriched with an FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>DCVC effect on ISR-associated ATF4 regulation of gene expression in cells</title><p id="Par39">Because ATF4-driven transcriptional activity is a key indicator of UPR/ISR activation, ATF4 gene targets, previously determined elsewhere (Bao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2016</xref>; Han et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>; Quiros et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2017</xref>; Shpilka and Haynes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2018</xref>), were tested for overrepresentation among DCVC-induced differentially expressed genes using a statistical enrichment test. Of the 301 differentially expressed genes (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) resulting from exposure to 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h, 15.6% (47 genes) were identified as ATF4 gene targets, reflecting a statistically significant overrepresentation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.52&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;22</sup>). Of the 47 ATF4 gene targets, 44 were upregulated and 3 were downregulated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]). These results support ISR activation as a major response in HTR-8/SVneo cells to DCVC exposure.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>DCVC effect on ISR-associated ATF4 regulation of gene expression in HTR-8/SVneo cells. Because ATF4 transcriptional regulation is a key regulator of the ISR, ATF4 gene targets were tested for overrepresentation among DCVC-induced differentially expressed genes using a statistical enrichment test. <bold>a</bold> Venn diagram depicting overlap between the number of ATF4 gene targets and genes differentially expressed (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35[FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) after a 12-h exposure to 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC compared with control (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.52&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;22</sup>). <bold>b</bold> Heatmap visualizing hierarchical clustering and logFC expression of 47 genes differentially expressed (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35[FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]), after exposure to 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h. Expression levels of other comparisons were included for reference purposes. <bold>c</bold> Visualization of <italic>ATF4</italic> expression, along with the same 47 significantly expressed ATF4 and ATF4&#x02009;+&#x02009;CHOP gene targets grouped by function and cell fate, with single gene-level logFC displayed. Genes displayed in blue are regulated by ATF4 alone, whereas genes displayed in salmon are co-regulated by ATF4 and CHOP</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig7a_HTML" id="MO7"/><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig7b_HTML" id="MO70"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">To further characterize the specific roles of individual ATF4 gene targets during ISR activation, the <italic>ATF4</italic> gene plus the 47 ATF4-regulated genes with an FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and magnitude logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] (up or down) were grouped by function with single gene-level logFC displayed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c). Most of the ATF4-regulated genes are involved in various biological processes necessary for cellular compensation to DCVC-induced stress. Notably, 5 amino acid transporter genes were significantly differentially expressed: <italic>SLC1A4, SLC1A5, SLC6A9,</italic> and <italic>SLC7A11</italic> (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c). Contrarily, some of the ATF4-regulated genes control biological processes that contribute to cell death. Moreover, many of these genes are co-regulated by dimerization with C/EBP homologous protein (CHOP), another transcription factor which is itself regulated by ATF4 (Han et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>; Hu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2018</xref>; Su and Kilberg <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2008</xref>). Particularly, 9 amino acid biosynthesis genes were differentially expressed at a significant level: <italic>AARS, ASNS, CARS, GARS, MARS, SARS, TARS</italic> and <italic>YARS</italic> (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;+&#x02009;logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c)<italic>.</italic> These findings suggest complex ISR signaling in the cells involving both compensation and cell death.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Validation of DCVC-induced integrated stress response in HTR-8/SVneo cells</title><sec id="Sec30"><title>eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation and ATF4 protein levels</title><p id="Par41">Because the majority of gene sets positively enriched by 12-h exposure to DCVC contained substantial core enrichment of ISR-associated genes in HTR-8/SVneo cells, we verified DCVC-induced ISR activation in cells using western blot analysis to measure phosphorylation levels of eIF2&#x003b1; and protein concentrations of ATF4, key regulators of ISR activation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Exposure to 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h increased the ratio of phosphorylated to non-phosphorylated eIF2&#x003b1; protein by 61% compared to non-treated controls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.031), indicating ISR activation. Furthermore, DCVC increased ATF4 protein concentrations by more than fourfold compared to controls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>b, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.027), consistent with activation of the ISR.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>DCVC effect on principle proteins involved in ISR activation. HTR-8/SVneo cells were treated with 0 (control) or 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h. Western blotting was used to measure eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation and ATF4 protein levels by a blot scanning system as described in the methods section. Graphical representation of: <bold>a</bold> relative eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation and <bold>b</bold> relative ATF4 protein concentrations normalized to total protein. Bars represent means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM. Data were analyzed with student t-test. Asterisks indicate significant difference compared to control: *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. <italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4 independent experiment, with 3 replicates per treatment in each experiment. Representative western blot images for <bold>c</bold> eIF2&#x003b1;/eIF2&#x003b1; and <bold>d</bold> ATF4 (All western blots are included in Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;7)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>DCVC effect on global protein synthesis</title><p id="Par42">We measured global protein synthesis attenuation, a principal functional feature of ISR signaling through phosphorylation of eIF2&#x003b1;. Although protein synthesis was not significantly altered after a 6-h exposure to DCVC, treatment with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h significantly attenuated protein synthesis 37% compared with controls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0003). The effect of 12-h treatment with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC was not statistically significant compared with controls.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>DCVC effects on global protein synthesis. HTR-8/SVneo cells were treated with 0 (control) or DCVC (10 or 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) for 6 or 12&#x000a0;h. Protein synthesis was measured with O-propargyl-puromycin (OPP) and 5 FAM-azide fluorescent staining quantified by plate reader. Bars represent means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM. Data were analyzed by two-way ANOVA (interaction between time and treatment, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.019) with posthoc Tukey multiple comparisons. Plus sign indicates significant difference compared to control and 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DCVC within same time point: <sup>+</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. <italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 independent experiments for each time point, with 4 replicates per treatment in each experiment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Effects of DCVC on placental villous explant gene expression</title><p id="Par43">To further characterize the effects of DCVC treatment on differential gene expression in placenta, RNA sequencing analysis was performed on another first trimester in vitro model, villous explants-a model that retains the native cells and tissue structure of the villi functional unit (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>; Suppl. Table 5). In MDS diagrams depicting samples plotted on relevant covariates, clustering by donor placenta, sex, and gestational week were observed (Suppl Fig.&#x000a0;6). Gestational week (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.00&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>) and placental donor (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.00&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>) were associated with MDS dimension 1. Gestational week (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.00&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>), and placental donor (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.00&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>) were associated with MDS dimension 2. Twelve-hour 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment altered gene expression levels in villous explants by a magnitude logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.3] for 2684 genes, compared to non-treated controls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>a). Among these genes, 1499 were upregulated and 1185 downregulated. Although differential expression for many genes surpassed the logFC criterion, as indicated, no genes met the primary false discovery rate criterion (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Effects of DCVC on placental villous explant gene expression. First-trimester placental villous explants were treated in vitro with 0 (control) or 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h. Differential gene expression was measured with edgeR using quasi-likelihood general linear modeling. <italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 independent experiments, each performed with tissue obtained from a different placental donor. <bold>a</bold> Volcano plot comparing differential gene expression between non-treated and DCVC-treated villous explants. No genes were differentially expressed (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Genes fulfilling the following criteria are denoted by dark pink color: logFC magnitude&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]. <bold>b</bold> Upregulated and downregulated gene sets from the MSigDB hallmark collection identified through GSEA as enriched after DCVC treatment. Gene sets are ordered according to the magnitude of normalized enrichment score (NES) and were considered significantly enriched with an FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Gene sets with an asterisk indicate that the pathways contained ISR/ATF4-regulated enriched genes (detailed information found in suppl. Table 6). Columns within grid denote biological categories to which gene sets belong (indicated by black square)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p><p id="Par44">Despite no gene-specific expression levels meeting the FDR criterion, gene set enrichment analysis identified enriched biological and molecular signaling pathways (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Five pathways were upregulated and each of these involves a cellular response to stress stimuli (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>b, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Representative pathways included: TNF&#x003b1; signaling via NFKB (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.60, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001), p53 pathway (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.93, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002) and unfolded protein response (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.91, FDR&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002). Furthermore, similar to HTR-8/SVneo cells, 8&#x02013;31% of individual genes enriched within each pathway gene set are specifically regulated by ATF4 (Suppl. Table 6). Despite the lack of significant differential expression for individual genes (FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), these results reflect a collective transcriptional response to DCVC exposure.</p><sec id="Sec33"><title>Relationship between placental villous explants and HTR-8/SVneo ATF4-regulated differential gene expression</title><p id="Par45">In addition to conducting separate evaluations of DCVC-induced differential gene expression in HTR-8/SVneo cells and explants, a comparison of altered gene expression across the two models was evaluated by calculating pairwise correlation coefficients of logFC estimates. Differential expression for all dually expressed genes between cells and tissues was correlated [<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.18, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;15</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>a). A separate pairwise comparison of logFC values for the 383 ATF4-regulated genes targets in HTR-8/SVneo cells versus explants further revealed that the two models were more strongly correlated with ATF4-regulated gene expression [<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;9</sup>] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>b), than all genes. These results support ISR activation in both models.<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Relationship between placental villous explants and HTR-8/SVneo differential gene expression. In order to characterize the relationship between differential gene expression in first trimester villous explants and HTR-8/SVneo cells exposed to 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h, respectively, Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic>) were calculated for the pairwise comparison of logFC values, either for all dually expressed genes (11,913), or ATF4 gene targets only (383). Displayed are correlation plots of logFC in gene expression between tissue and cells for 0 (control) vs. 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for: A) All genes (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;15</sup>), or B) ATF4 gene targets only (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;9</sup>). Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficient values are shown on each respective correlation plot and trend lines are displayed in red</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig11_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec35"><title>Concentration- and time-dependent DCVC effects in HTR-8/SVneo</title><p id="Par46">In the current study, the HTR-8/SVneo cell line was used the evaluate DCVC concentration- and time-dependent effects on gene expression patterns in placental cells. Both 6-h and 12-h differentially expressed genes demonstrated larger magnitude altered gene expression with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment compared to 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M, indicating a concentration-dependent response. Likewise, genes differentially expressed by 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M and 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC had larger expression changes with 12-h, compared to 6-h, indicating a time-dependent response. These results are consistent with several of our previous studies that demonstrated DCVC time- and concentration-dependent effects on mitochondrial dysfunction (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>) and molecular apoptotic signaling (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec36"><title>DCVC-induced upregulation of the integrated stress response</title><p id="Par47">In agreement with overall concentration- and time-dependent effects, the upregulated UPR pathway was enriched with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M and 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment. Moreover, evaluation of temporal patterns revealed that the groups of late responder genes upregulated by 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M and 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC were enriched for the ATF4 transcription factor, specifically indicating activation of the ISR. When ISR activation is triggered at the cellular level by stress stimuli, including the PERK branch of the UPR, the principal initiating event is the phosphorylation of the translation initiation factor eIF2&#x003b1; (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>). Furthermore, in order for cellular recovery to occur from stress-induced homeostatic perturbations, eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation concomitantly suppresses global CAP-dependent protein translation while allowing for transcription and translation of selected stress response genes with open read frames in their promotors; namely the central ISR regulatory transcription factor ATF4 (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>; Walter and Ron <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2011</xref>; Wortel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2017</xref>). Indeed, further verification of ISR activation in HTR-8/SVneo cells&#x02014;beyond differential gene expression&#x02014;demonstrated DCVC-induced increased eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation, global attenuation of protein synthesis, and elevation of ATF4 mRNA and protein concentrations, confirming ISR activation, as summarized in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>.<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Summary of proposed DCVC-induced activation of the Integrated Stress Response. DCVC-induced mitochondrial dysfunction activates one or more of the eIF2&#x003b1; kinases. Kinase(s) phosphorylate eIF2&#x003b1;. Phosphorylated eIF2&#x003b1; activates transcription and translation of ATF4 and causes global protein attenuation. ATF4 transcription factor up-regulates many genes involved in biological processes necessary to restore homeostasis. ATF4 also up-regulates transcription factor CHOP, which then interacts with ATF4 to activate transcription of genes involved in cell death signaling</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="204_2021_3011_Fig12_HTML" id="MO12"/></fig></p><p id="Par48">During initial ISR activation, eIF2&#x003b1; is phosphorylated by one or more of the four enzymes in the eIF2&#x003b1; kinase family, each of which responds to different stress stimuli: GNC2 (amino acid deprivation), PKR (viral infection), HRI (heme deficiency and ROS), and PERK (endoplasmic reticulum and mitochondrial stress) (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>). In the present study, because we previously measured elevated amino acid concentrations with 12-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020a</xref>), GNC2 is likely not the source of eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation. Although not directly tested here, previous evidence suggests that mitochondrial dysfunction, which is closely associated with ER stress (Malhotra and Kaufman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2011</xref>), may be the primary stimulus driving the DCVC-induced ISR, most likely activated by eIF2&#x003b1; kinases HRI and/or PERK (Quiros et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2017</xref>; Shpilka and Haynes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2018</xref>). Specifically, we previously reported that 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC decreases mitochondrial-dependent basal, maximum, and reserve oxygen consumption rates, decreased ATP-linked respiration and coupling efficiency, increased proton leak, and dissipated mitochondrial membrane potential in HTR-8/SVneo cells (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>; Hassan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2016</xref>). Moreover, it is well established that mitochondria are the key target of DCVC toxicity in kidney proximal tubular cells (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2001</xref>; Lash and Anders <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1987</xref>; Lash et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2003</xref>; van de Water et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">1993</xref>; van de Water et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1994</xref>; Xu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2008</xref>). The ATF4-mediated gene expression pattern we observed in HTR-8/SVneo cells closely resembles the mitochondrial stress signature response reported in a multi-omics study by Quiros et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2017</xref>), including up-regulation of 9 amino acid biosynthesis and 5 transport genes. Moreover, we previously reported elevated SLC1A5 protein concentrations with 12-h 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC in HTR-8/SVneo cells (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020a</xref>). Together, the available evidence suggests that mitochondrial dysfunction is likely a major stimulus driving DCVC-induced ISR activation.</p><p id="Par49">Molecular signaling through the ISR has a degree of complexity that allows for tight regulation and tailored response. Although the ISR largely promotes an adaptive, pro-survival program through attenuation of global protein synthesis (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>; Wortel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2017</xref>), if restoration to equilibrium fails due to prolonged or severe stress, then protein synthesis may resume via amino acid biosynthesis and transport, ultimately triggering apoptosis (Han et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>). Contrary to the role of amino acid biosynthesis in triggering cell death as reported by Han et al (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>), we previously demonstrated that HTR-8/SVneo cells are highly dependent on amino acids as a fuel source for successful compensatory mechanisms in response to DCVC treatment, demonstrating ISR complexity (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020a</xref>). Furthermore, ATF4-regulated gene expression plays a role in both compensation and cell death (Han et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>). ATF4 regulates the gene expression of other transcription factors, while simultaneously interacting with them to co-regulate additional gene targets. For example, ATF4 regulates the expression of <italic>DDIT3</italic> while also dimerizing with the gene&#x02019;s translated protein product CHOP. While adaptive genes are largely regulated by ATF4 alone, genes associated with cell death are primarily co-regulated by ATF4 and CHOP upon dimerization. (Han et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2013</xref>).</p><p id="Par50">Here, we report evidence of conflicting ISR pro-survival and pro-apoptotic signaling in HTR-8/SVneo cells after 12&#x000a0;h of 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment, highlighting both compensatory and pathological processes at play. The differential gene expression analysis revealed many upregulated ATF4 transcriptional gene targets involved in compensatory responses including metabolism, redox balance, amino acid transport, general stress response and autophagy (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c). On the other hand, co-regulated ATF4 and CHOP gene targets-implicated in cell death-were also upregulated including amino acid biosynthesis and apoptosis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c). Additionally, we observed no change in cell cycle progression or proliferation, suggesting that, overall, the cells were compensating for DCVC-induced stress after 12&#x000a0;h of exposure. These results are consistent with several of our previous studies that demonstrated simultaneous DCVC-induced pathogenic signaling and functional compensation in HTR-8/SVneo cells. Specifically, prior work demonstrated DCVC-induced altered macronutrient and metabolic pathway utilization despite no overall change in ATP levels (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020a</xref>). Additionally, we reported elevated caspase activity despite no detectable apoptosis (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>). Taken together, these results indicate that treatment with 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC for 12&#x000a0;h encompasses a critical molecular signaling transition in which, cell death signaling increases despite ongoing compensation, but without concomitant functional consequences.</p><p id="Par51">In addition to specific cellular stresses, elevated ISR signaling components have been implicated in early pregnancy disorders characterized by placental abnormalities. For example, phosphorylated eIF2&#x003b1;, ATF4 protein, and/or CHOP protein were elevated in placental tissue obtained from pre-eclamptic pregnancies compared with normal pregnancies (Du et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2017</xref>; Fu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2015</xref>). Another study reported mRNA expression suppression of an ATF4-mediated placental growth factor (<italic>PlGF</italic>) in placentae from women diagnosed with early-onset pre-eclampsia and confirmed those results using two trophoblast cell lines (Mizuuchi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2016</xref>). Furthermore, prolonged eIF2&#x003b1; phosphorylation decreased proliferation and invasion of trophoblast cell lines in vitro (Yung et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2008</xref>), a defining pathological characteristic of IUGR and pre-eclampsia (Brosens et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1972</xref>; Caniggia et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1999</xref>; Kadyrov et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2006</xref>; Meekins et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">1994</xref>). Consequently, ISR activation in trophoblasts, as modeled here by HTR-8/SVneo cells, maybe a mechanism by which the TCE metabolite DCVC contributes to placental dysfunction.</p></sec><sec id="Sec37"><title>Villous explants versus HTR-8/SVneo differential gene expression</title><p id="Par52">In the present study, two in vitro models were utilized to measure DCVC effects on first-trimester placental gene expression: villous explants and HTR-8/SVneo cells. Due to the limited availability of first-trimester placental tissues, only one experimental comparison was made between the two models, non-treated controls versus 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment for 12&#x000a0;h. Gene-specific expression levels varied considerably between tissues and cells. Treated tissues yielded no differentially expressed genes with an FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, yet thousands were altered with a magnitude logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3]. On the other hand, treated cells yielded hundreds of differentially expressed genes meeting FDR criterion, but only half the number of genes were altered with a magnitude logFC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.35 [FC&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.3] compared to villous explants. These variable results are consistent with the relatively weak calculated correlation between genome-wide differential gene expression in tissues and cells. Differences in these results may be attributed to the tissue model containing multiple non-deconvoluted cell types, versus the cell line model containing only one genetically identical cell type (Campbell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par53">Although individual differential gene expression results differed between the models, the collective impact of differentially expressed genes&#x02014;analyzed by GSEA&#x02014;yielded multiple upregulated biological processes and signaling pathways that were positively enriched with DCVC treatment in both models. Moreover, two of the commonly enriched pathways, TNF&#x003b1; and p53, were previously reported to be upregulated by DCVC treatment in HTR-8/SVneo cells (Elkin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>). Perhaps most strikingly, the commonly enriched pathways in both models contained enrichment of genes regulated by the transcription factor ATF4. These results were supported by the moderate correlation between differential gene expression of ATF4 gene targets in tissues and cells; a correlation that was nearly twice the magnitude of that between all differential gene expression in tissues and cells. Moreover, the consistent enrichment of ATF4 gene targets across both models is indicative of ISR activation with 12-h DCVC treatment. As such, the presence of multiple cell types may hinder the ability to accurately detect differential gene expression ascribed to extravillous trophoblasts in the tissue model. Moreover, because villous explants preserve the intact villi structure, there is more variability in the underlying physiology of the two models. For example, explants retain elements of functional paracrine regulation between cells types through release of secreted signaling molecules. Therefore, explants more closely mimic in vivo conditions, than cell lines (Mannelli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2015</xref>).</p><sec id="Sec38"><title>DCVC-induced downregulation of pathways involved in embryonic development</title><p id="Par54">Biological processes and signaling pathways involved in embryonic tissue development comprised the most common category among the downregulated pathways enriched by DCVC treatment. This was a consistent finding across DCVC concentrations and exposure durations in HTR-8/SVneo cells, but was not evident in tissues. Lending further evidence, PAX6 and SMAD3, two key transcription factors that regulate gene expression patterns in developing embryonic tissues (Liu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2004</xref>; Manuel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2015</xref>), were enriched with the group of genes with no expression changes at 6&#x000a0;h but downregulation after 12&#x000a0;h of 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC treatment. Furthermore, the histone modification tri-methylation site H3K27me3, which also regulates genes expression during embryonic development, was enriched with the same group of genes. Interestingly, H3K27me3 has been shown to regulate a pattern of gene expression in the placenta that protects tissues from environmental insults (Nugent et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2018</xref>). These results indicate that the pattern of downregulated genes induced by DCVC treatment may be a response similar to the ISR that is intended to protect the cells and promote adaption.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec39"><title>DCVC concentrations</title><p id="Par55">As for any toxicology study, concentrations of the toxicant tested must be carefully selected and justifiable. For the current study, concentrations of 10&#x02013;20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M DCVC were used as relevant to potential human exposure levels. The concentrations used in our study are relevant to the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) Permissible Exposure Limit (PEL) of 100 parts-per-million (ppm) averaged over an 8-h work day (ATSDR <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">2016</xref>). TCE concentrations up to 229&#x000a0;ppm were reported in 80 exposed workers (29% women) wearing aerosolized monitoring devices (29% women) (Walker et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2016</xref>). Moreover, female volunteers exposed to the PEL of TCE for 4&#x000a0;h by inhalation had an average peak blood concentration of 13.4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M for the metabolic precursor to DCVC, <italic>S-</italic>(1,2-dichlorovinyl)glutathione (DCVG) (Lash et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">1999</xref>), which is comparable to the concentrations used in this study. Finally, the concentrations that caused differential gene expression in our study are considerably lower than those used previously as high as 1&#x000a0;mM DCVC (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2001</xref>; Lash et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2001</xref>; Lash et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2003</xref>; van de Water et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">1995</xref>; Xu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2008</xref>).</p><p id="Par56">In addition to using low concentrations, we also investigated the effects of DCVC on placental cells for short exposure durations. Although longer exposures may more accurately reflect real-life exposures in vivo, this approach enabled us to evaluate the cells&#x02019; initial response to DCVC exposure, otherwise lost, and elucidate compensatory mechanisms used by the cells during the process of stress-driven compensation. Nevertheless, studies exploring longer DCVC exposure durations on the placenta should also be undertaken to understand the full range of effects on the cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec40"><title>Use of villous explants and HTR-8/SVneo as experimental models</title><p id="Par57">The study was conducted with a cell line and placental tissues in vitro<italic>,</italic> which may not represent biological interactions that occur in vivo. Although the tissue model keeps the villi structure intact, the critical interplay is lost ex vivo between fetal and maternal cells that play a pivotal role in placental development. Furthermore, genetic and epigenetic profile differences have been reported in HTR-8/SVneo cells when compared to primary extravillous trophoblasts cultured in similar conditions (Bilban et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2010</xref>; Novakovic et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2011</xref>). Nevertheless, HTR-8/SVneo cells express a signature combination of molecular markers particular to extravillous trophoblasts, including cytokeratin 7 and HLA-G when grown on Matrigel (Irving et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1995</xref>; Khan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2011</xref>; Kilburn et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2000</xref>; Takao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2011</xref>). Despite the drawbacks of using these in vitro models, both have been extensively used to investigate placental biology and the complex processes involved in placental development (Mannelli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2015</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec41"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par58">In summary, we used transcriptomics and gene set enrichment analyses in two first trimester placental models to identify previously unknown biological processes and molecular signaling pathways altered in response to short-term treatment with DCVC concentrations relevant to human exposures. Western blot analysis confirmed the involvement of these pathways and the functional consequences in the cell model. Although transcriptomics differed between models, GSEA demonstrated that the most substantially altered molecular signaling pathway was the ISR, and the most abundantly altered biological processes included amino acid transport, metabolism and biosynthesis, and regulation of tissue development. Evidence showed decreased global protein synthesis in agreement with ISR signaling. Despite these findings, we found no evidence for the change in cell cycle progression or proliferation under the exposure conditions used, suggesting that compensation occurred after 12&#x000a0;h of DCVC treatment. To our knowledge, this is the first report of DCVC-mediated activation of the ISR in any cell type. These findings support the biological plausibility of DCVC-induced placental toxicity, providing a compelling rationale for further studies of DCVC and its parent chemical TCE on placental pathophysiology.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec42"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM1_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 Effects of DCVC on cell cycle progression. HTR-8/SVneo cells were treated with 0 (control), 10 &#x003bc;M or 20 &#x003bc;M DCVC for 12 h. The percentage of cells in each phase of the cell cycle was determined by propidium iodide staining and flow cytometry, as described in the methods section. A) Graphical representation of cell cycle phase distribution. B) Representative cell cycle distribution histograms generated by flow cytometry and table showing percentage of cells in each phase per treatment group. Dark red represents G1/0 phase, stripes represent S phase and light red represents G2/0 phase. Bars represent means &#x000b1; SEM. Data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA (no significant interaction) with posthoc Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparisons. N=3 independent experiments (TIF 443 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM10"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM2_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file2 Effects of DCVC on cellular proliferation. For cellular proliferation experiments, HTR-8/SVneo cells were treated with 0 (control), 10 &#x003bc;M or 20 &#x003bc;M DCVC for 6 or 12 h. Cellular proliferation was measured by labeling nucleic acids with Cyquant fluorescent dye. Fluorescence signal, measured by a micro plate reader, was proportional to the number of cells in each well. Bars represent means &#x000b1; SEM. Proliferation was analyzed by two-way ANOVA (no significant interaction) with posthoc Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparisons. N=3 independent experiments for each time point, with 5 replicates per treatment in each experiment (TIF 176 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM11"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM3_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file3 Multidimensional scaling plots for HTR-8/SVneo cells treated with DCVC. HTR-8/SVneo cells were treated with 0 (control), 10 or 20 &#x000b5;M DCVC for 6 or 12 h. N=4 independent experiments. After mRNA isolation and sequencing, multidimensional scaling analysis was performed using the edgeR package for R. Plots depicting multidimensional scaling were clustered by treatment group, exposure duration and experiment day. Color keys are identified with each plot (TIF 222 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM12"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM4_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file4 Correlation plots for 10 versus 20 &#x000b5;M DCVC. Correlation plots of altered gene expression after treatment with 10 &#x000b5;M DCVC versus 20 &#x000b5;M DCVC using pairwise correlation coefficients of logFC estimates for A) 6 h (P&#x0003c; 1.0x10-15) and B) 12 h (P&#x0003c; 1.0x10-15) (TIF 556 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM13"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM5_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file5 Correlation plots for 6 versus 12 h. Correlation plots of altered gene expression after treatment with 10 &#x000b5;M DCVC versus 20 &#x000b5;M DCVC using pairwise correlation coefficients of logFC estimates for A) 6 h (P&#x0003c; 1.0x10-15) and B) 12 h (P&#x0003c; 1.0x10-15) (TIF 521 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM14"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM6_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file6 Multidimensional scaling plots for villous explants treated with DCVC. First trimester placental villous explants were treated in vitro with 0 (control) or 20 &#x000b5;M DCVC for 12 h. Multidimensional scaling analysis was performed using the edgeR package for R. Plots depicting multidimensional scaling were clustered by: treatment group, gestational week, biological sex of placenta and placental donor. Color keys are provided for each plot (TIF 286 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM15"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM7_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file7 Additional western blotting images (TIF 574 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM8_ESM.tif"><caption><p>Supplementary file8 (TIF 500 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM9_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary file9 (XLSX 1957 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM10_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary file10 (XLSX 1915 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM11_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary file11 (XLSX 2766 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM12_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary file12 (XLSX 2964 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM13_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary file13 (XLSX 1456 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM14_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary file14 (DOCX 21 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="204_2021_3011_MOESM15_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary file15 (DOCX 53 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Andrea Ruszala of the University of Michigan Advanced Genomics Core for her assistance with library preparation and RNA sequencing. We also thank Maureen Sartor and Alla Karnovsky of the Omics and Bioinformatics Core of the Michigan Center on Lifestage Environmental Exposures and Disease for assistance with metabolomics statistical analyses. We thank Northland Family Planning Centers of Michigan and their patients for participating in this research study. Finally, we gratefully acknowledge Sean Harris, PhD, Anthony Su, PhD, Faith Bjork, Kyle Campbell, JeAnna Redd and Molly Mulcahy for assistance with learning new laboratory techniques and for helpful scientific discussions, and Monica Smolinski for general lab assistance.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>ERE designed and performed the experiments, analyzed data, and wrote the manuscript. KMB and JAC assisted with experimental design, data analysis, and data interpretation. DB provided laboratory equipment and assisted with laboratory techniques, data analysis, and data interpretation. BAK obtained placental tissues and performed laboratory work on the tissues. RLC and DRA provided funding for the project and offered insight into the interpretation of the results. All authors reviewed and contributed to the manuscript and approved the final version.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences, National Institutes of Health (Grant Nos. P42 ES017198, P30 ES017885, P30 ES020957, R01 ES025574, R01 ES025531, T32 ES007062 and R01 ES028802); National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive Kidney Diseases (Grant Nos. R01 DK107535 and T32 DK071212); National Institute of Aging (Grant Nos. R01 AG055406 and P30 AG053760) and Wayne State University&#x02019;s Office of the Vice President for Research. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIEHS, NIDDK, NIA, or NIH.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data have been deposited Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) and are publicly available. GEO accession numbers are as follows: GSE154339 (HTR-8/SVneo) and GSE154489 (placental villous explants).</p></notes><notes notes-type="ethics"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par59">The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="Par60">Placental tissues were acquired as discarded tissues at the time of termination at a Michigan family planning clinic with Institutional Review Board approval (Wayne State University IRB# 013515MP4E) and written informed consent by patients, obtained by collaborating Wayne State University physicians.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Andrews S (2010) FastQC: a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data. In: Bahraham Bioinformaticz. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc</ext-link>. Accessed 27 Feb 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ATSDR (2016) Public Health Statement on Trichloroethylene. In: Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry.
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/ToxProfiles/tp19-c1.pdf">https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/ToxProfiles/tp19-c1.pdf</ext-link> Accessed 4 Nov 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ATCC (2015) American Type Culture Collection Product Sheet: HTR8/SVneo&#x000a0;(ATCC&#x000ae;&#x000a0;CRL3271&#x02122;). American Type Culture Collection</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>XR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberger</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial dysfunction remodels one-carbon metabolism in human cells</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.10575</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27307216?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27307216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: A practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title><source>J R Stat Soc: Ser B (Methodol)</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tauber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslinger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trophoblast invasion: assessment of cellular models using gene expression signatures</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.placenta.2010.08.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20850871?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20850871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolnick</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolnick</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohan-Ghadr</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of trophoblast differentiation and survival by low molecular weight heparin requires heparin-binding EGF-like growth factor</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1218</fpage><lpage>1229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/dex069</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28402449?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28402449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brosens</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the spiral arteries in the pathogenesis of preeclampsia</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol Annu</source><year>1972</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><?supplied-pmid 4669123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4669123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowden</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The placenta: a multifaceted, transient organ</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>370</volume><issue>1663</issue><fpage>20140066</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2014.0066</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25602070?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25602070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jauniaux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is the placenta?</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2015</year><volume>213</volume><issue>4 Suppl</issue><fpage>S6 e1</fpage><lpage>S6&#x02013;8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2015.07.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26428504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Colacino</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakulski</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell types in environmental epigenetic studies: biological and epidemiological frameworks</article-title><source>Curr Environ Health Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40572-020-00287-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32794033?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32794033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caniggia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Grisaru-Gravnosky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuliszewsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Post</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lye</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of TGF-beta 3 restores the invasive capability of extravillous trophoblasts in preeclamptic pregnancies</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1999</year><volume>103</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1641</fpage><lpage>1650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI6380</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10377170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of mitochondrial dysfunction in S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-l-cysteine-induced apoptosis</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>170</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/taap.2000.9107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11162782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11162782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enrichr: interactive and collaborative HTML5 gene list enrichment analysis tool</article-title><source>BMC Bioinform</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>128</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-14-128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jinot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human health effects of trichloroethylene: key findings and scientific issues</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2013</year><volume>121</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.1205879</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23249866?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23249866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitz</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The encyclopedia of DNA elements (ENCODE): data portal update</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D794</fpage><lpage>D801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx1081</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29126249?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29126249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts635</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23104886?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>eNOS/iNOS and endoplasmic reticulum stress-induced apoptosis in the placentas of patients with preeclampsia</article-title><source>J Hum Hypertens</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jhh.2016.17</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27030287?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27030287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durinck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasprzyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BioMart and Bioconductor: a powerful link between biological databases and microarray data analysis</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>3439</fpage><lpage>3440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti525</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16082012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16082012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durinck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spellman</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping identifiers for the integration of genomic datasets with the R/Bioconductor package biomaRt</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1184</fpage><lpage>1191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2009.97</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19617889?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19617889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trichloroethylene metabolite S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine induces lipid peroxidation-associated apoptosis via the intrinsic and extrinsic apoptosis pathways in a first-trimester placental cell line</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><year>2018</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2017.11.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29129777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29129777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The trichloroethylene metabolite S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine induces progressive mitochondrial dysfunction in HTR-8/SVneo trophoblasts</article-title><source>Toxicology</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2019.152283</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31476333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31476333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to trichloroethylene metabolite S-(1,2-Dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine causes compensatory changes to macronutrient utilization and energy metabolism in placental HTR-8/SVneo cells</article-title><source>Chem Res Toxicol</source><year>2020</year><volume>33</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrestox.9b00356</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31951115?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31951115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to trichloroethylene metabolite S-(1,2-Dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine causes compensatory changes to macronutrient utilization and energy metabolism in placental HTR-8/SVneo cells</article-title><source>Chem Res Toxicol</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrestox.9b00356</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31951115?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31951115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elkin</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placenta as a target of trichloroethylene toxicity</article-title><source>Environ Sci Process Impacts</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c9em00537d</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32022077?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32022077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Encode Project Consortium</collab></person-group><article-title>An integrated encyclopedia of DNA elements in the human genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>489</volume><issue>7414</issue><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A human physiologically based pharmacokinetic model for trichloroethylene and its metabolites, trichloroacetic acid and free trichloroethanol</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><year>1998</year><volume>152</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/taap.1998.8486</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9853003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9853003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forand</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis-Michl</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adverse birth outcomes and maternal exposure to trichloroethylene and tetrachloroethylene through soil vapor intrusion in New York State</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2012</year><volume>120</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.1103884</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22142966?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22142966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of markers of endoplasmic reticulum stress-induced apoptosis in the placenta of women with early and late onset severe pre-eclampsia</article-title><source>Taiwan J Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2015</year><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tjog.2014.11.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25675914?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25675914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Establishment and characterization of first trimester human trophoblast cells with extended lifespan</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>206</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/excr.1993.1139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7684692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Back</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ER-stress-induced transcriptional regulation increases protein synthesis leading to cell death</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb2738</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23624402?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23624402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TRRUST v2: an expanded reference database of human and mouse transcriptional regulatory interactions</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D380</fpage><lpage>D386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx1013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29087512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29087512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactive oxygen stimulation of interleukin-6 release in the human trophoblast cell line HTR-8/SVneo by the trichlorethylene metabolite S-(1,2-Dichloro)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>2016</year><volume>95</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>66</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod.116.139261</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27488030?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27488030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The C/EBP homologous protein (CHOP) transcription factor functions in endoplasmic reticulum stress-induced apoptosis and microbial infection</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3083</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.03083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30662442?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30662442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huckle</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Huckle</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chapter two - cell- and tissue-based models for study of placental development</article-title><source>Progress in molecular biology and translational science</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lysiak</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hearn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lala</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of trophoblast cells migrating from first trimester chorionic villus explants and propagated in culture</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>1995</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0143-4004(95)90100-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7479613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadyrov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingdom</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Huppertz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergent trophoblast invasion and apoptosis in placental bed spiral arteries from pregnancies complicated by maternal anemia and early-onset preeclampsia/intrauterine growth restriction</article-title><source>Am J Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2006</year><volume>194</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2005.07.035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16458661?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16458661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Castellucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extravillous trophoblast in humans: a review</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>1997</year><volume>18</volume><issue>Supplement 2</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0143-4004(97)80079-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Girish</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lala</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Guglielmo</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lala</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decorin is a novel VEGFR-2-binding antagonist for the human extravillous trophoblast</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1431</fpage><lpage>1443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/me.2010-0426</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21659473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21659473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilburn</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duniec-Dmuchowski</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Armant</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular matrix composition and hypoxia regulate the expression of HLA-G and integrins in a human trophoblast cell line</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>2000</year><volume>62</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod62.3.739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Golan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitro models using the human placenta to study fetal exposure to drugs clinical medicine</article-title><source>Reprod Health</source><year>2008</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4137/CMRH.S974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuleshov</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouillard</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enrichr: a comprehensive gene set enrichment analysis web server 2016 update</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><issue>W1</issue><fpage>W90</fpage><lpage>W97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw377</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27141961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27141961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on placental transfer. Trichlorethylene</article-title><source>IMS Ind Med Surg</source><year>1970</year><volume>39</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><?supplied-pmid 5263053?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5263053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-L-cysteine- and S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-L-homocysteine-induced renal mitochondrial toxicity</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>1987</year><volume>32</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3670284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3670284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Putt</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brashear</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)glutathione in the blood of human volunteers exposed to trichloroethylene</article-title><source>J Toxicol Environ Health A</source><year>1999</year><volume>56</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/009841099158204</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9923751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9923751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hueni</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Putt</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis, necrosis, and cell proliferation induced by S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-L-cysteine in primary cultures of humanproximal tubular cells</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>177</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/taap.2001.9295</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11708895?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11708895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Putt</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hueni</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Elfarra</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of necrosis, Apoptosis, and mitochondrial dysfunction in S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine sulfoxide-induced cytotoxicity in primary cultures of human renal proximal tubular cells</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>305</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1163</fpage><lpage>1172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.102.046185</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12626654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12626654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>923</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt656</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24227677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24227677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liberzon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinchback</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorvaldsdottir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular signatures database (MSigDB) 30</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1739</fpage><lpage>1740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr260</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21546393?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liberzon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Birger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorvaldsdottir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghandi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular signatures database (MSigDB) hallmark gene set collection</article-title><source>Cell Syst</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cels.2015.12.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26771021?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26771021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Festing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smad2 and Smad3 coordinately regulate craniofacial and endodermal development</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>270</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2004.03.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15183723?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15183723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loch-Caruso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjork</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trichloroethylene exposure in mid-pregnancy decreased fetal weight and increased placental markers of oxidative stress in rats</article-title><source>Reprod Toxicol</source><year>2019</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.reprotox.2018.11.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30468822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30468822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lun</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>It's DE-licious: a recipe for differential expression analyses of RNA-seq experiments using quasi-likelihood methods in edgeR</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>1418</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-3578-9_19</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27008025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27008025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ER stress and its functional link to mitochondria: role in cell survival and death</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>a004424</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a004424</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21813400?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21813400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mannelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ietta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Avanzati</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Skarzynski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulesu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological tools to study the effects of environmental contaminants at the feto-maternal interface</article-title><source>Dose Response</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1559325815611902</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1559325815611902</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26740808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26740808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manuel</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of cerebral cortical neurogenesis by the Pax6 transcription factor</article-title><source>Front Cell Neurosci</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>70</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncel.2015.00070</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25805971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25805971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Picken</surname><given-names>JC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Weakley</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Possible toxic factor of trichloroethylene-extracted soybean oil meal3</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><year>1959</year><volume>81</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja01513a039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meekins</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pijnenborg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanssens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McFadyen</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>van Asshe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study of placental bed spiral arteries and trophoblast invasion in normal and severe pre-eclamptic pregnancies</article-title><source>Br J Obstet Gynaecol</source><year>1994</year><volume>101</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-0528.1994.tb13182.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7947500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizuuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cindrova-Davies</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Olovsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Charnock-Jones</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placental endoplasmic reticulum stress negatively regulates transcription of placental growth factor via ATF4 and ATF6beta: implications for the pathophysiology of human pregnancy complications</article-title><source>J Pathol</source><year>2016</year><volume>238</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>550</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/path.4678</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26648175?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26648175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mootha</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PGC-1alpha-responsive genes involved in oxidative phosphorylation are coordinately downregulated in human diabetes</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1180</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12808457?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12808457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placental insufficiency is a leading cause of preterm labor</article-title><source>NeoReviews</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>5618</fpage><lpage>e525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/neo.15-12-e518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novakovic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Wide-ranging DNA methylation differences of primary trophoblast cell populations and derived cell lines: implications and opportunities for understanding trophoblast function</article-title><source>Mol Hum Reprod</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molehr/gar005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21289002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21289002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nugent</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Epperson</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placental H3K27me3 establishes female resilience to prenatal insults</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2555</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-04992-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29967448?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29967448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orendi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kivity</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sammar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Placental and trophoblastic in vitro models to study preventive and therapeutic agents for preeclampsia</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><issue>Supplement 1</issue><fpage>S49</fpage><lpage>S54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.placenta.2010.11.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21257083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pakos-Zebrucka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koryga</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mnich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljujic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Samali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The integrated stress response</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1374</fpage><lpage>1395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embr.201642195</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27629041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27629041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pijnenborg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosens</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pattern of interstitial trophoblastic invasion of the myometrium in early human pregnancy</article-title><source>Placenta</source><year>1981</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0143-4004(81)80027-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7301778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quiros</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamboni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multi-omics analysis identifies ATF4 as a key regulator of the mitochondrial stress response in mammals</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>216</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2027</fpage><lpage>2045</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201702058</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28566324?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28566324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team (2019) R: A language and environment for statistical computing. 3.6.1 edn. R Foundation forStatistical Computing, Vienna, Austria</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshlack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A scaling normalization method for differential expression analysis of RNA-seq data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>R25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-3-r25</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20196867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20196867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruckart</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bove</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maslia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of contaminated drinking water and preterm birth, small for gestational age, and birth weight at Marine Corps Base Camp Lejeune, North Carolina: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Environ Health</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>99</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-069X-13-99</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25413571?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25413571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>p53-independent Noxa induction by cisplatin is regulated by ATF3/ATF4 in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma cells</article-title><source>Mol Oncol</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1878-0261.12172</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29352505?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29352505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shpilka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mitochondrial UPR: mechanisms, physiological functions and implications in ageing</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm.2017.110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29165426?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29165426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steegers</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>von Dadelszen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Duvekot</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pijnenborg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pre-eclampsia</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2010</year><volume>376</volume><issue>9741</issue><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60279-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20598363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20598363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilberg</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C/EBP homology protein (CHOP) interacts with activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4) and negatively regulates the stress-dependent induction of the asparagine synthetase gene</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><issue>50</issue><fpage>35106</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M806874200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18940792?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18940792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mootha</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><issue>43</issue><fpage>15545</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0506580102</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16199517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Asanoma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of human trophoblast side-population (SP) cells in primary villous cytotrophoblasts and HTR-8/SVneo cell line</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e21990</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021990</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21760941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21760941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tetz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Korte</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mono-2-ethylhexyl phthalate induces oxidative stress responses in human placental cells in vitro</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><year>2013</year><volume>268</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2013.01.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23360888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23360888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) (2019a) Superfund: National Priorities List (NPL). In. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/superfund/superfund-national-priorities-list-npl">https://www.epa.gov/superfund/superfund-national-priorities-list-npl</ext-link> Accessed 5 Nov 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">U.S. EPA (Environmental Protection Agency) (2019b) TRI Explorer (2018 Updated Dataset (released October 2019) ) [Internet database]. In: United States Environmental Protection Agency. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epa.gov/triexplorer">https://www.epa.gov/triexplorer</ext-link> Accessed 4 Nov 2019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van de Water</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoetewey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bont</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagelkerke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between intracellular Ca2+ and the mitochondrial membrane potential in isolated proximal tubular cells from rat kidney exposed to the nephrotoxin 1,2-dichlorovinyl-cysteine</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>1993</year><volume>45</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2259</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-2952(93)90197-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8517866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">van de Water B, Zoeteweij JP, de Bont HJ, Nagelkerke JF (1995) Inhibition of succinate:ubiquinone reductase and decrease of ubiquinol in nephrotoxiccysteine S-conjugate-induced oxidative cell injury. Molecular pharmacology 48(5):928&#x02013;37</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van de Water</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoeteweij</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>de Bont</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagelkerke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of mitochondrial Ca2+ in the oxidative stress-induced dissipation of the mitochondrial membrane potential Studies in isolated proximal tubular cells using the nephrotoxin 1,2-dichlorovinyl-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>14546</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9258(17)36658-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8182062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The unfolded protein response: from stress pathway to homeostatic regulation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2011</year><volume>334</volume><issue>6059</issue><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1209038</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22116877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22116877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Warnes GR, Ben Bolker B, Bonebakker L, et al. (2019) gplots: Various R programming tools for plotting data</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Uppal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-resolution metabolomics of occupational exposure to trichloroethylene</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>45</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1517</fpage><lpage>1527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyw218</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27707868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27707868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstner</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Huff</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trichloroethylene. I. An overview</article-title><source>J Toxicol Environ Health</source><year>1977</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15287397709529469</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 403297?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">403297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wortel</surname><given-names>IMN</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Meer</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilberg</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surviving stress: modulation of ATF4-mediated stress responses in normal and malignant cells</article-title><source>Trends Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2017</year><volume>28</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>794</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tem.2017.07.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28797581?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28797581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Papanayotou</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Putt</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of mitochondrial dysfunction in cellular responses to S-(1,2-dichlorovinyl)-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine in primary cultures of human proximal tubular cells</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2008</year><volume>76</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2008.05.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18602084?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18602084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ATF4 regulates CD4(+) T cell immune responses through metabolic reprogramming</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1754</fpage><lpage>1766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.04.032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29742431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29742431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yung</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hynx</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence of placental translation inhibition and endoplasmic reticulum stress in the etiology of human intrauterine growth restriction</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2008</year><volume>173</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2353/ajpath.2008.071193</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18583310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18583310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parthenolide induces apoptosis via TNFRSF10B and PMAIP1 pathways in human lung cancer cells</article-title><source>J Exp Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-9966-33-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24387758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24387758</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>