<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">As previously described, the meniscus is partly vascularized, while articular cartilage is avascular [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In this study, we can report that among the proteins with at least two unique peptides, 25 can be classified as blood circulation proteins using the GO accession GO:000815. Of these, 8 were found to be meniscus-specific and none were unique to articular cartilage. Furthermore, serum albumin is the protein with the highest intensity in meniscus in the DDA analysis (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), which further supports the previous reports of a vascularized meniscus. The list of the ten most abundant proteins in meniscus also contains two additional well-known plasma proteins; haemoglobin subunit beta and serotransferrin (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). One protein that significantly differed between meniscus and articular cartilage was alpha-1-antitrypsin (A1AT). This protein is one of the top 20 most abundant proteins in plasma, and it is therefore not surprising that A1AT is on average approximately five times more abundant in meniscus than articular cartilage (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). However, several plasma proteins were identified also in articular cartilage in this study. Since articular cartilage is in contact with synovial fluid in the joint, and synovial fluid is an ultra-filtrate of plasma and therefore contains plasma proteins, the presence of plasma proteins in articular cartilage might be explained by the ability of the cartilage to absorb molecules, in this case plasma proteins, from its surroundings. This could for example be the case for angiogenin, a protein found in the circulation and reported to be angiogenic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. It was significantly more abundant in articular cartilage than meniscus in this study. Angiogenin is a 14 kDa and 123 amino acids long protein that is highly cationic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], making it similar to lyzosyme C in both size and charge [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. These common traits with lysozyme C, which is enriched in articular cartilage, could explain the presence of angiogenin in articular cartilage despite its avascular phenotype. Similarly, in one study, the authors reported that angiogenesis might be involved in OA, and hypothesised that articular cartilage might be able to take up circulating molecules, e.g. from the vascularised synovium and that there was an invasion of synovium into the articular cartilage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Furthermore, in a study investigating the role of angiogenesis in hip OA, it was noted that the grade of angiogenesis was related to the cartilage degeneration, hence it could be involved in the degenerative process [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].
</p>
