<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rauber 
 <italic>et al.</italic> documented more than 750 cases of accidental or deliberate ricin intoxication from castor bean ingestion, with 14 resulting in fatality [
 <xref rid="b6-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The ingestion fatal dose is 5–6 castor beans for children and 20 beans for adults [
 <xref rid="b7-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Although considerably less potent than botulinum neurotoxins and staphylococcal enterotoxins, ricin is still considered a significantly potential biological weapon because of its stability and worldwide availability as a by-product of castor oil production. In addition, it has been associated with several terrorist actions and therefore is a potential bioterrorism agent [
 <xref rid="b7-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) of U.S.A categorizes ricin as a Category B Agent (the second-highest priority), as it can be moderately easily disseminated, leading to low mortality but moderate to high morbidity. It can be injected into a subject, be used to contaminate food and water, or be dispersed as an aerosol. Ricin poisoning can cause severe tissue damages and inflammatory reactions and can result in death [
 <xref rid="b8-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The initial symptoms of ricin poisoning include nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and abdominal pain. In severe poisoning, the symptoms can progress to gastrointestinal bleeding with necrosis of the liver, spleen and kidney, and even cardiovascular collapse [
 <xref rid="b9-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. If inhaled, ricin can cause death within 36–48 h because of the failure of the respiratory and circulatory systems [
 <xref rid="b10-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. As a toxin, ricin is not a disease-causing agent. Therefore, it is not contagious and cannot be spread from person to person through casual contacts [
 <xref rid="b11-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
