<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While the damage on humans through aerosol exposure was not well reported, lesions induced by oral and parenteral exposures are consistent with those from animal studies, suggesting that the same would hold true for aerosol exposures. Studies on mice demonstrated that aerosolized ricin is deposited in trachea and lungs. Pulmonary deposition highly depends on aerosol particle size, which profoundly affects the mortality rate in the animal model [
 <xref rid="b12-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="b13-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Aerosolized ricin exposure leads to weakness, fever, cough, and pulmonary edema symptoms within 18–24 h and severe respiratory distress and even death within 36–72 h [
 <xref rid="b14-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. There is no effective treatment for ricin poisoning, and no vaccine or prophylactic antitoxin available for human either [
 <xref rid="b15-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Studies in rodents and nonhuman primates have demonstrated that ricin delivered into the pulmonary system leads to acute lung injuries and symptoms which resemble acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) [
 <xref rid="b16-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. When administered into the animal lungs, ricin induces a rapid and massive migration of inflammatory cells [
 <xref rid="b17-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Another early consequence of ricin exposure is the activation of a rapid-acting primary transcription factor that induces expressions of genes encoding several pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines [
 <xref rid="b5-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="b18-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="b19-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Primary human airway epithelial cells and primary murine macrophages respond to ricin 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> through the activation of both MAPK and NF-κB [
 <xref rid="b20-ijms-15-07281" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], but the specific cell types responsible for ricin’s lethal inflammatory effects 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> remain unclear.
</p>
