<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The problem in obtaining conclusive answers from XAS studies of this class of materials stems, in part, from the coexistence of different structural motifs within the catalyst, and the fact that only a fraction of the metal sites that contribute to the measured spectrum might contribute and in fact determine the catalytic activity. In this situation, a combination of 
 <italic>in situ</italic> XAS with other techniques is very helpful. For example, very recently, the input from electrochemical measurements, 
 <italic>operando</italic> wide-angle X-ray scattering (WAXS) and DFT simulations was used to interpret the changes in the 
 <italic>operando</italic> Ni K-edge EXAFS data, namely, the decrease in the amplitude of the main FT-EXAFS peaks and the contraction of interatomic distances under applied potential (
 <xref rid="fig42" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig42" ref-type="fig">42</xref>
 </xref>a,b). The observed changes under OER conditions were attributed to a partial transformation from the α-Ni(OH)
 <sub>2</sub>-like structure with intercalated water molecules and ions between the Ni(OH)
 <sub>2</sub> layers to a γ-NiOOH-like phase. However, the transformation was not complete, and a contribution of the α-Ni(OH)
 <sub>2</sub> phase was still present in WAXS data collected under OER conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref600">600</xref>
 </sup> The need for complementary approaches that are sensitive to structural transformations on different length scales is expected to be even more pressing in the future due increased morphological, structural, and chemical complexity of the new OER catalysts that are being developed. This includes Fe–Ni catalysts such as nanotubes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref606">606</xref>
 </sup> and nanotube arrays,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref607">607</xref>
 </sup> supported NiFe clusters,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref608">608</xref>
 </sup> ultrathin films,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref609">609</xref>
 </sup> NiFe Prussian blue analogues,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref610">610</xref>
 </sup> hybrid catalysts combining Au single atoms with NiFe double hydroxide supports
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref611">611</xref>
 </sup> and others.
</p>
