<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Overall, the addition of a secondary metal in spinel-like Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> is a common route to tune the catalyst properties. As discussed in 
 <xref rid="sec5.6" ref-type="other">Section 
  <xref rid="sec5.6" ref-type="other">5.6</xref>
 </xref>, in pure Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>, the tetrahedral sites are occupied by Co
 <sup>2+</sup> species, while the octahedral sites are occupied by Co
 <sup>3+</sup>. However, this can be controlled by the addition of another metal such as Fe in the example above, Zn or Al. Oxidation states of Zn and Al are 2+ and 3+, respectively, and they are expected to replace Co species with the corresponding oxidation state. As a result, the addition of these OER-inactive metals results in an increased (in the case of Zn) and decreased (in the case of Al) average oxidation state of Co, as confirmed by XANES measurements.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref332">332</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, EXAFS analysis revealed that the spinel structure is preserved upon such a substitution, with Zn and Al displacing Co from tetrahedral and octahedral sites, respectively. This allows one to identify the more catalytically relevant site. Indeed, by performing 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS measurements, no changes at the Co K-edge in ZnCo
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> were observed, while Co in CoAl
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> was oxidized under OER conditions, suggesting the formation of the catalytically active CoOOH phase and highlighting the importance of tetrahedrally coordinated Co
 <sup>2+</sup> species,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref332">332</xref>
 </sup> in accordance with the results for the Fe–Co spinel from ref (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref620">620</xref>). Interestingly, a previous study of ZnCo
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> catalysts yielded somewhat conflicting results.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref330">330</xref>
 </sup> While in this case XANES and EXAFS analysis confirmed similar well-ordered normal spinel structure, and no changes in the Co and Zn oxidation states were observed under OER conditions, higher OER activity was observed for ZnCo
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> than for Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref330">330</xref>
 </sup> The enhanced activity in the bimetallic catalyst was partially attributed to the leaching of the Zn species, which resulted in a structure with a high number of vacancies, facilitating the formation of the active CoOOH phase at the catalyst surface.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref330">330</xref>
 </sup> The role of Zn in ensuring a defect-rich structure favorable for OER was observed also in the study of Co–Zn oxyhydroxides,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref621">621</xref>
 </sup> where it was also found that the presence of Zn facilitates the stabilization of higher oxidation states of Co, as follows from the systematic shifts in the Co K-edge XANES data with increasing Zn doping.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref621">621</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
