<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Biovia Materials Studio software was employed to perform simulations in this study using the COMPASS (Condensed-phase Optimized Molecular Potentials for Atomistic Simulation Studies) forcefield [
 <xref rid="B24-polymers-12-02048" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-polymers-12-02048" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Initially, polymer chains containing 25 repeat units were built and geometry optimization was performed. Then, a periodic model of the PI, comprising of five polymer chains in cubic unit cell, was constructed and the total energy of the system was minimized using smart minimizing method. Annealing was performed by the NPT (constant number of particles (N), pressure (P), and temperature (T)) dynamics procedure through heating and cooling the system at 1 atm in the temperature range of 300 to 1000 K in steps of 50 K. Interactions of non-bond, van der Waals, and electrostatic forces, were calculated using an atom-based summation method and an Ewald summation method, respectively. The annealed cell was later put through a stage-wise equilibration procedure. First the cell was heated to 1000 K, and then the temperature was decreased in several stages to 600 K in steps of 100 K. After this, the temperature was decreased in several stages to 400 K in steps of 50 K and then decreased to 300 K in steps of 25 K. Each stage consisted of two consecutive NVT (constant number of particles (N), volume (V) and temperature (T)) and NPT runs at 1 atm and a specific temperature. The aim of the procedure was to obtain a refined system that would relax at the experimental density of the amorphous polymer at 1 atm and 300 K. Finally, the cell was relaxed by consecutive NVT (at 300 K) and NPT dynamics (at 1 atm and 298 K) to ensure that a constant density has been reached. Two criteria were used to determine the equilibrium of the system: (1) The density of the system remained stable for a long time; (2) the fluctuation of energy was lower than 10 % [
 <xref rid="B26-polymers-12-02048" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The plots of density and energy versus simulation time in the last NPT for PI systems are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-polymers-12-02048">supporting information Figures S1 and S2</xref>. It can be seen that the PI systems have reached equilibrium states. The equilibrated densities of Kapton, 2,7-CPPI and 2,7-CPI systems are 1.41, 1.56, and 1.57 g/cm
 <sup>3</sup>, respectively, which are fairly close to the experimental densities (1.42, 1.57 and 1.58 g/cm
 <sup>3</sup>). In all runs, Nosé method was used for temperature control [
 <xref rid="B27-polymers-12-02048" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In NPT runs, the pressure was controlled by Berendsen’s method. During these simulations, the cutoff for the nonbonded interactions was taken as 15.5 Å.
</p>
