<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Changes in the valence state, signified by the changes in the white line are typically accompanied by changes in the catalyst structure, for example, bond lengths, particle size, and induced strain.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref141">141</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref285">285</xref>
 </sup> EXAFS analysis can be used to follow these transformations 
 <italic>in situ</italic>. For example, it was proposed that the analysis of Pt–O bond lengths can be used to discriminate between different adsorbates (e.g., Pt–O and Pt–OH).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref350">350</xref>
 </sup> However, in practice, data of very high quality are needed to determine reliably the interatomic distances with the accuracy required for such analysis. This requirement is rarely compatible with measurements under catalyst working conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref285">285</xref>
 </sup> Another challenge is the sample-averaging nature of the EXAFS method and the heterogeneity of the catalyst structure, where the changes are often limited only to the surface. Studies of very small particles with sizes ∼1–2 nm can be helpful in this case. For example, Myers et al. employed 
 <italic>in situ</italic> XAS to investigate the changes in 1.8 nm dendritic Pt nanocatalysts for ORR.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref285">285</xref>
 </sup> Although the Pt precursors in the as-prepared samples were not completely reduced, the NPs were completely reduced 
 <italic>in situ</italic> in the 0.1 M HClO
 <sub>4</sub> electrolyte when a −0.7 V (vs Hg/Hg
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub>) potential was applied. Through multiple-scattering EXAFS data fitting, the coordination numbers in the first few coordination shells were obtained and from them, information about the particle shape. With applied potential increasing between −0.2 and +0.3 V, a significant decrease in the first peak of the FT-EXAFS spectrum was observed, 
 <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">33</xref>
 </xref>a, corresponding to a reduction of the Pt–Pt CNs (
 <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">33</xref>
 </xref>b). This effect was observed in both, N
 <sub>2</sub>- and O
 <sub>2</sub>-saturated electrolytes. At the same time, the more distant peaks in the FT-EXAFS spectra (dominated in fcc-type structures by multiple-scattering contributions) were relatively unaffected (
 <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">33</xref>
 </xref>a). This was interpreted as an evidence of an increase in the NPs surface disorder, with the NP core relatively unaffected by potential changes. Myers et al. argued that MS contributions are more significantly suppressed by the disorder than single-scattering contributions. Therefore, even in the as-prepared sample, the surface layers (which in all NPs are expected to be less ordered) practically do not contribute to the MS-related component in particle-averaged EXAFS, and the total MS signal is dominated by the contribution from the ordered NP core region. The lack of changes in the MS contribution under applied potential can thus be interpreted as the lack of structural changes in the NP core.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref285">285</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
