<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effect of surface disorder and associated stress was also probed by Erickson et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref349">349</xref>
 </sup> with 1.2 nm Pt NPs prepared by an incipient wetness method. It was observed that upon exposure to oxygen, the Pt–Pt interatomic distances increase with increasing applied potential, and are longer that those at the same potential under N
 <sub>2</sub>. This difference was attributed to the interaction between the Pt NPs and adsorbed oxygen species that resulted in an expansion of the interatomic distance. On the basis of the analysis of the CNs extracted from EXAFS data fitting, a 3D model of the NP structure was proposed (inset in 
 <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">33</xref>
 </xref>c), a truncated cuboctahedron. Two models of interatomic distance expansion were then compared: (i) uniform expansion, where all Pt–Pt distances were equally increased (minimum expansion), and (ii) a surface-restricted expansion, where only the distances between Pt atoms on the surface (green atoms in the inset in 
 <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">33</xref>
 </xref>c) were increased, representing the maximum expansion. The potential dependencies of the Pt–Pt distances for surface atoms calculated within both models are compared in 
 <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">33</xref>
 </xref>c. Strikingly, the bond expansion obtained within the second model was found to be in a good quantitative agreement with the direct 
 <italic>in situ</italic> surface stress data obtained using optical cantilever stress measurements,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref349">349</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref478">478</xref>
 </sup> pointing thus to a surface-localized stress, 
 <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig33" ref-type="fig">33</xref>
 </xref>d. Such insight into the surface disorder is particularly important in catalysis applications since a linear correlation between the interatomic distances at the surface and the energy of the d-band center has been theoretically predicted and discussed to affect the adsorbate binding.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref479">479</xref>
 </sup> For instance, an expansion of the interatomic distances increases the energy of the electrons near the Fermi level that can be subsequently transferred to adsorbates.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref349">349</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
