<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Efforts in understanding the regeneration of the holothurian digestive tract have provided important insights on the cellular processes involved in organogenesis. Experiments have identified the fundamental role of the cells in the mesentery during intestinal regeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. In normal, non-eviscerated animals, the mesentery extends along the interior body wall providing support to the intestine. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> shows a simplified drawing of the tissues found in the mesentery and intestine. This includes (1) the outer mesothelium made of peritoneocytes (or coelomic epithelium), myocytes and some neurons, (2) the inner connective tissue layer where few cells are found within an abundant extracellular matrix, and (3) the luminal epithelium made up primarily of enterocytes and some enteroendocrine cells. Following evisceration, the torn edges at the distal part of the mesentery acquire a thick oval morphology forming the initial intestinal rudiment from the esophagus to the cloaca. This growth is formed by evisceration-activated signals that trigger dedifferentiation of peritoneocytes and muscle cells in the mesothelium of the mesentery. Myocyte dedifferentiation is associated with elimination of the contractile apparatus through condensation of myofilaments into membrane bound spindle-like structures (SLSs)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. The presence of these structures has been used to reveal a spatio-temporal gradient where, initially, dedifferentiation is localized near the free margin of the mesentery, while the rest of the mesentery remains mostly in a differentiated state. This pattern progresses until eventually different regions with increasing levels of de-differentiation can be observed in the mesentery. It has been hypothesized that dedifferentiated cells give rise to precursor cells that eventually divide and re-differentiate into the cellular components that form the initial rudiment of the regenerating organ
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
