<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>After the non-destructive tests, the welded joints were subjected to the following destructive tests:
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>static tensile strength test, </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>technological face bend test, </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>impact tests (tests were carried out at a temperature of −30 °C), </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>macro and microscopic metallographic tests, ent,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>Vickers hardness tests,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>analysis of the chemical composition using a Magellan Q8 Bruker (Bruker Austria GmbH, Vienna, Austria) and optical emission spectroscopy,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>microanalysis of the chemical composition, performed using a JOEL JSM-5800LV EDX Penta FETx3 scanning microscope (JEOL Ltd., Akishima, Japan) and an accelerating voltage of 13 kV and 20 kV,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>tests of the chemical composition in the micro-areas of the welded joints performed using a SUPRA 35 scanning electron microscope (Zeiss, Jena, Germany) equipped with an EDS attachment (EDAX) and the back-scattered electron observation technique (BSE),</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>quantitative composition measured using a JXA-8230 electron probe microanalyser (JEOL Ltd., Akishima, Japan) and wavelength dispersion spectroscopy. In relation to the above-named method, the limit of detectability of heavy elements amounts to approximately 100 ppm. Images of the tested areas (with marked areas subjected to analysis) were made in light of back-scattered electrons (composition-contrast depending on the average atomic number),</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>tests of thin films performed using a Titan 80–300 kV high-resolution scanning transmission electron microscope (HR S/TEM, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), the diffraction solution was based on the publication [
    <xref rid="B39-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], 
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⮚</label>
   <p>X-ray phase analysis performed using an X’Pert PRO diffractometer (PANalytical, Almelo, The Netherlands) an X’Celerator strip detector (PANalytical, Almelo, The Netherlands), and a lamp equipped with a cobalt anode.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
