<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since precipitation is an exothermic process, and dissolution an endothermic one, they can be detected by thermal analysis. Cavazos and Colas used direct thermal analysis of Jominy-like end-quench samples, i.e., they evaluated the changes in slope of the measured temperature development at different positions in the sample [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. A more precise analysis of the thermal effects of solid-solid phase transformations is possible using calorimetry. DSC, in particular, allows for the detection of quench-induced precipitation in age-hardening metals [
 <xref rid="B31-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Amongst the potential methods for the in situ detection of quench-induced precipitation in aluminium alloys, DSC is the most effective approach, as it has significant advantages. These in brief are: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>DSC allows for controlled linear heating and cooling by providing the largest accessible dynamic scanning rate range, which now covers the whole cooling rate range of technological and physical relevance. By using a combination of different DSC devices, rates of about 10
    <sup>−5</sup> to 10
    <sup>5</sup> K/s [
    <xref rid="B83-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
    <xref rid="B84-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>] can be achieved.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>DSC samples are typically in the mm range, which in most cases allows further analysis after the DSC experiment, for instance for hardness testing or microstructural investigations [
    <xref rid="B83-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
    <xref rid="B84-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
    <xref rid="B113-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>In addition to linear cooling, nonlinear Newtonian heating and cooling can also be investigated using DSC [
    <xref rid="B114-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>With regard to the abovementioned detection limits, DSC offers the highest sensitivity of all techniques over the whole dynamic range. In particular, precipitation of any precipitate size and very small volume fractions of precipitation can be detected by DSC, and even cluster formation can be recorded [
    <xref rid="B99-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,
    <xref rid="B115-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>If properly conducted, DSC allows for quantitative evaluation of the enthalpy changes related to precipitation. Since these enthalpy changes are directly proportional to the atomic fraction transformed, analysis of the volume fraction of precipitates is possible [
    <xref rid="B116-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
    <xref rid="B117-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
    <xref rid="B118-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
    <xref rid="B119-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
