<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par53">To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to screen for PAAD antigens for developing mRNA vaccine. We constructed the aberrantly expressed and mutational landscape of PAAD and identified a series of targetable antigens, of which ADAM9, EFNB2, MET, TPX2, TMOD3 and WNT7A are promising mRNA vaccine candidates. Their upregulation was not only associated with poor prognosis and RFS, but also high APC and B cell infiltration. Therefore, these antigens play critical roles in the development and progression of PAAD and can be directly processed and presented to CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells in the event of adequate lymphocyte infiltration to induce an immune attack. Although these candidates have to be functionally validated, their potential for mRNA development is supported by previous reports. For example, ADAM9 is involved in tumor cell metastasis, proliferation, angiogenesis and immune evasion [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] and high levels of ADAM-9 in pancreatic cancer is associated with short OS and higher tumor grade and progression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Furthermore, ADAM9 is upregulated by aberrant KRAS/NF-kB signaling in cancer cells, and knocking down ADAM9 suppresses KRAS and MEK-ERK signaling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. EFNB2 acts as a oncogene in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) and is markedly upregulated in PDAC and correlated to clinical stage and Ki67 expression levels in PDAC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. EFNB2 knockout suppresses cancer cell proliferation, migration and invasion by inducing p53/p21-mediated G0/G1 phase blockade [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The aberrantly high levels and activation of MET are closely related with cancer onset, progression and metastasis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] and its upregulated in pancreatic cancer associated with grade [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Pharmacological or genetic ablation of MET significantly prolonged survival of mice bearing PDAC xenografts. TPX2 is a prognostic biomarker of KARS-mutant PDAC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], and its high expression levels correlate to shorter survival and increased frequency of oncogenic KRAS mutations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Targeted inhibition of KRAS decreased TPX2 expression in PDAC cells, which in turn reduced clonogenic and anchorage-independent growth and migration 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>
 <sup>41</sup>. TMOD3 is a tumor suppressor target and an independent prognostic marker of PDAC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], and its overexpression in hepatocellular carcinoma correlates with tumor progression and poor patient survival, and TMOD3-knockout liver cancer cells have decreased proliferation, invasion and migration [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. WNT7A is a ligand of the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway, and highly expressed in PDAC wherein it positively correlates with poor prognosis and lymph node metastasis. Inhibition of WNT7A disrupts Wnt/β-catenin signaling in pancreatic cancer cell lines and suppresses proliferation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].
</p>
