<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par54">Given that mRNA vaccine is only beneficial for a fraction of cancer patients, we classified PAAD into five immune subtypes based on immune gene expression profiles for selecting the appropriate population for vaccination. The five immune subtypes exhibited distinct molecular, cellular and clinical characteristics. Patients with IS1 and IS2 tumors showed better prognosis compared to other subtypes in both ICGC and TCGA cohorts. This suggests the immunotyping can be used for predicting the prognoses of PAAD patients, and we demonstrated its superior predictive accuracy compared to established tumor makers like CA199 and CA125, as well as traditional staging and grading. In addition to prognostic prediction, immunotyping is also indicative of the therapeutic response to mRNA vaccine. For instance, patients with IS4 and IS5 tumors with higher TMB and somatic mutation rates may have greater responsiveness to mRNA vaccine. The high expressions of ICPs in IS1 tumors in ICGC cohort, and in IS2 tumors in TCGA cohort suggest an immunosuppressive tumor microenvironment, which may inhibit the mRNA vaccine from eliciting an effective immune response. In contrast, the elevated expression of ICD modulators in IS4 tumors in ICGC cohort, and in IS5 tumors in TCGA cohort are suggestive of greater potential of mRNA vaccine in these immune subtypes. Interestingly, MET is also an ICD modulator, and may therefore be a stronger candidate for mRNA vaccine compared to the other selected antigens. Furthermore, the complex immune landscape of PAAD indicates considerable heterogeneity between individual patients as well as within the same immune subtype, which narrows down the immune components for developing personalized mRNA vaccine-based therapeutics. MAP 4 K1, TBC1D10C and TRAF3IP3 were identified as hub genes in the blue module, and their upregulation was negatively associated with the component 1 of immune landscape, suggesting that patients expressing high levels of these genes may not respond to the mRNA vaccine.</p>
