<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interface issues could not only exist between electrodes and SCEs, but also perplex the good connection between polymer chains and ceramic fillers. There have been many researches focusing on new approaches to improve the interface contact between polymers and ceramic. Whereas, the interfaces between ceramic nanoparticles and polymer chains in SCEs receive little attentions, but it is of great significance to construct an interface between ceramic and polymer with little resistance for high‐performance all‐solid‐state batteries.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref> Constructing excellent interfaces between ceramic fillers and polymer chains in SCEs could effectively solve the intrinsic problems of SCE to achieve high‐performance all‐solid‐state batteries. Frederieke Langer et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0118" ref-type="ref">118</xref> investigated lithium ion transition resistance of the ceramic/polymer interface using the Cu/PEO/LLZO/PEO/Cu system by electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS) to identify and quantify the interface transport processes. It revealed that the activation energy of Li ion transport across the interface is as high as 0.9 eV at temperature above the melting point of PEO and lithium ion transition was impeded. Zagórski et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">67</xref> presented the similar conclusion that a high interfacial resistance between the garnet particles and the PEO/LiTFSI matrix that could reach ≈10
 <sup>4</sup> Ω cm
 <sup>2</sup> (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0011" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>11</bold>
 </xref>a). Moreover, the local Li ion exchange at the LLZO/PEO interface leads to the minimization of the Li ion concentration gradient in the SCE, which facilitates the Li ion homogenous deposition and thus avoiding Li dendrite growth. To further investigate the origin of high LLZO/polymer interfacial resistance, Brogioli et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0119" ref-type="ref">119</xref> derived the mathematical model of the diffuse layers following the traditional derivation of the Gouy–Chapman–Stern equation (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0011" ref-type="fig">11</xref>b). By combining the theoretical calculations and experiments, it could be deduced that the large value of the interface resistance comes from high activation energy and does not from the electrostatic repulsion of lithium ion.
</p>
