<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As early as 1956, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Vague (1956)</xref> proposed that obesity as an important risk factor for cardiovascular disease is related to the distribution of adipose tissue in the human body, not just the increase of total adipose tissue. There are two types of adipose tissue in mammals: white adipose tissue (WAT), which is the main form of energy storage in the body, and brown adipose tissue (BAT). WAT is primarily composed of subcutaneous adipose tissue (SAT) and visceral adipose tissue (VAT). WAT can be enlarged by increasing adipocyte size (hypertrophy) or adipocyte number (hyperplasia); adipocyte hypertrophy is associated with adipose tissue dysfunction and inflammation, whereas hyperplasia is involved in the improvement of insulin sensitivity (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Silva and Baptista, 2019</xref>). Previous studies have shown that the expansion of SAT is dominated by adipocyte hyperplasia, while VAT [including omental, mesenteric, and perirenal adipose tissue (PAT)] is primarily increased by adipocyte hypertrophy (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Joe et al., 2009</xref>). Compared with SAT and VAT secretes higher levels of proinflammatory factors and lower levels of anti-inflammatory factors; therefore, it is easier to break down to increase plasma-free fatty acids (FFA). High concentrations of FFA can inhibit insulin signaling pathways in skeletal muscle and liver, induce insulin resistance, and increase the risk of diabetes and cardiovascular diseases (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">McFarlane et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Rocchini, 2002</xref>). Therefore, the accumulation of VAT is more closely associated with cardiovascular disease, insulin resistance, hypermetabolism, and cancer (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Dobbelsteyn et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Fox et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Tran et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Tchernof and Després, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Silva and Baptista, 2019</xref>). In addition, compared with other VATs [such as epididymal adipose tissue (EAT)], PAT has some characteristics of BAT. In adults, PAT depot is one of the most frequent depots where BAT have been found (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Svensson et al., 2014</xref>). Moreover, the expression of UCP1 in PAT is related to blood pressure (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2015</xref>). Whereas, some investigators indicate that EAT maximum thickness is better associated with cardiovascular risk factors (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Kawamoto et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Nishina et al., 2003</xref>).
</p>
