<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The anabolic androgenic steroids (AAS) are synthetic derivatives of testosterone, created to provide anabolic potency and low androgenic effect [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. While most users abuse AAS to improve physical performance, nearly all of them are unaware of the numerous side effects that can be associated with androgen misuse [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Cardiovascular diseases, cancer, liver dysfunction and psychiatric disorders are some of those well- documented problems [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Similarly, under the influence of AAS, the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal (HPG) axis is one of the most affected body systems [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The neural control of this axis resides within the hypothalamus, which is characterized by the expression of high levels of androgen and estrogen receptors (AR and ER) [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The medial preoptic area (mPOA) is a steroid-sensitive hypothalamic region, that is populated by neurons expressing gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Indeed, GnRH neurons respond to fluctuations of gonadal steroids, which result in neuroplasticity changes leading to pulsatile secretion of this peptide. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have shown that exposure to steroids is associated with alterations on GnRH expression and secretion. For instance, studies in rodents [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] showed that exposure to either androgens or estrogens reduced GnRH transcripts.
</p>
