<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The reported antiviral mechanisms of LF include (1) direct binding to viral protein and inhibition of the adsorption of virus to the target cells [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12–14</xref>]; (2) binding to heparan sulfate proteoglycans (HSPGs) on the host cell surface, which reduces viral attachment and subsequent viral entry [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15–19</xref>]. Heparan sulfate (HS) is a linear and sulfated polysaccharide that is abundantly expressed on the surface of almost all cell types in the forms of HSPGs. The negatively charged HSPGs often serve as an attachment factor for a diverse of viruses [
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]; (3) interfere with intracellular trafficking of virus [
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. LF was reported to have antiviral activity against SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. However, the broad-spectrum antiviral activity and antiviral mechanism of action of LF against common human coronaviruses as well as SARS-CoV-2 have not been systematically studied and therefore warrants further investigation. In this work, we profiled the broad-spectrum antiviral activity of LF against multiple common human coronaviruses including HCoV-OC43, HCoV-NL63, and HCoV-229E as well as SARS-CoV-2 and its mechanism of action. It was found that LF inhibits not only SARS-CoV-2, but also HCoV-OC43, HCoV-NL63, and HCoV-229E. The antiviral mechanism of action of LF was found to be mediated through binding to HSPGs on the host cell surface, thereby preventing viral attachment to the host cells. Several recent studies suggest that HSPGs serve as an attachment factor for the initial tethering of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein to host cell membrane and facilitates the subsequent binding to the specific receptor ACE2 [
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23–26</xref>]. Specifically, drug time-of-addition experiment and SARS-CoV-2 pseudovirus assays indicated that LF exerts its antiviral activity by blocking viral attachment to target cells. In addition, LF has direct binding to heparin, a mimetic of HSPGs, and pre-mixing LF with heparin decreased the inhibitory activity of LF on viral attachment and reduced antiviral activity of LF in cell culture. Furthermore, we have shown that LF has synergistic antiviral effect with remdesivir, which further warrants its development as a potential anti-coronavirus agent against both current circulating and future emerging coronaviruses.
</p>
