<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>LiNi
 <sub>0.5</sub>Mn
 <sub>1.5</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> is a typical high-voltage cathode material with a voltage plateau as high as 4.7 V.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>
 </sup> This material has a three-dimensional lithium-ion diffusion path and an excellent intrinsic rate performance.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref>
 </sup> In addition, it has been found that there may be a two-phase coexistence region and phase transition region in the voltage plateau, which can be attributed to the change in the degree of order caused by the rearrangement of Ni and Mn transition metals in the sublattice.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>
 </sup> However, in full-cell applications, it has been found that the battery capacity decays faster than the commercial standard.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>
 </sup> The capacity fading may be due to (1) the increase in interface impedance caused by the oxidation and decomposition of an electrolyte; (2) the loss of the active material caused by the dissolution of the transition metal. In addition, the stress caused by the crystal phase transformation during the lithium removal from the positive electrode may also cause capacity decay.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>
 </sup> The electrochemical thermodynamic parameters are very sensitive to the phase transition, which is helpful to analyze the crystal phase transition when the cathode is deintercalated with lithium and to clarify the mechanism of smooth phase transition by doping element modification. As of now, there is no report available on the entropy change in LiNi
 <sub>0.5</sub>Mn
 <sub>1.5</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>. In this paper, we study the entropy change characteristics of LiNi
 <sub>0.5</sub>Mn
 <sub>1.5</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>/Li half-cell in different states of discharge (SODs).
</p>
