<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, LIB recycling faces some challenges, which limit its scalability and fast development. 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>First, the collection of spent LIBs is costly and requires involvement of all members of the consumption chain, including producers, sellers, governments, waste managers, and consumers. For instance, in European Union, less than 20% of the spent LIBs were collected in 2016 according to Eucobat (European Compliance Organizations for Batteries) [
    <xref rid="B16-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] despite well-established regulations and recycling industry. In North America, recovery estimation is around 5% [
    <xref rid="B234-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">234</xref>]. Other than collection, shipment of spent LIBs, particularly large lithium-ion battery packs, is problematic. This critical aspect is one of the most discussed topics in conferences and workshops, as seen during NaatBat 2019 Battery Conference held in Buffalo. It is also studied by the United Nations Committee of Experts on the Transport of Dangerous Goods, and several sessions are dedicated to this subject.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Secondly, the diversity in LIB materials and rapid evolution of technologies make it difficult to plan the variation of material inflow. Over the past decade, cathode composition has faced a deep evolution from early stage of LCO to new composition such as NMC, LFP, NCA, and LMO. In addition, some products having cathode additives such as yttrium are now available on the market, which will eventually end up in recycling process. Moreover, modification of the anode material is undergoing, shifting from graphite to LTO, and, in the near future, to silicon-based materials. Further, the segment of electrolyte additives in lithium-ion batteries is a dynamic sector; we noted 312 patents on various additives in 24 months. Lastly, the current research push towards all-solid-state Li batteries is imposing new challenges necessitating early consideration of the end-of-life fate of these new devices to simplify recycling. Considering these upcoming changes, management of the mass balance, mitigation of health and safety issues (One of the example is propane sultone, which is adopted in some composition and has a safety issue to manage with accuracy (see CAS number 1120-71-4)), and waste management will continue to be a challenge for battery recycling plants.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Finally, strong competition between battery recyclers and the volatility of commodities market prices restrict profit margins for recyclers, which weaken the viability of the industry. This aspect must be addressed by reinforcement of producer responsibility to ensure the involvement of the producer of the waste in the recycling cost when recovered materials cannot compensate the processing cost, e.g., manufacturers of LFP and LMO systems. This concept is already largely accepted in Europe, where the recycling fee for alkaline batteries is shared by the manufacturer and importer.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
