<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="advs2293-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Patients with strong response to gluten have low‐level inflammation in the gut before challenge. A) Differential expression of epithelial proteins comparing “responder” and “non‐responder” biopsies at baseline. Color indicate significant proteins from Figure 
   <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1E</xref> (“Responders” after versus before challenge,
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, two‐sample Student 
   <italic>t</italic>‐test, FDR = 0.05, Benjamini Hochberg adjusted). B) Pearson correlation of fold change protein expression for significant proteins (“Responders” after versus before challenge, 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). C) 2D‐categorical enrichment for biological pathways from 
   <italic>t</italic>‐test fold change in expression. D,E) Comparison of expression for proteins that map to the indicated pathways (median 
   <italic>z</italic>‐score per responder group). F) Principle component analysis (PCA) plot of apical epithelial cell layer samples based on expression of 1151 proteins. Each point represents one biopsy (
   <italic>n</italic> = 11). G) Expression of proteins that map to KEGG complement and coagulation cascade in baseline samples from the epithelial proteome and the apical epithelial proteome dataset (epithelial dataset; ten pathway proteins, each point represents median 
   <italic>z</italic>‐scored protein expression per biopsy (
   <italic>n</italic> = 13); apical epithelial dataset, five pathway proteins, each dot represent 
   <italic>z</italic>‐scored expression per sample (
   <italic>n</italic> = 19) from 11 biopsies)(Welch 
   <italic>t</italic>‐test). A_R, after “responder”; B_R, before “responder”; A_NR, after “non‐responder”; B_NR, before “non‐responder”; R, “responder”; NR, “non‐responder”; GOBP, Gene Ontology Biological Processes; GOCC, Gene Ontology Cellular Compartment; GOMF, Gene Ontology Molecular Function; KEGG, Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ADVS-8-2003526-g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
