<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With the technical progress in recent years, lithium ion batteries (LIBs) have captured growing attention as promising candidates for traditional energy storage devices, because of characteristics of high energy efficiency, wide temperature adaptation range, long cyclic life, eco-benignancy, no memory effect, light weight, rapid charging/discharging dynamics (due to the minimum metal ion diameter relative to other metal ions), small volume, and low self-discharge. Because the ion lithium storage performance inherently depends on the electrode materials, the novel excellent-performance electrode substances which manage to deliver a great deal of energy for several minutes instead of hours are in high demand, to heighten the power output and reduce the charging duration within LIBs. These substances can hence expedite the technical leaps relevant to the deployment of portable/flexible electronics industries, vehicular sectors, and smart grid systems, and meet a massive demand for a novel large power-consuming energy storage system. The most generally applied routes for enhancing the energy/power rating properties can deal with the introduction of myriads of nanoscaled or/and holey (usually graded) architectures, which can—to the largest degree—shorten the Li
 <sup>+</sup> solid-like movement lengths, permit the faster lithium passage across whole electrodes, and enlarge the accessible interface boundaries between electrode substances and electrolytes. Besides, lots of intricate morphological engineering avenues involving the nanosheets, nanowires, nanotubes, hollow/yolk-shell, specific crystal facet exposure, and nanocubes have been widely used in conjunction with the powerful but sophisticated surface coating (SiOC, carbon, Si, TiO
 <sub>2</sub> and so on). These strategies aim at guaranteeing the effective stress relaxation of electrochemically active phases during lithiation, which can generally have a significant impact upon addressing the variables such as the electronic conductivity, hysteresis problem between discharge and charge (intrinsic to conversion reactions), reversible capacity retention and working voltage during cycling, another several key points of the usage of large current loads [
 <xref rid="B1-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].
</p>
