<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Actually, notwithstanding the superb lithium migration, graphite will dysfunction under large charge/discharge speeds as a result of adverse stress intensification and lithium dendrite growth, the latter inducing some safety issues like short circuiting, fire, and explosions [
 <xref rid="B6-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Such fatal drawbacks can intrinsically stunt the wide employment of the low-potential negative electrodes for high-rate usage, in that the electrode nonuniformity or any source of the augmented overpotentials will trigger off the harmful lithium galvanization potentials on the electrode surface or/and serious surface cracking/disintegration [
 <xref rid="B6-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Tetragonal rutile-typed SnO
 <sub>2</sub> nanocrystallites with a mean working potential (0.6 V vs. Li
 <sup>+</sup>/Li), possess the great-theoretic capacity and big-rate conversion-(de)alloying chemistry under no threat of a lithium dendrite production or marked solid-electrolyte interface evolution. However, SnO
 <sub>2</sub> particles inevitably undergo a detrimental decay of the full-cell potential and thus the energy content [
 <xref rid="B11-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. For this sufficiently-identified “elevated” potential and high-rate negative electrode, a reversible Li
 <sup>+</sup> storage capacity of the highly graded flower-like micro-spheres of ~2 μm assembled by thin SnO
 <sub>2</sub> nanosheets as subunits approaches roughly 400 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> under a high current density of 800 mA g
 <sup>−1</sup> [
 <xref rid="B11-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In comparison, over long-term study, hybridization with various carbonaceous allotropes has invested SnO
 <sub>2</sub> with a far superior reversible capacity—even reaching 634 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> at 6.4 A g
 <sup>−1</sup>—equivalent to about 3.7 lithium ions per transition metal (Li
 <sup>+</sup>/TM) (TM = transition metal) [
 <xref rid="B11-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Nonetheless, the application of nanoscaled and hierarchically holey structures in electrochemical energy storage technologies innately suffers from acute prejudice of volumetric and areal energy density owing to ultralow packing density. Besides, fabricating and characterizing such exquisitely engineered nanostructures might hardly evade both the supramolecular chemistry and in situ monitoring tools, always resulting in the high cumbersomeness and cost. The pertinent preparation protocols rarely get rid of both small product throughput or/and concomitant formation of chemical wastes, whilst also encountering performance deterioration in the course of repeated charging/discharging (due to events like the catalytic dissociation of electrolytes and topological fluctuation) [
 <xref rid="B15-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-nanomaterials-10-00249" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Simply speaking, the active anode materials with poor electrical conductivity and structural stability—as well as low Li-ion diffusivity and transition-metal cation dissolution—can markedly degrade the performance (capacity, rate performance, and cycling stability) of LIBs. In particular, the morphological evolution of such electrode materials can severely abolish the nano-structuring and exacerbate the initial capacity fading.
</p>
