<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The biofilm-forming capabilities of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> strains DH5α and 55989 
 <italic>agg</italic>3
 <sup>−</sup> expressing the different AAF variants were tested as described by Reisner and colleagues [
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] with the following modifications: the bacterial strains plated on LB agar containing the suitable antibiotics and incubated overnight at 37°C. A single colony was inoculated in 2 ml LB medium containing the suitable antibiotics and grown overnight at 37°C and 180 rpm for 7 h. Afterward, the starter cultures were diluted 1:100 in 3 ml LB medium containing the suitable antibiotics and incubated at 37°C and 180 rpm for 16 h. The cultures were diluted to OD
 <sub>600</sub> 0.05 using fresh medium supplemented with arabinose 1% (w/v). Per 96-well plate (clear U-bottom, PVC; Corning, New York, USA), eight wells per strain were filled with 140 µl each, and plates were kept static at 37°C (or 30°C or 20°C, respectively) for 48 h. In order to minimize evaporation, plates were kept in a metal box lined with moist paper towels. Afterward, the wells were washed three times with 200 µl PBS and the plate was dried at 80°C for 1 h. Staining of biofilm was done by incubation with 175 µl crystal violet (CV) (0.1%) per well for 1 h at room temperature. The CV solution was removed, and the wells were washed three times with double distilled H
 <sub>2</sub>O (ddH2O) and dried for 1 h. For the quantification of biofilm production, each well was treated with 200 µl destaining solution (80% ethanol, 20% acetone) for 30 min. Afterward, 100 µl were transferred to a new 96-well plate and the OD was measured using a Tecan Infinite F200 plate reader at 595 nm. For each strain and condition, we tested three independent biological replicates with six technical repeats each. Data evaluation was done as described by Stepanović and colleagues. The cutoff OD (ODc) was defined as three standard deviations above the mean OD of the negative control values [
 <xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Therefore, all tested samples shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6</xref>, except for the bacteria expressing AAF/III and AAF/V, produced significantly more biofilm than the negative control.
</p>
