<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">During initial ISR activation, eIF2α is phosphorylated by one or more of the four enzymes in the eIF2α kinase family, each of which responds to different stress stimuli: GNC2 (amino acid deprivation), PKR (viral infection), HRI (heme deficiency and ROS), and PERK (endoplasmic reticulum and mitochondrial stress) (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>). In the present study, because we previously measured elevated amino acid concentrations with 12-h 20 µM DCVC treatment (Elkin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020a</xref>), GNC2 is likely not the source of eIF2α phosphorylation. Although not directly tested here, previous evidence suggests that mitochondrial dysfunction, which is closely associated with ER stress (Malhotra and Kaufman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2011</xref>), may be the primary stimulus driving the DCVC-induced ISR, most likely activated by eIF2α kinases HRI and/or PERK (Quiros et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2017</xref>; Shpilka and Haynes 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2018</xref>). Specifically, we previously reported that 20 µM DCVC decreases mitochondrial-dependent basal, maximum, and reserve oxygen consumption rates, decreased ATP-linked respiration and coupling efficiency, increased proton leak, and dissipated mitochondrial membrane potential in HTR-8/SVneo cells (Elkin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2019</xref>; Hassan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2016</xref>). Moreover, it is well established that mitochondria are the key target of DCVC toxicity in kidney proximal tubular cells (Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2001</xref>; Lash and Anders 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1987</xref>; Lash et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2003</xref>; van de Water et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">1993</xref>; van de Water et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1994</xref>; Xu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">2008</xref>). The ATF4-mediated gene expression pattern we observed in HTR-8/SVneo cells closely resembles the mitochondrial stress signature response reported in a multi-omics study by Quiros et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2017</xref>), including up-regulation of 9 amino acid biosynthesis and 5 transport genes. Moreover, we previously reported elevated SLC1A5 protein concentrations with 12-h 20 µM DCVC in HTR-8/SVneo cells (Elkin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020a</xref>). Together, the available evidence suggests that mitochondrial dysfunction is likely a major stimulus driving DCVC-induced ISR activation.
</p>
