<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Amorphous metallic alloys exhibit outstanding mechanical, magnetic, and chemical properties that are unusual for solid metals. More than half a century has passed since Pol Duwez reported his remarkable findings in 1960 [
 <xref rid="B1-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], and the subject area has moved a long way. Once the potential of metallic glasses for any certain application was recognized, it was seen that a scaling-up method was needed to deploy metallic glasses commercially [
 <xref rid="B2-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. To produce metallic glasses continuously, in the early 1970s, researchers at Allied Chemical Corporation developed continuous casting or melt spinning processes for commercial manufacture of metallic glass ribbons and sheets, and at that time the field of melt spinning technique in producing metallic glasses started gaining momentum [
 <xref rid="B3-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Relations between processing parameters and ribbon quality and dimensions have been discussed by some researchers in recent years [
 <xref rid="B8-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]; however, only a small fraction of the metallic glasses have so far been commercially deployed mainly due to the difficulty in obtaining good quality in such thin products. For applications in transformer cores, metallic glasses such as Metglas
 <sup>®</sup> Alloy 2605SA1 can reduce transformation losses by 70% compared to crystalline iron cores [
 <xref rid="B2-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-materials-10-00420" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
