<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to secreted proteins and carbohydrates one major distinguishing feature of biofilms is the presence of secreted extracellular DNA (eDNA), particularly in staphylococcal biofilms where it is crucial for biofilm structural integrity and maintenance [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33–35</xref>]. In fact, the extracellular matrix of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm is primarily composed of eDNA and the polysaccharide intercellular adhesin (PIA) [
 <xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The formation of the eDNA matrix appears to be necessary for early staphylococcal biofilm development, as early DNase treatment profoundly impairs biofilm formation [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, the generation of the eDNA matrix is facilitated by autolysis of a subset of initial biofilm cells, regulated by the 
 <italic>cidABC</italic> and 
 <italic>lrgAB</italic> operons [
 <xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38–40</xref>]. Gene regulation in 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms is complex and involves the activity of several major global regulators [
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]; however, the environment in a biofilm can be altered by the presence of co-infecting microorganisms where polymicrobial interactions can result in augmented pathogenesis. To that end, the overall goal of this study was to elucidate the impact of inter-species interactions during a biofilm-associated infection in a host. Specifically, we used an established mouse model for 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> grown biofilms to demonstrate the therapeutic implications of device-associated polymicrobial infections. Further, we aimed to provide lacking insights into the transcriptional changes governing the interactions between these diverse pathogens, particularly within the context of antimicrobial resistance.
</p>
