<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig4">
 <label>Figure 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>AS6 regulates DNA repair, cell cycle, and apoptosis in MCF7 cells. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Key DNA repair genes affected by AS6. RNA-seq data showing a markedly reduced expression of 
   <italic>ATM</italic>, 
   <italic>p53</italic>, and 
   <italic>BRCA1</italic> in AS6-treated MCF7 cells. Light grey, untreated control; light pink, 0.5 μM AS6-treated cells. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3; **P &lt; 0.005; ***P &lt; 0.0005. (
   <bold>B</bold>) Real-time PCR data showing the expression of 
   <italic>ATM</italic>, 
   <italic>p53</italic>, and 
   <italic>BRCA1</italic> in AS6-treated HUMEC and MCF7 cells. 
   <italic>ACTIN</italic> was used as a reference gene for a normalization. From left to right bars, untreated control HUMEC, 0.5 μM AS6-treated HUMEC, untreated control MCF7 cells, 0.5 μM AS6-treated MCF7 cells. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3; error bars show s.d.; **P &lt; 0.005; ***P &lt; 0.0001. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Immunoblotting results showing a markedly reduced protein expression of ATM, p53, and BRCA1 in AS6-treated MCF7 cells. ACTIN was used as a loading control. Left, immunoblots; right, quantitative presentations of the signals, normalized with the control. AS6 concentrations in μM. Signal intensity of immunoblotting results throughout this manuscript was measured by Image J. Full-length blots were presented in Supplementary Fig. 
   <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>A. (
   <bold>D</bold>) Key cell cycle regulators affected by AS6. RNA-seq data showing a significantly reduced expression of 
   <italic>CDC20</italic>, 
   <italic>BUB1B</italic>, 
   <italic>PLK1</italic>, 
   <italic>CHEK1</italic>, 
   <italic>CDK1</italic>, 
   <italic>MCM4</italic>, and 
   <italic>CDC25A</italic> in AS6-treated MCF7 cells but not in HUMEC. White, untreated control HUMEC; purple, 0.5 μM AS6-treated HUMEC; Light grey, untreated control MCF7 cells; light pink, 0.5 μM AS6-treated MCF7 cells. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3; *P &lt; 0.01; **P &lt; 0.001; ***P &lt; 0.0001; ****P &lt; 0.00001. (
   <bold>E</bold>) Real-time PCR results confirming the reduced mRNA expression of 
   <italic>CDC20</italic>, 
   <italic>BUB1B</italic>, 
   <italic>CHEK1</italic>, 
   <italic>CDK1</italic>, and 
   <italic>MCM4</italic> in AS6-treated MCF7 cells but not in HUMEC. 
   <italic>ACTIN</italic> was used as a reference gene for a normalization. From left to right bars, untreated control HUMEC, 0.5 μM AS6-treated HUMEC, untreated control MCF7 cells, 0.5 μM AS6-treated MCF7 cells. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3; error bars show s.d.; *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.005; ***P &lt; 0.0001. (
   <bold>F</bold>) Immunoblotting results demonstrating a dramatically disrupted protein expression of critical cell cycle regulators CDC20, BUB1B, PLK1, CHEK1, MCM4, CDC25A, cyclin B1, and p21 in AS6-treated MCF7 cells. ACTIN was used as a loading control. Left, immunoblots; right, quantitative presentations of the immunoblotting signals, normalized with the loading control. AS6 concentrations in μM. Full-length blots were presented in Supplementary Fig. 
   <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>B. (
   <bold>G</bold>) Key apoptotic factors affected by AS6. Real-time PCR results of 
   <italic>CASP9</italic> showing its increased mRNA expression in MCF7 cells but not in HUMEC. 
   <italic>ACTIN</italic> was used as a reference gene for a normalization. From left to right bars, untreated control HUMEC, 0.5 μM AS6-treated HUMEC, untreated control MCF7 cells, 0.5 μM AS6-treated MCF7 cells. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3; error bars show s.d.; *P &lt; 0.05. (
   <bold>H</bold>) Immunoblotting showing a marked increase of HIF1α protein expression (left) and the quantification of the signal intensity (right) in AS6-treated MCF7 cells. ACTIN was used as a loading control. Full-length blots were presented in Supplementary Fig. 
   <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>C. (
   <bold>I</bold>) RNA-seq data of 
   <italic>HSP70</italic> and 
   <italic>HSP90</italic> mRNA expression in AS6-treated MCF7 cells. Light grey, untreated control; light pink, 0.5 μM AS6-treated cells. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3; **P &lt; 0.001; ***P &lt; 0.0001. (
   <bold>J</bold>) Real-time PCR results validating the increased 
   <italic>HSP70</italic> and 
   <italic>HSP90</italic> mRNA expression in AS6-treated MCF7 cells but not in HUMEC. From left to right bars, untreated control HUMEC, 0.5 μM AS6-treated HUMEC, untreated control MCF7 cells, 0.5 μM AS6-treated MCF7 cells. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3; error bars show s.d.; **P &lt; 0.005; ***P &lt; 0.0001. (
   <bold>K</bold>) Immunoblotting showing increased HSP70 and HSP90 protein expression (left) and the quantification of the signal intensity (right) in AS6-treated MCF7 cells. ACTIN was used as a loading control. Full-length blots were presented in Supplementary Fig. 4D.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_82551_Fig4a_HTML" id="MO4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_82551_Fig4b_HTML" id="MO45" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
