<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Besides immune-related hallmarks, we also involved tumor immunogenomic signatures, immune-related biological processes, tumor infiltrated immune cells, and immune checkpoints. These features reflect immunological activities from diverse aspects in tumor samples (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Grivennikov et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Mellman, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Greten and Grivennikov, 2019</xref>). In particular, tumor immunogenomic signatures represent genomic variations that were induced by or could induce immune reprogramming (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Thorsson et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, TGF-β signaling contributes to malignancy of cancer cells and immunosuppressive microenvironment, thus thwarting cancer immunotherapy (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Colak and ten Dijke, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Batlle and Massagué, 2019</xref>). A large amount of lncRNAs was related to TGF-β response in prostate cancer, suggesting their profound implication in TGF-β-mediated immune processes. For example, TGF-β1-simulated lncRNA DNM3OS induces transformation of prostate stromal cells by targeting miR-29a/29b/COL3A1 and miR-361/TGFβ1 axes (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2019</xref>). As another example, the therapeutic efficiency of PSMA-targeted human CAR T cells are enhanced upon TGF-β insensitivity in the treatment of prostate cancer (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Kloss et al., 2018</xref>). Furthermore, stromal fraction is the second frequent lncRNA-related immune feature, profoundly implicating in cancer development and immunity (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Tyekucheva et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">De Jaeghere et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahn and Kim, 2020</xref>). For example, lncRNA H19 derived from carcinoma-associated fibroblasts (CAFs) contributes to the stemness and chemoresistance of colorectal cancer by targeting miR-141 (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Ren et al., 2018</xref>). As another example, lncRNA-CAF induce transition from normal fibroblasts to CAFs by stabling IL-33, thereby leading to development of oral squamous cell carcinoma (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Ding et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
