<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The activities of immune cells and abundance of immune checkpoints were crucial factors that affect the outcomes of immunotherapy for tumor patients (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Cha et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Jafari et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020</xref>). Our analysis found that a large number of lncRNAs were significantly associated with memory resting CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, such as MAGI2-AS3 and CTD-3184A7.4. Memory CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell is a subset of T cell population that sustains in the absence of antigen and prepares for rapid immune response upon repeat antigen exposure (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Hope et al., 2019</xref>). It has been shown that central memory CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells in peripheral blood are associated with clinical response of PD-1 antibody therapy in melanoma patients. Our observations indicated that these lncRNAs might be able to modulate the activities of memory resting CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells. Overexpression of MAGI2-AS3 or knockdown of CTD-3184A7.4 may activate memory resting CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells to enhance immune response against tumor cells. Interestingly, MAGI2-AS3 has been widely studied in cancers, while these studies mainly focused in regulating cancer cells themselves (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Li D. et al., 2020</xref>). Our results point out that various lncRNA could have immune regulatory role other than their influence on cancer cells. In addition, the close connection between lncRNAs and immune checkpoints has been revealed, suggesting a profound implication of lncRNA in immune checkpoint regulation. For example, LncRNA KCNQ1OT1 inhibits the cytotoxicity of CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells and promotes the malignant ability of prostate cancer cells by targeting miR-15a/PD-L1 axis (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020</xref>). As another example, lncAMPC activates LIF/LIFR/Jak1/STAT3 pathway to stable PD-L1 and metastasis-associated genes, thereby contributing to metastasis and immunosuppression in prostate cancer (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). Of note, in prostate cancer, LINC00861 was closely associated with T cells regulatory, macrophages M2 and mast cells resting as well as a series of immune checkpoints, including PD1, PD-L1, and CTLA4. These evidence indicates a LINC00861-mediated tumor immune response beyond its reported regulation of malignant potential on cancer cells (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2021</xref>). Further experimental validation is needed to confirm the regulatory functions of the immune-related lncRNAs and select the most efficacious lncRNAs to boost the antitumor immune response. We believe that intervention of immune response through lncRNAs will be promising therapeutics for patients with prostate cancer.
</p>
