<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">The well-conserved gene structure in extant species indicates that this organization and arrangement might be present in the last common mammalian ancestor, which represented the vital function for organisms (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Madsen, 2009</xref>). In our study, the number of <italic>ACPT</italic> exons are 11 in placental mammals, which encode 427 amino acids (human ACPT sequence as the reference sequence). Our study collected that four residues (191N, 269N, 330N and 339N) of the extracellular region were for glycosylation, two residues (41H and 289D) directly involved in catalysis (from the UniProt database). In addition, mutation in seven residues were reported that were responsible for AI (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Seymen et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2017a</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2">Fig. S4</xref>). Besides, there are three disulfide bond regions, namely, site 159&#8211;378, site 214&#8211;312, site 353&#8211;357. In fact, we detected not only teratogenic mutations but also inactivated mutations in these functional sites and domains. For example, enamel in finless porpoise were degenerated (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Ishiyama, 1987</xref>), mutation in site 76 (R &#8594; C) was found in <italic>N. asiaeorientalis</italic>. Previous research has confirmed that site 76 mutated into Cys (C) in human ACPT would lead to hypoplastic AI (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Seymen et al., 2016</xref>), from which this result further supported that teeth in finless porpoise were degenerated in molecular level. Of cause, most obvious characteristics of <italic>ACPT</italic> is that different types of inactivating mutations were found in toothless and enamel-less mammals, for example, baleen whales, pangolins, sloths and so on (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2">Figs. S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2">S3</xref>). Therefore, <italic>ACPT</italic> could be a candidate gene for AI and studying mammalian tooth loss and enamel loss.</p>