<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Enhanced reactivity of CuZn catalysts for CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR was recently demonstrated.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref111">111</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref298">298</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref303">303</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref437">437</xref>
 </sup> Nanoporous CuZn showed significantly enhanced Faradaic efficiency for CO and formate production,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref299">299</xref>
 </sup> oxide-derived CuZn catalysts were found promising for the formation of C
 <sub>2</sub> products,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>
 </sup> while Zn-coated Cu electrodes were shown to have higher selectivity for CH
 <sub>4</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref300">300</xref>
 </sup> In particular, the higher yield of hydrocarbon products over CuZn catalysts was associated with the spillover of adsorbed CO from Zn to Cu sites.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref301">301</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref302">302</xref>
 </sup> However, recent 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS studies revealed that the dynamics of the Cu and Zn interactions can be significantly more intricate under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR conditions,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref111">111</xref>
 </sup> exemplifying the complexity of structural motifs and their rearrangements in bimetallic catalysts in general. In this study, Jeon et al. focused on size-selected colloidal CuZn NPs with sizes ∼5 nm and different Cu to Zn ratios. Catalytic activity studies showed a pronounced relationship between the catalyst composition and the selectivity of the reaction products, where Zn-rich NPs converted CO
 <sub>2</sub> mostly to CO, while Cu-rich NPs produced CH
 <sub>4</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref264">264</xref>
 </sup> However, the selectivity of these catalysts was found to change significantly with time, and the initial CH
 <sub>4</sub> production was first replaced by CO and last mainly by H
 <sub>2</sub>. Here, XAS data analysis served to clarify that CH
 <sub>4</sub> was formed when Cu/ZnO was present in the samples, while CO+H
 <sub>2</sub> was obtained once the Cu–Zn alloy was formed. Moreover, the findings in the former study revealed that not only different structural motifs are present in the CuZn NPs with different composition but also that these motifs changed with time as the structure of the catalysts transformed under reaction conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref111">111</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
