<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Operando</italic> XAS measurements carried out at the Cu K- and Zn K-edges showed a surprising difference in the reduction rates of Cu and Zn species under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR conditions. While both Cu and Zn are completely oxidized in the as-prepared samples and completely metallic in the final state, as evidenced by the similarity of the corresponding Cu K-edge and Zn K-edge XANES data with the spectra of reference oxides and metals, 
 <xref rid="fig30" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig30" ref-type="fig">30</xref>
 </xref>b, linear combination analysis showed that the reduction of the Cu species takes place much faster than that of Zn (
 <xref rid="fig30" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig30" ref-type="fig">30</xref>
 </xref>c). Further insight into the transformations of the catalyst structure came from the advanced analysis of EXAFS data carried out with the artificial neural network method, which allows the inversion of the EXAFS spectrum, extracting the entire RDF (
 <xref rid="fig30" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig30" ref-type="fig">30</xref>
 </xref>d). In agreement with XANES data, RDFs extracted by neural network from Cu K-edge EXAFS data demonstrated that Cu was in a metallic state immediately after the potential was applied. However, the structure of this metallic phase continued evolving, as best evidenced by the shift of all RDF peaks toward slightly larger interatomic distances. For the Cu
 <sub>50</sub>Zn
 <sub>50</sub> NP sample, the observed shift was in agreement with the difference between the interatomic distances in pure bulk Cu, and a bulk CuZn brass alloy. Thus, the shift of the RDF peaks is an evidence of the gradual CuZn alloying. By tracking the Cu—M interatomic distance, one can characterize the degree of alloying. For the Cu
 <sub>50</sub>Zn
 <sub>50</sub> NPs, the complete transformation from a Cu-like to a brass-like structure was observed. Importantly, the characteristic time of the structural modification (several hours) matched well the time in which the selectivity of the catalyst changes from the production of CH
 <sub>4</sub> to the production of CO and hydrogen. Time-dependent structural changes and those of the catalyst selectivity were less pronounced for other Cu–Zn compositions. For Cu-rich NPs, the interatomic distances plateaued at a value in-between those for metallic Cu and CuZn brass. For Zn-rich NPs, the CuZn alloy was formed soon after the potential was applied, without further pronounced changes in the structure. The extracted RDFs for this sample, however, marked deviations from the fcc-type structure characteristic for Cu-rich NPs. The NN-EXAFS results showed that not only the final state of the catalyst but also its transformation dynamics depend on the catalyst composition.
</p>
