<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Friebel et al. employed grazing incidence HERFD-XANES measurements at the Cu K-edge to study the segregation trends of Au and Cu under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR conditions in monolayers of Cu deposited on Au.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref191">191</xref>
 </sup> Subtle signal changes due to absorption by a thin layer (1–7 monolayers) of Cu were detected. Depending on the number of Cu layers, the spectra exhibited different shifts with respect to that of a Cu foil (
 <xref rid="fig29" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig29" ref-type="fig">29</xref>
 </xref>a). While in the HERFD-XANES spectrum of a sample with seven layers of copper the positions of all features resembled those for a Cu foil, all features in the spectrum of the sample with 1 monolayer of Cu were shifted to lower energies. By using 
 <xref rid="eq15" ref-type="disp-formula">eq 
  <xref rid="eq15" ref-type="disp-formula">15</xref>
 </xref> to establish the relation between the shift of the XAS features and the interatomic distances, the observed shift was consistent with the difference in the interatomic distances in copper and gold, suggesting expanded interatomic distances due to the Cu–Au interactions. Interestingly, even the spectrum of the multilayer sample experienced changes with time, and after 8 h under reducing potential, it resembled strongly the spectrum of the monolayer sample. This was interpreted as an evidence that a significant fraction of the Cu atoms diffused into the Au substrate and assumed the lattice constant of the surrounding Au matrix. For the same system under oxidizing (positive) potentials, the differences in the oxidation of monolayer versus multilayer systems were observed: at oxidizing potential, Cu in monolayer sample transformed directly to Cu(II), without the Cu(I) state, which was in fact observed for the multilayer system. This observation was confirmed also by cyclic voltammetry and highlights the importance of the Cu–Au interactions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref191">191</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
