<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To the best our knowledge in literature, this is the first study conducted in vivo on human normal and glaucomatous TMs. From this comparative analysis, 32 out of 60 explored candidates were significantly affected in POAG specimens, as compared to control specimens dissected out from non-glaucomatous sclerocorneal explants mimicking the surgical procedure (see Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Particularly, some cytokines (IL10, IL6, IL7, IL12p40/70, VCAM1, MIP1δ/α, sTNFRI) as well as Th1/Th2- (IL2, IL3, IL4, IL5) and tissue remodeling- (MMP2, VEGF, TGFβ
 <sub>1</sub>) related proteins were significantly increased. This increase would suggest the presence of both chronic inflammatory and tissue remodeling process in these glaucomatous TM specimens. The observation of increased TNFα, γIFN, IL2, IL3, IL4, IL5, IL7, IL12p40/70 and VCAM1 expression in TM specimens is in line with previous single and multiparametric conventional approaches performed in human TM-derived primary cultures, aqueous and tears [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. During glaucoma, macrophages produce cytokines including IL6, IL1β and TNFα, leading to an acute inflammatory response. These cytokines can induce ECM remodeling and alter cytoskeletal interactions in the glaucomatous TM [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The increased expression of IL6 and IL10 in glaucomatous TMs is in line with the increased IL10 and IL6 levels detected, respectively, in glaucomatous fluids (sera and aqueous) and strongly support the hypothesis of IL10 and IL6 as potential biomarkers of prognosis of disease or therapy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The high expression of IL6 might be explained with the remodeling process occurring in glaucomatous TMs and the IL6-TGFβ1 cross talk observed in TM-derived primary cultures [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. IL6 increased outflow facility in perfused anterior segments of porcine eyes and IL6 levels were increased in porcine TM cells as a result of oxidative challenge [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Besides, IL6 and IL8 have been implicated in induction of cellular senescence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. TNFα and IL6 mediate human microvascular endothelial tight junction modulation, by their ability of cytoskeletal rearrangment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Finally, IL8 was found to modulate the permeability of the Schlemm’s canal endothelial cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].
</p>
