<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although cumulating data indicate that MMPs and their inhibitors are increased in TMs’ tissue and derived cells, our data show no significant variation in MMPs/TIMPs expression, except for MMP2 and TIMP1. This finding might be consistent with a steady-fibrotic status and/or the presence of some inhibitory feedbacks due to endogenous/exogenous factors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Physiological ECM remodeling occurs via a tight cross talk between MMPs and their tissue-related inhibitors (TIMPs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The increased MMP2, the unchanged MMP9/MMP13 and the decreased MMP7/TIMP1 expression might be the result of an excessive ECM accumulation and a low proteolytic activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. One explanation for this result might be the overexpression of VEGF/TGFβ
 <sub>1</sub> (profibrogenic factors), IL7 (inhibitor of fibrosis) and/IL6/IL12/IL10/IL5/IL4/IL3 (profibrogenic cytokines), all directly/indirectly involved in the tissue remodeling process [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Another explanation might lie in the eye-drop therapy, since in addition to endogenous factors and ECM-derived products, the exogenous medications might influence TM remodeling, representing a side-effect of the therapy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Both endogenous (increased IOP) and exogenous-induced (medications) biomolecular changes might actively contribute to the biomechanical features of obstructive TM. It is noteworthy to highlight that the therapy usually starts with medications for reducing IOP in order to delay/prevent glaucoma progression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Hence, our POAG population is represented by patients chronically treated with IOP-lowering eye-drops and not undergoing previous surgery. Therefore, the possibility that TM specimens collected at the time of trabeculectomy might express a protein profile potentially influenced by the topical therapy cannot be excluded. It should be also noted that in this study population no corticosteroids/antibiotics therapy was used before trabeculectomy. It is well known that the therapy can alter gene expression of the TM influencing the results of our research, but this is what really happens in all glaucoma patients who daily use antiglaucoma drugs to counteract the development of the disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Therefore, although it is not possible (in this study) to eliminate the influences and interference of therapy, the proteins found reflect the real profile of glaucomatous proteome.
</p>
