<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="emi14620-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Normalized spectral counts (means ±; 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3) of differentially expressed β‐oxidation proteins during growth on a linear alkane (
   <italic>n</italic>‐C
   <sub>14</sub>/C14) a non‐hydrocarbon control (Pyruvate/PYR) and a branched alkane (Pristane/PRI) in 
   <italic>A. borkumensis</italic> SK2
   <sup>T</sup>; treatments not sharing a letter (
   <italic>a</italic> or 
   <italic>b</italic>) differ at 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 (Tukey's HSD). The β‐oxidation proteins have putatively been put on either the left‐ or right‐hand side of the figure to represent involvement in straight‐chain alkane degradation (left) or branched‐chain alkane degradation (right) based on their expression pattern.
  </p>
  <p>A and B. Acyl CoA synthetases which activate a fatty acid to form acyl‐CoA constitutively expressed all substrates (A) and differentially expressed in pristane (B).</p>
  <p>C and D. Acyl‐CoA dehydrogenases, which creates a double bond between the second and third carbons down from the CoA group on acyl‐CoA producing trans‐delta 2‐enoyl CoA differentially expressed in 
   <italic>n</italic>‐C14 (C) and pristane (D).
  </p>
  <p>E and F. Enoyl CoA hydratases, which remove the double bond in trans‐delta 2‐enoyl CoA adding a hydroxyl group to the to the third carbon down from the CoA group and a hydrogen on the second carbon down from the CoA group producing L‐3‐hydroxyacyl CoA differentially expressed in 
   <italic>n</italic>‐C14 (E) and pristane (F).
  </p>
  <p>G and H. The FadAB2 (G) and FadAB (H) operon consisting of β‐oxidation multifunctional enzyme complexes with 3‐hydroxyacyl‐CoA dehydrogenase (removes the hydrogen in the hydroxyl group added to L‐3‐hydroxyacl CoA producing 3‐ketoacyl CoA) and ketoacyl‐CoA thiolase (attaches a CoA group on the third carbon down from the CoA group producing acetyl‐CoA and acyl‐CoA which is two carbons shorter) activities were differentially expressed on 
   <italic>n</italic>‐C
   <sub>14</sub> and pristane, respectively.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="EMI-21-2347-g004" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
