<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The transitions to localized states result in XANES features in the region below the main absorption edge. The dipole-allowed transitions to vacant localized states result in a very sharp and intense feature (so-called white line (WL)), as observed, for instance, at the L
 <sub>3</sub> and L
 <sub>2</sub> absorption edges for transition metals with unoccupied 
 <italic>d</italic>-states (for example, Pt and Ir). In the case of K-edges, the 
 <italic>s</italic> to 
 <italic>d</italic> transition is dipole-forbidden, while the intensity of the allowed quadrupole transitions is orders of magnitude weaker; thus, such an intense WL is not observed for pure metals. At the same time, if the absorbing atom forms chemical bonds, due to the hybridization effect, the vacant 
 <italic>d</italic>-orbital may assume the character of 
 <italic>p</italic>-type states, and the corresponding photoelectron transition becomes dipole-allowed, resulting in sharp features (so-called pre-edges). The hybridization depends on the symmetry of the absorbing site and is allowed, for example, in tetrahedral bonding motifs, while it is prohibited in octahedral coordination.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>
 </sup> Because of the distortions of the octahedral structural units due to the Jahn–Teller effect, weak pre-edges can be observed, as shown in 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>a for the Cu K-edge in oxidized Cu nanoparticles (NPs). In this case, the environment around the absorbing Cu
 <sup>2+</sup> species is similar to that in CuO, featuring a strongly distorted CuO
 <sub>6</sub> octahedron with axial Cu–O bonds being ∼0.8 Å longer than 4 in-plane Cu–O bonds (see the inset in 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>a).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>
 </sup> The resolution of the XANES features strongly depends on the absorption edge energy and for heavy elements is reduced significantly due to the high energy of the excitation and the short lifetime of the core-hole created. Improved resolution of the XANES features can be achieved in the so-called high energy resolution fluorescence detected (HERFD) mode, where instead of measuring transmission or fluorescence due to filling-in the created core hole, the fluorescence associated with a state with a longer lifetime is monitored.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
