<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Further analysis revealed that 
 <italic>GSK3B</italic> was an important potential target for m
 <sup>5</sup>C regulators (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). It showed strong association with m
 <sup>5</sup>C regulators (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8B</xref>) and differential proteins and was also important in GO biological processes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8A</xref>). Importantly, 
 <italic>GSK3B</italic> was significantly and positively associated with nearly all m
 <sup>5</sup>C regulators, whereas it was negatively correlated with NSUN6, indicating that it probably is a downstream target of m
 <sup>5</sup>C regulators (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8C</xref>). In order to further explore the targeted drugs of the 
 <italic>GSK3B</italic> gene in GI cancer, we divided the tumor samples into two groups based on the median GSK3B expression level for differential expression analysis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8D</xref>). The first 150 genes were selected from the significantly up-regulated and down-regulated differential genes, respectively, for potential drug target analysis. The results showed that streptozotocin (P-selectin inhibitor) was used for further analysis with the highest score of 96.16 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8E</xref>). Next, the targeted gene of the compound on streptozotocin was identified 
 <italic>via</italic> the PharmMapper database, then we found 29 common genes of the gene target and GSK3B differential genes, and PPI network was used to display the relationship of 29 genes and the streptozotocin (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8F</xref>). 
 <italic>GSK3B</italic> has been shown to be frequently up-regulated in many types of cancer (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Darrington et al., 2012</xref>; T. 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2019</xref>), and inhibition of it was considered efficient in suppressing tumor growth (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Edderkaoui et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2019</xref>). Moreover, there have been many studies on GSK3B inhibitors, including Metavert molecule in PAAD (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Edderkaoui et al., 2018</xref>), BT-000775 molecule in BRCA (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Ogunleye et al., 2019</xref>), BIO molecule in TNBCs (triple-negative breast cancers) (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Vijay et al., 2019</xref>), AR-A014418 and SB-216763 molecules in STSs (soft tissue sarcomas) (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Abe et al., 2020</xref>), etc.
</p>
