<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Calcium imaging experiments revealed that this ability of K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 channels to resist ATP induced P2X4-mediated depolarizations enhances Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> entry into microglia through P2X4 receptors stimulated with 100 μM of ATP [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. For example, we observed that the K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 blockers ShK-223 and PAP-1 reduced ATP-induced Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> influx through P2X4 receptors in LPS-differentiated microglia which express high K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 current densities, much more strongly than in unstimulated microglia despite the fact that LPS stimulation downregulates P2X4 receptor expression in cultured microglia. In contrast, K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 blockade had no effect on ATP-induced calcium transients in IL-4 stimulated microglia, which express very low levels of K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3. Interestingly, while LPS also increases K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 and reduces P2X4 expression on microglia 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, both K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 and P2X4 expression increase in parallel in the setting of ischemic stroke as shown by our laboratory on acutely isolated microglia from the infarcted brain hemisphere of mice subjected to ischemic stroke and by other groups on rodent and human microglia by immunohistochemistry or qPCR [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43–46</xref>]. This suggests that following ischemic stroke K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 might be regulating the more complex purinergic microglial calcium signaling initiated by the danger signal ATP more strongly than 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. ATP and other neuronal debris in the infarcted area of the brain activate microglia, which then continuously produce and release more inflammatory mediators within 24 to 72 hours and thus damage and kill more neurons in the penumbra leading to an inflammatory expansion of the infarct. The increased K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 expression that is observed on microglia in the infarct border within 2–5 days [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] presumably enables activated microglia to sustain stronger calcium signals through the increased number of P2X4 receptors and thus to produce more inflammatory mediators, damaging more neurons and activating more microglia. This hypothesis would be in line with the finding that the K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 blocker PAP-1 reduced microglia activation and brain levels of IL‐1
 <italic>β</italic> and IFN‐
 <italic>γ</italic>, leading to roughly 40% smaller infarct areas and improved neurological deficit scores in both mouse and rat models of ischemic stroke [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. By depolarizing microglia Kv1.3 blockers reduce calcium influx through P2X4 receptors triggered by ATP released from damaged neurons and thus dampen further calcium-dependent activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome, NF-κB and other transcription factors leading to reduced inflammatory mediator production (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>) and reduced pathology.
</p>
