<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The analysis of reference publications [
 <xref rid="B1-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and individual research [
 <xref rid="B4-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] revealed that, in cases of S700MC steel, the analysis of the phase transformations of austenite was affected by welding thermal cycles and the value of carbon equivalent cannot constitute the only factors taken into consideration during the assessment of weldability. The tested steel has a low carbon content (0.056% by mass), limited primarily by hardening elements (titanium and niobium), which reduces its role in hardening by supersaturation of ferrite and by limiting its action during γ-α transformation. The short cooling time creates a martensitic phase. Martensite formed after cooling is a low-carbon variety (does not reduce the plasticity of steel). The properties of welded joints made of the previously mentioned steel are primarily influenced by their structure and stability of the hardening phases and changes in their dispersion as well as aging processes. In precipitation-hardened S700MC steels, the process of manufacturing results in obtaining quasi-equilibrium between mechanical and plastic properties of such steels. The primary components of these steels include carbon, manganese, and microadditions of V, Nb, Ti, and N, which, on one hand, reduce weldability, whereas, on the other hand, provide high mechanical properties. To maintain a desirable balance between the previously mentioned properties, it is necessary to maintain a compromise between the general content of alloying components, their quantitative ratio, and good weldability. The welding process can significantly disturb the mentioned balance, which, in turn, may lead to considerably deteriorated plastic properties both in the HAZ and in the weld. The varying stability of Nb, V, and Ti nitride precipitates and carbide precipitates is tantamount to their varying ability to restrict the growth of austenite grains in the HAZ to a varied effect on weld properties [
 <xref rid="B33-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The lack of control over the decomposition and repeated precipitation of hardening phases may worsen both plastic and mechanical properties of joints. The welded joints represented quality level B in accordance with the ISO 13919-1 standard. The horizontal position made it possible to prevent the outflow of a significant volume of the liquid weld metal formed during the process, which could take place during welding in the flat position. Laser welding led to a decrease in tensile strength to approximately 790 MPa in relation to that of the base material (820 MPa). Similar results were also obtained for MAG welded joints. The hardness tests of the welded joint revealed that the weld hardness was lower by approximately 40 HV1 in relation to that of the base material (280 HV1). In the case of MAG welding, hardness increases in the weld area, which is related to the introduction of elements increasing the chart (Ni,Cr,Mo) to the weld. MAG welded joints have significantly higher impact values, especially in the weld area. This is due to the reduced concentration of micro-additives as a result of mixing the base material with the filler material. During laser welding of the test steel additive material, the increase in dilution is accompanied by a local increase in the content of micro titanium and niobium alloy, especially near the melting area. A significant amount of precipitates of hardening elements has a very adverse impact on the plastic properties of the weld. For welded joints made with a laser beam, despite the very low linear energy (5 kJ/cm) and low carbon equivalent (0.33%), toughness is unsatisfactory (i.e., below 20 J/cm
 <sup>2</sup>). The concentration of microagents in the weld made using the laser beam without filler material is significantly higher than that in welds made using arc, which, in turn, leads to a higher amount of dispersive precipitates [
 <xref rid="B38-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The high content of hardening phases in the joint during cooling leads to intensive precipitation hardening by fine dispersion deposits (Ti,Nb) (C,N) with a size of several nm, which consequently reduces plastic properties. In order to increase weld toughness, it seems advisable to use hybrid welding or to perform the welding process using the filler metal, which reduces the content of titanium and niobium alloying micro-agents in the weld. This is confirmed by the results of MAG welded joints testing.
</p>
