<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">Prototypical cancer vaccines consist of a tumor antigen with/without an adjuvant, which reprograms the immune system to recognize and eliminate cancer cells. They have the advantages of relative non-toxicity, minimal non-specific effects, broad therapeutic window and induction of persistent immunological memory [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Therefore, cancer vaccines can overcome the drug resistance, adverse reactions, limited therapeutic efficacy and high costs associated with standard chemo- and immunotherapies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Based on the antigen form, cancer vaccines are classified into the peptide, tumor cell, dendritic cell, DNA and RNA types [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. However, the first four types have several disadvantages that limit their clinical potential. For instance, development of personalized peptide vaccines require genetic analysis of the tumor, which is not possible for inoperable pancreatic cancer and may postpone the treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In addition, development of DC vaccines is time and resource consuming, and although they can trigger Th and CTL cells responses, the therapeutic efficacy is poor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Tumor cell vaccines showed promising outcomes in preclinical models but failed in clinical trials [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Finally, DNA sequences can integrate into the tumor cell genome and cause insertional mutations, eventually neutralizing the therapeutic effect [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In contrast, messenger RNA (mRNA) does not pose any risk of insertional mutagenesis since it cannot integrate into the genome. It is also degraded by cellular RNases and therefore has a short and regulatable half-life in vivo, indicating good safety profile [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Furthermore, advances in sequence modification and carrier strategies have increased the in vivo stability, cellular uptake and expression of mRNA molecules [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In the context of clinical applications, mRNA vaccines can be manufactured in a cost-effective manner due to development of rapid in vitro transcription reactions. Finally, mRNA sequences can be designed and modified to encode any pathological antigen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], which is highly significant during a pandemic or for individualized therapies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Therefore, mRNA vaccines are highly suitable for targeting tumor-specific antigens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], and multiple preclinical and clinical trials have been initiated [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. For example, Sebastian et al. reported that the RNActive® vaccine CV9201 induced antigen-specific immune response in 65% (30/46) of stage IIIB/IV non-small cell lung cancer patients, and achieved stable disease in 31% evaluable patients and treatment-free survival of 5 stage IV patients for more than 1 year [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Likewise, Kübler et al. demonstrated that CV9103 triggered an immune response in advanced castration-resistant prostate cancer patients and prolonged overall survival (OS) in a phase I/IIa study, and remained well-tolerated and immunogenic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. However, no mRNA vaccine against pancreatic cancer antigens has been developed so far, and no patient sub-population suitable for vaccination has been identified.
</p>
