<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CAP mainly contains the vagus nerve, acetylcholine (ACh) secreted by the vagus nerve terminal, and α7nAChR from inflammatory cells [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The vagus nerve is a mixed nerve with an afferent fiber that makes up approximately 80% of the vagus nerve [
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Previous studies have revealed that the afferent vagal fibers play a vital role in transferring peripheral inflammatory or pathogen-derived signals to the nucleus of the solitary tract. Additionally, it connects to the cranial nerve network in the central nervous system, and the efferent fibers carry parasympathetic motor control fibers that are related to communication in the autonomic nervous system from brainstem to organs [
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. These fibers release Ach, which then activates α7 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor (α7nAchR) on the surfaces of macrophages, lymphocytes, neurons, and other cells, exerting significant regulation of inflammatory cytokine production and inflammation [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The vagus nerve is the main component of a neural reflex mechanism (the inflammatory reflex) that controls innate immunity and inflammatory responses during pathogen invasions and tissue damage. The absence of this reflex (due to neural injury or absence of essential components) can lead to excessive innate immunity and cytokine toxicity [
 <xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Recently, studies have indicated that vagus nerve stimulation reduces the levels of proinflammatory cytokines in serum and local tissue, and vagotomy increases the levels of proinflammatory cytokines, aggravating inflammatory and immune lesions in experimental models of endotoxin, sepsis, ischemia/reperfusion, and other diseases [
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Furthermore, vagotomy may affect the activation and recruitment of immune cells that participate in inflammation. Mihaylova et al. reported that vagotomy decreased immune cell counts in the spleen of rats with endotoxemia [
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Therefore, activation of efferent vagus nerves could significantly regulate inflammatory and immune responses to improve diseases. In this study, CAP inhibition by unilateral cervical vagotomy increased proinflammatory cytokines and aggravated inflammation.
</p>
