<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent decades, studies have shown that CAP induction by vagus nerve stimulation or an α7nAChR agonist reduces inflammation and improves disease states, and inhibiting CAP promotes inflammatory responses and aggravates diseases [
 <xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Additionally, investigators found that the spleen is vitally important to inhibit systemic inflammatory response by α7nicotinic agonists or vagus never stimulation. Splenectomy abolishes the reduction of inflammatory cytokines, regardless of stimulation of the efferent vagus nerve in sepsis and other inflammatory diseases [
 <xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In addition, the spleen is recognized as the largest immune organ, where CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells play a crucial role in anti-inflammatory effects. Activating CAP with nicotine reduced the expression of Th17-related IL-17 and Ror-γ, increased expression of Th2-related IL-4 and Gata3, and attenuated the inflammatory response in a murine collagen-induced arthritis (CIA) model of rheumatoid arthritis [
 <xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Galitovskiv et al. found that nicotine reduced the inflammatory response by reducing the proportions of Th17 cells and increasing the numbers of Treg cells in ulcerative colitis [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In agreement with previous studies, we demonstrated that CAP regulation modifies the percentage of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells subsets in VMC. Flow cytometry results show that CAP inhibition from right cervical vagotomy increased the proportions of Th1 and Th17 cells and decreased the proportions of Th2 and Treg cells in the spleen. Furthermore, pnu282987 administration displayed opposite results, and the changes of Th cell subsets in VMC mice after vagotomy were alleviated by pnu282987 treatment. With the viral infection injured cardiomyocytes, the host immune response was activated, which led inflammatory immune cells to infiltrated and attacked myocardium. And CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells and their cytokines played a vital role in mediating immune response during the development of VMC [
 <xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref>]. The results of Western blot and qPCR revealed that vagotomy operation could change the levels of Th cell-specific transcription factors and cytokines in myocardium. The expression levels of Th1 cell-related IFN-γ and T-bet as well as Th17 cell-related IL-17 and Ror-γ were upregulated. Th2 cell-associated IL-4 and Gata3 as well as Treg cell-associated Foxp3 expression levels were downregulated. These changes increased the inflammatory response, aggravated myocardial lesions, and worsened cardiac function in VMC+Vag mice.
</p>
