<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The underlying mechanism regulating Th cell subset differentiation after activation or suppression of CAP is not well understood. We hypothesized that nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB) [
 <xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and signal transducer and activator of transcription (JAK-STAT) signaling pathways may participate in modulating the differentiation of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells. Wang et al. have confirmed that nicotine, α7nAChR agonist, could prevent the activation of NF-κB signaling pathway induced by endotoxin, and α7nAChR antagonist methllycaconitine has shown the opposite effect [
 <xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Nizri et al. found that nicotine, which activates the α7nAChR on the CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells of autoimmune encephalomyelitis mice, significantly inhibited NF-κB signaling and prevented the overreaction of Th1 and Th17 cells, reducing inflammatory damage to the nervous system [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In myocarditis, left stellectomy reduced inflammation via activation of the JAK2-STAT3-mediated signaling cascade [
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Mathur et al. found that STAT3 is required for Th17 cell differentiation [
 <xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. De Jonge et al. proposed that activation of CAP by the α7nAChR agonist nicotine in macrophages incited JAK-STAT signaling, leading to the inhibition of NF-κB transcription factor, ultimately exerting an anti-inflammatory effect [
 <xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Increased STAT3 phosphorylation inhibits NF-κB DNA binding, which is probably involved in the direct interaction of dimerized STAT3 with the p65 subunits. These results indicate that the inhibitory effect of α7nAChR agonists or vagus nerve stimulation on NF-κB activation is modulated by protein–protein interactions. Our results indicated that CAP inhibition by vagotomy or MLA suppressed JAK2-STAT3 activation, enhanced NF-κB activation in splenic CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells. Vagotomy or MLA treatment increased the proportion of Th1 and Th17 cells, and decreased the proportion of Th2 and Treg cells. Pnu administration reversed these changes. Inhibiting NF-κB pathway by PDTC reduced the percentages of Th1 and Th17 cells, whereas inhibiting STAT3 pathway by NSC reduced the percentages of Th2 and Treg cells in Pnu or MLA group, respectively. These results revealed that CAP regulates the differentiations of splenic CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell subsets, related with JAK2-STAT3 and NF-κB signal transduction pathways.
</p>
