<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The objective of the thermal treatment is to improve the leaching efficiency by either removing or decomposing the carbon and binder and by oxidizing or reducing the active material to a more soluble form. Hence, Chen at al. used thermogravimetry-differential scanning calorimetry (TG-DSC) to determine the optimal temperature (550 °C) that would lead to the decomposition of the binder during the thermal treatment of LCO in air [
 <xref rid="B88-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. As illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-00801-f007">Figure 7</xref>, the PVDF binder started to decompose at approximately 300 °C and its decomposition continued until 549 °C, when the carbon also started to decompose [
 <xref rid="B88-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. The high exothermic peak at 519 °C corresponded to PVDF and the decomposition of carbon. A reducing atmosphere or vacuum pyrolysis would lower the valence of Co, Ni, and Mn, which would, thus, increase their solubility [
 <xref rid="B4-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. For example, Yang et al. concluded that thermal treatment in the range of 550–650 °C in inert atmosphere would increase the efficiency of H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub> leaching [
 <xref rid="B91-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. The XRD results indicated the reduction of Ni ions from NMC to metallic Ni, while the Co
 <sup>3+</sup> and Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> ions appeared to maintain their trivalent form. Similarly, Li et al. observed the presence of NiO and Ni
 <sup>0</sup> in NMC samples that underwent vacuum pyrolysis [
 <xref rid="B92-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. However, comparison of reductive or inert thermal treatment process with other type of pretreatment did not lead to a significant enhancement in leaching performance, with most processes reaching more than 95% extraction of Li, Co, Ni, and Mn independent of the pretreatment conditions applied. 
</p>
