<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">To determine the direct role of Clusterin in bladder cancer cells growth, we used siRNAs and lentivirus to modulate Clusterin levels in UMUC3 and J82 cells (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3a</xref>). Knockdown of Clusterin dramatically suppressed cell viability, migration, colony formation, and induced apoptosis compared with control cells (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>, Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3b–d</xref>). We next examined the effect of metformin with Clusterin-silencing conditions. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref> showed that in Clusterin knockdown UMUC3 cells, low concentration of metformin (0–8 mM) inhibited proliferation stronger than in parental cells, indicating that both knocking down Clusterin and metformin treatment inhibited cellular proliferation in a synergetic fashion. However, when the concentrations of metformin (8–64 mM) were high, metformin itself reduced the expression of Clusterin, making the loss of Clusterin in these cells almost completely. Thus, the inhibitory effect of metformin in Clusterin knockdown cells is inversely lower than in parental cells, suggesting that anticancer effect of metfornin relies on Clusterin expression. Therefore, in lower Clusterin J82 cells, knocking down of Clusterin did not induce any significant decrease in the inhibitory effect of metformin (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>). Metformin also significantly inhibited basal migration, colony formation, and induced apoptosis in control cells. However, these effects of metformin in Clusterin knockdown cells were significantly reduced (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3b–d</xref>). We also successfully induced Clusterin overexpression in UMUC3 and J82 cells (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3e</xref>). Bladder cancer cells with stable Clusterin overexpression led to increased cellular proliferation, colony formation and migration (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3f–h</xref>). Meanwhile, cells with stable Clusterin overexpression were characterized by higher metformin induced inhibition of proliferation, colony formation as well as migration compared with control cells (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3f–h</xref>). Taken together, these results suggested that bladder cancer cells characterized by higher Clusterin are more sensitive to metformin induced inhibition of growth.
</p>
