<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Previously, we found that metformin reduced FASN expression in bladder cancer cells.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, FASN and SREBP-1c were significantly higher in bladder cancer cell lines and tissues (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4a, b</xref>). Therefore, we systematically investigated the function of metformin in bladder cancer lipogenesis. Lipid-droplet staining showed that metformin, dramatically decreased the number, size, and staining intensity of lipid bodies both in UMUC3 and J82 cells (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>, Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4c</xref>). Meanwhile, SREBP-1c and its downstream effectors were significant decreased (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1g</xref>, Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4d</xref>). We also conducted lipid metabolite analysis with metformin treatment via Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometer (GC-MS). As shown in (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h</xref>), the contents of long-chain and short-chain fatty acids were significantly decreased in comparison to that of the controls. Since Clusterin participates in lipid transport and metabolism,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup> we speculated that whether Clusterin plays roles in metformin caused lipogenesis inhibition. As shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1i</xref>, the depleted levels of fatty acids correlated with the striking reduction in Clusterin expression. Meanwhile, knocking down Clusterin decreased cellular neutral lipid levels and both protein and mRNA expressions of SREBP-1c and its downstream effectors (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1j, k</xref>, Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4e, f</xref>), suggesting that silencing Clusterin restrained the transcriptional activity of SREBP-1c and inhibited lipogenesis. Furthermore, double immunofluorescence staining showed Clusterin was distributed in the cytoplasm while SREBP-1c located in both cytoplasm and nucleus (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4g</xref>). Knockdown Clusterin significantly reduced SREBP-1c in both nucleus and cytosol (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4h</xref>). However, CO-IP showed no binding between Clusterin and SREBP-1c in cells (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4i</xref>). Taken together, these results confirmed that metformin reduced formation of neutral lipid which is mediated by Clusterin.
</p>
