<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Metformin is an insulin-sensitizing biguanide drug, commonly used in the treatment of type II diabetes mellitus [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], especially in obese patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Besides its effects on glucose metabolism, metformin displayed anti-cancer effects in various human cancer cell lines and diabetic patients with various cancer types [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], including EC [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The effects of metformin on malignant tissue may be direct or indirect. Indirect effects include a reduction in circulating glucose and insulin levels via a blockage of gluconeogenesis in the liver, which diminishes insulin resistance due to an inhibition of the IGF1 signaling pathway in tumor cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Direct anti-cancer effects of metformin target signaling pathways that are involved in cellular growth and proliferation, e.g. by activation of adenosine monophosphate-activated protein kinase (AMPK), a key regulator in energy homeostasis. Upon activation by liver kinase B1 (LKB1), AMPK induces various tumor suppressor genes, e.g. phosphatase and tensin homolog (PTEN), and thus downregulates growth-related pathways, especially mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) signaling [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Alterations in the phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K)/protein kinase B (AKT/PKB)/mTOR pathway mediate EC growth and development and can be caused by a loss of PTEN or mutations of PI3K family members [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Additionally, metformin may act on growth and proliferation independent of AMPK, e.g. via downregulation of the proliferation marker Kiel-67 antigen (MKI67), via the transcription factor paired box gene 2 (PAX2), or via Ras-related guanosine triphosphate hydrolases (Rag GTPases) [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Growing attention was also given to the inhibition of mitochondrial respiratory-chain complex 1 (NADH:ubiquinone oxidoreductase) by metformin in recent years. Like AMPK, the complex is involved in cellular energy homeostasis, but a direct involvement of AMPK in this mechanism is still a matter of debate [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Further affected proteins and pathways like the inhibition of signal transducer and activator of transcription 3 (STAT3) [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], various routes of apoptosis induction [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], or regulation of microRNA (miRNA) [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] have been suggested as potential targets for the biguanide drug, but the underlying mechanism of action of metformin’s anti-cancer activity is still not completely understood.
</p>
