<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present study, the effects of metformin on the human EC cell line HEC-1A were investigated using an affinity proteomic approach. HEC-1A cells were derived from a moderately differentiated grade 2 endometrial adenocarcinoma of a 71-year-old woman and are characterized by a poor expression of estrogen receptor α (ERα) [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. However, HEC-1A cells express ERβ and G protein-coupled estrogen receptor 1 (GPER) and therefore maintain a low estrogen sensitivity. Therefore, HEC-1A cells represent a postmenopausal model with low sensitivity for ß-estradiol (E2), which are able to form E2 from estrone (E1) to some extent [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Cells were treated long-term with metformin over a period of 7 days and changes in the expression pattern of 1,300 different proteins were compared to the expression in untreated control cells as well as insulin-treated cells. Insulin treatment was incorporated into the study in order to implement a model for insulin resistance and related hyperinsulinemia, conditions that are often observed in obese and prediabetic patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Although the HEC-1A cell line is characterized by low estrogen sensitivity, cells were additionally provided with E2 in order to mimic increased estrogen levels in the present study. Elevated estrogen levels represent a common risk factor for EC development and progression and are therefore essential for a realistic 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> simulation of the environment in EC patients and women with increased risk for EC development [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. It was shown that E2 stimulates cellular proliferation, migration and growth of HEC-1A cells independent of ERα via a GPER-mediated activation of diacylglycerol kinase α (DGKα) [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. With the presented data, we contribute to a better understanding of the anti-cancer activity of metformin as well as its underlying mechanism of action in EC cells.
</p>
