<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par25">Analysis of ToxB sensitivity within the context of the wheat pedigree found three varieties to represent hubs for frequent transmission of ToxB sensitivity: &#8216;Xi19&#8217; (&#8216;Cadenza&#8217;&#160;&#215;&#160;&#8216;Rialto&#8217;), &#8216;Cordiale&#8217; (&#8216;Cadenza&#8217;&#160;&#215;&#160;&#8216;Reaper&#8217;) and &#8216;Aardvark&#8217; ([&#8216;Cadenza sib&#8217;&#160;&#215;&#160;&#8216;Lynx&#8217;]&#160;&#215;&#160;&#8216;Lynx&#8217;). However, a good indication was found that the germplasm for &#8216;Cadenza&#8217; and its sibs used during early breeding activities segregated for alleles at <italic>Tsc2</italic>. This was based on the following evidence: (1) the inability to trace the source of sensitivity in the immediate parents of all three hub varieties, (2) the observation that all hub varieties contained &#8216;Cadenza&#8217; in their immediate parentage, (3) the ToxB-sensitive variety &#8216;Arriva&#8217; represents a &#8216;Lynx&#8217; (insensitive)&#160;&#215;&#160;&#8216;Cadenza&#8217; cross, and (4) &#8216;Cadenza&#8217; has the sensitive variety &#8216;Axona&#8217; as one of its parents. A similar assumption was made for the key hub variety &#8216;Aardvark&#8217;, whose parentage includes a sib of &#8216;Cadenza&#8217;&#160;&#215;&#160;&#8216;Lynx&#8217; (insensitive), and which ToxB phenotyping found to be insensitive, despite being a parent of 12 varieties for which no other source of sensitivity was found. On the assumption of segregation at the <italic>Tsc2</italic> locus for the &#8216;Cadenza&#8217; and &#8216;Aardvark&#8217; germplasm used during breeding, all but eight ToxB-sensitive lines could be traced via the pedigree to the spring wheat variety &#8216;Maris Dove&#8217;, released in the UK in 1971. Of the eight ToxB-sensitive lines not accounted for in the pedigree, one was a coded breeder&#8217;s line with unknown parentage, three contained coded breeders lines in their pedigrees preventing further investigation, one contained parents with unknown sensitivity (&#8216;Emerald&#8217;. Parents: &#8216;Tadipor&#8217;&#160;&#215;&#160;&#8216;Macao&#8217;), one had insensitive parents (&#8216;Cyber&#8217;. Parents: &#8216;Lynx&#8217;&#160;&#215;&#160;(&#8216;Talon&#8217;&#160;&#215;&#160;&#8216;Beaver&#8217;), one was the sensitive landrace &#8216;Thatcher&#8217;, and the last (&#8216;Ardone&#8217;) had &#8216;Thatcher&#8217; in its immediate parentage.</p>