<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the commercialization proposed by Sony in 1990, Li-ion batteries (LIBs) have dominated in various fields, such as electronics, electric vehicles, and smart-grids, as the energy storage system (Goodenough and Kim, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Etacheri et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Devi et al., 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). As the most successful battery technology nowadays, LIBs possess several advantages including high energy density, good capacity retention, no memory effect and low self-discharge, surpassing last generation of batteries i.e., lead-acid batteries, nickel metal hydride batteries (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Zeng et al., 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). However, the growing demand for battery with even higher energy density is difficult to be satisfied by LIBs because their energy storage relies on the intercalation mechanism (Cabana et al., 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Choi and Aurbach, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Hong et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). To further increase the energy density, great interest has been again aroused to develop lithium batteries directly using Li metal as the anode, which has remained quiescence from 1980s. The technical challenge of Li anode comes from the lithium dendrite formed on surface during cycling, which could penetrate the separator and result in the short-circuit of the battery and thus fire-catching or even explosion (Janek and Zeier, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Despite the endeavors to suppress the dendrite formation, the progress is limited and none of the solutions meets the commercial standards (Cengiz et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Michel et al., 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).
</p>
