<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several key challenges, however, should be overcome before the Mg battery technology comes true (Yoo et al., 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Saha et al., 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Bucur et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). For instance, due to the electrochemical reduction, a passivation layer is formed on Mg anode surface once Mg is on contact with conventional carbonate-based electrolyte solvents used in LIBs (Muldoon et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). While conducting for Li ion in LIBs, solid electrolyte interface (SEI) is insulating for Mg ion and thus prevents the conventional electrolyte solvents to be used in Mg batteries (Pan et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Novel electrolytes are therefore developed for Mg batteries and most of them are based on Grignard reagents dissolved in ethereal solvents or glymes such as tetrahydrofuran (THF) (Deivanayagam et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Nevertheless, concerns on safety and stability still remain for the high vapor pressure and the high flammability of ether-based organic solvents. Furthermore, the presence of Cl
 <sup>−</sup> anions in Grignard reagents results in the high corrosion and the electrolytes also have narrow electrochemical operation window (&lt;2 V vs. Mg/Mg
 <sup>2+</sup>), indicating limited practical application (Tutusaus et al., 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Therefore, solid-state electrolyte employed by all-solid-state Mg batteries is a safe alternative in terms of heat and mechanical shock resistance (Ikeda et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>; Imanaka et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Janek and Zeier, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Famprikis et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Nevertheless, the development of solid-state Mg ion conductor with sufficient conductivity is a key challenge at ambient temperature because of the sluggish mobility resulted by the high charge density of Mg ion (Janek and Zeier, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Famprikis et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Many efforts are thus devoted to improve the mobility of Mg ion within the solid conductor and the target is 10
 <sup>−3</sup>-10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at ambient temperature, which is comparable with those of solid electrolytes used in lithium or sodium batteries (Janek and Zeier, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).
</p>
