<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>M. capricolum subsp. capripneumoniae</italic> strain 87,001 has been identified to possess an S41 peptidase that plays a role in stress response, metabolism, heat resistance, metal ion transport, and virulence [
 <xref rid="cit0196" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0232" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>]. A similar peptidase has also been found in Mmc (
 <italic>MMCAP2_0241</italic> gene), which confers this bacterium a proteolytic phenotype; disruption of this gene leads to an altered proteome profile, enhanced H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> production, increased sensitivity to heat shock, and decreased lactate dehydrogenase activity [
 <xref rid="cit0196" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. Moreover, 
 <italic>M. gallisepticum</italic> has two putative peptidase coding genes: 
 <italic>MGA_1102</italic> with a zinc peptidase-like motif and 
 <italic>MGA_1079</italic> with a trypsin-like peptidase motif; these are essential for pathogenicity but not for colonization and persistent infection [
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. 
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic> encodes three putative peptidases, type I signal peptidase (MhSpase I), Xaa-pro aminopeptidase (PepP), and oligoendopeptidase F (PepF). MhSpase I exerts a pro-apoptotic effect on PK15 swine epithelial cells by activating caspase-3, and this effect depends, at least in part, on the native conformation of the protein. PepP cleaves the N-terminal penultimate proline from bradykinin, substance P, and neuropeptide Y, while PepF cleaves full-length bradykinin, substance P, and neurokinin A. Both PepP and PepF modulate mucociliary clearance and inflammatory response [
 <xref rid="cit0238" ref-type="bibr">238–240</xref>]. Furthermore, the 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> Hubei-1 strain also secretes thirteen cytoplasmic peptidases and an extracellular cysteine protease (MMB_0708) that can degrade the host extracellular matrix proteins into oligopeptides to satisfy the 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> nitrogen requirement [
 <xref rid="cit0143" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Similarly, 
 <italic>M. hominis</italic> also presents a peptidase [
 <xref rid="cit0102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], but its function warrants further investigation.
</p>
