<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">In rice, 
 <italic>OsSPL16</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>], 
 <italic>OsNAC024</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>], 
 <italic>OsSUS</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>], 
 <italic>OsGIF1</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>], and 
 <italic>OsAGO17</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] genes have been functionally demonstrated to regulate the seed size. In this study, we found the target mRNAs from 5 miRNA-mRNA pairs (fta-miR156c-5p-FtPinG0000496000.01, fta-miR167c-5p-FtPinG0002560000.01, fta-miR396a-5p-FtPinG0000680700.01, fta-miR530c-5p-FtPinG0002594600.01 and fta_novel_miR17-FtPinG0007576600.01) were homologous with these 5 rice seed size genes, respectively, which indicated that these genes might have a conserved regulatory role in the seed size of Tartary buckwheat seed and the corresponding miRNAs were the key miRNAs for controlling Tartary buckwheat seed size. Notably, to date, these seed size genes had not been identified as the target genes of any miRNAs in previous studies. Therefore, our results provided the first-hand information on the post-transcription regulation of these seed size genes. It is well known that the Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> signal transduction pathways play important roles in many developmental processes including seed development in plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. In this study, we found that three of the 56 identified miRNA-mRNA pairs were involved in Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> signal transduction because the target mRNAs were homologous to the calcium binding protein and CBL-interacting protein kinases, respectively. This suggested that these miRNAs could regulate Tartary buckwheat seed development though Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> signal transduction pathways. In a previous study, we found that the total seed flavonoid content was dynamically accumulated during Tartary buckwheat seed development, and identified one SG7 subgroup R2R3-MYB TF gene (
 <italic>FtPinG0009153900.01</italic>) was the key regulatory gene of flavonoid biosynthesis in the developing Tartary buckwheat seed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Interestingly, in this study, we found fta-miR858a-5p-
 <italic>FtPinG0009153900.01</italic> pair displayed significantly expression negative correlation. In addition, fta-miR858a-5p also exhibited conspicuous negative correlation with the orthologs of 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana MYB123</italic>, which was the well-known regulator of proanthocyanidin accumulation in developing seed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. These indicated that the flavonoid biosynthesis of Tartary buckwheat seed is involved in miRNA-mediated post-transcription regulation and fta-miR858a-5p is the key regulator.
</p>
