<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, the publication of the genome and transcriptome of 
 <italic>E. granulosus</italic> has offered meaningful insights into the development [
 <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], immunobiology, evolution, and mechanisms of host-parasite crosstalk, which provided new information on the development of new, effective treatments and interventions for echinococcosis control. However, there may still be deficiencies in currently available genomic resources for 
 <italic>E. granulosus</italic> [
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. After this landmark step, a series of studies including on miRNA expression [
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and transcriptome analysis [
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] were subsequently published for different developmental stages of 
 <italic>E. granulosus.</italic> However, very few proteomic studies have been published on 
 <italic>E. granulosus</italic>, although numerous studies on proteomic profile analysis have been carried out on a wide range of parasites, such as 
 <italic>Mesocestoides</italic> [
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]
 <italic>, Hymenolepis diminuta</italic> [
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]
 <italic>, Schistosoma japonicum</italic> [
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], 
 <italic>Trichuris muris</italic> [
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], 
 <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> [
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], and 
 <italic>Taenia solium</italic> [
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Protein-compositions have been reported and some of the proteins are considered novel candidate diagnostic antigens [
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], or valuable tools for the identification of new therapeutic targets for the control of larval parasites [
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. It is, therefore, necessary to detect the protein expression of 
 <italic>E. granulosus</italic> at the different developmental stages, which may provide information to better understand host-parasite interrelationships, and may point out potential targets for vaccines or drug discovery studies.
</p>
