<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Over a 3.5 year period, 12 individual aardvarks were darted and implanted with data loggers (see below) to record their body temperature and activity. At different timepoints throughout the study, our sample size ranged between one and five individuals for body temperature and one and four individuals for activity, as a result of aardvark deaths and failure of biologging devices (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref> for details). In July 2012, we instrumented six aardvarks; five of these aardvarks died in March 2013 during the summer drought (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Rey et al., 2017</xref>) and we retrieved biologgers from four of their carcasses (<italic>A01</italic>, <italic>A02</italic>, <italic>A04</italic>, and <italic>A05</italic>). In July 2013, we recaptured the surviving aardvark (<italic>A06</italic>), and instrumented six additional aardvarks (aardvarks <italic>A07</italic>&#8211;<italic>A12</italic>). One aardvark (<italic>A10</italic>) died during the winter of 2013. One aardvark (<italic>A11</italic>) died in the early summer of 2014, nearly 17 months after implantation, with no prior signs of body condition deterioration or weakness. In July 2014, we removed and reimplanted biologgers into two aardvarks (<italic>A07</italic> and <italic>A08</italic>), and one aardvark (<italic>A12</italic>) was added to the study in July 2014 for the third study year (July 2014 to September 2015; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref> for details). Another died in winter 2015 (<italic>A09</italic>), after its body condition deteriorated. Aardvark body mass during capture averaged 35 kg (range 26.5&#8211;43.0 kg). Determination of sex was not done for the aardvarks captured before 2013. All aardvarks captured after 2013 (<italic>A06</italic>&#8211;<italic>A12</italic>) were females, as classified based on a published description of aardvark genitalia (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Pocock, 1924</xref>).</p>