<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">We captured and immobilised our aardvarks as previously described (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Rey et al., 2014</xref>). Each aardvark was immobilised using a propelled dart administered intramuscularly. Each dart was filled with a combination of 150 mg ketamine, 4 mg medetomidine, and 10 mg midazolam using concentrated drugs (ketamine: 200 mg mL<sup>&#8211;1</sup>; medetomidine: 50 mg mL<sup>&#8211;1</sup>; and midazolam: 50 mg mL<sup>&#8211;1</sup>; Kyron Laboratories, South Africa), and topped up with sterile water to reach a final volume of 2 mL. Anaesthesia was maintained by inhalation of isoflurane (Isofor, 0.5&#8211;6%, SafeLine Pharmaceuticals, South Africa) in 100% medical oxygen. During surgery, each aardvark received a ringer&#8217;s lactate drip administered at a maintenance rate of 5 mL kg<sup>&#8211;1</sup> h<sup>&#8211;1</sup>. We monitored respiration (respiratory rate, peripheral haemoglobin oxygen saturation, and end-tidal carbon dioxide) and cardiovascular (pulse rate and arterial blood pressure) variables, and rectal temperature throughout anaesthesia. A &#8764;100 &#215; 100 mm section of the paralumbar region of each aardvark was shaved, washed and sterilised using antiseptic solutions (chlorhexidine: 5%, chlorhexidine gluconate: 0.5% in alcohol, F10 Products, Health and Hygiene, South Africa). Local anaesthetic (lignocaine hydrochloride: 2%, 3 mL, Bayer Animal Health, South Africa) was injected subcutaneously at the surgical site. Additionally, each aardvark received a long-acting antibiotic intramuscularly (Duplocillin, procaine benzylpenicillin: 6,000 IU kg<sup>&#8211;1</sup>, Intervet, South Africa), a non-steroidal anti-inflammatory (meloxicam: 0.5 mg kg<sup>&#8211;1</sup>, Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals, South Africa) and an opioid analgesic (buprenorphine hydrochloride: 0.01 mg kg<sup>&#8211;1</sup>, Reckitt Beckinser Healthcare, United Kingdom) subcutaneously.</p>