<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">This study has several limitations. Firstly, sample size is a major limitation for the reliability of our statistical tests. Expanding the research population would increase the robustness of our conclusions. Another limitation is that the body mass index (BMI) information was incomplete in the current study, which may impact results as obesity is considered a strong predictor for poor prognosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Moreover, other potential factors could account for the differences in critical non-survivors and survivors. For example, the sampling interval was not unified across patients, so some crucial physiological and biochemical changes may have been missed in our study. In addition, the time from onset to sampling was not consistent in each patient. Different times (7–11 days) are considered as the demarcation line between the early and late phases of the disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In our study, the earliest sampling date was 15 days after disease onset, resulting in a lack of samples collected during the early stage. Furthermore, in this study, age was significantly different between severe patients and critical non-survivors, consistent with the fact that older people exhibit a significantly higher fatality rate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Although we adjusted for the effects of age in analysis, the significant differences may still impact our results, and may explain why the trend in RBC decline differed slightly between the validation and experimental groups (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). Nevertheless, as we collected multiple samples at different times in each patient with disease progression and validated the RBC and Hb results from a larger cohort, we believe that our results are consistent with real dynamic changes in COVID-19 patients.
</p>
