<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Solvent extraction can also be used to separate Co(II), Ni(II), Mn(II), and Li(I) from one another using PC-88A, Cyanex 272, or P507 [
 <xref rid="B72-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>,
 <xref rid="B153-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>,
 <xref rid="B154-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>,
 <xref rid="B155-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. Cyanex 272 is frequently used in mineral industry for separation of Co(II) from Ni(II) from sulfate solutions. However, Nguyen et al. reported some phase disengagement issues when used at high concentration [
 <xref rid="B156-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Moreover, some co-extraction of lithium occurred (less than 20%), requiring a loaded organic scrubbing stage with Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> solution [
 <xref rid="B156-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Alternatively, D2EHPA can be employed to extract Co(II), Ni(II), and Mn(II) together at pH 3.5 with 6 min contact time, leaving lithium sulfate in the aqueous solution [
 <xref rid="B79-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B150-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. In their review paper, Nguyen et al. proposed two flowcharts using solvent extraction for the separation of various metals and impurities found in the leach solution [
 <xref rid="B156-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. As a first example, a mixture of 5-nonylsalicylaldoxime (Acorga M5640) and 2-ethylhexyl phosphoric acid mono-2-thylhexyl ester (Ionquest 801) allowed the extraction of Cu(II), Al(III), and Fe(III) from Co(II), Ni(II), and Li(I) [
 <xref rid="B156-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Then, Co(II) could be separated from the remaining ions in solution with Cyanex 272, as described earlier. In another example involving a solution of Mn(II) and Co(II), Nguyen et al. suggested using a mixture of Cyanex 272 and PC88A in conjunction with ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA) [
 <xref rid="B156-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. The latter chelating agent reduced significantly the extraction efficiency for Co(II), thus making possible the separation of Mn(II) from Co(II) [
 <xref rid="B156-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. In terms of technology for solvent extraction, supported liquid membrane (SLM) attracts some attention and was successfully employed by Swain et al. for the separation of Co(II) and Li(I) using a mixture of Cyanex 272 and DP-8R [
 <xref rid="B157-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>].
</p>
