<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Electrochemical Measurement</italic>: Electrochemical tests were carried out in CR2016 coin batteries. The electrolyte was 1 
 <sc>m</sc> LiPF
 <sub>6</sub> in ethylene carbonate (EC), ethyl methyl carbonate (EMC), dimethyl carbonate (DMC) (1:1:1, volume) with the additive of vinylene carbonate (VC). All battery employed the Celgard 2400 separator. The measurement of the free Li capacity in composite was done by charging the battery to 1 V at 0.2 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup> with the pure Li as the counter and reference electrode. In the symmetrical battery type, either Li–B–Mg composite disks or pure Li on both sides were used. Galvanostatic experiments were conducted on a battery testing system (LANHE CT 2001A, Wuhan LAND electronics Co., P.R. China) under a current density of 0.5 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup>. A symmetrical cuvette‐type optical battery was assembled to in situ observe the surface change of Li–B–Mg composite and pure Li under 3 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup> by a metallurgical microscope (Caikon Optical Instrument DMM‐330C, with 8.9 mm extra‐long working distance 10× objectives
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref>). The electrochemical impedance spectroscopy (EIS, Princeton PARSTAT 4000, AMETEK Co. Ltd) was tested in the frequency range of 10
 <sup>5</sup>–0.01 Hz. Commercialized LiCoO
 <sub>2</sub> powder used for the cathode in full batteries (both coin‐type and pouch batteries) was purchased from Hunan Shanshan Advanced Energy Co., Ltd. For coin‐type full battery, the cathode slurry comprising LiCoO
 <sub>2</sub>, super P and polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) at the weight ratio of 8:1:1 was coated onto the Al foil. The slurry coated Al foil was cut into a 12 mm diameter disk after drying overnight under vacuum at 120 °C. The active substance loading of cathode is 1.40 mg cm
 <sup>−2</sup>. In the pouch battery the designed capacity of the anode is 50% more than that of cathode and the assembly as well as the safety property tests was conducted in Dongguan Juda Electronics Co. LTD (Guangdong, China). Before electrochemical performance testing, the pouch batteries underwent a preformation procedure, which was performed under two constant‐current charging and a constant‐voltage charging processes with the upper limit voltages of 3.3 V, 3.6 and 4.2 V respectively.
</p>
