<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We further studied the biological process related to these genes using GO and KEGG enrichment analysis. We found that these target genes were significantly enriched in biological processes (BP) related to immune cells such as neutrophil activation, neutrophil degranulation, hematopoietic cell lineage, and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> infection (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> for details). Previously, a multicohort analysis by Sweeney et al. suggested that neutrophil activation, neutrophil degranulation, monocytes, as well as T cell-associated process had been involved in sepsis development and formation (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). They utilized data sets containing cohorts of children and adults, men and women, with a mix of community- and hospital-acquired sepsis, while we focused on pediatric sepsis; this may support the fact that these processes are common for all-age sepsis. This host response in septic progression involves many defense mechanisms with strong cellular activation, including neutrophil activation. In this process, neutrophil cells are key to innate immunity through their complex interactions with vascular cells, and their activation may be involved in systemic tissue damage. Their activation also leads to the release of neutrophil traps, which are involved in pathogen containment and phagocytosis, as well as coagulation activation (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Several reports have demonstrated that neutrophils generally have a relatively high expression in sepsis patients (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Previously, a study using high-throughput technologies has been able to identify differentially expressed pediatric septic shock biomarkers using gene expression data to predict long-term outcomes (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In this study, highly expressed genes in pediatric sepsis are enriched in multiple KEGG pathways and GO terms, which are related to neutrophils. Therefore, high expression of related genes may be one of the potential causes of increased neutrophil content in pediatric sepsis. On other hand, sepsis can be induced by viruses, bacteria, fungi, etc. The enrichment of neutrophils in the study might be due to the high infection rate of bacteria in children's specimen. Previously, it was suggested that sepsis was closely associated with hematopoietic stem cell exhaustion and hematopoietic cell lineage, which was processed through a Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4)-related mechanism (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> is now the most common cause of bacteremia and infective endocarditis in industrialized nations worldwide and is associated with excess mortality when compared to other pathogens. It has been suggested that 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> is the primary cause of pediatric sepsis (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Overall, these pathways are related to pediatric sepsis on some levels, and they provide a significant research starting point.
</p>
