<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Cytoplasmic male sterility (CMS), which naturally exists in higher plants, is a useful mechanism for analyzing nuclear and mitochondrial genome functions and identifying the role of mitochondrial genes in the plant growth and development. Polima (
   <italic>pol</italic>) CMS is the most universally valued male sterility type in oil-seed rape. Previous studies have described the 
   <italic>pol</italic> CMS restorer gene 
   <italic>Rfp</italic> and the sterility-inducing gene 
   <italic>orf224</italic> in oil-seed rape, located in mitochondria. However, the mechanism of fertility restoration and infertility remains unknown. Moreover, it is still unknown how the fecundity restorer gene interferes with the sterility gene, provokes the sterility gene to lose its function, and leads to fertility restoration.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Result</title>
  <p id="Par2">In this study, we used multi-omics joint analysis to discover candidate genes that interact with the sterility gene 
   <italic>orf224</italic> and the restorer gene 
   <italic>Rfp</italic> of 
   <italic>pol</italic> CMS to provide theoretical support for the occurrence and restoration mechanisms of sterility. Via multi-omics analysis, we screened 24 differential genes encoding proteins related to RNA editing, respiratory electron transport chain, anther development, energy transport, tapetum development, and oxidative phosphorylation. Using a yeast two-hybrid assay, we obtained a total of seven 
   <italic>Rfp</italic> interaction proteins, with 
   <italic>orf224</italic> protein covering five interaction proteins.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par3">We propose that 
   <italic>Rfp</italic> and its interacting protein cleave the transcript of 
   <italic>atp6/orf224</italic>, causing the infertility gene to lose its function and restore fertility. When 
   <italic>Rfp</italic> is not cleaved, 
   <italic>orf224</italic> poisons the tapetum cells and anther development-related proteins, resulting in 
   <italic>pol</italic> CMS mitochondrial dysfunction and male infertility. The data from the joint analysis of multiple omics provided information on pol CMS’s potential molecular mechanism and will help breed 
   <italic>B. napus</italic> hybrids.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Supplementary Information</title>
  <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12870-021-02852-7.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
