<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>After infecting with BVDV for 48 h, with three parallel samples in each group, the MDBK cells were collected from the E and C groups, followed by total RNA extraction by TRIzol (Invitrogen, USA), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The purity, concentration, and integrity of the total RNA was evaluated using Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). The samples with RNA integrity number (RIN) value of &gt;9.7 and optical density 260:280 ratio of &gt;2.0 were selected for library construction and deep sequencing. For the construction of lncRNA libraries, ribosomal RNAs (rRNAs) were removed from the total RNA extractions using Ribo-zero TM rRNA Removal Kit (Epicentre, Madison, WI, USA). The enriched messenger RNAs (mRNAs) and ncRNAs were fragmented into cDNA using random primers (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA). With the synthetization of second-strand cDNA, the cDNA fragments were purified by QiaQuick PCR extraction kit (Qiagen, Germany) before adding the end-repaired poly (A), and then ligated to Illumina sequencing adapters. Subsequently, the second-strand cDNAs were digested by uracil-N-glycosylase, and the digested products were size-selected using agarose gel electrophoresis followed by PCR amplification. Gene sequencing was performed using Illumina HiSeq
 <sup>TM</sup> 4000 and bioinformatics analysis was supported by Gene Denovo Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Guangzhou, China). The protocol for the transcript analysis is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1(a</xref>). Briefly, after filtering the off-machine raw data, clean reads were obtained followed by alignment to the reference genome; Next, use Cufflinks to reconstruct transcripts to obtain the known transcripts and the new transcripts; Next, use CPC, CNCI and other software to predict the coding ability of the new transcripts to obtain the newly predicted lncRNAs; And then, perform analysis of the mRNAs and lncRNAs, respectively; Finally, perform the association analysis of lncRNAs-mRNAs. All raw sequence reads were deposited into the NCBI database as a BioProject (accession no. PRJNA596327).
</p>
