<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">Regardless of the plant species, at least two classes of genes are involved in anthocyanin biosynthesis: structural genes encoding the enzymes that directly catalyze the production of anthocyanins, and regulatory genes that control the transcription of structural genes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. In most cases, the anthocyanin biosynthetic structural genes are regulated by transcription factors (TFs) belonging to the R2R3–MYB, basic helix–loop–helix (bHLH) and WD-repeat protein families, in the form of the ‘MBW’ complex
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Recent reports pointed out that gene regulation by TFs may play a key role controlling anthocyanin pigmentation in purple carrots
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, the broad variation observed among purple carrot root genotypes, regarding both anthocyanin concentration and pigment distribution in the phloem and xylem tissues, suggests independent genetic regulation in these two root tissues
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. In this sense, Xu et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> found that the expression pattern of a R2R3–MYB TF, 
 <italic>DcMYB6</italic>, is correlated with anthocyanin production in carrot roots and that the overexpression of this gene in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> enhanced anthocyanin accumulation in vegetative and reproductive tissues in this heterologous system. Similarly, Kodama et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> found that a total of 10 
 <italic>MYB</italic>, 
 <italic>bHLH</italic> and 
 <italic>WD40</italic> genes were consistently up- or downregulated in a purple color-specific manner, including 
 <italic>DcMYB6</italic>. Iorizzo et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> identified a cluster of MYB TFs, with 
 <italic>DcMYB7</italic> as a candidate gene for root and petiole pigmentation, and 
 <italic>DcMYB11</italic> as a candidate gene for petiole pigmentation. Bannoud et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> showed that 
 <italic>DcMYB7</italic> and 
 <italic>DcMYB6</italic> participate in the regulation of phloem pigmentation in purple-rooted samples. Finally, Xu et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>, by means of loss- and gain-of-function mutation experiments, demonstrated that 
 <italic>DcMYB7</italic> is the main determinant that controls purple pigmentation in carrot roots.
</p>
