<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) is as a premier method for 
 <italic>in situ/operando</italic> studies of catalysts in a broad range of experimental conditions. Since it is an element-specific method, it is well-suited to single out the active sites in multielement systems and can be applied to the investigation of a broad range of materials (ordered, disordered, nanostructured, liquids, etc.)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>
 </sup> The prominent role of XAS in catalyst research is also based on its ability to provide very diverse information about a given sample in a single experiment. Through the in depth analysis of XAS features, one can gain access to minute variations in bond lengths (picometer scale) due to only thermal expansion, surface relaxation, and interactions with the support, ligands, and adsorbates but also probe the changes in the material’s nanoscale morphology, the macroscopic evolution of its composition and crystallographic structure, and even map heterogeneous distributions of different species in macroscopic samples.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>
 </sup> When carried out under 
 <italic>operando</italic> conditions, such studies can provide key information about the identity of the active species and their activation/deactivation under reaction conditions, the reaction intermediates and preferred reaction mechanisms, and the role of the reaction environment.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, 
 <italic>operando</italic> spectroscopic studies often require new developments in the instrumentation as well as data analysis and software. The solutions that worked well for decades in the studies of well-defined samples under ambient conditions can be inadequate for the characterization of dynamic processes in realistic heterogeneous and disordered samples in contact with diverse environments. The unique challenges of 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS studies, and new approaches undertaken to address them, are the main topics of this Review.
</p>
