<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>During cooling, only exothermic precipitation occurs, making interpretation of DSC cooling curves easier than for DSC heating curves. However, in most cases, several different reactions overlap, and their deconvolution may be challenging. Multiple reactions occurring sequentially were detected for all alloys investigated.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The nature and kinetics of quench-induced precipitates in age-hardening Al-alloys were analysed for 27 different alloys, and both differences and similarities were identified between different alloying systems: 
   <list list-type="simple">
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Quench-induced precipitation occurs at both, grain boundaries and predominantly inside grains. The latter particularly holds for grain sizes above several tens of µm.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Nucleation of quench-induced precipitation generally occurs on existing crystal defects such as grain boundaries, primary precipitates and dispersoids.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>At high temperatures (≈500–350 °C), the stable equilibrium phases of the alloy system precipitate as coarse particles with a low aspect ratio (aspect ratios = length/ (thickness or diameter) is about 1 to 5), and nucleation occurs on coarse primary particles.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>At medium temperatures (≈350–200 °C) in the AlMgSi system, precipitation of MgSi precursor phases occurs as rods with aspect ratios of about 10. In the AlZnMg(Cu) system, precipitation of the η-Mg(Zn,Al,Cu)
      <sub>2</sub> phase occurs as plates with aspect ratios of up to 10. In both alloy systems, quench-induced precipitation at medium temperatures nucleates on dispersoids.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>At low temperatures (≈250–150 °C) in the AlZnMg(Cu) system, thin plates enriched with Cu and Zn were detected as quench-induced precipitation. At very low temperatures (≈150–50 °C) in the AlZnMg(Cu) and AlMg(Cu) systems, quench-induced precipitation of clusters was revealed.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The major aspects influencing the quench sensitivity are: 
   <list list-type="simple">
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>The concentrations of the main and dispersoid-forming alloying elements;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>The density of nucleation sites (coarse primary particles, particularly dispersoids, grain boundaries, undissolved secondary phases, eutectic structure), i.e., the initial microstructure initial prior to the start of cooling;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Concentrations and nucleation sites form the major reason for the significant alloy batch sensitivity in terms of the kinetics of quench-induced precipitation. For instance, for different batches of 6082, the upper critical cooling rate (UCCR) might vary by up to a factor of 10;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Moreover, the result of the solution treatment in terms of complete or incomplete dissolution influences the quench sensitivity; incompletely dissolved remaining particles can instantly start to grow with the onset of cooling (with no nucleation required, and no undercooling). This can increase the UCCR by a factor of three.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The most highly concentrated Al alloys have a UCCR in the range of several hundreds of K/s. Lean commercial alloys such as 6060 may have a UCCR as low as 0.5 K/s, and for pure laboratory alloys (with a substantially reduced number of nucleation sites), this may be even lower (e.g., pure binary Al0.26Si about 0.02 K/s).</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>A systematic methodology for the analysis, evaluation and construction of continuous cooling precipitation diagrams for precipitation hardening alloys and guidelines for reading these were derived. This significantly advances the state of the art in the heat treatment of aluminium alloys.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>It was shown that alloys with the highest alloying element contents are able to achieve the highest hardness if the necessary high upper critical cooling rate is reached. However, if the technological application requires slower cooling (for instance due to thick products or to keep distortion low), a lower concentration of alloying elements can lead to higher hardness due to quench-induced precipitation kinetics and the related loss of age-hardening potential.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>A kinetic assessment of the specific precipitation enthalpy data allowed us to model the kinetic development of quench-induced precipitation and verification of the model using these DSC data. In addition, the resulting strength and hardness after subsequent artificial ageing were modelled for AlMgSi and AlZnMg(Cu) alloys.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
