<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Measurements in transmission mode normally ensure the best signal-to-noise ratio. However, such measurements impose significant requirements in terms of the sample quality. The sample thickness and the concentration of the absorbing atoms should be large enough so that significant X-ray absorption is ensured, with absorption jump values Δμ
 <sub>0</sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>)
 <italic>d</italic> of ∼0.1 or better. At the same time, the absorption cannot be too large since a significant number of X-ray photons needs to pass through the sample to be reliably detected by the 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>T</sub> detector. The optimal Δμ
 <sub>0</sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>)
 <italic>d</italic> value should be close to 1 and the total absorption 
 <italic>μd</italic> less than ∼3.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref>
 </sup> Also essential for transmission measurements is the sample homogeneity, where the sample thickness and the concentration of the absorbing species are required to be uniform (on the scale of μm) within the whole X-ray irradiated area. Too strong X-ray attenuation and nonuniformity of the sample will result in the distortion of the XAS features, an increased relative contribution of higher harmonics, and incomplete cancellation of the 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> signal variations due to, for example, monochromator glitches (spurious changes in 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> due to the additional Bragg reflections from the monochromator crystals at certain energies).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref74">74</xref>
 </sup> Clearly, such conditions are not always possible to satisfy when 
 <italic>in situ</italic> and 
 <italic>operando</italic> studies are carried out. This is the case, for instance, when the absorbing species are diluted and nonuniformly distributed or when the matrix or support material and the elements in the sample environment (e.g., electrodes and electrolyte in an electrochemical cell) are too attenuating. In these situations, measurements in fluorescence mode are often helpful.
</p>
