<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>TOL_1175 which was significantly expressed only during growth on 
 <italic>n-</italic>C
 <sub>14</sub> codes an alkane monooxygenase which is homologous to AlkB2 from the psychrophilic obligate hydrocarbon degrader 
 <italic>Oleispira antarctica</italic> (OLEAN_C23040, 65% identity). A transcriptional regulator belonging to the GntR family (TOL_1176) was detected in the data set but was not significantly differentially expressed. The gene coding for the regulator is located adjacent to the 
 <italic>alkB2</italic> gene on the genome. This organization of a GntR transcriptional regulator being adjacent to the 
 <italic>alkB2</italic> gene can be seen in other alkane-degrading bacteria, e.g., 
 <italic>P. putida</italic> GPo1, 
 <italic>A. borkumensis</italic> and 
 <italic>A. hongdengensis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">van Beilen et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Sabirova et al., 2011</xref>). The electron shuttling proteins rubredoxin and rubredoxin reductase are required for electron transfer to AlkB which it uses for alkane hydroxylation (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">van Beilen et al., 2006</xref>). In general, bacterial cytochrome P450s are the proteins which require ferredoxin and ferredoxin reductase for electron transfer, rather than rubredoxin and rubredoxin reductase. However, TOL_2658 which was exclusively expressed on alkanes and had 11-fold greater expression on 
 <italic>n-</italic>C
 <sub>14</sub> compared to 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>28</sub>, encodes an alkane monooxygenase, and TOL_2659, which was expressed in a similar pattern (12-fold higher on 
 <italic>n-</italic>C
 <sub>14</sub>), encodes a ferredoxin. Ferredoxin and ferredoxin reductase have been shown to functionally replace rubredoxin and rubredoxin reductase 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Peterson et al., 1966</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Benson et al., 1977</xref>). Additionally, analysis of sequenced microbial genomes and metagenomes from terrestrial, freshwater and marine environments found four out of 23 genes encoding multi-domain AlkB system comprised an N-terminal ferredoxin domain, a ferredoxin reductase domain and a C-terminal alkane monooxygenase domain (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Nie et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
