<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The organization of the genes involved in alkane degradation differs significantly among OHCB (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Van Beilen et al., 2003</xref>). For example, the genetic organization of 
 <italic>A. borkumensis</italic> is similar to that of 
 <italic>P. putida</italic> Gpo1 where all the proteins required to oxidize an alkane up to the corresponding acyl-CoA derivative are encoded by the 
 <italic>alkBFGHJKL</italic> operon, which includes the alkane monooxygenase and rubredoxins, alcohol and aldehyde dehydrogenases, and an acyl-CoA synthetase (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">van Beilen et al., 1994</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). This pathway appears to have been horizontally transferred across many bacteria (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">van Beilen et al., 2001</xref>). In contrast 
 <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> does not share this level of organization, as many of the proteins involved in alkane degradation that were upregulated are encoded by genes that are distributed throughout the genome rather than on a single operon. In general, alkane-degrading bacteria have multiple alkane monooxygenases which expand the 
 <italic>n</italic>-alkane range of the host strain (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">van Beilen et al., 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). For example, 
 <italic>Alcanivorax borkumensis</italic> contains two 
 <italic>alkB</italic> and three P450 type monooxygenase genes (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Schneiker et al., 2006</xref>) and multiple monooxygenases exist in the Actinobacteria, 
 <italic>Amycolicicoccus subflavus</italic> DQS3-9A1 and 
 <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> Q15/NRRL B-16531 (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">Whyte et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Nie et al., 2013</xref>). When several alkane monooxygenases coexist in a bacterium, they are normally located at different sites in the chromosome, and the alkane-responsive regulators that control expression of the degradation genes (e.g., LuxR/MalR or AraC/XylS) may or may not be adjacent to them (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2012</xref>).
</p>
