<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Protein concentration was determined by the Bradford Protein Assay using Bio-Rad (Hercules, CA, USA) protein assay dye reagent concentrate. An aliquot containing 100 µg of each cell lysate sample was adjusted to 200 µL with 4 M urea and then reduced and alkylated by triethylphosphine and iodoethanol, as described previously [
 <xref rid="B15-proteomes-01-00219" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A 150 µL aliquot of a 20 µg/mL trypsin solution was added to the sample and incubated at 35 °C for 3 h, after which another 150 µL of trypsin was added, and the solution incubated at 35 °C for 3 h. Exactly 20 µg of each tryptic digest sample was injected randomly as two technical replicates onto a C18 reversed phase column (TSK gel ODS-100V, 3 µm, 1.0 mm × 150 mm) at a flow rate of 50 µL/min as part of the Surveyor autosampler and MS HPLC system (Thermo-Electron, Waltham, MA, USA) coupled to a Thermo-Finnigan linear ion-trap (LTQ) mass spectrometer. The mobile phases A and B were 0.1% formic acid in water and 50% ACN with 0.1% formic acid in water, respectively. The gradient elution profile was as follows: 10% B (90% A) for 7 min and 10%–67.1% B (90%–32.9% A) for 163 min, 67.1%–100% B (32.9%–0% A) for 10 min. The spectral data were collected in the “data dependent MS/MS” mode with the ESI interface using a normalized collision energy of 35%. Dynamic exclusion settings were repeat count 1, repeat duration 30 s, exclusion duration 120 s, and exclusion mass width 0.6 
 <italic>m/z</italic> (low) and 1.6 
 <italic>m/z</italic> (high). A blank was injected between each sample to clean and balance the column and to eliminate carryover. The acquired data were searched against the International Protein Index (IPI) database (ipi.HUMAN.v3.83) using SEQUEST (v. 28 rev. 12) algorithms in Bioworks (v. 3.3). General parameters were set to: peptide tolerance 2.0 amu, fragment ion tolerance 1.0 amu, enzyme limits set as “fully enzymatic-cleaves at both ends”, and missed cleavage sites set at 2. Peptide and protein identifications were validated by PeptideProphet [
 <xref rid="B16-proteomes-01-00219" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and ProteinProphet [
 <xref rid="B17-proteomes-01-00219" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] in the Trans-Proteomic Pipeline (TPP, v. 3.3.0) [
 <xref rid="B18-proteomes-01-00219" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Only proteins with probability ≥0.9000 and peptides with probability ≥0.8000 were reported. Protein abundance was determined using IdentiQuantXL
 <sup>TM</sup> [
 <xref rid="B19-proteomes-01-00219" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Briefly, after chromatogram alignment and peptide retention time determination, a weighted mean 
 <italic>m/z</italic> of each peptide was calculated and a tab delimited file was created to extract peptide intensity using MASIC [
 <xref rid="B20-proteomes-01-00219" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Peptides were then filtered according to intensity CV across all samples and intensity correlation, for those identifying a particular protein. Protein abundance was calculated from all qualified corresponding peptides matched to that protein.
</p>
