<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Non-functioning pituitary adenoma (NFPA) is a very common type of intracranial tumor. Monitoring and predicting the postoperative recurrence of NFPAs is difficult, as these adenomas do not present with serum hormone hypersecretion. Long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) and protein-coding genes (PCGs) play critical roles in the development and progression of numerous tumors. However, the complex network of RNA interactions related to the mechanisms underlying the postoperative recurrence of NFPA is still unclear. In the present study, 73 patients with NFPA were investigated using high-throughput sequencing and follow-up investigations. In total, 6 of these patients with recurrence within 1 year after surgery were selected as the fast recurrence group, and 6 patients with recurrence 5 years after surgery were selected as the slow recurrence group. By performing differential expression analysis of the fast recurrence and slow recurrence groups, a set of differentially expressed PCGs and lncRNAs were obtained (t-test, P&lt;0.05). Next, protein-protein interaction coregulatory networks and lncRNA-mRNA coexpression networks were identified. In addition, the hub lncRNA-mRNA modules related to NFPA recurrence were further screened and transcriptome expression markers for NFPA regression were identified (log-rank test, P&lt;0.05). Finally, the ability of the hub and module genes to predict recurrence and progression-free survival in patients with NFPA was evaluated. To confirm the credibility of the bioinformatic analyses, nucleolar protein 6 and LL21NC02-21A1.1 were randomly selected from among the genes with prognostic significance for validation by reverse transcription-quantitative PCR in another set of NFPA samples (n=9). These results may be helpful for evaluating the slow and rapid recurrence of NFPA after surgery and exploring the mechanisms underlying NFPA recurrence. Future effective biomarkers and therapeutic targets may also be revealed.</p>
</abstract>
