<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <p id="Par1">Arsenic is reportedly a biphasic inorganic compound for its toxicity and anticancer effects in humans. Recent studies have shown that certain arsenic compounds including arsenic hexoxide (AS
  <sub>4</sub>O
  <sub>6</sub>; hereafter, AS6) induce programmed cell death and cell cycle arrest in human cancer cells and murine cancer models. However, the mechanisms by which AS6 suppresses cancer cells are incompletely understood. In this study, we report the mechanisms of AS6 through transcriptome analyses. In particular, the cytotoxicity and global gene expression regulation by AS6 were compared in human normal and cancer breast epithelial cells. Using RNA-sequencing and bioinformatics analyses, differentially expressed genes in significantly affected biological pathways in these cell types were validated by real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction and immunoblotting assays. Our data show markedly differential effects of AS6 on cytotoxicity and gene expression in human mammary epithelial normal cells (HUMEC) and Michigan Cancer Foundation 7 (MCF7), a human mammary epithelial cancer cell line. AS6 selectively arrests cell growth and induces cell death in MCF7 cells without affecting the growth of HUMEC in a dose-dependent manner. AS6 alters the transcription of a large number of genes in MCF7 cells, but much fewer genes in HUMEC. Importantly, we found that the cell proliferation, cell cycle, and DNA repair pathways are significantly suppressed whereas cellular stress response and apoptotic pathways increase in AS6-treated MCF7 cells. Together, we provide the first evidence of differential effects of AS6 on normal and cancerous breast epithelial cells, suggesting that AS6 at moderate concentrations induces cell cycle arrest and apoptosis through modulating genome-wide gene expression, leading to compromised DNA repair and increased genome instability selectively in human breast cancer cells.
 </p>
</abstract>
