<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>Polymicrobial catheter infection mouse model</bold>. The previously described rodent model [
 <xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] was adopted, with modifications. Mice were immunosuppressed by the addition of dexamethasome (Sparhawk Laboratories; Lenexa, KS) in drinking water at final concentration of 0.4 mg/L one day prior to infection, which was maintained throughout the study. 5–8 fragments of polyurethane triple-lumen central venous catheters (1 or 0.5 cm in length) (Jorgensen Laboratories; Loveland, CO) were pre-coated overnight with fetal bovine serum (Gibco™; Waltham, MA) at 37°C. Catheters were then inoculated with single or mixed-species cell suspensions of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and/or 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> in RPMI 1640-HEPES at final concentrations of 1 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> cells/ml for 90 mins at 37°C to allow for microbial adhesion to catheters. For each experimental set, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>-infected catheters were processed for assessment of microbial recovery to confirm standardized microbial adherence to catheters prior to implantation. For implantation in animals, following 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> infection, fragments were rinsed with PBS and kept on ice until implanted. Mice were anesthesized by intraperitoneal injections (0.5 ml) of TBE solution (250 mg/kg body weight) and the dorsum was shaved; small incisions were aseptically made (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2a-i</xref>), and a subcutaneous tunnel created allowing for insertion of 5–8 pieces of catheters (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2a</xref>-ii). Incisions were sealed using 3M Vetbond™ tissue glue and lidocaine analgesic gel was applied to the incision area (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2a</xref>-iii). Animals were placed in a supine position under a heating lamp and monitored until they recovered from anesthesia, and then daily for any developing clinical signs of distress. Animals were euthanized by CO
 <sub>2</sub> inhalation followed by cervical dislocation and catheters were harvested individually.
</p>
