<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">Aggrecan is the most abundant proteoglycan in articular cartilage and plays a very important role to trap water and make the articular cartilage able to withstand compressive load. In this analysis, the aggrecan level was approximately 10 times higher in articular cartilage than in meniscus (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This is consistent with previous studies, which have reported that aggrecan mRNA levels are lower in human meniscus than articular cartilage and that total proteoglycan synthesis is lower in bovine fibrochondrocytes of the meniscus than articular chondrocyte-populated constructs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Furthermore, most of the aggrecan is bound to hyaluronic acid and link proteins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], which is probably why the proteoglycan link protein 1 (HPLN1) correlate with aggrecan (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). In contrast, the proteoglycan versican was more abundant in meniscus, both in DDA and DIA (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Versican was first described as a fibroblast proteoglycan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], and in one study comparing aggrecan and versican mRNA levels in chondrocytes and fibroblasts, it was observed that versican mRNA levels were higher in fibroblasts than chondrocytes, while aggrecan could only be detected in chondrocytes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. This could explain the higher abundance of versican in meniscus since it contains both chondrocyte-like cells and fibroblast-like cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Aggrecan and versican belong to the same family of hyaluronan-binding proteoglycans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], and while the function of aggrecan in articular cartilage is well-known, more research is needed to fully elucidate the role versican plays in the meniscus.
</p>
