<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since raloxifene increased the expression of genes of the 20S catalytic core, we reasoned that the elevation in the 20S may increase the degradation of unstructured proteins, which are less soluble and more prone to aggregation. We therefore tested the effect of raloxifene in females and estrogen in males on the level of insoluble proteins. For this analysis, following sonication in lysis buffer, the supernatants containing soluble proteins, were separated from the pellets, containing the insoluble proteins. The pellets were then subjected to a second round of protein extraction (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2I</xref>). Since the insoluble fractions do not contain cytoskeletal proteins, such as actin or tubulin, often used for loading controls, we assessed the protein concentration of the soluble fractions, from which the insoluble fractions were derived, and established a soluble/insoluble protein ratio. We found that spinal cord extracts from females treated with raloxifene show significantly fewer proteins in the insoluble fractions than in extracts from vehicle-treated females (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2J</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2K</xref>). In contrast, spinal cords extracts from males treated with estrogen show more proteins in the insoluble fractions than vehicle-treated males (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2J</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2K</xref>). Since insoluble proteins can lead to the formation of protein aggregates, we used a filter trap assay to assess whether the increase in insoluble proteins correlates with increase in protein aggregates. In this assay, the pore size of the membrane allows passage of small molecular weight protein complexes, while large aggregates remain trapped and can be detected by Ponceau staining. Equal amounts of insoluble proteins were loaded on the membrane. We found that raloxifene decreases the amount of high molecular weight aggregates, while estrogen increases their levels (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2L</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2M</xref>).
</p>
