<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have demonstrated that SELDI mass spectrometry can be employed to explore the proteome of a complex tissue (brain) and have obtained protein profiles of differentially expressed proteins from mitochondrially enriched protein fractions from experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE) and control mouse brain. We have shown that appropriate homogenization protocols and protein fractionation using anion exchange beads can be employed to reduce sample complexity without introducing significant additional variation into the SELDI mass spectra beyond that inherent in the SELDI- MS method itself. Overall reproducibility is comparable to that reported by others for analyses performed on a single machine with a coefficient of variation less than 19%. Although, SELDI-MS coupled with principal component analysis and hierarchical cluster analysis provides protein patterns that can clearly distinguish the disease state from controls, the identification of individual differentially expressed proteins requires a separate purification of the proteins of interest by polyacrylamide electrophoresis prior to trypsin digestion and peptide mass fingerprint analysis. Unambiguous identification of differentially expressed proteins can be difficult if protein bands consist of several proteins with similar molecular weights. Our multi-dimensional use of subcellular fractionation and ion exchange fractionation prior to 1D PAGE was insufficient to resolve all proteins, although the use of a larger number of ion exchange fractions might have resolved more proteins. We have shown that myelin basic protein isoform 8 (MBP8) (14.2 kDa) levels are lower in EAE samples with advanced disease relative to controls, while an MBP fragment (12.4 kDa), likely due to calpain digestion, is increased in EAE brain tissue relative to controls. Although differential expression of MBP and its proteolytic fragments appears to be a consistent feature of EAE, we have shown that MBP is not found associated with mitochondria obtained from fresh tissue, and instead its appearance in mitochondrially enriched fractions used here is most likely due to tissue freezing and storage.</p>
