<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SELDI-MS was originally developed for rapid, high throughput biomarker discovery in biological fluids (plasma, serum, urine, cerebrospinal fluid) but has been employed to examine the proteomes of cell lysates and tissues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. The approach combines time-of-flight mass spectrometry with protein capture using a variety of chromatographic protein chip surfaces (anion and cation exchange, normal phase, reverse phase, and immobilized metal ion) as well as chemistries for covalent attachment of proteins for affinity capture. It is most sensitive for monitoring low molecular weight (&lt; 20kDa) proteins and peptides. Complex protein samples may also be fractionated (i.e. fractionation on anion exchange beads) prior to spotting protein chips in order to reduce the complexity of SELDI mass spectra. SELDI-MS Expression Difference Mapping allows rapid analysis of multiple samples over multiple conditions to identify differentially expressed proteins. Principal component analysis (PCA) and hierarchical clustering can also be employed to identify the mass spectral peaks that distinguish disease from controls [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>-
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. Reproducibility in various proteome profiling technologies, including SELDI-TOF mass spectrometry, has been a major challenge. Sources of variability intrinsic to the SELDI-MS technique include variation in the ionization and desorption processes and in time-of-flight measurement and ion detection. Errors also can be introduced in mass spectral preprocessing steps such as baseline correction, normalization, and mass spectra alignment. Attempts to reduce proteome complexity and enhance protein identification by the use of sample fractionation steps, including sub-cellular and anion exchange fractionation, can also introduce variability from sample to sample.
</p>
