<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Within human populations and between primates, there is a large number of genes that are differentially expressed at the mRNA level but not as proteins. By directly measuring translation levels for these genes, previous studies have proposed that post-translational protein buffering can explain the decreased variation at the protein level (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Battle et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018b</xref>). Conversely, there are also genes that are more variable at the protein levels than at the mRNA levels (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Battle et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Chick et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2013</xref>). Our previous work demonstrated that some protein-specific QTLs are also highly correlated with differences in APA (
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Mittleman et al., 2020</xref>). Considered all of these observations, we expanded this analysis and demonstrated that genes that are differentially expressed as proteins, but not at the mRNA level, between human and chimpanzee, tend to have divergent APA patterns. We also found that the divergent protein levels are likely due to post-translational molecular mechanisms. While we cannot directly test the mechanism here, we hypothesize that APA could lead to variation in protein levels as a consequence of protein autoregulation, by differentially including RNA and protein-binding motifs (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Buccitelli and Selbach, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">de Bie and Ciechanover, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Müller-McNicoll et al., 2019</xref>). Alternatively, APA could contribute to temporal and spatial differences in protein expression, which would affect our ability to quantify protein with traditional techniques (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Buccitelli and Selbach, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Tian and Manley, 2017</xref>).
</p>
