<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As a follow-up experiment to our previous paper on the role of K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 in regulating P2X4 mediated calcium influx, we here specifically asked the question if the K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 blocker ShK-223 would also reduce SOCE in LPS differentiated microglia, the same stimulation condition, where we had observed the highest K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 current densities and the largest effects of K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 inhibition on ATP induced calcium signaling [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Using the ratiometric calcium indicator Fura-2 to track changes in the free intracellular calcium concentration ([Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub>) we found that LPS differentiated microglia had a resting cytosolic calcium concentration [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> that varied between 60 nM and 370 nM, averaging 150 ± 8.8 nM (n = 50; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3a,c,g</xref>), which is consistent with a previous report [
 <xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. To elicit SOCE, intracellular calcium stores were first depleted with thapsigargin (Tg), a blocker of the endoplasmic reticulum Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-ATPase, applied in a nominally Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-free bath solution. Removal of extracellular calcium produced a roughly 25 nM decrease in [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3a</xref>) indicating the presence of a calcium influx at rest. Subsequent application of Tg (1 μM) elicited small amplitude (&gt; 25 nM) asynchronous elevations in [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> due to passive calcium mobilization from stores. Re-addition of calcium into the bath solution elicited a rapid elevation in [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> above the resting levels caused by SOCE. The magnitude of the SOCE-induced [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> transients (“peak SOCE”) measured as the difference between [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> level in the Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-free bath solution and maximal [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> elevation following calcium re-addition varied significantly among individual cells with peak SOCE distribution displaying a maximum at 120 nM and a tail up to 1800 nM (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1b</xref>). This heterogeneity in the strength of SOCE is likely caused by variations in resting membrane potential, which provides the driving force for calcium entry during SOCE. The resting membrane potential of LPS-differentiated microglia has been found to vary between −90 mV and −40 mV in individual cells [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] and thus could account for the observed differences in SOCE. 
</p>
