<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A previous study reported that elevation in resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> was associated with a reduced ability of external stimuli such as the P2Y receptor agonist UTP or complement factor 5a to elicit [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> transients in LPS-activated microglia [
 <xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Because in our study both resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> levels and peak SOCE values varied among individual cells, we explored whether variation in resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> may account for heterogeneity in peak SOCE values. Plotting peak SOCE values versus resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub>, revealed a positive correlation between peak SOCE and resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3c</xref>). When we split the data into two groups with a cutoff value of 600 nM for peak SOCE, the relationships between resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> and peak SOCE in each group were stronger than in the whole population, indicating the presence of at least two cell populations, which differ in both magnitude of SOCE and strength of correlation between resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> and peak SOCE. Thus, within the population of LPS-treated cells, an elevation in resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> is not causally linked to the reduced ability of activated microglia to respond to external stimuli with a [Ca 
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> transient, as was previously suggested by Hoffman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. Our data suggest that a common influence, such as the level of membrane potential, which is controlled by a variety of channels, including K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3, K
 <sub>ir</sub>2.1 and THIK-1, may be responsible for the positive correlation between resting [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> and peak SOCE observed in our study. For example, overexpression or functional upregulation of hyperpolarizing channels could hyperpolarize the membrane and increase the driving force for both calcium entry via constitutively active calcium permeable channels such as metabolically activated transient receptor potential (TRP) channels and store-operated channels activated following store depletion such as CRAC channels.
</p>
