<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>pasteurii</italic> has a specific mechanism of nutrient source utilization. It has been shown that 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>pasteurii</italic> is unable to utilize glucose [
 <xref rid="pone.0246818.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and therefore yeast extracts are commonly used in laboratories as its carbon source. Moreover, the efficient urease activity of 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>pasteurii</italic> may play an important role in the utilization of nitrogen source, and play a crucial role in the mineralization of 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>pasteurii</italic>. Furthermore, it has been reported that the nutritional cost in the culture medium may be as high as 60% of the total operating cost [
 <xref rid="pone.0246818.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A large amount of urea and ammonium salts are used in the culture medium, as not only consume a large amount of agricultural fertilizers, but also tend to pollute the environment. Therefore, the high cost of growth nutrients becomes a major obstacle for the commercialization and large-scale application of microbial induced mineralization technology. Under such backgrounds, researchers have begun to work on the development of nutrient alternatives for 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>pasteurii</italic>. They have successively adopted human urine and pig urine as alternative nitrogen sources [
 <xref rid="pone.0246818.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246818.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246818.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], or used industrial wastewater as carbon sources [
 <xref rid="pone.0246818.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246818.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], reducing the cost of bacterial mineralization to some degree. However, treatments of raw materials were generally required in those studies, and limited bacterial culture or mineralization are often observed. Therefore, it is both necessary and urgent to investigate the utilization of different nitrogen source of 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>pasteurii</italic> and reveal relevant metabolic mechanisms.
</p>
