<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">As the COVID-19 pandemic continues, the direct zoonotic origin
(intermediate host) of SARS-CoV-2 remains elusive. Many animals have
been reported to be infected by SARS-CoV-2 in nature or the laboratory,
suggesting a possibly wide host range for this novel coronavirus.
Currently, the number of animals that have been experimentally tested
is very small compared to the huge number of animal species. Previous
studies suggested that receptor recognition is an important determinant
of host range.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> Therefore, we proposed a computational pipeline for identifying
the intermediate hosts of SARS-CoV-2 by modeling the binding affinity
between host ACE2 and the viral S-RBD. A recent study showed that,
besides ACE2, alternative receptors such as ASGR1 or KREMEN1 may be
sufficient to enable entry of SARS-CoV-2 into secretory cells and
immune nonresident macrophages,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref></sup> suggesting
that these receptors may also play a role in SARS-CoV-2 susceptibility.
However, in that study it was shown that, as the main receptor, ACE2
has a much higher binding capability for the extracellular domain
of S protein than ASGR1 and KREMEN1; furthermore, ACE2 displayed a
more significant correlation with virus susceptibility of ciliated
cells when compared with the other two receptors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref></sup> At present, little is known about the atomic level protein&#8211;protein
interactions between S and ASGR1 or KREMEN1, making it difficult to
accurately model the binding affinity between the viral proteins and
these receptors. Additionally, several in vitro and in vivo studies
suggest that the susceptibility of different animals is mainly determined
by the ACE2 receptor, as substituting the ACE2 alone is sufficient
to enable SARS-CoV-2 infection of otherwise insusceptible cell lines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref></sup> or animal models.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref></sup> Therefore, the potential role
of these alternative receptors on host determination was not considered
in this work.</p>