<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To our knowledge, no automatic sorting system that could sort various types of LIBs according to their chemistry is commercially available. In addition, the next-generation materials, such as LFP or Li
 <sub>2</sub>MSiO
 <sub>4</sub>, could further hinder the design of such sorters. Moreover, sorting spent LIBs could even be more difficult because LIBs of the same chemistry could have various intrinsic compositions owing to doping, binders, electrolytes, anode materials, etc. [
 <xref rid="B84-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. To manage these challenges, a research group from the Worcester Polytechnic Institute has developed a process that included all major types of LIBs, which generated a final refurbished NMC cathodic material and iron phosphate residue [
 <xref rid="B43-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Similarly, Huang et al. developed a process suitable for treating a mixture of low-value cathodic materials, namely LMO and LFP [
 <xref rid="B86-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. However, such processes could be very sensitive to variations in feed composition and would most probably require a proper feed management system, including storage and blending to homogenize the proportions of both types of batteries. In addition, the development of new battery chemistries (different anode or cathode materials) could significantly affect the efficiency of the process, and thus, it would require major modifications or the implementation of pre-sorting. Lastly, the hydrometallurgical treatment of mixed battery streams requires a complex flowsheet to produce high grade products. Considering the sorting technology gap, wide variety of LIB compositions, and cost of automatic sorters, the recycling of blended portable LIBs will most probably continue to be performed in facilities able to treat a stream of mixed cathode materials that use pyrometallurgical or complete leaching hydrometallurgical processes (such as Recupyl).
</p>
