<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par53">Based on these ceRNA networks and lncRNA-mRNA co-expression relationships, we obtained two novel ceRNA regulatory subnetworks for MIR4435-2HG and ELFN1-AS1. According to the univariate and multivariate Cox analysis, ELFN1-AS1 was identified as an independent prognostic factor for CRC patients. MIR4435-2HG positively regulated PLAU, VCAN, LOX, COL5A2, and OSBPL3 mRNA expression by acting as a miRNA sponge. PLAU upregulation in primary tumor tissues is positively correlated with distant metastasis and indicates poor patient prognosis in CRC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. MiR-193a inhibits CRC cell growth and progression partly by downregulating the expression of target gene PLAU, which is consistent with our prediction of PLAU/miR-193a interaction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. VCAN is overexpressed in various human malignancies, including CRC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], and CRC patients with high VCAN expression have worse disease outcomes than those with lower expression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Upregulation of LOX expression is correlated with the progression and metastasis of various solid tumors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. There have been contradictory reports regarding the role of LOX in CRC. Csiszar et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] reported that reduced LOX expression in colon tumor tissue supports the function of LOX as a tumor suppressor gene. However, recent studies found that LOX expression was significantly increased in tumor tissue and correlated with poor clinical outcomes of CRC patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. COL5A2 is upregulated in CRC tissue compared to normal tissue, suggesting that COL5A2 is involved in CRC carcinogenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]; however, there are no reports about the role of OSBPL3 in CRC. E2F1 and SRM were predicted to be co-expressed genes involved in the ELFN1-AS1 regulatory network. Several studies have demonstrated that E2F1 is an oncogene involved in CRC proliferation and metastasis. Higher E2F1 expression levels indicate a shorter OS in CRC patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. However, there is also evidence to support E2F1 as a tumor suppressor gene involved in the induction of apoptosis in CRC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. SRM encodes one of the key enzymes in the polyamine biosynthesis pathway. Polyamines are essential for cell proliferation and growth, and high expression of polyamines has been linked to several tumors, including CRC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. However, the direct correlation between the expression of SRM and human tumorigenesis remains unclear.
</p>
