<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55">Tumor-infiltrating immune cells (TIICs) include T cells, dendritic cells (DCs), B cells, macrophages, neutrophils, mast cells, and natural killer (NK) cells. They are major components of the complex microenvironment that regulates tumor progression and predicts prognosis in CRC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. To further explore the immune infiltration-related mechanism of how ceRNA regulates CRC prognosis, the estimated proportions of 22 tumor-infiltrating immune cell types in CRC were evaluated by CIBERSORT analysis based on MIR4435-2HG and ELFN1-AS1 expression levels. Our results revealed that nine immune cell types, including CD4+ memory resting T cells, CD4+ memory activated T cells, CD8+ T cells, gamma delta T cells, follicular helper T cells, plasma B cells, neutrophils, monocytes, and resting myeloid DCs, showed statistical differences between the high and low expression groups. Several recent studies reported that the type, density, and location of tumor-infiltrating immune cells are associated with favorable outcomes in CRC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. The densities of CD4+ and CD8 + memory T cells were negatively correlated with local tumor invasion based on the T stage of the TNM classification [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. DCs are potent antigen-presenting cells that play an important role in initiating, programming, and regulating antitumor immune responses. DC-based immunotherapy has been used as anti-cancer immunotherapy to treat various cancers, including CRC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. The peripheral neutrophil-to-lymphocyte ratio (NLR) and lymphocyte-to-monocyte ratio (LMR) are prognostic factors for CRC patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. The association of MIR4435-2HG and ELFN1-AS1 lncRNA expression with tumor-infiltrating immune cell types supports their role as valuable prognostic markers and immunotherapeutic targets in CRC.
</p>
