<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The mRNA expression profile of COL11A1 gene obtained from TCGA dataset of colorectal cancer from the various servers like ONCOMINE, UALCAN, and GEPIA collectively discloses significant upregulations at transcriptional level in cancer tissue than the normal colon tissue across various cancer subtypes including colon adenocarcinoma, colon mucinous adenocarcinoma, rectal adenocarcinoma, and cecum adenocarcinoma (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1C–J</xref>); and even in the various clinicopathological parameters including patients’ age, cancer stage, nodal metastasis status, and TP53 mutation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2A–F</xref>). Epigenetic changes in the gene are known to be the leading causes of neoplastic transformation, and regarding this, our result on the promoter methylation of the COL11A1 gene across various parameters indicates negative relation with the expression profile in a way suggesting the hypermethylation of the COL11A1 gene may regulate the of development cancer (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2G–L</xref>). The KM-plots obtained for the overall survival (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>) and disease-free survival (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>) show poor prognosis of colorectal cancer i.e., the higher expression of the COL11A1 gene signifies poor survivability. The coexpression and correlation of the top 25 positively correlated genes with the COL11A1 gene are depicted on the heatmap (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). Herein, we have found that THBS2, COL10A1, COL5A2, and COL1A2 are the most significant gene having the highest positive correlation (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4B–E</xref>). Further, upon the survival assays of THBS2, COL10A1, COL5A2, and COL1A2 genes it has been found a similar pattern of lower survival probability on overexpression (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3D–K</xref>). Collectively all these experimental data clearly reveal that the COL11A1 gene along with its associated THBS2, COL10A1, COL5A2, and COL1A2 might serve as a prognostic biomarker for colorectal cancer.
</p>
