<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The genomic alteration and mutation are the major inducers for the initiation and development of several cancers (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Loeb et al., 2008</xref>). In our study, it has been observed that up to 12% mutation that relates to the COL11A1 gene contributes to the development of colorectal cancer with the highest alteration in mucinous adenocarcinoma of colon and rectum (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). Further analysis from the COSMIC server illustrates that substitution mutation is the most prevalent mutation that constitutes the highest frequency of G &gt; A types of changes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5A,B</xref>). In addition, the prevalence of THBS2, COL10A1, COL5A2, and COL1A2 enhances the frequency of alteration and depicting a positive correlation with COL11A1 mutation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5F–I</xref>). A functional network of the interaction among the neighboring genes of the COL11A1 in colorectal cancer displays physical interactions, co-expression, predicted co-localization, pathways, genetic interaction, and shared protein domains (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>). Collectively, we can postulate that the COL11A1 gene interacts with the neighboring mediators to induce the downregulation of various biological signaling pathways. Enrichment network created through NetworkAnalyst shows GO enrichment of various biological and molecular pathways where the genes significantly associated with extracellular structure organization, collagen fibril organization, protein complex subunit organization, collagen metabolic process, and cell migration (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6C,D</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Table 5</xref>). The PPI networks indicate the RAB31, COL1A1, COL1A2, COL3A1, COL11A1, and VCAN as the most important protein network that likely to be connected and show betweenness among themselves to significantly promote the prognosis of colorectal cancer (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>).
</p>
