<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The KEGG pathways established from DAVID analysis reveals that it shows the highest intimacy with the ECM-receptor interaction and PI3K-Akt signaling pathway (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). Moreover, our study through the PathwayMapper tab of the cBioPortal website indicates the frequency of alteration of the various signaling cascades of RTK-RAS-PI3K, Wnt, TGF-β, and TP53 pathways that consequently leads to colorectal cancer. The RTK-RAS-PI3K signaling axis is important in regulating the cell growth and survival (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2020</xref>). Perturbation in these signaling cascades is known to contribute in the induction as well as in the development of cancer. The mutation of KRAS is found to be higher in colorectal cancer and thought to enhance the malignancy character of the transformed cells (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Zenonos and Kyprianou, 2013</xref>). The alteration of the PI3K pathway mainly including the RTK upstream regulator of PI3K, catalytic subunit PIK3CA, PTEN negative regulator, and the downstream regulator of PI3K lead to the surge of cancer development (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Yuan and Cantley, 2008</xref>). Herein, our study reveals the impact of COL11A1 gene product in the alteration of PTEN, PIK3CA, KRAS, and BRAF which might downregulate the RTK-RAS-PI3K signaling pathways to induce cancer development (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7A</xref>). On the other hand, the Wnt signaling pathway is associated with the regulation of various developmental and physiological processes including cell division, specification, proliferation, and even maintenance of tissues and abnormal signaling leading to colorectal cancer (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Clevers, 2006</xref>). The mutation of APC leads to overactivation of Wnt signaling pathways resulting in 80% of colorectal cancer prognosis (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Koveitypour et al., 2019</xref>). The influence of COL11A1 and its associated gene triggers alteration of APC for around 66.7% that resulted in the overactivation of Wnt signaling pathways leading to cancer development (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7B</xref>). TGF-β signaling pathway plays a vital role in tissue maintenance and is associated with inflammation and carcinogenesis by restraining the cell growth, differentiation, and apoptosis (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Koveitypour et al., 2019</xref>). Mutation of TGF-β receptor type 2 (TGFBR2) leads to the microsatellite instability causing colorectal cancer, and also the loss of function of SMAD4 in the TGF-β signaling pathway promotes the tumor progression and poor survival in colorectal cancer (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Itatani et al., 2019</xref>). The alteration of the TGF-β signaling pathway by the COL11A1 gene indicates that the SMAD4 alteration frequency of 15.5% might drive the formation of cancer (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7C</xref>). TP53 pathway is the regulator of the cell cycle, DNA replication, apoptosis, and response to a wide range of stresses and safeguards maintenance of genomic integrity and acts as a tumor suppressor gene (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Aubrey et al., 2016</xref>). The mutation of TP53 leads to colorectal cancer elevating the invasiveness, metastasis, and poor survival (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2015</xref>). The association of the COL11A1 gene with its correlated gene from our study influences the alteration of TP53 by 53.0% disrupting the pathway results in uncontrolled cell proliferation and metastasis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7D</xref>).
</p>
