<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Li‐O
 <sub>2</sub> battery is another attractive battery system for energy storage owing to its high theoretical specific energy density (≈3500 Wh kg
 <sup>−1</sup>).
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0130" ref-type="ref">130</xref> In spite of a great deal of reports focused on liquid and solid electrolytes used in Li‐O
 <sub>2</sub> or Li‐air cells, few researches are investigated for the application of the SCEs these cells.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0131" ref-type="ref">131</xref> The deterioration of cycling performance constantly occurred in Li‐O
 <sub>2</sub> batteries with liquid electrolyte because of leakage and volatilization of solvents in air, which could be prospectively avoided by adopting all‐solid‐state electrolyte.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0127" ref-type="ref">127</xref> Meanwhile, the solid electrolyte with high ionic conductivity is chemically stable with LiO
 <sub>2</sub>, Li
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and O
 <sub>2</sub>. According to previous reports, it is found that the LAGP could adsorb O
 <sub>2</sub> owing to its open structure followed by the reduction of oxygen and the formation of LiO
 <sub>2</sub> and Li
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, which facilitates the process of electrochemical reaction.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0132" ref-type="ref">132</xref> A solid SCE integrating the poly(methyl methacrylate‐styrene) (PMS), LAGP, and small amount of nano‐fumed SiO
 <sub>2</sub> was also successfully fabricated and then reinforced by a polyethylene(PE) supporter.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0133" ref-type="ref">133</xref> The as‐prepared PMS‐LAGP@PE shows an ion conductivity of 0.32 × 10
 <sup>−3</sup> S· cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at room temperature, Li
 <sup>+</sup> transference number of 0.75 and stable electrochemical window up to 5.2 V versus Li/Li
 <sup>+</sup>. The solid‐state Li‐O
 <sub>2</sub> battery assembled with this SCE and single‐walled carbon nanotube‐based cathode delivers long cycle life (350 cycles, &gt;145 days) at a current density of 200 mA g
 <sup>−1</sup> with a capacity limit of 1000 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> at 50 °C. In addition, the SCE membrane is used as protective layer to protect the Li metal from reacting with liquid electrolyte and cathode material in Li‐air battery. Safanama and Adams
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0134" ref-type="ref">134</xref> prepared a SCE membrane consisting of polyvinyl butyral resin, PVDF, benzyl n‐butyl phthalate, LAGP, and LiBF
 <sub>4</sub> (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0013" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>13</bold>
 </xref>). This LAGP‐based SCE membrane presents high ion conductivity (1.0 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup>) and chemical stability in both acidified and neutral LiCl solutions. Due to the employment of LAGP/polymer protective layer, the aqueous/hybrid Li‐air battery cycled for 140 h with small overpotential and average energy efficiency of 93% under a current density of 0.03 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup>.
</p>
