<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f024">Figure 24</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f025">Figure 25</xref> display microstructural images depending on the cooling rate in Al0.72Si. Optical microscopy after very slow cooling with 10
 <sup>−4</sup> K/s (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f024">Figure 24</xref>) reveals polygonal-shaped Si particles. If cooling is carried out ten times faster, at 10
 <sup>−3</sup> K/s, the number of quench-induced particles is substantially increased (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f024">Figure 24</xref>B), while their particle size is reduced. From 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f023">Figure 23</xref>, it can be seen that the volume fraction of quench-induced precipitation is similar for these two very slow cooling rates. In Ref. [
 <xref rid="B117-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B132-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>] we demonstrated that these polygonal-shaped precipitates originate from the HTRs seen in cooling DSC. At a cooling rate of 10
 <sup>−2</sup> K/s, quench-induced particles are further reduced in size. A detailed analysis of the OM images reveals that next to the polygonal-shaped particles, further plate-like particles (appearance: needle or rod-shaped) with distinct orientations appear (see also 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f026">Figure 26</xref>). It has been proven that these plate-shaped particles originate from the LTRs [
 <xref rid="B117-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B132-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. After cooling at 1 K/s, no quench-induced precipitates can be seen in OM. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f025">Figure 25</xref> demonstrates that the vast majority of quench-induced precipitates form inside the grains. In high-purity alloys such as this one, grains are generally coarse. The OM results are consistent with the DSC results in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f022">Figure 22</xref>, indicating that at 0.01 K/s, the HTR has already been suppressed to a great extent. However, at this cooling rate, and for even faster cooling at 0.1 K/s, TEM unambiguously shows that some precipitates form during the quench (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f027">Figure 27</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f028">Figure 28</xref>).
</p>
