<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Quantitative PCR was performed using the QuantStudio 7 Flex real-time PCR detection system (ThermoFIsher) and SYBR Green (#1725274, Bio-Red). The thermal cycling conditions used were as follows: one cycle at 95 °C for 1 min, 40 cycles at 95 °C for 15 s, and 60 °C for 15 s. The primers used in real-time PCR test were listed as follows: GRB2 forward primer AATTATGTCACCCCCGTGAA, GRB2 reverse primer TGTTCTGCACTCCCTCACAG; LYN forward primer ACCAAGGTGGCTGTGAAAAC, LYN reverse primer CTGGTGACCACAGCGTAGAG; PRKACB forward primer CTTTGGGTTTGCCAAAAGAG, PRKACB reverse primer CTAATGCCCACCAATCCACT; PIK3CB forward primer GCACATTCCTGCTGTCTCAG, PIK3CB reverse primer TCACGGCATTCAGTTTGATT; PIK3R3 forward primer AGCCTGTGGAAATGGCATAG, PIK3R3 reverse primer CTCTCATGAAGGAGGCCAAG; STAT5B forward primer GTCCCAGAAACACCTCCAGA, STAT5B reverse primer TCAGGCTCTCCTGGTACTGG; PTPN6 forward primer TGCTTATGGGCCCTACTCTG, PTPN6 reverse primer TAATGCCAGATCTCCCGAAT; AKT3 forward primer ACGACCAAAGCCAAACACAT, AKT3 reverse primer TCTTGCCTCTGCAGTCTGTC; IL2RB forward primer AGAAGTGCTGGAGAGGGACA, IL2RB reverse primer CGGGAGGTGGAAGAAGAAGT; CSF2RA forward primer GAATGTTCGTGCACATTTCG, CSF2RA reverse primer ACCCTCCCTTCCTGAATTTG; IL5RA forward primer CTCTGCTATCAGGCCCTTTG, IL5RA reverse primer AGCAATGGATTGGAAAAGCA; IL7R forward primer GGTTTGCCTAGTGCTTTTGC, IL7R reverse primer GGCAGAATGCCATCCTTTTA; MAPK3 forward primer GGGAGGGGAGGAGTGGAG, MAPK3 reverse primer GCTGCCCCTTCACCATCT; CYC1 forward primer CACGGAGGATGAAGCTAAGG, CYC1 reverse primer AGCCTCACTGTTGGGGTATG; COX8A forward primer AGCTTGGGATCATGGAATTG, COX8A reverse primer AGAACGGACCCCTTCACTCT; UQCRC1 forward primer ACTGTTAGACCTCGCCCAGA, UQCRC1 reverse primer GGGCAAAAGGTAGAGCATCA; LDHA forward primer GTACTGCATTTGCCCCTTGA, LDHA reverse primer CTGGATCCCAGGATGTGACT; GYPA forward primer GAACTGTGTCGGAGCACTCA, GYPA reverse primer ATGTCCGGTTTGCACATCTT; ALAS2 forward primer TTCCTACTTCGGGAACATGG, ALAS2 reverse primer GAGGCACACAACAAAGCAGA; FOXO3 forward primer GGCGGACTTTGTGTTTGTTT, FOXO3 reverse primer AAGCCACCTGAAATCACACC; β-ACTIN forward primer CATCGAGCACGGCATCGTCA, β-ACTIN reverse primer TAGCACAGCCTGGATAGCAAC. Relative mRNA levels were calculated using the 2
 <sup>−ΔΔCT</sup> method and normalized by β-actin in the same sample.
</p>
