<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Built on the fact that hACE2 is highly susceptible
to SARS-CoV-2, many previous studies only performed sequence analyses
and used the sequence identity between animal ACE2 proteins and hACE2
to predict intermediate hosts,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref></sup> as it was believed that the ACE2 proteins that are similar to hACE2
may also be susceptible.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref></sup> We calculated the MCCs
for distinguishing experimentally determined effective ACE2 receptors
from the less effective ones listed in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref> using sequence identity. The maximum MCCs
were 0.51, 0.73, and 0.53 with the optimum sequence identity cutoff
of 66&#8211;78%, 61&#8211;65%, and &#8804;60% in terms of all,
interface, and key residues, respectively (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jproteome.0c00717/suppl_file/pr0c00717_si_001.pdf">Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>), which were much lower than that achieved by the
classification via binding energy assessment (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jproteome.0c00717/suppl_file/pr0c00717_si_001.pdf">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>). Four New-World monkeys (<italic>Sapajus apella</italic>, <italic>Aotus nancymaae</italic>, <italic>Saimiri boliviensis</italic>, and <italic>Callithrix jacchus</italic>) share a relatively high sequence identity of &gt;92%, 80%, and
80%
with hACE2 in terms of all, interface, and key residues, respectively
(<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jproteome.0c00717/suppl_file/pr0c00717_si_001.pdf">Supplementary Tables S4 and S7</ext-link>). Following
the optimum sequence identity cutoffs, the ACE2 proteins of these
New-World monkeys were predicted to be very effective receptors. However,
in vivo infection studies showed <italic>C.&#160;jacchus</italic> was
not susceptible to SARS-CoV-2;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup> in vitro
experiments also suggested that the ACE2 proteins of <italic>S.&#160;apella</italic>, <italic>S.&#160;boliviensis</italic>, and <italic>C.&#160;jacchus</italic> cannot be used by SARS-CoV-2.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref></sup> In contrast,
dogs, cats, and ferrets, which have a much lower sequence identity
to hACE2 than the new-world monkeys (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jproteome.0c00717/suppl_file/pr0c00717_si_001.pdf">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>), can be infected by SARS-CoV-2 in nature and/or in
vivo.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>&#8722;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref></sup> These results suggest that an ACE2 protein with a higher sequence
identity to hACE2 is not necessarily an effective receptor, whereas
those with lower identities are not necessarily poor ones. Therefore,
sequence identity between hACE2 and animal ACE2 may not be a good
descriptor for host identification.</p>