<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>L-Tyr induces melanin production and increases the synthesis of proteins related to melanogenesis as previously reported [
 <xref rid="B55-ijms-22-01591" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-ijms-22-01591" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>], trends confirmed in B16F1 cells exposed to L-Tyr (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01591-f001">Figure 1</xref>f). 
 <italic>Mitf</italic> did not change in cells exposed to L-Tyr; therefore, the differences found at the mRNA and protein levels for TYRP1, as well as the increase in TYR and DCT suggested that, in melanogenesis, other types of post-transcriptional regulation would be involved, such as the differential expression of sets of miRNAs: miR-211-5p and miR-148b-3p, previously reported as regulators of the pigmentation. Different miRNAs regulated 
 <italic>Mitf</italic> and, in turn, is a transcriptional regulator of 
 <italic>p21</italic>, 
 <italic>Cdk2</italic> [
 <xref rid="B100-ijms-22-01591" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-ijms-22-01591" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-ijms-22-01591" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>] and miR-211-5p, the latter, which regulates pigmentation by targeting EDEM1, a TYR inhibitor. miR-211-5p increased to 2.5 X by exposure to L-Tyr and decreased 2 X by 5-Brd-2′-dU. We did not find a miR-211-5p direct specific gene target involved in the melanogenesis. However, this was the only miRNA that showed differences between the two phenotypes—pigmented and unpigmented melanoma cells. It is exciting that miR-211-5p has been proposed as an indirect regulator of pigmentation through binding to the TGF β-2 receptor, a factor responsible for the transcription of pigmentation-associated genes Dct, TYRP1, TYR, and PMEL17 [
 <xref rid="B103-ijms-22-01591" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>] and binding to the TYR inhibitor EDEM1 mRNA [
 <xref rid="B104-ijms-22-01591" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]; additionally, MITF may regulate the expression of miR-211-5p [
 <xref rid="B103-ijms-22-01591" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Together, these results suggest a possible pigmentation regulatory circuit in which genes regulated by miR-211 and the MITF factor would be participating, including the coordinated expression of sets of miRNAs.
</p>
