<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <caption>
  <title>Key messages</title>
 </caption>
 <sec>
  <title content-type="box">What is already known about this subject?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Interferon-responsive gene expression has been associated with cutaneous lupus erythematosus (CLE) pathogenesis and can be measured in skin biopsies; however, biopsy is relatively invasive and can result in infection or scarring.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Skin tape RNA sampling is an emerging modality to potentially replace invasive skin biopsy; this technique has proven useful to inform on disease-specific gene expression in atopic dermatitis and psoriasis diseases and is in use in the clinic to diagnose melanoma.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title content-type="box">What does this study add?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>To our knowledge, this is the first use of a non-invasive skin tape method to measure RNA expression in CLE skin.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>This study is also the first to identify gene signatures that discriminate between CLE-affected and healthy volunteers’ skin and between CLE-affected and CLE-unaffected skin from tape-derived RNA.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title content-type="box">How might this impact on clinical practice or future developments?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>This tape RNA method and associated gene signatures may be used as surrogate to punch biopsy to further elucidate CLE natural disease course and/or response to treatment. This novel use of the tape RNA technique will promote easier access to molecular data from CLE skin samples while prioritising patient welfare. While confirmation and validation of this methodology in a large-scale study is needed, it shows promise for use in precision medicine—the right treatment for the right patient.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
</boxed-text>
