<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50">PZP is associated with pregnancy, and it is produced in the liver, placenta and other tissues. The blood concentration of PZP increases during pregnancy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Mechanically, elevated estrogen levels during pregnancy may regulate PZP levels [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Moreover, elevated PZP has been identified as an indicator associated with 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> infection. Sputum but not serum concentrations of PZP have been significantly associated with the Bronchiectasis Severity Index, the frequency of exacerbations and symptoms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Previous research has also uncovered the role of PZP in cancers. In hepatocellular carcinoma, PZP has low expression in tumor tissues, and the downregulation of PZP is correlated with poor clinical outcomes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Our research identified and validated PZP as a novel serum biomarker for screening LAC in patients with T2DM by SWATH-MS, PRM-MS and ELISA analyses. Besides, we also analyzed the expression of PZP and its correlations with immune cell infiltration in lung cancer. The results showed that 
 <italic>PZP</italic> mRNA was downregulated in lung cancer tissues and significantly correlated with immune cell infiltration (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S4A-B). However, in the TCGA database, not all patients have T2DM before the diagnosis of lung cancer. Besides, the TCGA database only provides gene expression data at the mRNA level. Serum biomarkers are not only derived from tumor cell, but may also be released by tumor-related immune cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. According to the HPA database, PZP is highly expressed in immune cells, including T cells and macrophages. In previous research, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> infection-induced PZP elevation was derived from neutrophils [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Therefore, serum PZP may be derived from tumor-related immune cells, but further studies still need to confirm the source of PZP and its diagnostic value by large-scale analysis.
</p>
