<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ordered pristine bulk Co oxides are believed to be inactive for OER, and the observed catalytic activity is commonly associated with the presence of defects, undercoordinated sites, and amorphous phases.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref549">549</xref>
 </sup> Good electrocatalytic performance requires also a good electrical conductivity, which may be insufficient in some bulk oxides. Therefore, different routes have been proposed to prepare efficient Co-based catalysts. Among recent examples, one can mention the formation of Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>-graphene composites
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref575">575</xref>
 </sup> and Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> nanocrystals supported on carbon nanotubes,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref576">576</xref>
 </sup> the activation of Co-species in metal–organic frameworks by plasma treatment,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref577">577</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref578">578</xref>
 </sup> and the preparation of amorphous CoO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> clusters from biopolymers.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref579">579</xref>
 </sup> Nevertheless, the disordered nature of the active catalysts in all of these examples limits the applicability of many experimental tools, such as X-ray diffraction. At the same time, Co K-edge XAS data provided useful insight into the structures of the as-prepared catalysts and confirmed the disordered structures of the Co–O structural motifs. However, significant structural changes in these catalysts are expected under working conditions, and, thus, 
 <italic>operando</italic> measurements are essential.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref549">549</xref>
 </sup> An alternative, often used in the studies of OER catalysts, are 
 <italic>quasi in situ</italic> measurements, that is, so-called freeze-quench approach where the catalyst is rapidly frozen under applied potential by immersing it in liquid nitrogen to preserve its state, and then disconnected from the electrodes. As shown in 
 <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">39</xref>
 </xref>a, at least for some material systems such an approach was demonstrated to yield similar results as the 
 <italic>in situ</italic>/
 <italic>operando</italic> measurements but allows the collection of EXAFS data of better quality.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref580">580</xref>
 </sup> Both 
 <italic>operando</italic> and 
 <italic>quasi in situ</italic> XAS measurements have been instrumental for probing the active state of Co-based OER catalysts.
</p>
