<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nevertheless, results of numerous EXAFS experiments for different Co-based oxides point to the same general trend, namely, the formation of CoOOH species consisting of edge-sharing CoO
 <sub>6</sub> structural units under reaction conditions (high pH or high anodic potential), which are believed to be the active phase for OER.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref549">549</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref551">551</xref>
 </sup> The fingerprints of these structural motifs in EXAFS spectra collected under OER conditions, namely, the characteristic interatomic distances and shapes of the main peaks in FT-EXAFS spectra are shown in 
 <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">39</xref>
 </xref>b and c. The importance of such structures for OER catalysis has been demonstrated in a number of 
 <italic>in situ</italic> and 
 <italic>quasi in situ</italic> studies of phosphate-derived amorphous cobalt oxide catalysts (Co-Pi),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref580">580</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref582">582</xref>
 </sup> Co-based perovskites,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref583">583</xref>
 </sup> oxychloride-derived Co oxide catalysts,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref584">584</xref>
 </sup> CoO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> NPs,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref585">585</xref>
 </sup> Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>/CoO core–shell structures,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref586">586</xref>
 </sup> and pure Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> spinel structures.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref244">244</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref587">587</xref>
 </sup> The latter case seems to be special because of the thermodynamic stability of the spinel structure. More importantly, by employing the freeze-quench XAS approach in combination with 
 <italic>in situ</italic> X-ray diffraction, Bergmann et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref244">244</xref>
 </sup> showed that the transformation of Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> to a CoOOH-like amorphous structure under OER conditions is reversible and that the spinel structure is recovered after reaction.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref244">244</xref>
 </sup> In a follow-up study from the same group,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref574">574</xref>
 </sup> by comparing the 
 <italic>in situ</italic> transformations under OER conditions in four well-defined model catalysts (Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> with spinel structure, CoO with rocksalt (rs-CoO) and wurtzite-type (w-CoO) structure, as well as CoOOH with low crystallinity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref574">574</xref>
 </sup>), the formation of a surface CoO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>(OH)
 <sub>
  <italic>y</italic>
 </sub> layer was observed in all cases. However, unlike the case of Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>, the structural changes in other model compounds were irreversible, and were especially pronounced in w-CoO. Considering the aforementioned ambiguity of the interpretation of distant coordination shell contributions to the Co K-edge EXAFS spectra, a useful complementary information can be extracted from O K-edge analysis. Here, the differences in the oxide structures result in significantly different spectral features (
 <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">39</xref>
 </xref>d–f). Moreover, by collecting O K-edge data in the total electron yield mode, surface specific information about 
 <italic>operando</italic> catalyst transformations can be obtained. For example, significant changes in the O K-edge XAS spectra for the Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>, rs-CoO, w-CoO, and CoOOH model catalysts were observed after OER conditioning. By using 
 <italic>ab initio</italic> XAS simulations, the dominant feature visible in the spectra for all catalysts under reaction conditions at 530.5 eV, 
 <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">39</xref>
 </xref>e, was attributed to 3- or 4-coordinated O species characteristic for octahedral structural units. A second feature at ∼531.5 eV was attributed to 2-fold coordinated bridging oxygen species at the edges and corners of CoO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>(OH)
 <sub>
  <italic>y</italic>
 </sub> domains, which were found to be important for fast OER processes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref574">574</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
