<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The structural transformation of cobalt oxides under OER conditions is accompanied by an increase in Co oxidation state, which results in a potential- and pH-dependent shift of the Co K-edge XANES features (
 <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">39</xref>
 </xref>a).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref580">580</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref582">582</xref>
 </sup> Under OER conditions, the oxidation state of Co within the catalytically active CoOOH units is believed to be close to 3+,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref580">580</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref582">582</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref588">588</xref>
 </sup> although reports showing oxidation state &gt;3+ also exist.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref582">582</xref>
 </sup> However, the definition of the absorption edge position is ambiguous, and changes in materials structure can also result in the shift of the absorption edge position. For example, according to 
 <xref rid="eq15" ref-type="disp-formula">eq 
  <xref rid="eq15" ref-type="disp-formula">15</xref>
 </xref>, a decrease of the interatomic distances will also result in a positive shift of the XANES features. Moreover, since the increase of the oxidation state is often accompanied by a reduction of the interatomic distances, 
 <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig39" ref-type="fig">39</xref>
 </xref>b, it might be hard to disentangle both contributions simply based on a comparison with reference compounds. Therefore, accurate quantitative determination of the Co oxidation state from Co K-edge XANES is challenging, especially if the increase in the oxidation state is paralleled by significant structural changes. In such cases, the observed spectra may not be directly fitted with a linear combination of reference spectra for standard compounds with well-defined oxidation states. Friebel et al. proposed the analysis of pre-edge features at the Co K-edge as a more robust tool to monitor the Co oxidation state.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref384">384</xref>
 </sup> By employing advanced RIXS spectroscopy, significant differences in the RIXS spectra for reference materials with different oxidation states were observed (
 <xref rid="fig40" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig40" ref-type="fig">40</xref>
 </xref>a,b). The RIXS spectrum for electrodeposited CoO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> catalyst under OER conditions, 
 <xref rid="fig40" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig40" ref-type="fig">40</xref>
 </xref>c, exhibited similarity with that of CoOOH. However, the broad feature observed in the CoOOH spectrum at an excitation energy ∼7713 eV, attributed to the nonlocal transitions to 3d states, was less pronounced in the spectrum of the CoO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> catalyst. Moreover, potential-dependent changes in the pre-edge in HERFD-XAS were observed (
 <xref rid="fig40" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig40" ref-type="fig">40</xref>
 </xref>d–f). These changes were explained by a gradual increase in the intensity of an additional feature in the Co K-edge XAS that is not observed in the CoOOH spectrum (
 <xref rid="fig40" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig40" ref-type="fig">40</xref>
 </xref>g). The latter, based on DFT simulations, was attributed to a contribution of Co
 <sup>4+</sup> species. Interestingly, the presence of Co
 <sup>4+</sup> species was concluded to be rather detrimental for OER activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref384">384</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
