<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Other transition metal oxides have also been investigated for applications in OER, and edge-sharing metal–oxygen octahedra are believed to be the key structural motifs in many of them.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref589">589</xref>
 </sup> For example, Mn-based oxides attract attention because of their potential for applications in acidic media, low toxicity, and the very large diversity of possible structure models.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref549">549</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref590">590</xref>
 </sup> For instance, the effect of the MnO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> catalyst synthesis route on its structure and OER performance was explored.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref589">589</xref>
 </sup> By comparing Mn K-edge EXAFS spectra, a significant difference in the contributions of distant coordination shells was observed for catalysts prepared by a chemical synproportionation method (i.e., from a solution containing Mn precursors in 2+ and 7+ oxidation states)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref591">591</xref>
 </sup> versus an impregnation-based synthesis (from Mn
 <sup>2+</sup> precursors), 
 <xref rid="fig41" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig41" ref-type="fig">41</xref>
 </xref>a, despite the fact that the resulting Mn oxidation state was similar in both catalysts (ca. 3.5, according to XANES analysis). Moreover, the EXAFS signal of the catalyst prepared by the former method was dominated by fingerprints of edge-sharing octahedral structural motifs, while for the catalysts prepared by impregnation, a significant number of corner-sharing octahedral units was suggested (
 <xref rid="fig41" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig41" ref-type="fig">41</xref>
 </xref>b). Interestingly, a higher intrinsic OER activity was observed for the catalysts prepared via the synproportionation method containing predominantly edge-sharing octahedra. Under reaction conditions, the Mn average oxidation state increased up to ∼4, paralleled by a decrease of the Mn–O interatomic distances. However, no significant changes in the catalyst structure were observed. Recently, the presence of edge-sharing MnO
 <sub>6</sub> structural units was detected by EXAFS analysis also in the study of OER-active mesoporous MnO
 <sub>2</sub> prepared by thermal treatment on manganese carbonate,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref592">592</xref>
 </sup> and in MnO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> catalysts prepared by a spray process.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref593">593</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
