<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In all of these cases, a prominent role for ensuring high OER activity was attributed to Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> species, with MnO
 <sub>2</sub> oxide considered catalytically inactive.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref594">594</xref>
 </sup> Unfortunately, Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> species are thermodynamically unstable under reaction conditions. Recently, Chan et al. have demonstrated that Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> can be introduced into MnO
 <sub>2</sub> films and be kinetically stabilized within tetrahedral sites through a synproportionation reaction between MnO
 <sub>2</sub> and Mn(OH)
 <sub>2</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref590">590</xref>
 </sup> In their work, a MnO
 <sub>2</sub> film was electrodeposited, and Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> species were introduced by alternating the potential between 1.1 and −0.4 V (NHE) in the presence of Mn
 <sup>2+</sup> and NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>–</sup> ions in the electrolyte. Changes in the Mn K-edge position confirmed the incorporation of Mn
 <sup>3+</sup> species, 
 <xref rid="fig41" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig41" ref-type="fig">41</xref>
 </xref>c, while a gradual decrease of the Mn–O coordination number (from the original value of 6, 
 <xref rid="fig41" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig41" ref-type="fig">41</xref>
 </xref>d), suggested that Mn is incorporated in tetrahedrally coordinated sites, forming a spinel-like structure.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref590">590</xref>
 </sup> The oxidation state of Mn can also be controlled by introducing another metal. For example, it was demonstrated that having Au NPs in the MnO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> films increases the Mn oxidation state in the as-prepared state as well as under OER conditions and promotes the OER activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref595">595</xref>
 </sup> More common are OER catalysts where a transition metal is combined with another 3d metal, resulting in unique structural motifs. Examples of such catalysts are discussed in the next subsection.
</p>
