<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because of the fact that the measured XAS spectrum is an average of contributions for all absorbing species, for a heterogeneous mixture, the obtained XAS signal μ
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>) may be described as a combination of the corresponding spectra for the pure compounds 
 <italic>s</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>), weighted by the concentration of the specific species 
 <italic>w</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>ij</italic>
 </sub>:
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>
 </sup>
 <disp-formula id="eq19">
  <graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m030" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>19</label>
 </disp-formula>If the spectra 
 <italic>s</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>) are known, the concentrations of different species can be obtained via simple linear combination analysis (LCA), where the parameters 
 <italic>w</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>ij</italic>
 </sub> are optimized to achieve a good match between the experimentally measured spectrum and the linear combination of reference spectra 
 <italic>s</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>). For decades, this has been the most common approach for the analysis of XANES spectra for materials experiencing structural transformations or changes in composition. For example, it is a very common approach to monitor the reduction (oxidation) of catalysts during the activation or under reaction conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref111">111</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref367">367</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref369">369</xref>
 </sup> By extracting LCA weights for different reference materials 
 <italic>w</italic>
 <sub>i</sub>, the average oxidation state can be obtained simply as 
 <inline-formula id="d33e4919">
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m031.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, where 
 <italic>q</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> is the charge state of the absorbing species in the reference samples.
</p>
