<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">The freshwater mussel 
 <italic>A. plicata</italic> is a common species found in a wide variety of habitats, and it is likely that rare species with narrow habitat requirements might experience more severe levels of stress after translocation. Yet conservation projects involving translocation usually focus on rare and endangered species. 
 <italic>Amblema plicata</italic> experienced stress in captivity 11 months post translocation, as evidenced by increased expression of transcripts in gill tissue coding for heat shock proteins, antioxidants, and immune response. Although we only collected a small amount of gill tissue in order to maintain a non-lethal sampling procedure, more insight could be gained in future studies by sampling the whole soft body or various other tissue types, since different tissues may show variable responses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. For example, analysis of mantle tissue might provide more information about changes in expression of genes regulating growth and mantle formation, and analysis of foot and adductor muscles could provide more insight into energy use and demand by other organs. Analysis of gene expression in other tissues could also provide more information about the distribution of the stress response among various organs. However, sampling multiple tissue types or internal organs could be lethal to the organism, an important consideration especially when working with threatened or endangered species. In our study, increased expression of transcripts involved in energy metabolism indicated that mussels were experiencing chronic, moderate stress. Although we estimate that the studied mussels were experiencing only moderate stress, we find our ability to detect stress 11 months after translocation to be concerning, especially because 
 <italic>A. plicata</italic> is usually considered a tolerant species. Furthermore, a chronically stressed mussel may not grow at a normal rate or reproduce successfully, both of which are important factors in successful propagation projects. In this study, we did not attempt to isolate the effects of a specific stressor (e.g., food supply, substrate composition, water temperature) but recognize that mussels moved into captivity are presumably exposed to changes in multiple environmental variables, and multiple stressors often have synergistic and unpredictable effects on gene expression
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>
 </sup>. Differences in water composition between the Muskingum and Scioto rivers could also contribute to stress observed in our translocated animals, and future work should consider the ways that differences between these systems might contribute to the stress experienced by translocated mussels. Because wild 
 <italic>A. plicata</italic> live in both the Muskingum and Scioto Rivers, neither system is inherently unsuitable for this species; the stress response we see in the captive mussels is thus probably related to translocation or captivity.
</p>
