<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the constraints on the evolution of large bodies and long lifespans in animals is an increased risk of developing cancer. If all cells in all organisms have a similar risk of malignant transformation and equivalent cancer suppression mechanisms, then organisms with many cells should have a higher prevalence of cancer than organisms with fewer cells, particularly because large and small animals have similar cell sizes (
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Savage et al., 2007</xref>). Consistent with this expectation there is a strong positive correlation between body size and cancer incidence within species; for example, cancer incidence increases with increasing adult height in humans (
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Million Women Study collaborators et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Nunney, 2018</xref>) and with increasing body size in dogs, cats, and cattle (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Dobson, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Dorn et al., 1968</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Lucena et al., 2011</xref>). There is no correlation, however, between body size and cancer risk between species; this lack of correlation is often referred to as ‘Peto’s Paradox’ (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Caulin and Maley, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Leroi et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Peto et al., 1975</xref>). Indeed, cancer prevalence is relatively stable at ~5% across species with diverse body sizes ranging from the minuscule 51 g grass mouse to the gargantuan 4800 kg African elephant (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abegglen et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Boddy et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Tollis et al., 2020</xref>). The ultimate resolution to Peto’s Paradox is trivial, large-bodied and long-lived species evolved enhanced cancer protection mechanisms, but identifying and characterizing the mechanisms that underlie the evolution of augmented cancer protection has proven difficult (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Ashur-Fabian et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Seluanov et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Gorbunova et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Tian et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Sulak et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
