<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">One of the challenges for discovering how animals evolved enhanced cancer protection mechanisms is identifying lineages in which large-bodied species are nested within species with small body sizes. Afrotherian mammals are generally small-bodied, but also include the largest extant land mammals. For example, maximum adult weights are ~70 g in golden moles,~120 g in tenrecs,~170 g in elephant shrews,~3 kg in hyraxes, and ~60 kg in aardvarks (<xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">Tacutu et al., 2013</xref>). In contrast, while extant hyraxes are relatively small, the extinct Titanohyrax is estimated to have weighed ~1300 kg (<xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz et al., 1995</xref>). The largest living Afrotheria are also dwarfed by the size of their recent extinct relatives: extant sea cows such as manatees are large bodied (~322&#8211;480 kg) but are relatively small compared to the extinct Stellar&#8217;s sea cow which is estimated to have weighed ~8000&#8211;10,000 kg (<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Scheffer, 1972</xref>). Similarly African Savannah (4800 kg) and Asian elephants (3200 kg) are large, but are dwarfed by the truly gigantic extinct Proboscideans such as Deinotherium (~12,000 kg), <italic>Mammut borsoni</italic> (16,000 kg), and the straight-tusked elephant (~14,000 kg) (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Larramendi, 2015</xref>). Remarkably, these large-bodied Afrotherian lineages are nested deeply within small-bodied species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>; <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">O Leary et al., 2013a</xref>; <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Springer et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">O Leary et al., 2013b</xref>; <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Puttick and Thomas, 2015</xref>), indicating that gigantism independently evolved in hyraxes, sea cows, and elephants (Paenungulata). Thus, Paenungulates are an excellent model system in which to explore the mechanisms that underlie the evolution of large body sizes and augmented cancer resistance.</p>