<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many mechanisms have been suggested to resolve Peto’s paradox, including a decrease in the copy number of oncogenes, an increase in the copy number of tumor suppressor genes (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Caulin and Maley, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Leroi et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Nunney, 1999</xref>), reduced metabolic rates, reduced retroviral activity and load (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Katzourakis et al., 2014</xref>), and selection for ‘cheater’ tumors that parasitize the growth of other tumors (
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Nagy et al., 2007</xref>), greater sensitivity of cells to DNA damage (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abegglen et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Sulak et al., 2016</xref>), enhanced recognition of neoantigens by T cells, among many others. Among the most parsimonious routes to enhanced cancer resistance may be through an increased copy number of tumor suppressors. For example, transgenic mice with additional copies of 
 <italic>TP53</italic> have reduced cancer rates and extended lifespans (
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">García-Cao et al., 2002</xref>), suggesting that changes in the copy number of tumor suppressors can affect cancer rates. Indeed, candidate genes studies have found that elephant genomes encode duplicate tumor suppressors such as 
 <italic>TP53</italic> and 
 <italic>LIF</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abegglen et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Sulak et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">Vazquez et al., 2018</xref>) as well as other genes with putative tumor suppressive functions (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Caulin et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Doherty and de Magalhães, 2016</xref>). These studies, however, focused on a priori candidate genes; thus it is unclear whether duplication of tumor suppressor genes is a general phenomenon in the elephant lineage or reflects an ascertainment bias.
</p>
