<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There was a significant difference between the two caste destined larvae in quantitative protein expressions at 72 hours, suggesting that the difference in biological requirements that lead the two larvae into caste divergence has already began. This is in contrast to previous studies 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Cristino1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Winston1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> which support the notion that day 3 larva is totipotent and are able to differentiate into either worker or queen. The divergences of the two caste destined larvae became more profound at 120 hours through quantitatively and qualitatively upregulated proteins. Qualitatively, the worker larvae upregulated proteins were reduced from 11 to 9, while the number increased significantly in queen destined larvae from 11 to 16, confirming the divergence 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Evans2" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Gadagkar1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> dictated and directed by specific proteins types and amounts. In particular, the variations between the two larvae in terms of proteins for carbohydrate metabolism and energy production increased their metabolic activities at both developmental stages significantly. More specifically, the over-expression of transketolase, aldehyde reductanse and enolase at 72 hours in queen destined larvae and ATP synthase beta subunit and phosphoglycerate mutase in worker destined larvae suggests that the two larvae differed in their glucose level and saccharidase activity at this or an earlier stage. Moreover, out of the 6 upregulated proteins related to carbohydrate metabolism and energy production in the queen destined larvae, 2 proteins were upregulated in worker destined larvae at late stages of 120 hours. In support of this, important carbohydrate metabolism and energy production metabolic proteins like aldehyde dehydrogenase, transketolase, ATP synthase ßsubunit, phosphoglycerate mutase and enolase showed considerable age-linked increase in queen destined larvae. Together with functional enrichment and biological network analysis, our data suggests that carbohydrate metabolism and energy production proteins play special and central roles in caste differentiation and determination 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Winston1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Ishay1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Randolt2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Moreover, especially for the queen larvae, phosphoglycerate kinase and aldehyde dehydrogenase became apparent only at 120 hours and enolase, phosphoglycerate mutase and transketolase were present at both developmental stages. The particular over-expression of these specific proteins in the queen intended larvae indicate their explicit function towards enhancing the metabolic energy requirement of queen larvae to assist in attaining queen distinctive physiological and behavioral characters 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Winston1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. The metabolism of aldehyde dehydrogenase has been already reported selectively in the queen mandible 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Hasegawa1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> and its discriminatory occurrence in queen destined larvae in this study is most likely to equip the mandible of the future queen with special functions like production of pheromonal signals that involve the regulation of the reproductive hierarchies 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Strauss1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Moreover, aldehyde dehydrogenase involved in glycolysis pathways together with transketolase involved in pentose phosphate pathway were observed as changing protein copy number. Hence, as changes in gene copy number are a vital source of variation and driving force in phenotypic evolution 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Aitman1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Eichler1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, likewise, we consider their over-expression as motivators for metabolic activities in queen larvae towards attaining distinctive phenotypic features 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Corona1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Evans2" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Barchuk2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.
</p>
