<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Cascade impactors are the most widely used device to evaluate the aerodynamic behaviour for DPIs
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>. Among them, the Next Generation Impactor (NGI), consisting of an artificial larynx, a pre-separator and impactor stages, not only has the characteristics of Andersen Cascade Impactor (ACI), but also has the advantages of fast analysis speed and easier manual operation
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>. Nowadays, there is still lack of direct and precise methods for 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> evaluation of laryngeal administration. Perkins et al.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> reported computational fluid dynamics to predict the ideal inhaled particle size range for targeted laryngeal deposition. Wang et al.
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> measured powder deposition with an idealized mouth–throat geometry and the powders retained in the filter indicated lung delivery. The 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> NGI evaluation method to DPIs can be utilized as a surrogate to evaluate laryngeal administration with maximum throat portion and less fine particle fraction (FPF), because the powders pass through the oral cavity 
 <italic>via</italic> inhalation after the capsule is punctured by the inhalation device
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>. The 
 <italic>United States Pharmacopeia</italic> (USP) defined throat of NGI as a right angle according to the characteristics of the human larynx, though its internal structure is highly simplified, which is mainly used to simulate the deposition of inhaled powders in the mouth, pharynx and larynx of human body during actual use process. Meanwhile, the emptying rate can be also introduced from DPIs methodology for laryngeal powder systems administered in capsules.
</p>
