<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CK-19 is an epithelial cytoskeletal protein associated with classical PTC based on its frequent over-expression [
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, CK-19 has not previously been analyzed in cyst fluids of thyroid lesions. We observed significantly up-regulated levels of CK-19 in depleted cyst fluids from cPTCs by LC-MS/MS, which was confirmed by IHC and WB. However, microscopical evaluation of morphologically normal thyrocytes surrounding cPTC did not show any CK-19 immunostaining, indicating a primary role of the cPTC cells in secretion of CK-19, which is also consistent with data from other publications [
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The staining patterns for HBME-1 were similar to CK-19, supporting the role of these proteins as post-operative markers of both classical and cystic PTC in clinical routine at the stage of final pathological diagnosis [
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Further validation in the extended material was performed on non-depleted cyst fluid samples by ELISA, which is a commonly used method in clinical diagnostics. We used the CYFRA 21–1 assay to determine concentration of CK-19 in biological fluids, which is consistent with other reports investigating the diagnostic utility of CK-19 measurement in serum samples of patients with thyroid or lung cancers by analyses of cytokeratin fragments [
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Our findings by ELISA demonstrate up-regulation of CK-19 in cPTCs, supporting the results of LC-MS/MS, IHC and WB experiments. By ROC curve analyses, we determined that 55 ng/ml or more is an optimal cut-off for CK-19 concentration in non-depleted cyst fluid for discrimination of cPTC from benign thyroid cysts by ELISA. Moreover, this suggested cut-off value is consistent with ROC curve parameters corresponding to a level of good diagnostic accuracy, supporting the role of CK-19 in diagnosis of cPTC. However, CK-19 concentrations &gt;55 ng/ml were also found in cyst fluid from some benign thyroid samples, indicating a limitation for CK-19 application as an independent test (
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Taken together, our data indicate that the determination of CK-19 concentration in cyst fluid by the CYFRA 21–1 assay can be an effective complementary tool to routine FNAB for discrimination of cPTC from benign thyroid cysts, which is in agreement with meta-analysis data suggesting CK-19 as a marker of thyroid malignancy [
 <xref rid="pone.0126472.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
