<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Early work by Krishtal et al., in 1980, demonstrated for the first time that application of extracellular acid could evoke inward currents in sensory neurones [
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and further work has shown that localized tissue acidification (pH ≤6.0) causes pain in humans [
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21–23</xref>]. Thus, there is a clear link between acidosis, acid-evoked sensory neurone activation and pain. There are a variety of ion channels and receptors that can be modulated by acid, which have been reviewed in detail elsewhere [
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], but here we will concentrate on ASICs, which underlie the transient inward currents first recorded 40 years ago. With the exception of ASIC4 and ASIC5, all ASIC subunits show robust expression in sensory neurones [
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and their activation by extracellular acid causes transient proton-gated currents that are mainly carried by Na
 <sup>+</sup>, although ASIC1a homomers also show Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> permeability [
 <xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The ASIC-mediated cation influx leads to neuronal depolarization, which, if of sufficient magnitude to activate voltage-gated sodium channels, can induce action potential firing in nociceptors (sensory neurones tuned to detect noxious stimuli [
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]) and ultimately evoke the sensation of pain. Whilst ASICs are gated by extracellular protons, their proton sensitivity can be modulated by other extracellular ions such as Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> and Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> (discussed in later sections). As illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>, homomeric ASIC3 and some ASIC3 containing heteromers (especially ASIC2a/3) display a pronounced sustained current in the continued presence of acidity following partial inactivation of the initial transient inward current. This sustained current implies that in the presence of prolonged tissue acidosis, ASIC3 would remain activated, supporting a sustained inward Na
 <sup>+</sup> current in sensory neurones causing their membrane depolarization and ultimately prolonged action potential firing. Thus, ASIC3 can effectively transduce the prolonged tissue acidosis occurring in pathological conditions into pain. 
</p>
