<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">Numerous studies have shown that several different genes, including 
 <italic>RDR</italic>, 
 <italic>DCL</italic>, 
 <italic>HYL</italic>, 
 <italic>SE</italic>, 
 <italic>HEN</italic>, 
 <italic>HST</italic>, and 
 <italic>AGO</italic>, play crucial roles in plant miRNA biosynthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In this study, we identified 8 
 <italic>RDR</italic>, 4 
 <italic>DCL</italic>, 1 
 <italic>HYL</italic>, 2 
 <italic>SE</italic>, 1 
 <italic>HEN</italic>, 2 
 <italic>HST</italic>, and 8 
 <italic>AGO</italic> genes in the Tartary buckwheat genome. The phylogenetic analyses showed that 8 RDR, 4 DCL, and 8 AGO could be divided into 4, 4, and 3 subfamilies, respectively. The results were consistent with the previous studies in other plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], and indicated that the evolution of these gene families was conserved in these plants. Expression analysis revealed that 1 
 <italic>AGO</italic>-like 
 <italic>FtAGO1</italic> had the highest expression in seeds in these identified genes, 1 
 <italic>AGO</italic>-like 
 <italic>FtAGO4</italic> exhibited specific high expression in seeds, and 2 
 <italic>AGO</italic>-like 
 <italic>FtAGO2</italic> and 
 <italic>FtAGO3</italic> exhibited significant differential expression during seed development. Notably, 
 <italic>OsAGO17</italic>, which belongs to the same subfamily as these four 
 <italic>FtAGO</italic> genes, had been functionally demonstrated to positively regulate the grain size and grain weight in rice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. This suggested that these four 
 <italic>FtAGO</italic> genes might also play a similar role with 
 <italic>OsAGO17</italic> in Tartary buckwheat seed development. In addition, we also found that 
 <italic>FtHYL1</italic>, 
 <italic>FtHST2</italic>, and 
 <italic>FtAGO8</italic> displayed especially high expression in seeds, and 
 <italic>FtDCL1</italic>, 
 <italic>FtDCL3</italic>, 
 <italic>FtDCL4</italic>, and 
 <italic>FtRDR4</italic> were obviously differential expression during seed development. These indicated that these miRNA biosynthesis genes might also have important regulatory roles in Tartary buckwheat seed development.
</p>
