<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">ToxB protein was heterologously expressed via an 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> SHuffle strain and purified using immobilised metal affinity chromatography (IMAC) as described in See et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2019</xref>). Briefly, the DNA sequence that encodes the mature ToxB protein (GenBank accession PZD27634) (Martinez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2001</xref>) was cloned into the pET21a(+) (Novagen) vector using the primers ToxB-sigP_F (5′-GGAATTC
 <underline>CATATG</underline>AACTGCGTCGCCAATAT-3′) and ToxB_R (5′-CCG
 <underline>CTCGAG</underline>ACAACGTCCTCCACTTTGCA-3′) that included the engineered 
 <italic>NdeI</italic> and 
 <italic>XhoI</italic> sites (underlined), respectively. The resulting construct contained the predicted ToxB protein fused to a poly-histidine tag at the C-terminal, and was used to transform the 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> SHuffle strain. The SHuffle strain harbouring the ToxB expression construct was grown in Terrific Broth medium and induced with β-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) at a final concentration of 100 µM for the expression of ToxB. Cells were harvested by centrifugation and resuspended in 5 ml binding buffer (20 mM sodium phosphate, 40 mM imidazole, 500 mM NaCl, pH 7.4) for the purpose of downstream his-tag purification. Cells were then lysed using sonication of 10-s pulses with 10-s intervals for 1 min (Sonoplus HD 3100, Bandelin, Germany). The cell debris was pelleted by centrifugation, and the ToxB protein was purified from the cell extract using HisPur Ni-NTA purification spin columns (Thermo Scientific) by gravity flow according to manufacturer’s instructions. Purified protein was dialysed in 20 mM sodium phosphate buffer, pH 7.4, quantified via the bicinchoninic acid assay (Smith et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">1985</xref>) and stored in freeze-dried form at − 80 °C. Prior to infiltration, protein was resuspended in sterile water to a concentration of 200 µg/ml.
</p>
