<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">The putative minor QTL identified in the MAGIC population on the long arm of chromosome 2A differs from previously identified QTL controlling sensitivity to 
 <italic>Ptr</italic> race 5 isolates located on chromosomes 2BS (
 <italic>Tsr6</italic>, Singh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2010</xref>), 2AS and 2BL (Friesen and Faris 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2004</xref>). Due to the low percentage of the phenotypic variation accounted for, and its identification only in the CIM–cov10 analyses, the status of this QTL is currently putative. While further investigation of this minor QTL would initially only have been thought to be of interest in determining the genetic pathways controlling the fine control of wheat ToxB sensitivity, it is interesting to note that this QTL co-locates with a robust QTL in the same MAGIC population conferring both adult plant and seedling resistance to the related necrotrophic pathogen 
 <italic>P. nodorum</italic> (
 <italic>QSnb.niab-2A.3</italic> at ~ 140 cM) (Lin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2019</xref>). Similarly, a minor QTL controlling sensitivity to the 
 <italic>P. nodorum</italic> effector Tox3 (Downie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2018</xref>) is reported to collocate with another chromosome 2A 
 <italic>P. nodorum</italic> field resistance QTL
 <italic>, Qsnb.niab.2A.4</italic> (Lin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2019</xref>). Collectively, these results indicate that minor necrotrophic fungal pathogen effector sensitivity QTL may also be relevant to field resistance to this class of wheat necrotrophic fungal pathogens, as has been shown for the major 
 <italic>P. nodorum</italic> effector sensitivity loci 
 <italic>Tsn1, Snn1</italic> and 
 <italic>Snn3-B1</italic> in wheat (e.g. Friesen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2009</xref>; Phan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2016</xref>; Ruud et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2017</xref>).
</p>
