<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">In general, depression and anxiety clinically display distinct fundamental symptoms, but are often diagnosed simultaneously
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. Because of this considerable overlapping in comorbidity and pathophysiology, the data in most clinical and basic studies are often mixed
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>, potentially obscuring our understanding of the factors modulating the two diseases. Several researchers are slowly starting to analyze separately non-comorbid subjects to reveal the unique and common characteristics of the nervous systems
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Both depression and anxiety are heterogeneous diseases controlled through various brain structures, including the hippocampus and prefrontal cortex. Several studies have suggested that depression and anxiety result in a reduced volume and dendritic spine density of the prefrontal cortical regions in humans and animals
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. The prefrontal cortex, as a sensitive brain region to stress, participates in executive, cognitive, and socio-emotional functions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Chronic stress-induced morphological and functional changes that take place in the prefrontal cortex can result in both the cognitive and emotional dysfunctions leading to depression or anxiety
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Despite the abnormal prefrontal cortical plasticity observed in depressive, as well as anxious individuals, the corresponding inherent patterns might be markedly distinct and remain unknown. Hence, to identify distinct and common molecular features underlying susceptibility and resilience to depression or anxiety has become a pressing need.
</p>
