<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>KPNA3 and KPNA4, both belonged to the karyopherin alpha two subfamily [
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], play vital roles in protein nuclear transportation [
 <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15–18</xref>], nuclear pore complexes (NPC) assembly [
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref>], and in regulating transcriptional activity [
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], innate immune response [
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24–26</xref>] and cell death [
 <xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27–30</xref>]. Previous studies also demonstrated that some viruses such as Japanese encephalitis virus [
 <xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], porcine circovirus type 2 [
 <xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and influenza virus [
 <xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34–37</xref>] could hijack KPNA3/4 to competitively block the interaction of KPNA3/4 with their cargos, and then to restrict their function to establish infection or evade the host antiviral response. Our data showed that the over-expression or knockout of KPNA3/4 could decrease or increase the viral replication of FAdV-4, respectively. However, the effect of KPNA3/4 on the viral replication of FAdV-4 in our studies was not very significant. This might be related with the potential complement activity for KPNA3 and KPNA4 due to their similar functions [
 <xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. To overcome this, we also tried to generate LMH cells with double knockout of KPNA3 and KPNA4. However, such LMH cells with double knockout of KPNA3 and KPNA4 could not be generated, indicating the key roles of KPNA3 and KPNA4 in cell survival. Recently, one study reported that KPNA3, KPNA4, and KPNB1 were important regulators of inflammation via activation of RelA/p65 and permeability via loss of cell surface VE-Cadherin in endothelial cell (EC) [
 <xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Considering that the infection of FAdV-4 causes a significant decrease of colloid osmotic pressure [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], it is not difficult to speculate that the interaction between Fiber-2 of FAdV-4 with KPNA3/4 might be related with hydropericardium symptom.
</p>
