<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>
   <bold>DEHP impacted the progress of germline cyst breakdown and follicular assembly. (A)</bold> Clustering of germ cell population with UMAP, colored based on sample groups. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Clustering of germ cell population with UMAP, colored based on 12 cell clusters. 
   <bold>(C)</bold> Expression of 
   <italic>Taf7l</italic> and
   <italic> Figla</italic> separating the germ cell clusters into different developmental stages based on UMAP. The color intensity of cyan or maroon represents gene expression level; grey refers to the double-negative cells and the color threshold of gene expression is 0.5. 
   <bold>(D)</bold> Expression of representative genes in cell clusters for germ cell-specific developmental stages, the pre-stage of follicle formation with highly expressed meiosis related genes: 
   <italic>Meioc, M1ap</italic>; the early-stage marked by high expression of key genes for follicle formation: 
   <italic>Figla, Lhx8</italic>; the late-stage contained genes required for oocyte growth: 
   <italic>Zp3, Padi6</italic>. 
   <bold>(E)</bold> The three separated developmental stages in germ cell clusters. Cell cluster classification, feature plots and cell percentages of sample groups for the three stages are shown in the upper, middle, and bottom panels. 
   <bold>(F)</bold> Representative images of ovarian sections with normal and DEHP-treated groups at PD3. Germ cells were marked by MVH (green) and cell nuclei were counterstained with propidium iodide (PI, red). Scale bar = 25 μm. (G) The percentages of germ cells within cysts and follicles at PD3 with and without DEHP exposure. Data are presented as mean ± SD (N = 3 for independent repeats, the total germ cell counting at PD3 in number was 1,710, 1,355, and 1,401, and 2,004, 1,828, and 2,341 at PD3-DEHP). **
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="thnov11p4992g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
