<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Loss of tooth or enamel is widespread in multiple mammal lineages. Although several studies have been reported, the evolutionary mechanisms of tooth/enamel loss are still unclear. Most previous studies have found that some tooth-related genes have been inactivated in toothless and/or enamel-less mammals, such as 
  <italic>ENAM</italic>, 
  <italic>ODAM</italic>, 
  <italic>C4orf26</italic>, 
  <italic>AMBN</italic>, 
  <italic>AMTN</italic>, 
  <italic>DSPP</italic>, etc. Here, we conducted evolutionary analyses on 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> playing a key role in amelogenesis, to interrogate the mechanisms. We obtained the 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> sequences from 116 species, including edentulous and enamel-less mammals. The results shows that variant ORF-disrupting mutations were detected in 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> coding region among nine edentulous baleen whales and three enamel-less taxa (pygmy sperm whale, aardvark, nine-banded armadillo). Furtherly, selective pressure uncovered that the selective constraints have been relaxed among all toothless and enamel-less lineages. Moreover, our results support the hypothesis that mineralized teeth were lost or degenerated in the common ancestor of crown Mysticeti through two shared single-base sites deletion in exon 4 and 5 of 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> among all living baleen whales. 
  <italic>D</italic>
  <sub>N</sub>/
  <italic>d</italic>
  <sub>S</sub> values on transitional branches were used to estimate 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> inactivation records. In the case of aardvark, inactivation of 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> was estimated at ~23.60–28.32 Ma, which is earlier than oldest aardvark fossil record (
  <italic>Orycteropus minutus</italic>, ~19 Ma), suggesting that 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> inactivation may result in degeneration or loss of enamel. Conversely, the inactivation time of 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> estimated in armadillo (~10.18–11.30 Ma) is later than oldest fossil record, suggesting that inactivation of 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> may result from degeneration or loss of enamel in these mammals. Our findings suggested that different mechanisms of degeneration of tooth/enamel might exist among toothless and enamel-less lineages during evolution. Our study further considered that 
  <italic>ACPT</italic> is a novel gene for studying tooth evolution.
 </p>
</abstract>
