<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In eukaryotes, about 40% of the cell’s proteins are either membrane bound or secretory and are therefore directed to the endoplasmic reticulum (ER), where they endure a dynamic folding environment and withstand the rigorous monitoring of quality-control pathways to reach functional maturity [
 <xref rid="B18-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Only correctly folded proteins are transferred to the Golgi apparatus for maturation [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Consequently, mature proteins are targeted to their final destination, they are directed to the plasma membrane or in organelles of the secretory and endocytic compartments, or they are secreted from the cell. When the folding process fails, defective proteins are dislocated across the membrane for cytosolic proteasome degradation through mechanisms known as ERAD (endoplasmic reticulum-associated degradation) [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Both wild type and mutant variants of membrane proteins with complex topologies are prone to ER quality control and degradation. The chloride channel protein CFTR (cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator), characterized as the first integral membrane mammalian ERAD substrate, is the most extensively studied example [
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Given its complex and inefficient folding pathway, the vast majority of newly synthesized wild type CFTR protein is selected for ERAD [
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], as is the epithelial sodium channel, ENaC [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and the thiazide-sensitive NaCl co-transporter (NCC) [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The low folding efficiency is further decreased by mutations as seen in the most frequent mutation of CFTR, (CFTRΔF508), which is sufficient to retain almost all of the protein in the ER and targeted for ERAD, leading to cystic fibrosis [
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. ERAD is a multistep mechanism comprising the recognition, targeting, retranslocation, extraction, ubiquitination, and degradation by the proteasome. In general, the selection of proteins for ERAD involves substrate-specific interactions with molecular chaperones such as shock protein 70 (Hsp70) and 40 (Hsp40) families, and with co-chaperones regulators [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Similar to ENaC and CFTR, our previous studies provided evidence for NKCC2 as a substrate for an ERAD quality control system [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. We have previously showed that similar to CFTR, the vast majority of newly synthetized NKCC2 protein is retained in the ER and destined for ERAD very likely because the protein is unable to fold correctly limiting therefore its export from the ER and its traffic to the cell membrane [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In that pathway, the protein lectin OS9, which interacts with the C-terminal tail of NKCC2, can function to promote the degradation of the co-transporter by the proteasome [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Moreover, melanoma-associated antigen D2 (MAGE-D2), another regulator of NKCC2 biogenesis, recently identified mutated in patients with transient Bartter syndrome by our team, has been also implicated in the ER quality control of NKCC2 [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Indeed, we previously showed that MAGE-D2 mutations lead to a very severe form of antenatal Bartter syndrome by altering the expression of NKCC2 and its structurally related kidney Na-Cl co-transporter NCC [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. With this regard, we suggested that MAGE-D2 is very likely to cooperate with Hsp40, a binding partner of NKCC2 and a key modulator of protein folding and stability to regulate the ERAD of the co-transporter [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Although all these data clearly highlight the fact the ER quality control is a critical step in NKCC2 trafficking to the cell surface, very little is known about the specific molecular determinants involved in this process. In this study, we sought to identify additional factors and partners that target NKCC2 for ER-associated degradation and could help to define more the mechanisms by which NKCC2 is subject to ERAD. Here, we identified STCH and the stress inducible Hsp70 (Hsp72/HSPA1A) as two novel binding partners of NKCC2. The stress-inducible Hsp70 (Hsp72/HSPA1A) is commonly simply named Hsp70. STCH is also known as “microsomal stress 70 protein ATPase core” and “heat shock 70-kDa protein member 13” (HSPA13) [
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. STCH is constitutively expressed in all human cell types and is induced by incubation with calcium, but not by exposure to heat shock [
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In contrast to the extensively studied stress-inducible Hsp70 [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], only few studies have linked STCH to some diseases [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and its major cellular and molecular function has remained poorly defined. Here, we demonstrate that STCH and Hsp70 interact with the immature form of NKCC2 mainly at the ER. Importantly, we provide evidence that STCH and Hsp70 differentially regulate the expression of NKCC2 and its disease-causing mutants. Interestingly, we show that STCH promotes efficient ER associated degradation of NKCC2 in a proteasome and lysosome dependent manner, revealing therefore a new molecular pathway in the regulation of the co-transporter. Taken together, these findings may open new avenues in studying the regulation of NKCC2 quality control and in ultimately identifying new “druggable” targets to prevent and/or treat kidney disorders related to sodium balance in general, and type I Bartter syndrome in particular.
</p>
