<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par32">The current consensus is that ToxB sensitivity is predominantly conferred by a single locus, <italic>Tsc2</italic> (Friesen and Faris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2004</xref>; Abeysekara et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2010</xref>). The wheat reference genome has been constructed in the variety &#8216;Chinese Spring&#8217;, which is insensitive to ToxB. The only other <italic>Ptr</italic> effector sensitivity locus that has been cloned is <italic>Tsn1</italic>, at which recessive alleles confer insensitivity to the effector ToxA. The protein kinase/NBS-LRR gene underlying <italic>Tsn1</italic> is deleted in almost all ToxA-insensitive varieties (Faris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2010</xref>), supporting the hypothesis that the gene underlying <italic>Tsc2</italic> may also be absent in ToxB-insensitive varieties, including &#8216;Chinese Spring&#8217;. To date, a small number of hexaploid wheat varieties have been resequenced, including &#8216;Claire&#8217;, &#8216;Paragon&#8217;, &#8216;Robigus&#8217; (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wheatis.tgac.ac.uk/grassroots-portal/blast">https://wheatis.tgac.ac.uk/grassroots-portal/blast</ext-link>). However, we found none of these varieties to be sensitive to ToxB. Here we investigated the genome sequence of the synthetic hexaploid wheat accession &#8216;W7984&#8217; (Chapman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2015</xref>), previously shown to carry a ToxB-sensitive allele at the <italic>Tsc2</italic> locus (Friesen and Faris <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2004</xref>). While the &#8216;W7984&#8217; contigs have low (55%) genome coverage and have short length (contig N50 6.7&#160;kb), we nevertheless thought it useful to undertake an analysis of the potential gene space in a ToxB-sensitive line. This analysis allowed the identification of additional candidate genes within the ToxB-sensitive line &#8216;W7984&#8217; super-contig that were not present in ToxB-insensitive variety &#8216;Chinese Spring&#8217;, providing potential leads for future analysis. We did not further our analysis of the &#8216;W7984&#8217; genome sequence due to its fragmented nature, and because a number of projects are currently resequencing additional hexaploid bread wheat varieties. These include the 10&#8201;+&#8201;Wheat Genomes Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.10wheatgenomes.com/">https://www.10wheatgenomes.com/</ext-link>), as well as an ongoing project to resequence all eight parents of the &#8216;NIAB Elite MAGIC&#8217; population (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gtr.ukri.org/projects?ref=BB%2FP010741%2F1">https://gtr.ukri.org/projects?ref=BB%2FP010741%2F1</ext-link>). As MAGIC founder &#8216;Xi19&#8217; is ToxB sensitive, we hope that the future completion of the &#8216;Xi19&#8217; genome assembly will aid identification of the genetic variant(s) underlying <italic>Tsc2</italic>.</p>