<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Certain mycoplasmas degrade immunoglobulins (Ig) as a strategy to subvert the host immune system. Based on the available data, mycoplasmas utilize three mechanisms for degrading Ig. The first mechanism is the secretion of IgA protease, as reported in 
 <italic>U. urealyticum</italic> and 
 <italic>U. parvum</italic>, which participates in facilitating microorganism colonization and host immune system evasion on the mucosal surface by proteolytic activity against IgA
 <sub>1</sub> [
 <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0138" ref-type="bibr">138–140</xref>]. The second mechanism is retaining the Ig binding protein and Ig protease (MIB-MIP) system to degrade IgG. For instance, Mmc carries the MIB-MIP system that requires sequential assembly, in which MIB first captures IgG by binding to the Fv region of IgG, and then MIP binds to the MIB-IgG complex to exert serine protease activity, followed by cleavage of the domains between IgG V
 <sub>H</sub> and C
 <sub>H</sub>3, thereby contributing to evasion of host immunity [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. 
 <italic>M. mycoids subsp. mycoids</italic> also expresses the MIB and MIP homologous proteins, whereas 
 <italic>M. hominis, U. urealyticum, U. parvum</italic>, and 
 <italic>U. diversum</italic> contain the MIB-MIP-encoding genes, but whether these genes are involved in the degradation of IgG remains unknown [
 <xref rid="cit0103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. In addition, some mycoplasmas, such as 
 <italic>M. genitalium</italic> and 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic>, lack the MIB-MIP system, but they can express protein M and DUF31-annotated genes in cells and play a role similar to that of the MIB-MIP system [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0141" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>]. The third mechanism of degrading Ig is the expression of cysteine proteases (CysP). 
 <italic>M. synoviae</italic> and 
 <italic>M. gallisepticum</italic> CysP can cleave chicken IgG into Fab and Fc fragments, thereby facilitating their survival in the host [
 <xref rid="cit0142" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>].
</p>
