<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Typically, metal–air batteries (Li or Na) exhibit higher theoretical specific energy than LIBs which can make metal–air battery systems attractive and useful for hybrid and hybrid electric vehicles.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref> Electrochemical power devices based on metal as anode and oxygen as a cathode active material have the highest energy density because the latter is not stored inside the device but is accessible from the environment. The theoretical specific energy of lithium–air batteries (LABs) is comparable with the theoretical specific energy of gasoline.[qv: 5c,7] The air cathode performance limits the cell capacity jeopardizing the commercial success of LAB technology. First, there is the consumption of solvent during the discharge process in the cathode reaction for both alkaline and acidic aqueous electrolytes. Second, there is the incompletion of discharge due to the blockage of pore orifices/openings.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref> Therefore, one of the possible avenues toward LAB performance enhancement is the cathode material architecture,
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> which can keep the active lithium ion and oxygen transport and can be filled with a substantial amount of products of oxygen reduction reaction (ORR) without the pores blockage. Dual pore materials, proposed in a field of gas diffusion electrodes (GDEs) for fuel cells are promising for energy capacity increase.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref> Third, there is the air cathode degradation. Delivering most of the cell energy, the air cathode has the most of the cell voltage drop.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> The accumulation of LiO
 <sub>2</sub> during discharge process yielding a mixed products as well as high voltages on charging caused the decomposition of solvent in parallel to lithium peroxide reduction.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref> The oxygen solubility and rate of diffusion became crucial factors for battery energy capacity. The use of electrolytes with high oxygen solubility and high oxygen diffusivity yields in an enhancement of cathode capacity.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>
</p>
