<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the group I and II elements, sodium metal‐based battery technology has emerged as a potential alternative to lithium‐based batteries owing to its similar electrochemical properties, high natural abundance (sixth most abundant element in earth crusts, 
 <bold>Table</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">
  <bold>1</bold>
 </xref>), and its standard reduction potential (−2.71 V vs SHE) is 230 mV above to lithium (−3.04 V vs SHE) which enables cell to produce large potential and thus store a lot of energy. Moreover, its comparatively high electronegativity in combination with low atomic weight can provide high specific capacity up to ≈1200 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> which can offer economically viable solution compared to Li (3860 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup>) in many applications.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref> The combination of metallic sodium as one reactant for the battery with the inexhaustible source such as oxygen as the other reactant at the cathode is the basic concept of the so‐called Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> battery. The natural abundance of both reactants is a prerequisite for the realization of large‐scale and high‐energy rechargeable batteries with many possible applications including the most challenging for grid‐based technologies.[qv: 6c,15] Although, Li–O
 <sub>2</sub> batteries exhibit the highest specific energy, they encounter major issues related to the low electrical energy efficiency (due to large charge/discharge overpotentials &gt;1 V), insoluble discharge products, and complex side reactions.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref> Contrary to Li–O
 <sub>2</sub> battery, Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> batteries display a better electrical energy efficiency with pure carbon cathode and the discharge product, which is metal superoxide, is more stable when the anode is metallic sodium.[qv: 14a,16b,17] In further advancement, two different kinds of Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> batteries were designed with the main difference lying in the types of electrolytes used, i.e., either nonaqueous electrolytes or the combination of an organic and aqueous electrolytes separated by a membrane in an hybrid architecture for the cell.
</p>
