<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Certainly, there have been tremendous efforts to identify the discharge product in nonaqueous Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> battery, but there has not been any conclusive evidence for any of the discharge product yet. Some reports suggest formation of NaO
 <sub>2</sub> as a sole discharge product whereas, the Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> was also found as discharge product in some studies.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref> In a seminal study published by Bender et al., the authors estimated the free enthalpy of formation (Δ
 <italic>G</italic>) for Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> (−449.7 kJ mol
 <sup>−1</sup>) and NaO
 <sub>2</sub> (−437.5 kJ mol
 <sup>−1</sup>), and found that there is only −12.2 kJ mol
 <sup>−1</sup> difference between the two discharge products. Since this difference is of the same order of magnitude as a hydrogen‐bond, it is extremely difficult to claim with certainty the thermodynamically preferred discharge product.[qv: 19d] It was also demonstrated that crystallite size also affects the formation of discharge product due to competition between surface and bulk energies.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref> Kang et al. showed that Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> is more stable in bulk phase; while NaO
 <sub>2</sub> was found stable at nanoscale level where surface effects dominate. Moreover, the design of the cell also affects the formation of the discharge product as investigated by Bi et al. The authors observed NaO
 <sub>2</sub>‐based discharge product when the cell was built up with stainless‐steel chamber, however, Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> was created when a glass chamber cell was used; while the rest of the conditions such as anode, cathode, and electrolyte remain the same.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref> Since the thermal conductivity of glass (0.8 W m
 <sup>−1</sup> K
 <sup>−1</sup>) is much lower than stainless‐steel (50 W m
 <sup>−1</sup> K
 <sup>−1</sup>), the heat transfer from the reaction site to the chamber could be lead to various temperature distribution affecting the kinetics. But another origin could be that peroxide‐based discharge product usually forms when there is water in the system which might come from air or the decomposition of electrolyte. However, the authors concluded their case it might be due to the leakage in vacuum‐grease‐sealed glass chamber.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>
</p>
