<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In nonaqueous Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> battery systems, considerable efforts have also been given to understand and characterize the discharge product growth and chemical composition by various imaging and spectroscopic techniques.[qv: 6c,21] NaO
 <sub>2</sub> on a discharged electrode was confirmed as product using Raman spectroscopy by Adelhelm's group.[qv: 6c] Typically, NaO
 <sub>2</sub> exhibits a Raman band at 1156 cm
 <sup>−1</sup>, Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> has two Raman bands in range of 700–825 cm
 <sup>−1</sup> whereas, the Raman band at ≈225 cm
 <sup>−1</sup> is ascribed to Na
 <sub>2</sub>O. Ex situ Raman spectra of discharged electrode showed clear bands corresponding to NaO
 <sub>2</sub>; which was also confirmed using ex situ X‐ray diffraction (XRD). Initially, ex situ techniques were utilized to recognize the discharge products and their morphology, however, those methods are not ideal for such sensitive discharge products that might get contaminated from the atmosphere. Therefore, to understand charge–discharge reaction mechanism of aprotic Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cell, in situ characterization techniques are highly desirable. Wang et al. have used CoO/CoP heterostructured nanosheets as bifunctional electrocatalyst to catalyze the charge–discharge reaction. Further, they utilized in situ XRD to recognize the discharge product. The authors found Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>·2H
 <sub>2</sub>O as the major product while NaOH and Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> diffractogram peaks were also observed in XRD.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> Liu et al. used in operando synchrotron radiation powder X‐ray diffraction (SR‐PXD) to probe the effect of electrolyte salt on the growth of crystalline NaO
 <sub>2</sub> and quantify its formation.[qv: 21d] Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cells showed formation of NaO
 <sub>2</sub> confirmed by in situ XRD however, note that the Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cell with NaOTf salt displayed higher discharge capacity than the cell built by using NaPF
 <sub>6</sub> salt. Additionally, the average domain size of NaO
 <sub>2</sub> was found smaller in cell having NaOTf salt (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>4</bold>
 </xref>a,b) which helped in improving the discharge capacity. The authors proposed that the origin is due to a balance between nucleation and growth phenomena of crystallites during the discharge.[qv: 21d]
</p>
