<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Soft X‐ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS), an effective tool to get information related to electronic and chemical structure of products by probing states near Fermi level, was also employed in operando by Xueliang's group.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref> The two most common discharge products (NaO
 <sub>2</sub> and Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>) in Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cell have different electronic configuration as presented in Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c which helps to understand the formation and degradation of discharge product.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref> O K‐edge XAS can be recorded by exciting O 1s electron to unoccupied orbital states of O 2p such as π* and σ* antibonding states.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">25</xref> Peroxide species (O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>2−</sup>) does not have π* transition because it has a completely filled π* orbital therefore, exhibits no associated XAS peak. However, superoxide species (O
 <sup>2−</sup>) has partially filled π* orbital which allows transition of electron to π* orbital and thus shows a corresponding transition peak at 532 eV (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d).
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref> XAS also shows a broad peak at 536 eV which can be ascribed to the transition of electrons to σ* antibonding state.[qv: 23,25a,26] The X‐ray absorption near edge structure (XANES) was also carried out by Landa‐Medrano et al. to understand the discharged state of Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cell and concluded that discharged product is composed from both NaO
 <sub>2</sub> and Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>.[qv: 21e] Further, authors also confirmed the distribution of NaO
 <sub>2</sub>, Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, and organic side products (OSPs) using soft X‐ray transmission microscopy (TXM) which also supported the XANES data. Analysis of spatial distribution of NaO
 <sub>2</sub> and Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> on cubical‐shaped discharged product showed uniform distribution of both NaO
 <sub>2</sub> and Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, however, OSP were distributed at the edges of cubes.
</p>
