<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to TXM, in situ transmission electron microscopy (TEM) and in situ Raman imaging techniques are also employed to study the charge–discharge mechanism in Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cells.[qv: 21a–c] Kwak et al. built a solid state Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> nanobattery using Na metal as anode, carbon nanotube (CNT) as air electrode, and Na
 <sub>2</sub>O as solid electrolyte which was synthesized on the surface of metallic Na for in situ analysis of reaction mechanism.[qv: 21a] During discharge of cell (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e), formation and growth of NaO
 <sub>2</sub> can be easily seen with time using time resolved in situ TEM. The nucleation of NaO
 <sub>2</sub> starts as soon as the discharge process begins and after 48 s, the agglomeration of new formed nuclei occurs on the initial nucleation site. Interestingly, the decomposition and shrinkage of the discharge product was observed on charging the cell (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f). However, some traces of discharge product on electrode surface remained and are associated with the higher overpotentials during charging of the Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cells. Recently, Sun et al. studied extensively the charge mechanism of Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cell using Raman spectroscopy, energy dispersive X‐ray analysis, and XAS.[qv: 21f] Raman spectra of partially charged state of CNT‐PAN (polyacrylonitrile)‐based air electrode did not show any feature related to NaO
 <sub>2</sub>, however, two new Raman bands at 1080 and 1036 cm
 <sup>−1</sup> were observed related to Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> and Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>·2H
 <sub>2</sub>O, respectively.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref> Raman mapping suggested that Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> was mostly distributed at the outer surface of crystals whereas, Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>·2H
 <sub>2</sub>O was found at the inner surface of crystal which was also reported by Landa‐Medrano et al.[qv: 21e] XAS studies of discharged NCNT‐PAN‐based air electrode displayed three absorptions at 532, 532.9, and 534.4 eV ascribed to NaO
 <sub>2</sub>, Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, and Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub>, respectively. Upon charging the same electrode, it was observed that the absorption peak corresponding to Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> first increases (in partial charged electrode) and then reduced (on fully charged condition). On other hand, XAS peak related to Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> continuously grows and features related to NaO
 <sub>2</sub> diminish with charging. It was also observed that major portion of Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> remained undecomposed even when the cell was charged up to 4.5 V. The carbonate‐based remnant, formed by reaction of sodium ions with electrolyte, can be possible origin of high overpotentials during charging of cell.
</p>
