<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These various ex situ and in situ studies provide in‐depth insight about charge and discharge mechanism in nonaqueous Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cell. Although, NaO
 <sub>2</sub> has been broadly accepted as major discharge product, yet, some authors also reported the concomitant formation of Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>·2H
 <sub>2</sub>O and even Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub>, all those species are insoluble in organic electrolytes while during the charge some discharge products disappear, Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> on the contrary is stable even at high potential. This implies that a high energy is needed to decompose it; which results in high charge overpotentials, low round trip efficiency and poor rechargeability. The existing Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> batteries also suffer with poor kinetics owing to the formation of microsized NaO
 <sub>2</sub> cubes as discharged product. Taking the advantage of higher ionic and electronic conductivity of NaO
 <sub>2</sub> than Na
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, Khajehbashi et al. provide a unique solution to improve the kinetics and rate performance of cell.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">28</xref> Since NaO
 <sub>2</sub> is paramagnetic in nature, its combination with high spin electrocatalyst such as Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> can lead the formation of NaO
 <sub>2</sub> nanowires as discharge product. The formed 1D structure improves the electrical transfer in comparison to microsized NaO
 <sub>2</sub> cubes or particles. This distinctive designed cell showed improvement in rate performance, high energy density, low charge overpotential, and good cyclic stability. Additionally, the use of organic electrolytes also has concerns for toxicity, flammability, economic, and environmental impact. Most of nonaqueous Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cell studies employed pure and dry O
 <sub>2</sub> rather than air to prevent undesired parasitic reactions related to the components of ambient air such as water, CO
 <sub>2</sub>, CO, and N
 <sub>2</sub>. One possible strategy could be use of oxygen diffusion membrane that can selectively allow O
 <sub>2</sub> from air while avoiding diffusion of the other components, as the case for aprotic Li–O
 <sub>2</sub> batteries.[qv: 5c,29] However, inclusion of oxygen diffusion membrane in a cell will impede its high rate applications because water vapor can permeate through any membrane.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref> Either way whether use of pure and dry O
 <sub>2</sub> or incorporation of oxygen diffusion membrane will certainly increase the cost of the aprotic Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> cell.
</p>
