<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite these examples, variations in mechanisms of nuclear processes between organisms are well known. For example, nuclear envelope morphology during mitosis is usually either distinctly open or closed but can be semi-closed in some species such as 
 <italic>Schizosaccharomyces japonicus</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. These variations necessitate distinct mechanisms for segregation of nuclear components during division and reassembly. Open mitosis likely arose on multiple occasions, while closed mitosis is probably the ancestral as evidenced by the broader distribution of this mode [
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Further, the mechanisms by which chromosomes are segregated are highly variable. While mitosis nearly exclusively requires a microtubule-based spindle, the location of the spindle anchor varies considerably, being at turns within the nucleus, embedded in the NE or in the cytoplasm [
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Nuclear positioning and mechanotransduction, which in metazoa is mediated by the LINC complex, is also likely divergent; in vascular plants, there is a range of additional systems mediating cytoskeletal connections, while some organisms lack the LINC complex altogether [
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Moreover, the nuclear lamina, a fibrous network residing on the nucleoplasmic surface of the NE, is represented by several apparently diselected for investigation. Givenstinct systems; NMCP/CRWN proteins of plants, lamins in many lineages including metazoa and NUP-1/2 of the kinetoplastida [
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25–29</xref>]. So far, mammalian lamin orthologs have not been detected in yeasts, either experimentally [
 <xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] or 
 <italic>in silico</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. However, in spite of lacking canonical lamins, yeast NPC components, nucleoporins and NE-associated proteins provide a platform for anchoring chromatin to the NE and for events related to gene expression regulation, transcription, mitosis and NE stability [
 <xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31–33</xref>]. Lamins are likely the ancestral lamina proteins while the more restricted plant and kinetoplastid systems appear to be lineage specific and likely later emerging [
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Finally, the kinetochore in kinetoplastids is composed of a distinct set of proteins differentiating these organisms from all other eukaryotes [
 <xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
