<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar cases with increasing areas of the dissolution peaks at higher heating rates can be found in multiple cases of different age-hardening Al alloys and different initial heat treatment states [
 <xref rid="B120-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>,
 <xref rid="B144-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>,
 <xref rid="B149-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. One likely reason for the more severe suppression of precipitation compared to dissolution is the different diffusion distances of these reactions. This can be seen in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f017">Figure 17</xref>, which schematically shows the development of these reactions over time in similarly large microstructure areas. In 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f017">Figure 17</xref>A, showing precipitation from a homogeneously distributed solid solution, the alloying element atoms have to diffuse a certain distance in order to consolidate with one precipitate particle, forming its own crystal structure. This effectively causes the exothermic heat effect of precipitation. In 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f017">Figure 17</xref>B, the dissolution of an existing precipitate only requires the crystal structure of the precipitate to be dissolved in order to provoke the endothermic heat effect. This dissolution of the previously existing precipitate structure requires the alloying elements to diffuse over a much shorter distance; this requires a shorter duration to complete the reaction. Thus, if the time available for the reaction is shortened and we assume that both the dissolution and precipitation of similar phases proceed at very similar or equal diffusion rates, it must be concluded that the kinetic suppression of both types of reactions is similar. However, since the diffusion distances are different, a similar shortening of the reaction time causes a more severe suppression of the precipitation reactions. As a side effect, due to the increased heating or cooling rates (and hence a shortened diffusion time), precipitates tend to become smaller, and this also arises from the reduced diffusion pathways. However, dissolution reactions are also increasingly suppressed with rising heating rates.
</p>
