<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Contributors:</bold> Conceptualisation: CB, TLR, NF, JFM, DR. Data curation: CGW, TLR, SH. Formal analysis: CGW, WW, TLR. Funding acquisition: NF. Investigation: TLR, CL, JFM, AT, SH, XZ. Methodology: CGW, WW, TLR, GM, XZ. Project administration: CM, CB, TLR, GM. Software: CGW, SH. Supervision: CB, TLR, NF. Validation: TLR. Visualisation: CGW, WW, CB, TLR. Writing—original draft preparation: CB, WW, TLR, JFM. Writing—review and editing: CGW, WW, CB, TLR, CL, NF, JFM, AT, GM, DR, XZ, SH, CR, CM.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Funding:</bold> Biogen sponsored this study. Biogen provided funding for medical writing support in the development of this manuscript. Biogen reviewed and provided feedback on the article to the authors.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>
   <bold>Competing interests:</bold> JFM is a consultant and/or investigator for AbbVie, Aclaris, Almirall, Avotres, Biogen, Celgene, Dermavant, EMD Serono, Incyte, Janssen, Leo, Lilly, Merck, Novartis, Pfizer, Sanofi Regeneron, Sun and UCB. WW, SH, AT, CM, GM, CB, NF and TLR are employees and shareholders of Biogen. CGW, XZ, CR and DR are former employees of Biogen. XZ, CR and DR are now employees of Vertex, Genomics Institute of the Novartis Research Foundation and Rheos Medicines, respectively. CL has been an investigator for Biogen. NF serves on the board of OMass Therapeutics.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not required.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Ethics approval:</bold> This study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and other ethical principles described in Title 45, United States Code of Federal Regulations Part 46, Subparts A and B, and approved by the institutional review boards at Brigham and Women’s Hospital (approval ID # 2013P002615/MGH) and Boston University School of Medicine (approval ID # H-34177). Written informed consent was obtained from all participants. The study started on 6 May 2014 and completed on 26 May 2016.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Data availability statement:</bold> Requests for data supporting this manuscript should be submitted to the Biogen Clinical Data Request Portal (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicalresearch.biogen.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://clinicalresearch.biogen.com</ext-link>).
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Supplemental material:</bold> This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.
  </p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
