<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Analysis of the 
 <italic>Tsc2</italic> region was carried out in eleven steps. (1) The W7984 assembly scaffolds (Chapman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2015</xref>) were aligned to the reference ‘Chinese Spring’ genome, RefSeq v1.0 (IWGSC 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>) with MiniMap2 v2.15 (Li 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2018</xref>) using command line options: ‘-I 20G -ax asm5 –secondary = no’. Scaffolds with primary alignments to a region conservatively encompassing the 
 <italic>Tsc2</italic> locus (2B: 21536610..0.27030113 bp) (SAM flags 0 and 16) were extracted from the W7984 assembly and ordered and orientated based on their SAM file coordinates and mapping orientation flags before being joined together as one fragment with each contributing scaffold separated by 100 Ns. (2) The synthetic 2B assembled fragment and the corresponding region of CS42 (chr2B: 21536610..0.27030113 bp) were then repeat masked using Repeatmasker v4.0.8 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.repeatmasker.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.repeatmasker.org</ext-link>) using the command line option: ‘-species Triticum aestivum’. (3) The two repeat masked sequences were aligned using minimap2 v2.16, using the ‘Chinese Spring’ region as reference and with the command line options:‘–cs = long -c -t 20 -K 500 M –Y’. Methods for the liftover of the ‘Chinese Spring’ gene models are further described in Supplementary Text 1. (4) RNA-seq reads (&gt; 8 billion) from BioProject accession numbers PRJDB2496, PRJEB12497, PRJEB25593, PRJEB25639, PRJEB25640, PRJNA213168, PRJNA243835 were obtained from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Short Read Archive (SRA). Further details on the processing of the RNA-seq data and subsequent transcript assembly, gene model and splice junction prediction are listed in Supplementary Text 1. (5) Protein datasets sourced from the genome assemblies of three cereal species (listed in Supplementary Text 1) were aligned to our synthetic 2B fragment from ‘W7984’ that spanned the 
 <italic>Tsc2</italic> region using GenomeThreader v1.7.1 (Gremme et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2005</xref>). Protein alignments were further filtered using the script ‘filter_exonerate.py’ from the ei-annotation suite (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/lucventurini/ei-annotation" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/lucventurini/ei-annotation</ext-link>), using the Portcullis junctions above as externally validated junctions and with further parameters: ‘-minI 20 -maxE 1000 -maxM 5000’, which excluded any hit with terminal introns longer than 1 kbps or internal introns longer than 5 kbps. (6) Transcript reconstruction: Mikado (Venturini et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2018</xref>) leverages transcript assemblies generated by multiple methods to improve transcript reconstruction. Loci were first defined across all input assemblies with each assembled transcript scored based on metrics relating to open reading frame (ORF) and cDNA size, relative position of the ORF within the transcript, un-transcribed region (UTR) length and presence of multiple ORFs. Mikado was used to integrate the Illumina assemblies generated above, as described in further detail in Supplementary Text 1. (7) Gene predictions: the information obtained from steps 1–6 was used for final gene prediction using Augustus (Stanke and Morgenstern 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2005</xref>) as described in Supplementary Text 1. (8) Determining the likelihood of gene presence/absence in ‘Chinese Spring’: Percentage gene presence in ‘Chinese Spring’ (CS) was determined by using BLAST to query the CS chr2B region for each CDS followed by calculating the mean average of the best % CDS presence (nident/qlen * 100) for each transcript. Where there was more than one splice variant present, the transcript with the highest average CDS presence was used to represent the % gene presence in CS. (9) Functional annotation of the synthetic 2B assembled fragment predicted genes was carried out via BLAST queries to the uniprot90 protein database (releaseDate = ‘2019-04-10’ version = ‘2019_03’). For each predicted peptide, the top 20 BLAST hits (based on e-values ≤ 1e−25) were retained. The gene functions were then assigned by hand. Where there was no function known or where BLAST results were &gt; 1e−25, proteins were labelled as uncharacterised. (10) Identifying the corresponding CS gene IDs to the synthetic gene predictions: The coding sequences for each of the transcripts from both the synthetic region and corresponding CS region were extracted using gffread. BLAST was used to query the CS coding sequences with the predicted synthetic coding sequences. The best BLAST results (determined by e-value and bit score) were taken for each query and coding sequences with less than a 90% CDS identity (nident / qlen * 100) were ignored. (11) Circos (Krzywinski et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2009</xref>) plots were constructed using a 10-kb jumping window for both gene and repeat counts. Marker positions within the synthetic assembled region were determined using BLAST. Canonical kmer repeats (&gt; 1) are 91 bp and contain no 
 <italic>N</italic> labelled bases. Candidate genes were identified using the following search terms from the Uniprot functional annotation 'resistance', 'defence' 'disease', 'wall-associated', 'lrr', 'nbs', 'stress' and 'cysteine-rich'.
</p>
