<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For wrought steel products, steel billets are usually heated above 1200 °C with a long soaking time. The effect of Mn diffusion on AF transformation under this condition should be further considered. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01070-f009">Figure 9</xref> shows the microstructures formed with austenitization at 1250 °C for 1–60 min. For a short holding time of one minute, bainite sheaves were still observed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01070-f009">Figure 9</xref>a). As the austenitization holding time increased to 30 min, full acicular ferrite microstructures were formed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01070-f009">Figure 9</xref>c). Grain boundary ferrite was also inhibited, which existed in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01070-f009">Figure 9</xref>a,b. For a long holding time of 60 min, bainite tended to form again, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01070-f009">Figure 9</xref>d. The hardness of the steel samples also varied in accordance with the microstructure evolution, which is presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01070-f010">Figure 10</xref>b. Austenite grains had grown sufficiently large for AF formation after heating to 1250 °C. The transformation behaviors were, thus, mainly influenced by Mn diffusion during different holding times. The calculation results of Mn diffusion at 1250 °C are presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-01070-f010">Figure 10</xref>a. It indicates that the holding time has an influence on Mn diffusion distance. Within one minute, Mn diffusion was not sufficient and MDZ had not developed well, such that the inclusion-induced nucleation effect decreased. As the holding time increased to 30 min, the formation of full AF microstructures indicated that MDZs around inclusions were well developed. However, after 60 min holding, acicular ferrite nucleation ability seemed to exhibit a declining tendency. It is speculated that after saturation of Mn in oxide, the extent of MDZ would decrease due to the continued diffusion of Mn atoms. Further studies and confirmation need to be carried out.
</p>
