<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 26S proteasome is composed of a catalytic core (20S) and regulatory core (19S) (for a review (
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6)</xref>). The 20S forms a barrel-shaped complex composed of 2 rings of 7 beta-subunits, which encode the 3 proteolytic activities (trypsin like, chymotrypsin like, and caspase like). The beta-rings are sandwiched by 2 rings of 7 alpha-subunits. While the importance of the 20S catalytic core alone in the ubiquitin-independent degradation of unstructured proteins has begun to be recognized (
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), the 20S alone has low activity against structured and ubiquitinated proteins, due to the narrow opening of the catalytic core. Access to the proteolytic center is facilitated by the regulatory cores. The 19S regulatory core is composed of a lid and a base. The lid provides the ubiquitin receptor and deubiquitinating enzymes, while the base provides the unfolding activity to unfold structured proteins and push them toward the proteolytic chamber for degradation. In addition to the 19S, other regulatory cores have been described, including the 11S, which unlike the 19S do not provide unfoldase activity and therefore are predicted to be suitable for the degradation of unstructured proteins that do not required unfolding (for a review (
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6)</xref>). Adding to the complexity of proteasome-mediated protein degradation is the large array of transiently proteasome-associated regulatory proteins, the post-translational modifications of several subunits that modulate their activity, and the tissue specific nature of different proteasome species (for a review (
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6)</xref>). In addition, considering that in order to be functional proteasome complexes must be assembled properly, the expression of proteasome assembly factors also impacts the overall activity of the proteasome.
</p>
