<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pituitary adenomas are benign neuroendocrine tumors (
 <xref rid="b1-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="b2-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) that originate from adenohypophyseal cells, and they account for 10–20% of intracranial neoplasms, in epidemiological data from the United States between 2005 and 2009 (
 <xref rid="b3-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="b5-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Pituitary adenomas can be divided into functional and non-functional adenomas according to clinical and biochemical characteristics, like GH-secreting adenoma characterized acromegaly caused by growth hormone abnormal rise (
 <xref rid="b6-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Non-functional pituitary adenomas (NFPAs) are the most common and account for 43% of pituitary adenomas, in epidemiological data from Iceland between 1955 and 2012 (
 <xref rid="b7-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="b8-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). NFPA is often characterized by a lack of symptoms associated with excessive hormone production, like acromegaly and Cushing's disease (
 <xref rid="b6-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Due to the mass effect on surrounding structures, NFPA may cause headaches, visual defects, and/or hypopituitarism (
 <xref rid="b7-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="b9-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Surgical resection is the primary treatment for NFPA, although patients are often left with tumor residue, as the tumor can invade the cavernous sinus or area surrounding the internal carotid artery (
 <xref rid="b10-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="b11-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In total, 12–58% of patients with NFPA with macroadenoma may experience regrowth within 5 years (
 <xref rid="b12-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="b15-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Radiotherapy is often recommended for patients with tumor residue, although its long-term complications, such as visual defects and hypopituitarism, are still of concern (
 <xref rid="b16-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="b17-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Therefore, surgery is still the best option for patients with tumor recurrence. Serum hormone monitoring is an approach used to detect functional pituitary adenoma (
 <xref rid="b18-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>); however, early intervention is difficult to achieve due to the absence of an effective evaluation approach for NFPA. Therefore, research on the molecular mechanisms underlying tumor recurrence and effective prognosis prediction methods is important.
</p>
