<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>First of all, we measured the level of miR-34b-5p in patients with septic AKI and healthy people. Pro-inflammatory factors (TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6), SCr, and BUN were increased in the collected patient serum, confirming sepsis and AKI in these patients. Meanwhile, septic AKI patients showed a higher expression of miR-34b-5p. We then established a LPS-induced cell model of septic AKI to investigate the effect of miR-34b-5p 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. LPS treatment increased the expressions of miR-34b-5p, pro-apoptotic proteins, and pro-inflammatory cytokines in HK-2 cells. miR-34b-5p overexpression further aggravated LPS-induced renal cell apoptosis and inflammation. Serval studies have reported the involvement of miR-34b-5p in inflammation and apoptosis. For instance, miR-34b-5p was induced by p53 to block NF-κB-inducing kinase and therefore inhibit noncanonical NF-κB signaling [
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Overexpression of miR-34b-5p promoted tumor cell apoptosis in serval cancers, including thyroid carcinoma [
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], colorectal cancer [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and oral cancer [
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Also, miR-34b-5p mediated recurrent seizures-induced apoptosis of hippocampal astrocytes [
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Nonetheless, the effect of miR-34b-5p in septic AKI remains obscure to date. In contrast to miR-34b-5p, the 3p strand of miR-34b (miR-34b-3p) impeded NF-κB signaling as well as the release of pro-inflammatory cytokines in sepsis-induced AKI [
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Moreover, miR-34b was detected to alleviate inflammatory response and apoptosis in high glucose-induced HK-2 cells [
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Considering the above evidence, miR-34b may exert differential effects in septic AKI by different strands and further investigation is needed to confirm the promotive effect of miR-34b-5p in septic AKI.
</p>
