<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">While insulin was first identified in mammals, it soon became evident that peptides with sequences similar to insulin can be found in diverse multicellular animals, including many non-vertebrate species such as insects and worms (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). In many of these species, the insulin-like peptides were found through directed efforts to identify peptides with similarity to insulin, but increasingly, they are now being reported from searches of genome sequences. Multiple insulin-like genes have been characterized in the genomes of many non-vertebrate species that are due to lineage-specific gene duplication events (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). A parallel set of duplications of insulin-like genes has also occurred within vertebrates. In addition to the insulin gene (<italic>INS</italic>), nine other genes encoding peptides with similarity to insulin both in their primary sequences and secondary structures have been identified in the human genome, including 2 insulin-like growth factors (<italic>IGF1</italic> and <italic>IGF2</italic>), 4 insulin-like factors (<italic>INSL3</italic>, <italic>INSL4</italic>, <italic>INSL5</italic>, and <italic>INSL6</italic>), and three relaxins (<italic>RLN1</italic>, <italic>RLN2</italic>, and <italic>RLN3</italic>) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). While the relationships among these genes cannot be fully resolved by phylogenetic analysis, due to their short protein lengths, information derived from their locations within the genome has helped to largely resolve the order and timing of the gene duplication events that generated this gene family (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). As summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figure 1A</bold>
</xref>, these studies suggest that the initial gene duplication event that originated this gene family separated an ancestor for the insulin and insulin-like growth factor (<italic>IGF1</italic> and <italic>IGF2</italic>) genes from an ancestor of the insulin-like (<italic>INSL</italic>) and relaxin (<italic>RXN</italic>) genes. This duplication was then followed by a duplication that separated the insulin gene from an ancestor of the insulin-like growth factor (<italic>IGF1</italic> and <italic>IGF2</italic>) genes. Both of these gene duplication events occurred before the two genome duplications that are associated with the origin of vertebrates (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p>