<fig xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="f1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Duplication of insulin-like genes in vertebrates. <bold>(A)</bold> Phylogeny of the insulin supergene family members inferred from their sequences and their genomic locations (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The divergence of the multiple human relaxin (<italic>RLN1</italic>, <italic>RLN2</italic>, and <italic>RLN3</italic>) and insulin-like peptide (<italic>INSL3</italic>, <italic>INSL4</italic>, <italic>INSL5</italic>, and <italic>INSL6</italic>) are indicated by the triangle. Grey box indicates the two genome duplications (2R) that occurred near the origin of vertebrates. <bold>(B)</bold> Origin of the duplicated rodent insulin genes. The <italic>Ins1</italic> gene originated by a retroposition event, shown by the arrow, in the common ancestor of the mouse (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>) and rat (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>), while <italic>Ins2</italic> is located at the locus-of origin (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). <bold>(C)</bold> Duplication of the insulin gene in the frog <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). A pair of insulin genes, <italic>ins.L</italic> and <italic>ins.S</italic>, are found in the <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> genome due to a genome duplication that has occurred since its divergence from the diploid frog <italic>Xenopus tropicalis</italic>. The grey box indicates the genome duplication. <bold>(D)</bold> Summary of the duplications of insulin genes in bony fish (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). A triplication of the insulin gene, yielding <italic>insa</italic>, <italic>insb</italic>, and <italic>insc</italic> genes, occurred in an early ancestor of teleost fish (the order of the duplications events yielding the <italic>insa</italic>, <italic>insb</italic>, and <italic>insc</italic> is unresolved). These duplications occurred at about the same time as the fish-specific genome duplication (the genome duplication is shown as a grey box) &#8211; it is unclear whether if any of the insulin gene duplications were due to the genome duplication. A latter duplication of the <italic>insa</italic> gene in an ancestor of a subset of teleost fish resulted in an <italic>insaa</italic> and an <italic>insab</italic> gene in many fish (e.g., clownfish; <italic>Amphiprion ocellaris</italic>). Insulin genes within some fish genomes also originated <italic>via</italic> retroposition, as indicated by the arrow, with the Northern pike (<italic>Esox lucius</italic>) <italic>insa2</italic> gene being an example.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-12-649255-g001"/></fig>