<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ijms-22-02207-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>STCH alters NKCC2 stability and maturation. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Total NKCC2 protein abundance is reduced by STCH in a dose-dependent fashion. HEK cells were co-transfected with Myc-NKCC2 (0.2 μg/well) and increasing amounts of STCH (0.2–0.6 μg/well) as indicated. NKCC2 proteins were detected by Western blotting with Myc antibody (left panel). 
   <bold>Right panel</bold>, densitometric analysis of total, immature, and mature NKCC2 proteins. Data are expressed as a percentage of control. *, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3). (
   <bold>B</bold>) STCH co-expression decreases the expression of NKCC2 proteins. 
   <bold>Upper panel</bold>, representative immunoblot analysis showing the effect of STCH overexpression on NKCC2 protein abundance in HEK cells. Cells were transfected with Myc-NKCC2 alone (0.2 μg/well) or in the presence of GFP-STCH (0.6 μg/well). 16–18 h post-transfection, total cell lysates were subjected to immunoblot analysis for Myc-NKCC2 and anti-GFP. 
   <bold>Lower panel</bold>, quantitation of steady state mature, immature, and total NKCC2 expression levels with or without STCH co-expression. Data are expressed as a percentage of control 
   <italic>±</italic> SE, *, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.04 (
   <italic>n</italic> = 4); #, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.003 (
   <italic>n</italic> = 4); **, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.002 (
   <italic>n</italic> = 4), versus control. (
   <bold>C</bold>) STCH decreases NKCC2 stability and maturation. 
   <bold>Upper panel</bold>, representative immunoblot showing cycloheximide chase analysis of NKCC2 in the presence or absence of GFP-STCH. 14–16 h post-transfection, HEK cells transiently expressing WT NKCC2 alone or in combination with STCH, were chased for the indicated time after addition of cycloheximide. Total cell lysates were separated by SDS-PAGE and probed by anti-Myc antibodies. 
   <bold>Lower panels,</bold> quantitative analysis of NKCC2 stability and maturation. The density of the mature and immature form of NKCC2 proteins was normalized to the density at time 0. #, *; 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3) versus control. 
   <italic>NS</italic>, a non-specific band illustrating the equal loading of protein extracts.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ijms-22-02207-g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
