<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ijms-22-02207-f007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 7</label>
 <caption>
  <p>STCH and Hsp70 differentially regulate NKCC2 and its disease-causing mutants. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Representative immunoblot of two independent experiments showing opposite effects of STCH and Hsp70 on NKCC2 protein abundance. HEK cells were co-transfected with Myc-NKCC2 (0.1 μg/well) and increasing amounts of GFP-STCH (0.1–0.5 μg/well) or Myc-Hsp70 (0.1–0.5 μg/well) as indicated. NKCC2, Hsp70, and STCH proteins were detected by immunoblotting with anti-Myc and anti-GFP anti-bodies. 
   <bold>Lower panel</bold>, densitometric analysis of total NKCC2 proteins. Data are expressed as a percentage of control (
   <italic>n</italic> = 2). (
   <bold>B</bold>) Hsp70 co-expression increases NKCC2 maturation efficiency. 
   <bold>Upper panel</bold>, two representative immunoblots illustrating the effect of Hsp70 overexpression on NKCC2 protein abundance and maturation in HEK cells. Cells were transfected with Myc-NKCC2 alone (0.1 μg/well) or in the presence of Myc-Hsp70 (0.1–0.5 μg/well). Then, 24–48 h post-transfection, total cell lysates were subjected to immunoblot analysis for NKCC2 and Hsp70 proteins using anti-Myc. 
   <italic>NS</italic>, a non-specific band illustrating the equal loading of protein extracts. 
   <bold>Lower panel</bold>, densitometric analysis of the maturation efficiency (ratio of the mature vs. immature form of NKCC2) of WT NKCC2 in the presence or absence of Hsp70. Data are expressed as percentage of control ± S.E. Each point represents mean ± SE from three independent experiments (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3). *, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus control. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Differential regulation of NKCC2 mutants by STCH and Hsp70. HEK cells were transiently transfected with NKCC2 or BS1 mutants (A508T or Y998X) in the presence or absence of STCH or Hsp70, as indicated. NKCC2, Hsp70, and STCH proteins were detected by immunoblotting with Myc antibody and anti-GFP. 
   <bold>Lower right panel</bold>, densitometric analysis of total NKCC2 proteins. Data are expressed as a percentage of control. * and #, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus control. NKCC2 alone, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 6. NKCC2 with STCH, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 5. NKCC2 with Hsp70, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 5. A508T alone, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 4. A508T with STCH, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3. A508T with Hsp70, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3. Y998X alone, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 6. Y998X with STCH, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3. Y998X with Hsp70, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 4. 
   <bold>Lower left panel</bold>, densitometric analysis of the maturation efficiency (ratio of the mature vs. immature form of NKCC2) of WT NKCC2 (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3), A508T (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3), and Y998X (
   <italic>n</italic> = 4), the presence or absence of Hsp70. Data are expressed as percentage of control ± S.E. *, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus control.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ijms-22-02207-g007" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
