<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig12">
 <label>Figure 12</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Average PAL values for 36 differential DNA repair pathways. (A) calculated using PRJEB11591 dataset for follicular adenoma (FA), follicular cancer (FC), follicular variant of papillary cancer (FV), classical variant of papillary cancer (PC) and their matched adjacent pathologically normal tissues: FA.N, FC.N, FV.N, PC.N, respectively. Pathway name abbreviations: p1 - ATM Pathway, p2 - ATM Pathway Cell Survival, p3 - ATM Pathway G2-Mitosis progression, p4 - Biocarta atm signaling pathway, p5 - Biocarta cell cycle G2M checkpoint pathway, p6 - BRCA1 Pathway, p7 - BRCA1 Pathway Chromatin Remodeling, p8 - BRCA1 Pathway Homologous Recombination Repair, p9 - BRCA1 Pathway Mismatch Repair, p10 - DNA Repair Mechanisms Pathway, p11 - KEGG Base excision repair pathway, p12 - KEGG Fanconi anemia pathway, p13 - KEGG Homologous recombination pathway, p14 - KEGG Mismatch repair pathway, p15 - KEGG Non homologous end joining pathway, p16 - KEGG Nucleotide excision repair pathway, p17 - Mismatch Repair in Eukaryotes Pathway, p18 - NCI ATM pathway, p19 - NCI ATM Pathway (G1 S transition checkpoint), p20 - NCI ATR signaling pathway, p21 - NCI ATR signaling Pathway (Pathway negative regulation of transcription during mitosis via CHEK1), p22 - NCI ATR signaling Pathway (regulation of double strand break repair via homologous recombination), p23 - NCI ATR signaling Pathway (response to G2 M transition DNA damage checkpoint signal), p24 - NCI DNA PK pathway in nonhomologous end joining Pathway (double strand break repair via nonhomologous end joining), p25 - NCI DNA PK pathway in nonhomologous end joining Pathway (V D J recombination), p26 - NCI Fanconi anemia pathway, p27 - NCI Fanconi anemia Pathway (regulation of double strand break repair via homologous recombination), p28 - NCI Fanconi anemia Pathway (Sister Chromatid Exchange Process), p29 - NHEJ mechanisms of DSBs repair effect, p30 - Nucleotide excision repair effect, p31 - p53 Signaling Pathway, p33 - p53 Signaling Pathway Gene Expression DNA Replication and Repair via TP53, p34 - reactome Fanconi Anemia pathway, p36 - Reactome Mismatch repair MMR directed by MSH2, MSH3, MutS beta pathway, p37 - Reactome Mismatch repair MMR directed by MSH2, MSH6, MutS alpha pathway, p38 - Reactome Repair synthesis for gap filling by DNA polymerase in TC NER pathway. (B) Average PAL for tumor tissues and the corresponding adjacent pathologically normal tissues. Each dot represents a "pathway – thyroid tumor type" case, totally 144 cases represented (36 pathways in four tumor types).</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alttext0110">Figure 12</alt-text>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr12" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
