<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Long noncoding RNA (lncRNA) has been identified as important regulator in hypothalamic-pituitary-ovarian axis associated with sheep prolificacy. However, little is known of their expression pattern and potential roles in the pineal gland of sheep. Herein, RNA-Seq was used to detect transcriptome expression pattern in pineal gland between follicular phase (FP) and luteal phase (LP) in 
   <italic>FecB</italic>
   <sup>
    <italic>BB</italic>
   </sup> (MM) and 
   <italic>FecB</italic>
   <sup>++</sup> (ww) STH sheep, respectively, and differentially expressed (DE) lncRNAs and mRNAs associated with reproduction were identified.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par2">Overall, 135 DE lncRNAs and 1360 DE mRNAs in pineal gland between MM and ww sheep were screened. Wherein, 39 DE lncRNAs and 764 DE mRNAs were identified (FP vs LP) in MM sheep, 96 DE lncRNAs and 596 DE mRNAs were identified (FP vs LP) in ww sheep. Moreover, GO and KEGG enrichment analysis indicated that the targets of DE lncRNAs and DE mRNAs were annotated to multiple biological processes such as phototransduction, circadian rhythm, melanogenesis, GSH metabolism and steroid biosynthesis, which directly or indirectly participate in hormone activities to affect sheep reproductive performance. Additionally, co-expression of lncRNAs-mRNAs and the network construction were performed based on correlation analysis, DE lncRNAs can modulate target genes involved in related pathways to affect sheep fecundity. Specifically, 
   <italic>XLOC_466330</italic>, 
   <italic>XLOC_532771</italic>, 
   <italic>XLOC_028449</italic> targeting 
   <italic>RRM2B</italic> and 
   <italic>GSTK1</italic>, 
   <italic>XLOC_391199</italic> targeting 
   <italic>STMN1</italic>, 
   <italic>XLOC_503926</italic> targeting 
   <italic>RAG2</italic>, 
   <italic>XLOC_187711</italic> targeting 
   <italic>DLG4</italic> were included.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par3">All of these differential lncRNAs and mRNAs expression profiles in pineal gland provide a novel resource for elucidating regulatory mechanism underlying STH sheep prolificacy.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Supplementary Information</title>
  <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12863-020-00957-w.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
