<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pattern recognition receptors, including TLR2 and TLR4, are also essential to the MAM-triggered immune response apart from MHC class II. This theory is derived primarily from C3H/HeSnJ (TLR2
 <sup>+</sup>/TLR4
 <sup>+</sup>) and C3H/HeJ (TLR2
 <sup>+</sup>/TLR4
 <sup>−</sup>) mice. After exposure to MAM, C3H/HeSnJ mice induce type 2 cytokines, such as IL-4, IL-6, and IL-10, while C3H/HeJ mice induce type 1 cytokines, such as IL-2, IL-12, TNF-ɑ, and IFN-γ [
 <xref rid="cit0289" ref-type="bibr">289</xref>]. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> experiments have demonstrated that, after injection of live 
 <italic>M. arthritidis</italic>, C3H/HeJ mice are more vulnerable to toxic death than C3H/HeSnJ mice. In the same way, the increased sensitivity of C3H/HeJ mice to severe arthritis caused by live 
 <italic>M. arthritidis</italic> is associated with type 1 cytokine profile, whereas, BALB/c mice (TLR4
 <sup>+</sup>) display a type 2 cytokine profile in response to MAM and develop a mild arthritis caused by 
 <italic>M. arthritidis</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0289" ref-type="bibr">289</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0296" ref-type="bibr">296</xref>], indicating that MAM differentially regulates the cytokine response by unique interaction with TLRs, and this interaction may be associated with the severity of disease induced by 
 <italic>M. arthritidis</italic>. Mu et al. demonstrated that MAM can directly interact with both TLR2 and TLR4, and that TLR4 signaling may downregulate the MAM/TLR2 inflammatory response in the presence of both receptors [
 <xref rid="cit0290" ref-type="bibr">290</xref>]. Blockage of C3H/HeN (TLR2
 <sup>+</sup>/TLR4
 <sup>+</sup>) mice-derived macrophages by TLR4 antibody induces type 1 cytokine response, which releases high amounts of IL-12p40 in response to MAM. Compared with the wild-type C3H/HeN mice, TLR2-knockout C3H/HeN mice release significantly less IL-12 [
 <xref rid="cit0290" ref-type="bibr">290</xref>]. These results suggest that TLR2 is involved in the induction of MAM type 1 cytokine production, and that crosstalk between TLR2 and TLR4 affects the nature of the cytokine response pattern. However, Marina et al. showed that MAM cannot bind to TLR2- and TLR4-transfected cells. Co-transfection of TLR2 or TLR4 with HLA-DR significantly increases MAM binding and subsequent T cell activation compared to cells expressing HLA-DR alone. Anti-HLA-DR antibody can eliminate the upregulation of MAM binding and activity in HLA-DR/TLR transfected cells [
 <xref rid="cit0278" ref-type="bibr">278</xref>], which suggests that co-expression of TLR2 or TLR4 with HLA-DR enhances MAM-induced T cell activation, which is dependent on HLA-DR but completely independent of TLR2 or TLR4.
</p>
