<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most studies on the function of insulin assume that this peptide is of endogenous origin, or from relatively closely related species. Indeed, humans have been treated with insulin from several other mammalian sources (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Recent studies analyzing the sequences of viral genomes have revealed that some viruses that infect vertebrates could be another source of insulin-like peptides, with these peptides having the potential to affect physiology and pathophysiology (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Altindis et al. (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) identified four viruses, which infect fish, whose genomes predict peptides with similarity with insulin, which they called viral insulin-like peptides (VILPs). While these new VILPs sequences share similarity with insulin, differences exist at the regions corresponding to the B-chain/C-peptide and C-peptide/A-chain processing sites (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
  <bold>Figure 2</bold>
 </xref>), thus, and might not generate two-chain molecules (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). However, like the incompletely processed vertebrate insulin sequences described above, the VILPs share the conserved cysteine residues involved in disulphide bridging and are requisite to the maintain the 3D structure (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Some VILPs have been shown to bind to insulin receptors and regulate glucose metabolism in mice (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), indicating that it may function in its proinsulin form, and that they might have a pathophysiological role beneficial to the viruses. Insulin-like molecules are used as toxins by cone snails (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>), thus the use of an insulin-like peptide by a virus in pathophysiology should not be a surprise. It has long been known that full length proinsulin can bind and activate the insulin receptor (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>), as do the single-chain IGF1 and IGF2 hormones with their specific receptors, thus, the incompletely processed insulin molecules encoded by genes in fish, mammals, or viruses could impact physiology or pathophysiology.
</p>
