<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>DSC heating curves of precipitation hardening alloys for a specific initial condition allow us to judge whether dissolution or precipitation reactions are predominant at certain times and temperatures.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Interpretations of DSC heating curves for precipitation-hardening alloys are often found to be challenging. The strong superposition of opposite endo- and exothermic reactions (dissolution/precipitation) make exact interpretations difficult; that is, single DSC peaks, their peak positions and peak areas are not necessarily equal to the maximum intensity of the underlying microstructural reaction.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Nevertheless, as a general rule, it can be derived that: 
   <list list-type="simple">
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Any diffusion-controlled reaction is increasingly suppressed with increasing heating rate. Suppression of precipitation reactions seems to be easier than suppression of dissolution reactions. Consequently, at sufficiently high heating rates, only dissolution reactions will occur.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Any diffusion-controlled reaction shifts to higher temperatures with increasing heating rate. Increasing the heating rate by a factor of 100 typically causes shifts on the order of more than 100 K.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>If the alloy and heating rate specific solvus temperature is exceeded, the total integral of the DSC heating curve reveals the enthalpy level of the initial alloy state. This enthalpy level provides information about the thermal stability of the initial condition, and is higher for more stable conditions.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>For aluminium alloys undergoing different initial heat treatment states such as “as quenched”, T4, T6 or T7, DSC heating curves show severe differences at temperatures below about 300 °C. Above this temperature, the differences are typically small.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>DSC heating is able to identify appropriate temperature ranges for solution treatment, particularly at slow heating rates, since for slower heating the alloy- and heating-rate-specific solvus temperature can be identified. At very slow heating rates, the latter will be close to the equilibrium solvus temperature. Additional experiments can be performed to check whether a complete dissolution of the major alloying elements has been achieved. These additional experiments include isothermal DSC during soaking within the previously identified temperature range.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
