<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par3">To date, three <italic>Ptr</italic> effectors have been described and demonstrated to be pathogenicity factors: ToxA, ToxB and ToxC. Each <italic>Ptr</italic> race is largely differentiated by its expression of one or a combination of these three effectors (Lamari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2003</xref>). ToxA was the first <italic>Ptr</italic> effector to be isolated and is the most well studied (Ballance et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">1989</xref>; Tomas et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">1990</xref>; Faris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">1996</xref>). The majority of <italic>Ptr</italic> isolates worldwide produce ToxA (Friesen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2005</xref>) comprising of races 1, 2, 7 and 8. ToxA triggers necrosis in wheat lines carrying susceptible alleles at the <italic>Tsn1</italic> locus. The mature PtrToxA protein encodes a 13.2&#160;kDa peptide containing a fibronectin type III-like domain (Balance et al. 1996; Ciuffetti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1997</xref>) and includes an arginyl-glycyl-aspartic acid (RGD) motif thought to be important for receptor binding and internalisation into wheat cells (Meinhardt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2002</xref>; Manning et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2008</xref>). The <italic>ToxA</italic> gene is thought to have been transferred to <italic>Ptr</italic> via horizontal gene transfer from another wheat necrotrophic pathogen, <italic>Parastagonospora nodorum</italic> (Friesen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2006</xref>). In wheat, the <italic>Tsn1</italic> locus confers sensitivity to ToxA from both <italic>Ptr</italic> and <italic>P. nodorum</italic>. <italic>Tsn1</italic> encodes a predicted protein containing a nucleotide-binding site leucine-rich repeat (NBS-LRR) domain and a serine/threonine protein kinase (S/TPK) domain (Faris et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2010</xref>). Wheat varieties insensitive to ToxA predominantly carry a complete deletion of <italic>Tsn1</italic>. However, while <italic>Tsn1</italic> is necessary to mediate ToxA recognition, several yeast&#8208;2&#8208;hybrid studies have reported different interacting proteins in the host. Early work showed that ToxA interacts with plastocyanin (Tai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">2007</xref>) and the chloroplast ToxABP1 protein (Manning et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2007</xref>), both of which may promote the induction of reactive oxygen species leading to cell death. More recently ToxA has been demonstrated to interact with the wheat pathogencitiy-related PR-1-5 protein in a highly specific manner (Lu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2014</xref>). ToxA-induced necrosis was enhanced by co-infiltration of both ToxA and PR-1-5 into sensitive wheat lines, but not with a non-interacting PR-1-5<sup>N141A</sup> mutant (Lu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2014</xref>). Therefore, the interaction of ToxA with the PR-1-5 protein appears to play a role in promoting necrosis in <italic>Tsn1</italic>-containing wheat. The role of ToxA as a key tan spot disease determinant has been demonstrated in interactions with many but not all wheat cultivars (Ciuffetti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1997</xref>). Recent work screening Australian wheat lines with a <italic>Ptr</italic> mutant carrying a deletion of <italic>ToxA</italic> has further highlighted the importance of ToxA in tan spot disease (See et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2018</xref>). Disease levels were significantly reduced on about one third of the <italic>Tsn1</italic> wheat lines. The observation that disease levels did not always decrease highlights that while ToxA is a key determinant in tan spot disease, it is not the whole story.</p>