<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In summary, a total of 90 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> on a genome-wide level were identified in potato. The FPKM based expression analysis led to the identification of eighteen candidate 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic>, expressed in a tissue-specific manner [4 in roots (
 <italic>StbZIP</italic> 25, 34, 50, and 89), 8 in tubers (
 <italic>StbZIP</italic> 4, 22, 34, 42, 50, 63, 68, and 89), and four each in mesocarp and endocarp (
 <italic>StbZIP</italic> 20, 34, 42, 50, 87, and 89)]. Differential expression analysis (log 2 FC) under salt stress identified 2 positively (
 <italic>StbZIP</italic> 62 and 66), and 11 negatively (
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> 7, 2, 4, 6, 23, 32, 38, 48, 49, 71, and 75) dysregulated 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic>. In response to water stress, 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> 1, 14, 25, 53, 54, 82 showed positive upregulation (log2FC), while 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> 3, 38, 62, and 71 were regulated negatively. The application of mannitol on potato showed the upregulated of 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> 21 and 66. Heat stress led to positive up-regulation of 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> 1, 5, 7, 8, 15, 17, 23, 30, 37, 41, 62, 66, and 82, while StbZIPs 3, 24, 27, 32, 53 were upregulated but negatively. Likewise, the expression analysis upon treatment with phytohormones led to the identification of 8 
 <italic>StbZIP</italic> that were dysregulated upon ABA treatment [
 <italic>StbZIP</italic> 1, 7, 25, and 88 were positively upregulated, and 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> 8, 21, 24, and 37 were negative downregulated], and three upon IAA treatment (
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> 5, 32, and 59 upregulated positively). No major changes in the expression of 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> were observed upon treatment with IAA and BAP. The phylogenetic analysis, annotation of function, and expression analysis opens the path for further functional validation studies and the use of 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> for engineering potato for tolerance to various abiotic stresses. Similarly, the identified SSRs from candidate 
 <italic>StbZIPs</italic> will also be useful in potato crop improvement programs. The function of these genes can be validated by using either overexpression or gene knockout approaches.
</p>
