<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To unravel the structural and functional features of ATP2 we screened three ATP2 orthologs for heterologous expression in 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. In the present study we succeeded to express the 
 <italic>P. chabaudi</italic> ATP2, PcATP2, a fair paradigm of 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> ATP2 due to its high conservation in 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> species (Figure supplement 1). This expression system was found to be successful in our group for PfATP6 [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], or for a yeast P4-ATPase [
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The production of recombinant malaria MTPs is still very challenging, probably being one of the reasons for what 73% of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic>-encoded MTPs are still considered as putative [
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, the use of recombinant proteins has been pivotal in malaria research, allowing the identification of substrates and inhibitors [
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], providing protein sample for structural studies [
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] or for confirming that PfATP6 is not an artemisinin drug-target [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. One possible reason to explain the difficulty of expressing P-type ATPases encoded by apicomplexan parasites in heterologous hosts is that they contain non-conserved amino acid stretches within the two large cytoplasmic regions connecting TMs 2 and 3 and TMs 4 and 5 (
 <xref rid="F0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>)[
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], enclosing a high density of positively-charged and asparagine residues, a potential handicap for heterologous expression due to endoplasmic reticulum (ER) retention [
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. These extensions are absent in many other P-type ATPases, and as judged by a 3D model of PcATP2 based on the recent cryo-EM structure of Drs2p and ATP8A1 [
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], they contain a large proportion of non-structured regions (
 <xref rid="F0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>). Confocal microscopy images of 
 <italic>S. cerevisie</italic> expressing PcATP2-GFP-BAD alone or co-expressed with PcCdc50B-His indicates that PcATP2-GFP-BAD is located in intracellular compartments (Figure supplement 7). This could indicate a possible retention of PcATP2-GFP-BAD in the ER as observed before in mammalian cell-lines for other P4-ATPase mutants presenting some folding defect [
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Logically, in the absence of organellar markers we are unable to make further conclusions about the exact localization of PcATP2. Interestingly, a recent study showed that the 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> K
 <sup>+</sup> channel PfKch2 is also expressed in internal compartments of 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> but it is active after detergent solubilization and purification[
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. 
</p>
