<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The PcATP2/PcCdc50B complex produced in 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> showed ATPase activity in detergent micelles, in the presence of the aminophospholipids POPS and POPE (
 <xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>), thus demonstrating the capacity of PcATP2 to recognize these two phospholipids. Two amino acid clusters determine, at least in part, the lipid head-group selectivity of P4-ATPases [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In PcATP2, these clusters correspond to residues Gln65 and Leu66 in TM1, and Ala455 and Asn456 in TM4 (Figure supplement 1). PS-selective P4-ATPases normally contain polar residues at these two clusters (two Gln at the corresponding positions 65 and 66 of PcATP2, and two Asn at the equivalent positions 455 and 456 of PcATP2) that establish H-bonds with PS. In contrast, PC-selective P4-ATPases usually contain non-polar residues at the same positions [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. PcATP2 has one polar residue at each cluster (Figure supplement 1) that, in principle, could be sufficient to coordinate PS, PE, and even PC. Although in the ATPase assays it is possible the presence of a non-functional fraction of PcATP2, it is also possible that PcATP2 is partially autoinhibited using a mechanism similar to its yeast homolog Drs2p [
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In fact, the GFAFS motif at the C-terminus of Drs2p involved in enzyme’s autoinhibition by interacting with the nucleotide binding site [
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], is also well conserved in PcATP2 (as well in the other 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> ATP2 orthologs), although the length of the C-terminal of the 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> sequences is ∼60 amino acid shorter (Supplementary Figure 5). In addition, PcATP2 shares with Drs2p a few residues in a ⁠short loop region of the nucleotide domain (residues 698–704 in Drs2p, see Supplementary Figure 5) that directly interact with the GFAFS motif to stabilize the autoinhibitory conformation [
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Moreover, and as suggested by the presence of a PI4P binding motif on its amino acid sequence (Figure supplement 6)[
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], PcATP2 is also upregulated by this lipid as we observed a statistically significant increase of POPS and POPE-stimulated ATPase activity in the presence of PI4P (
 <xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). PI4P is an essential lipid for the malaria parasite since the inhibition of PI4P synthesis in the Golgi apparatus completely blocks the late steps of the intraerythrocytic cycle of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> by interfering with membrane biogenesis around the developing merozoites [
 <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. PI4P is found at the plasma membrane and at the Golgi apparatus in all stages of the erythrocytic cycle [
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Interestingly, the 
 <italic>P. berghei</italic> ATP2 was also localized at the interface parasite/host [
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. It will be relevant to investigate if the lethal effects as a result of depleting PI4P or suppressing ATP2 are somehow connected and linked to the biogenesis of the parasite’s membranes.
</p>
