<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The present study provides insights into the study of H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> roles with the DNA methylation and their impact on the physiological adaptation to stress factors. The data has high reliability and accuracy. The mapping efficiency obtained is comparable to the informed in other WGBS studies [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Likewise, the proportion of the three-methylation context in the transgenic tobaccos was similar to those reported in other plant models as soybean [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], barrel clover [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], maize [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], tomato [
 <xref rid="B52-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], burberry [
 <xref rid="B48-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and watermelon [
 <xref rid="B49-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], among others. In all these studies, the higher methylation levels were located in the CG context. Similar results in the distribution of DmC in different genomic regions were obtained by Manoharlal et al. In their study presents a methylome-transcriptomic profile of tobacco after gibberellin A3 application [
 <xref rid="B53-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The high number of methylations in intergenic regions may be in part due to the high content of repetitive sequences in the tobacco genome. Thus, part of the differences in the proportion of hypermethylated and hypomethylated regions in their study and ours may be due to the variable of treatment and the transgene, respectively.
</p>
