<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To realize the application of SCEs in lithium metal batteries, multiple indexes of SCEs need to be evaluated, including thickness, ionic conductivity, electrochemical window, mechanical strength, potential reaction with electrode, thermal behavior, environmentally benign, and cost.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0089" ref-type="ref">89</xref> The ionic conductivity of SCEs membrane falls in the range from 10
 <sup>−4</sup> to 10
 <sup>−5</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> and the electrochemical window is enhanced above 5 V versus Li
 <sup>+</sup>/Li for the incorporation of ceramic filler. A skillful design of PEO
 <sub>8</sub>‐LiTFSI‐10 wt% LLZTO (“ceramic‐in‐polymer”) and PEO‐LLZTO‐PEG‐60 wt% LiTFSI (“polymer‐in‐ceramic”) shows good flexibility, wide electrochemical window (up to 5.0 V versus Li/Li
 <sup>+</sup>), and relatively high ionic conductivity (above 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at 55 °C).
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">44</xref> The PEO‐LLZTO composite electrolytes show strong stability with lithium anode and ability to effectively suppress lithium dendrite growth. The LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/Li cells using both types of composite electrolytes also present good cycle and rate performance. Besides, Li et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0097" ref-type="ref">97</xref> applied a 3D fiber‐network‐reinforced bicontinuous composite solid electrolyte in dendrite‐free lithium metal batteries. The LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/Li cell with this LATP/PAN‐PEO/LiTFSI membrane presents an initial discharge capacity of 144 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> with a tremendously stable coulombic efficiency of 99.5% ± 0.5% over 100 cycles at 60 °C, indicating outstanding interfacial stability between electrolyte and Li metal. The strong mechanical strength and enhanced stability on interface promote the suppression of lithium dendrite by constructing the LATP/PAN‐reinforced 3D bicontinuous structure. Furthermore, owing to the reinforced oxidation stability, the SCEs are suitable to match high‐voltage cathode materials, such as LiNi
 <italic>
  <sub>x</sub>
 </italic>Co
 <italic>
  <sub>y</sub>
 </italic>Mn
 <sub>1−</sub>
 <italic>
  <sub>x</sub>
 </italic>
 <sub>−</sub>
 <italic>
  <sub>y</sub>
 </italic>O
 <sub>2</sub>, LiCoO
 <sub>2</sub>, and LiMn
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0089" ref-type="ref">89</xref> For example, Park et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">45</xref> fabricated a flexible solid electrolyte film using poly(1,4‐butylene adipate) and LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> hybridized with Li
 <sup>+</sup>‐conductive LAGP. The as‐assembled all‐solid‐state Li/LiNi
 <sub>0.6</sub>Co
 <sub>0.2</sub>Mn
 <sub>0.2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> cell using this flexible solid electrolyte film delivers an initial discharge capacity of 169.5 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> with good capacity retention at 55 °C. Zhang et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">51</xref> also found that the chemical structure of PVDF backbones changed greatly with presence of Li
 <sub>6.75</sub>La
 <sub>3</sub>Zr
 <sub>1.75</sub>Ta
 <sub>0.25</sub>O
 <sub>12</sub> in PVDF/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> SCEs, which results in significantly improved ionic conductivity and mechanical strength. The results of experiments and first‐principle calculations indicated that the chemical dehydrofluorination of the PVDF skeleton would occur owing to the Lewis base formed by the complex between the La atom of LLZTO and N atom or C=O group of solvent molecules. The as‐prepared LiCoO
 <sub>2</sub>/Li cell with 10% LLZTO/PVDF composite membrane shows high coulombic efficiency and capacity retention of 98% after 120 cycles and high discharge capacity of 130 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> at 4 C at 25 °C. The SCEs show excellent compatibility with both cathode and silicon anode.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0121" ref-type="ref">121</xref> The as‐assembled Si/LLZO‐PPC/Li cells exhibit 2520, 2260, 1902, and 1342 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> at 0.1 C, 0.2 C, 0.5 C, and 1 C, respectively. The Si in full Si/LFP cell shows a specific capacity of 2296 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup>, which remains 82.6% after 100 cycles at room temperature and 0.1 C.
</p>
