<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7895974</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">21426</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-21426-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterising open chromatin in chick embryos identifies cis-regulatory elements important for paraxial mesoderm formation and axis extension</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>Gi Fay</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4009-6540</contrib-id><name><surname>Folkes</surname><given-names>Leighton</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weldon</surname><given-names>Shannon A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9419-7374</contrib-id><name><surname>Maniou</surname><given-names>Eirini</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Heredia</surname><given-names>Victor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5760-011X</contrib-id><name><surname>Godden</surname><given-names>Alice M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Ruth M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9289-0263</contrib-id><name><surname>Sauka-Spengler</surname><given-names>Tatjana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4335-8577</contrib-id><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>Grant N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4644-1816</contrib-id><name><surname>Moxon</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4577-4240</contrib-id><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nsterberg</surname><given-names>Andrea E.</given-names></name><address><email>a.munsterberg@uea.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8273.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1092 7967</institution-id><institution>School of Biological Sciences, Cell and Developmental Biology, </institution><institution>University of East Anglia, Norwich Research Park, </institution></institution-wrap>Norwich, UK </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4991.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8948</institution-id><institution>MRC Weatherall Institute of Molecular Medicine, Radcliffe Department of Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Oxford, </institution></institution-wrap>Oxford, UK </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.83440.3b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000121901201</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Developmental Biology and Cancer, </institution><institution>University College London, Great Ormond Street Hospital, Institute of Child Health, </institution></institution-wrap>London, UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>1157</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Somites arising from paraxial mesoderm are a hallmark of the segmented vertebrate body plan. They form sequentially during axis extension and generate musculoskeletal cell lineages. How paraxial mesoderm becomes regionalised along the axis and how this correlates with dynamic changes of chromatin accessibility and the transcriptome remains unknown. Here, we report a spatiotemporal series of ATAC-seq and RNA-seq along the chick embryonic axis. Footprint analysis shows differential coverage of binding sites for several key transcription factors, including CDX2, LEF1 and members of <italic>HOX</italic> clusters. Associating accessible chromatin with nearby expressed genes identifies cis-regulatory elements (CRE) for <italic>TCF15</italic> and <italic>MEOX1</italic>. We determine their spatiotemporal activity and evolutionary conservation in Xenopus and human. Epigenome silencing of endogenous CREs disrupts <italic>TCF15</italic> and <italic>MEOX1</italic> gene expression and recapitulates phenotypic abnormalities of anterior&#x02013;posterior axis extension. Our integrated approach allows dissection of paraxial mesoderm regulatory circuits in vivo and has implications for investigating gene regulatory networks.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">How paraxial mesoderm formation and differentiation is regulated is unclear. Here, the authors identify accessible chromatin and gene expression signatures that define different stages of paraxial mesoderm development in the chick and identify CREs important for vertebrate anterior&#x02013;posterior axis formation.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Cell biology</kwd><kwd>Developmental biology</kwd><kwd>Genetics</kwd><kwd>Molecular biology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">The partitioning of paraxial mesoderm into repetitive segments, termed somites, is a key feature of vertebrate embryos. During amniote gastrulation, mesoderm cells emerge from the primitive streak and migrate in characteristic trajectories to generate axial, paraxial and lateral plate mesoderm (LPM)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Paraxial mesoderm is located on either side of the midline tissues, neural tube and notochord. As the body axis extends, it consecutively generates pairs of somites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> epithelial spheres comprised of multipotent progenitor cells. In response to extrinsic signals, epithelial somites (ES) undergo dramatic morphogenetic changes and reorganise<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. On the ventral side cells undergo an epithelial to mesenchymal transition (EMT) to form the sclerotome, while on the dorsal side the cells in the dermomyotome remain epithelial. From the dermomyotome edges cells transition to form the myotome, in-between the sclerotome and dermomyotome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Concomitantly with somite morphogenesis, the differentiation potential of somite cells becomes more restricted, with cells eventually becoming specified towards the lineages of the musculoskeletal system, including chondrocytes and skeletal muscle cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Overall the process of somitogenesis generates a spatiotemporal gradient of differentiation within the paraxial mesoderm along the embryonic body axis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">In addition, somite derivatives exhibit regional differences depending on their anterior&#x02013;posterior axial position. Regional identity is already established at gastrula stages and is controlled by the stepwise transcriptional activation of <italic>HOX</italic> gene expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. For example, members of the <italic>HOXB</italic> cluster are first activated in a temporal colinear fashion in prospective paraxial mesoderm, prior to ingression through the primitive streak<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. The colinear activation of <italic>HOX</italic> genes culminates in nested expression domains within the paraxial mesoderm, thereby conferring regional identity along the axis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. To determine the structural features associated with colinear expression, the 3D organisation of <italic>HOX</italic> clusters has been investigated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. It has also been shown that posterior Wnt signalling and CDX transcription factors (TFs) are important regulators of the &#x0201c;trunk&#x0201d; <italic>HOX</italic> genes in the centre of <italic>HOX</italic> clusters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. In particular, CDX2 is essential for axial elongation with mutations leading to posterior truncations associated with changes in <italic>HOX</italic> expression domains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. CDX activity is associated with histone acetylation and mediates chromatin accessibility of regulatory elements<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Superimposed onto regional differences is the control of cell identity and differentiation, and several well-characterised TFs serve as markers for musculoskeletal lineages. Chondrogenic cells express <italic>PAX1</italic>, <italic>PAX9</italic> and <italic>SOX9</italic> and dermomyotomal myogenic progenitors are characterised by PAX3 and PAX7. Committed myoblasts express <italic>MYF5</italic> and <italic>MYOD</italic>, while MYOG and KLHL31 are markers for differentiated myocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Other transcriptional regulators that are important in paraxial mesoderm include TCF15 (Paraxis), a bHLH TF required for somite epithelialization;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> CDX (Caudal), which is necessary for axis elongation;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and MEOX1, which is involved in somite morphogenesis, patterning and differentiation, particularly of sclerotome-derived structures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. In human, mutations of MEOX1 are found in patients with Klippel-Feil Syndrome, which is associated with fusion and numerical defects in the cervical spine as well as scoliosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Whilst the sequence of marker gene expression in paraxial mesoderm is well defined<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, the epigenetic and genomic mechanisms that control these transcriptional programmes remain largely unknown. The identification of enhancers has improved through high-throughput sequencing assays and comparative genomic analysis, however, experimental validation of enhancer activity remains challenging. In this study, we assay spatiotemporal changes in both gene expression signatures and accessible chromatin that occur in differentiating paraxial mesoderm along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis. We define differentially accessible chromatin regions within <italic>HOX</italic> genes that are associated with regional identities. Footprint analysis shows differential occupancy and coverage of binding sites along the axis for several TFs, including HOXA10, HOXA11, CDX2, LEF1 and RARA. CDX2 and LEF1 are both involved in similar processes during axis extention. However, network analysis shows that CDX2 and LEF1 footprints are associated with different expressed genes and there is little overlap in the genes they interact with. Correlating accessible chromatin with nearby expressed genes identifies cis-regulatory elements (CREs). We focus here on enhancers located upstream of <italic>TCF15</italic> and <italic>MEOX1</italic> and validate these in vivo, using electroporation of fluorescent reporters into gastrula-stage chick embryos. Time-lapse imaging shows the onset of enhancer activation in paraxial mesoderm and mutation of candidate TF motifs or epigenome modification leads to loss of gene expression and phenotypic changes. The <italic>MEOX1</italic> CRE is evolutionary conserved in amphibians and human. Altogether our data characterises the accessible chromatin and gene expression landscapes in paraxial mesoderm, at different stages of somite maturation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Transcriptional profiling of developing paraxial mesoderm</title><p id="Par6">To conduct genome-wide transcriptome analysis during the spatiotemporal transition of paraxial mesoderm, we collected presomitic mesoderm (PSM), ES, maturing somites (MS) and differentiated somites (DS) from Hamburger&#x02013;Hamilton stage 14 (HH14)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> chick embryos in triplicate (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). At this stage, the four most posterior somites are epithelial, but in MS cells in the ventral part undergo EMT, the dorsal dermomyotome lip forms in the epaxial domain adjacent to the neural tube and myogenic cells begin to transition into the early myotome. Differentiating somites are compartmentalised, with a primary myotome beneath the dermomyotome and a sclerotome ventrally<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Transcriptional profiling of developing somites.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Schematic representation of HH14 chick embryo with presomitic mesoderm (PSM), epithelial somite (ES), maturing somite (MS) and differentiated somite (DS) dissected for RNA-seq and ATAC-seq, in triplicate. <bold>b</bold>&#x02013;<bold>d</bold> Volcano plots showing enriched genes (log fold change &#x0003e;1.5) comparing PSM with ES, ES with MS, and MS with DS. <bold>e</bold> Heat map showing GO terms associated with PSM or DS enriched genes. <bold>f</bold> Clusters of highly correlated genes identified for myoblast differentiation and&#x000a0;cartilage condensation. <bold>g</bold> Wnt, FGF and retinoic acid (RA) signalling pathways are shown in heat map. <bold>h</bold> Heat map showing k-means linear enrichment clustering across PSM, ES, MS and DS. <bold>i</bold> Dimension reduction algorithm t-SNE used to map top genes in each cluster determined by k-means. <bold>j</bold> Cluster B and <bold>k</bold> Cluster I are shown with some genes labelled to identify key transcription factors and signalling components.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_Fig1_HTML" id="d32e547"/></fig></p><p id="Par7">After harvesting, tissues were processed for RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Principal component analysis (PCA) showed that PSM, ES, MS and DS samples cluster into three distinct groups, with MS and DS samples clustering together (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a</xref>). Differential gene expression analysis comparing PSM and ES revealed up-regulation of 713 genes and down-regulation of 583 genes; comparing ES and MS revealed up-regulation of 145 genes and down-regulation of 155 genes; and comparing MS and DS revealed up-regulation of 53 genes and down-regulation of 26 genes. Comparisons between samples confirmed that the greatest differential was observed between PSM and any of the somite samples, followed by the number of differentially expressed genes between the most recently formed epithelial somites&#x000a0;and the most differentiated somites (ES versus DS) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1b</xref>).</p><p id="Par8">Previously described somite TFs, such as <italic>NKX6-2</italic>, <italic>NKX3-2</italic>, <italic>ZIC1</italic> and <italic>HES5</italic>, were highly enriched in ES compared to PSM, as well as the gap junction protein GJA5 (Connexin 40). Marker genes important for myogenic (<italic>MyoD1</italic> and <italic>ACTC1</italic>) and chondrogenic (<italic>PAX9</italic>, <italic>FST</italic>) cell lineages were enriched in MS compared to ES. Markers for chondrocytes (Chondromodulin, <italic>CNMD</italic>), bone homoeostasis (Leucine-rich repeat containing, <italic>LRRC17</italic>) and cartilage (Keratan sulfate proteoglycan Keratocan, <italic>KERA</italic>) were identified (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b&#x02013;d</xref>). Myogenin (<italic>MYOG</italic>), a TF involved in differentiation of muscle fibres was enriched in DS compared to MS, as was expression of the neural crest cell (NCC) TF <italic>SOX10</italic>, due to NCCs migrating through the rostral half of differentiating somites. Other genes highly expressed in DS include the serine protease inhibitor, <italic>SPINK5</italic>; Troponin T2 (<italic>TNNT2</italic>) and Myomesin (<italic>MYOM1</italic>), encoding important proteins of the contractile sarcomere; <italic>CREBRF</italic>, a negative regulator of the endoplasmic reticulum stress response and <italic>ZFPM2</italic>, a zinc finger TF (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>).</p><p id="Par9">The functional clustering by gene ontology (GO) terms of differentially expressed genes across all four stages reveals enrichment of biological processes involved in cell differentiation in DS and MS versus PSM and ES samples. Genes involved in myoblast differentiation, cartilage condensation, skeletal muscle fibre development and myotube cell development were up-regulated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>). Further analysis of genes involved in positive regulation of myoblast differentiation shows that they display dynamic expression across the four groups and include classic markers for different stages of paraxial mesoderm differentiation. Genes differentially expressed in somite compartments include in the dermomyotome and myotome: <italic>MYF5</italic>, <italic>MYF6</italic>&#x000a0;and <italic>MYOD1</italic>, whilst <italic>MYOG</italic> and <italic>KLHL31</italic> are associated with differentiated muscle. Classic markers for chondrogenesis and cartilage condensation within the sclerotome include the TFs, SOX9, PAX1 and PAX9, and the extracellular matrix component, COL11A1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>). Functional clustering of differentially expressed genes also reveals enrichment of signalling pathways involved in anterior&#x02013;posterior pattern formation. These pathways are expressed in an opposing fashion and include the FGF and Wnt signalling pathways, which are highly expressed in PSM and the retinoic acid (RA) signalling pathway, which is more highly expressed in somite samples (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1g</xref>).</p><p id="Par10">We next used weighted gene co-expression network analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> to characterise gene co-expression clusters across the four samples of the top 400 differentially expressed genes. We identified 11 clusters based on k-means clustering. The heat map shows the gene expression levels across the four different samples, and the t-SNE plot illustrates the dimensional distribution of the different clusters (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1h, i</xref>). The top three GO terms associated with clusters include &#x0201c;anatomical structure morphogenesis&#x0201d; (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1f</xref>). Clusters B and I comprise genes that increase or decrease in expression across the spatiotemporal series, from PSM to DS (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>j, k). Cluster I features components of FGF (<italic>FGF13</italic>, <italic>FGF7</italic>, <italic>FGF10</italic>, <italic>FGF18</italic>, <italic>SPRY1</italic>), BMP (<italic>BMP2</italic>, <italic>BMP4</italic>, <italic>BMPER</italic>, <italic>NOG</italic>) and WNT (<italic>WNT8C</italic>, <italic>WNT5B</italic>) signalling pathways in addition to classic PSM markers such as <italic>MESP2</italic>, <italic>RIPPLY2</italic>, <italic>MSGN1</italic> and <italic>MESP1</italic>, known to be important for somitogenesis. Cluster B features markers of cellular differentiation programmes such as <italic>ZIC1</italic>, <italic>ZIC4</italic>, <italic>MEOX1</italic>, <italic>TCF15</italic> and include the myogenic regulatory factors, <italic>MYOD1</italic> and <italic>MYF5</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Profiling chromatin accessibility dynamics in paraxial mesoderm along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis</title><p id="Par11">To identify genomic regulatory elements that control paraxial mesoderm and somite differentiation programmes, we used Assay for Transposase-Accessible Chromatin using sequencing (ATAC-seq)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. This mapped chromatin accessibility across the paraxial mesoderm along the axis, in PSM, ES, MS and DS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Distinct chromatin accessibility profiles were evident at different stages of somite development, indicative of the dynamic progression of axial development. PCA showed a high reproducibility between biological triplicates of each sample type (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2g&#x02013;l</xref>), but dynamic changes in chromatin accessibility were observed between them. Using DiffBind<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> we show the densities and clustering of differentially accessible chromatin regions (peak sites) (rows), as well as the sample clustering (columns) for PSM against ES, ES against MS, and MS against DS. We identified differentially accessible peaks with differential densities showing clusters of peak sites with distinct patterns of chromatin accessibility levels for PSM against ES (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>), ES against MS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), and MS against DS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). MA plots show the highest number of differentially accessible peaks is evident when comparing PSM and ES (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;27,692, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). The number of differentially accessible peaks is lower when comparing ES against MS, and MS against DS (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4670, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1965, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e, f</xref>). This is in line with the transcriptome data, where greater differences were seen between PSM and ES compared to the differences observed between different stages of somite maturation.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Genome-wide profile of chromatin accessibility dynamics during somite development.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Correlation heat maps of accessible chromatin regions (ATAC-seq peak sites) comparing PSM and ES, <bold>b</bold> ES and MS and <bold>c</bold> MS and DS. <bold>d</bold> MA plots of significantly differential peak sites (pink) comparing PSM with ES, <bold>e</bold> ES with MS and <bold>f</bold> MS with DS. <bold>g</bold> Bar plot showing proportions of total genome sequence of peaks in PSM, ES, MS and DS (error bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;SD). Nearly half of all peaks lie within 50&#x02009;kb of the promoter and TSS and half are in intergenic and intron regions. <bold>h</bold> GO terms associated with enriched transcription factors in DS compared to PSM. For enriched GO terms, <italic>p</italic> values were obtained from a modified Fisher exact test. <bold>i</bold> Number of transcription factor binding sites identified within 2&#x02009;kb upstream of differentially expressed genes in DS compared to PSM. <bold>j</bold> Motif enrichment analysis performed using Homer. Transcription factor motifs identified as enriched in PSM accessible regions and <bold>k</bold> in DS accessible regions. Percentage indicates increase of motifs identified in either PSM or DS for each motif.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_Fig2_HTML" id="d32e830"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">The genomic distribution of accessible regions was similar in all four sample types: between 39 and 42% were in intergenic regions, ~10% were in introns, 0.5% in exons, 2&#x02013;3% at the TSS and 43&#x02013;46% of accessible regions were within a 50&#x02009;kb region upstream of the TSS which includes the promoter (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2g</xref>). Functional terms associated with predicted TF binding sites that were enriched in accessible peaks in DS compared to PSM included cell fate specification and terms related to morphogenesis or skeletal myogenesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2h</xref>). Consistent with the latter, we identified &#x0003e;200 binding sites for myogenin (MYOG) that are located within accessible chromatin peaks within 2&#x02009;kb of genes differentially expressed in DS, where skeletal muscle differentiation occurs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2i</xref>). The MYOG motif is well conserved across mouse and human, thus is likely to be conserved across avian species also. Other enriched TFs identified include bHLH proteins (TCF12, ASCL1, ARNT1), of which TCF12 is expressed in skeletal muscle, is part of the canonical Wnt pathway and implicated as a transcriptional repressor in colorectal cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Specificity proteins, Sp1, Sp2, Sp3 and Sp8, are zinc finger proteins known to interact with bHLH proteins such as MyoD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Furthermore, Sp8 is a downstream effector of the Wnt pathway in neuromesodermal stem cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Sp1 and Sp3 bind to GC and GT boxes and can be displaced from these sequences by KLF16, a Kr&#x000fc;ppel-like zinc finger protein for which binding sites are also enriched and increased in PSM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2j</xref>). Other zinc finger TFs include ZNF384, ZNF740 and ZNF263, which are involved in the regulation of cell differentiation genes including those relevant to musculoskeletal development. For example, ZNF384 regulates extracellular matrix genes MMP1, MMP3, MMP7 and COL1A1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>; ZNF740 recruits the chromatin regulator HDAC1 to the SMAD4-DNA complex and prevents the recruitment of the transcriptional activators CREBBP and EP300<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. The binding motifs for ZNF740 are increased in PSM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2j</xref>). ZNF263 is involved in adipogenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The Ewing sarcoma RNA binding protein 1 (EWSR1) regulates gene expression, cell signalling, RNA processing and transport. Chimeric proteins resulting from chromosomal translocations between EWSR1 and various TF genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> are involved in tumorigenesis such as Ewing sarcoma in bones and bone connective tissues. Furthermore, the binding motif for retinoic acid receptors (RXRA) is enriched. Motif enrichment analysis of differentially accessible regions identified additional TF motifs that were increased in number in either PSM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2j</xref>) or DS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2k</xref>). In PSM this included motifs for TFAP2C/TFAP2B and ZIC3/ZIC4, whose functions in axial elongation and/or musculoskeletal development are currently unknown. In DS, this included motifs for FOXO1/FOXO3 and MEOX1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Identification of differential footprints during somite development</title><p id="Par13">To further interrogate the accessible chromatin landscape during somite development, we used HINT-ATAC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> to discover differential TF footprints in regions of open chromatin identified in PSM, ES, MS or DS. Initially we focussed on the CDX2 TF, which is a readout for posterior WNT signalling and has been implicated in defining neuromesodermal progenitors (NMP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. CDX2 is essential for axial elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and is highly expressed in the PSM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). Consistent with high levels of WNT signalling activity in the PSM, HINT-ATAC identified a greater number of CDX2 footprints in open chromatin in this region when compared to ES, MS and DS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b&#x02013;d</xref>). Similarly, LEF1, a transcriptional effector for canonical WNT signalling, is highly expressed in the PSM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e</xref>). LEF1 is also expressed in somites, where it becomes restricted to the myotome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. We identified a greater number of LEF1 footprints in the PSM when compared to any of the somite samples, consistent with the more restricted expression of <italic>LEF1</italic> in the latter (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3f&#x02013;h</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Differential footprints identified for CDX2 and LEF1 during somite development.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Gene expression from mRNA-seq (error bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;SEM, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) for <italic>CDX2</italic>. <bold>b</bold> Tn5 insertion frequency across all accessible regions containing at least one CDX2 motif, at nucleotide resolution in PSM, ES, MS and DS reveals the presence of a footprint centred on the CDX2 motif. Differential footprinting for CDX2 motif comparing PSM and ES, <bold>c</bold> PSM and MS, and <bold>d</bold> PSM and DS. <bold>e</bold> Gene expression for <italic>LEF1</italic> (error bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;SEM, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). <bold>f</bold> Differential footprinting for LEF1 motif comparing PSM and ES, <bold>g</bold> PSM and MS, and <bold>h</bold> PSM and DS. Similar GO terms for genes associated with (<bold>i</bold>) CDX2 footprints and (<bold>j</bold>) LEF1 footprints. For enriched GO terms, <italic>p</italic> values were obtained from a modified Fisher exact test. <bold>k</bold>, <bold>l</bold> Protein&#x02013;protein network analysis using STRING database. Interactions between genes identified with (<bold>k</bold>) CDX2 and (<bold>l</bold>) LEF1 footprints in an accessible region, within 10&#x02009;kb upstream or downstream. Highlighted in red are genes correlated with embryonic morphogenesis in CDX2-associated genes and animal organ morphogenesis in LEF1-associated genes. <bold>m</bold> Venn diagram of CDX2-associated genes against LEF1-associated genes identified only four common genes&#x02014;<italic>Msgn1</italic>, <italic>Sall4</italic>, <italic>Spry1</italic> and <italic>DDC</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_Fig3_HTML" id="d32e1011"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">A reverse coverage pattern was observed for TFs involved in somite differentiation. For PAX3, an important TF that regulates the myogenic programme and highly expressed during somite development, HINT-ATAC revealed an increase in the number of PAX3 footprints in ES open chromatin when compared to PSM. The number of PAX3 footprints increased further in MS and DS when compared to PSM (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3a&#x02013;d</xref>) suggesting there is a greater coverage of bound sites in maturing and differentiating somites consistent with the role of PAX3 in myogenic progenitors in the dermomyotome. Another key somite TF, TWIST2 (also known as DERMO1), is important for EMT during somitogenesis. <italic>TWIST2</italic> was highly expressed in the paraxial mesoderm and expression increased as somites differentiate (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2e</xref>). The number of genome-wide TWIST2 footprints were very similar in PSM and ES (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2f</xref>), however, the number of footprints increased in MS and DS when compared to PSM (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2g, h</xref>). Retinoic acid receptor alpha (RARA) is a nuclear receptor, which acts as a transcriptional repressor in absence of ligand but a transcriptional activator when RA is present (see<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup> for review). RARA is highly expressed in somites (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3i</xref>). HINT-ATAC identified fewer RARA footprints in PSM compared to MS and DS (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3k, l</xref>).</p><p id="Par15">The inverse coverage patterns identified for CDX2, LEF1 versus RARA were consistent with the opposing expression patterns for WNT and RA pathway components within paraxial mesoderm along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1g</xref>). To further dissect the roles of CDX2 and LEF1 in posterior axis elongation we determined genes associated with either CDX2 or LEF1 footprints in accessible regions within 10&#x02009;kb upstream or downstream. GO terms for these genes were overlapping and include: anatomical structure morphogenesis/development, metabolic process and regulation, for both CDX2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3i</xref>) and LEF1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3j</xref>). We next performed STRING analysis, using a threshold of 0.700, to obtain a protein&#x02013;protein interaction (PPI) map for genes identified with CDX2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3k</xref>) or LEF1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3l</xref>) footprints in accessible regions within 10&#x02009;kb. This revealed genes with strong PPIs, including those associated with enriched biological processes such as embryonic morphogenesis for CDX2 and animal organ morphogenesis for LEF1. LEF1 footprints correlated with CDX2 consistent with CDX2 being regulated by the Wnt signalling pathway. Furthermore, the phenotypical traits of CDX2 mouse mutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> include posterior truncations reminiscent of those found in LEF1/TCF1 double mutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Thus, to explore whether CDX2 and LEF1 could regulate similar genes, we examined all differentially up-regulated genes in the PSM and investigated whether there are associated CDX2 and LEF1 footprints. We found 101 genes with a CDX2 footprint and 42 genes with a LEF1 footprint within 10&#x02009;kb up- or downstream. Surprisingly, when comparing these sets of genes only four genes&#x02014;<italic>Msgn1</italic>, <italic>Sall4</italic>, <italic>Spry1 and DDC</italic>&#x02014;were associated with both CDX2 and LEF1 footprints, and the majority of correlated genes was different (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3m</xref>). Our analysis suggests that CDX2 and LEF1 are part of discrete networks acting in parallel to govern similar processes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3k, l</xref>), but they regulate different sets of genes important for these processes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Chromatin accessibility and differential TF footprints in the HoxA cluster</title><p id="Par16">We next examined the <italic>HOXA</italic> cluster, one of four <italic>HOX</italic> gene clusters imposing regional identity along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis via the colinear expression of its members. We determined how <italic>HOXA</italic> gene expression patterns correlate with the accessible chromatin landscape. RNA sequencing determined expression levels of each member of the <italic>HOXA</italic> cluster in PSM, ES, MS and DS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Their expression reflects the organisation of the genes within the cluster: the more 3&#x02032; located genes have a more anterior expression boundary compared to the genes located more 5&#x02032;, which are restricted more posteriorly. Accordingly, we find that <italic>HOXA1, HOXA2</italic>, <italic>HOXA3</italic>, <italic>HOXA4</italic>, <italic>HOXA5</italic> and <italic>HOXA6</italic> are all highly expressed across the length of the axis: in PSM, ES, MS and DS. A small decrease in <italic>HOXA7</italic> gene expression was detected in DS, with more pronounced decreases observed for <italic>HOXA9</italic>, <italic>HOXA10</italic>, <italic>HOXA11</italic> and <italic>HOXA13</italic>, which were also reduced progressively in MS and ES. The colinear pattern of gene expression correlated with differentially accessible chromatin within the <italic>HOXA</italic> cluster (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). Accessible chromatin regions were seen in PSM, ES, MS and DS near the promoter of <italic>HOXA1, HOXA2, HOXA3, HOXA4, HOXA5</italic> and <italic>HOXA6</italic>. However accessible chromatin for HOXA7 was reduced at the promoter in DS compared to PSM, ES and MS. For the more posteriorly restricted genes, <italic>HOXA9</italic>, <italic>HOXA10</italic>, <italic>HOXA11</italic> and <italic>HOXA1</italic>3 accessible chromatin peaks were reduced in ES, MS and DS compared to PSM, which correlated with their reduced expression. We demonstrate the same relationship between gene expression and chromatin accessibility along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis across the <italic>HOXB</italic>, <italic>HOXC</italic> and <italic>HOXD</italic> clusters (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4a&#x02013;f</xref>). In the <italic>HOXA</italic> cluster we identified footprints within accessible regions in intergenic regions. Notably, we identified footprints for TFs involved in patterning along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis, including footprints for CDX1/2, LEF1 and for members of the HOX clusters themselves, as well as for some of the TFs with enriched motifs in accessible regions such as RXRA, TFAP2B/C, SP1, SP2, ZIC1/3, FOXO1/4, ZNF263 (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2i&#x02013;k</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). To investigate the impact of the dynamic changes in <italic>HOXA</italic> gene expression along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis, we next explored the number of TF footprints for HOXA2, HOXA5, HOXA10 and HOX11 in PSM and DS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c&#x02013;f</xref>). We observed the same number of footprints for HOXA2 and HOXA5 when comparing PSM and DS, however, a significant decrease in coverage was detected for HOXA10 and HOXA11 footprints in anterior DS compared to PSM. This reveals a strong association between gene expression levels along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis and the genome-wide coverage of HOXA binding sites.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Chromatin accessibility and differential footprints for HoxA cluster.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Gene expression from mRNA-seq for HoxA cluster (error bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;SEM, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) in paraxial mesoderm regions. <bold>b</bold> Genome browser views of ATAC-seq profile across the <italic>HoxA</italic> cluster. ATAC and RNA profiles are shown in green for PSM, in blue for ES, in yellow for MS and in red for DS. Grey boxes indicate intergenic accessible regions and transcription factor footprints identified within those regions. Genome-wide differential footprinting for (<bold>c</bold>) HoxA2, (<bold>d</bold>) HoxA5, (<bold>e</bold>) HoxA10 and (<bold>f</bold>) HoxA11 between PSM and DS.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_Fig4_HTML" id="d32e1222"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Identification and validation of paraxial mesoderm-specific regulatory elements</title><p id="Par17">Next, we identified differentially accessible peaks that were open specifically in PSM or in somite samples, ES, MS or DS. We hypothesise that these could represent putative enhancers. For example, differentially accessible peaks identified flanking genes highly expressed in the PSM included a peak downstream of <italic>MSGN1</italic> present in PSM and not in ES, MS or DS (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5a</xref>); a peak downstream of <italic>WNT8C</italic> and a peak within intron 1 present in PSM but not in somite tissues (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5b</xref>); and peaks upstream and downstream of <italic>FGF4</italic> present in PSM and low or absent in&#x000a0;somite tissues (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5c</xref>). For the muscle differentiation gene, <italic>MYOG</italic>, a peak was identified upstream of the gene in DS, MS and interestingly also in ES, but not in PSM (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5d</xref>). For <italic>RDH10</italic>, which is associated with RA signalling and highly expressed in somites but less abundant in PSM, a differential peak was identified in ES, MS and DS and not in PSM (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5e</xref>). Similarly for <italic>GREM1</italic>, an antagonist of BMP signalling highly expressed in developing somites, a differential peak present in all somite samples but not in PSM was identified downstream of the gene (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5f</xref>). In most cases, chromatin accessibility correlated well with gene expression and in some cases it preceded transcript detection, e.g. <italic>MYOG</italic>, or high level gene expression, e.g. <italic>TCF15</italic> (see below). The putative enhancer activities of these differential peaks remain to be confirmed experimentally, however, we validated and further characterised some somite enhancers by embryo electroporation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. We focussed on <italic>TCF15</italic> and the homeodomain TF, <italic>MEOX1</italic>, two classic markers identified in the group of genes that increased during the differentiation of paraxial mesoderm and somites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1j</xref>, Cluster B). In addition, MEOX1 binding motifs were increased in accessible regions in DS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2k</xref>).</p><p id="Par18">We examined open chromatin peaks flanking the <italic>TCF15</italic> and <italic>MEOX1</italic> genes within 10&#x02009;kb. Identified peaks representing candidate CREs were cloned upstream of the herpes simplex virus thymidine kinase (HSV-TK) minimal promoter, driving expression of a stable Citrine reporter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Electroporation targeted the prospective mesoderm of gastrula-stage HH3&#x02009;+&#x02009;embryos (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5g, h</xref>), and reporter gene expression profiles were monitored until HH11.</p><p id="Par19">We identified two CREs upstream of <italic>TCF15</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). These sequences are chick specific and the fluorescent enhancer reporters showed spatially restricted activities. For the first element, <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1 (1500&#x02009;bp) we observed activity in the PSM, in all somites and in the notochord (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). The second element, <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 (700&#x02009;bp), showed activity mainly in PSM and somites, as well as some activity in LPM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c, e</xref>). In situ hybridisation showed that expression of <italic>TCF15</italic> was restricted to PSM and somites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5g</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> and it is not clear at present why <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1 and <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 drive ectopic reporter expression also in the notochord and LPM. To address the possibility that repressive elements that limit enhancer activity were missing, we combined <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1 and <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2. This reporter led to Citrine expression in PSM and LPM, however not in the notochord (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>) suggesting that the region comprising <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 may include elements that suppress ectopic expression in the notochord. It is possible that the TCF15 Enh-2 drives another gene in LPM cells, alternatively accumulation of Citrine in LPM may reveal sites of <italic>TCF15</italic> expression that cannot be detected by in situ hybridisation. Time-lapse movies for <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 show Citrine fluorescence was first detected in a HH6 embryo in prospective paraxial mesoderm cells as they converge towards the midline (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5i</xref> and Supplementary Movie&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Strong signal was seen in the first somite at HH7 and subsequently in all newly formed somites, as well as the PSM and prospective paraxial mesoderm cells.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Identification of a regulatory element for TCF15.</title><p><bold>a</bold> ATAC-seq profile at the <italic>TCF15</italic> locus. Grey boxes indicate putative enhancers identified (<italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1 and <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2). RARA footprint identified within <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2. Mutant reporter sequence for <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 RARA mutant. <bold>b</bold>
<italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15/15) and <bold>c</bold>
<italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9/9) reporter expression in presomitic mesoderm (Psm), notochord (Nc), somites (So) and lateral plate mesoderm (Lpm). <bold>d</bold> Combined <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1/Enh-2 reporter expression (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9/9). <bold>e</bold> Transverse sections of embryo in <bold>c</bold> immunostained for Citrine showing <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 expression in somites and lateral plate mesoderm, white dashed line in <bold>c</bold> indicates location of section, representative of (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4/4). Nuclei stained with DAPI (blue). <bold>f</bold>
<italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 Citrine reporter with RARA binding site mutation displays lack of expression in somites (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/6). Epigenome engineering using dCas9-Krab with (<bold>g</bold>) control scrambled sgRNAs resulted in no change (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8/9) and (<bold>h</bold>) sgRNAs targeting endogenous RARA binding site led to loss of <italic>TCF15</italic> expression (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/8) as shown by wholemount in situ hybridisation. <bold>i</bold> Percentage of embryos with normal (blue) or reduced (orange) <italic>TCF15</italic> in situ expression after electroporation of control scrambled sgRNA with dCas9-Krab or sgRNAs targeting <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 RARA binding site with dCas9-Krab. All scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;500&#x02009;&#x003bc;m except for <bold>e</bold> scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_Fig5_HTML" id="d32e1477"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Because reporter activity observed with <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 reflected more closely the spatial gene expression pattern of <italic>TCF15</italic>, we next sought to identify TFs that regulate this element. HINT-ATAC identified a TF footprint for RARA within <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2, consistent with RARA expression and coverage of binding sites across the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3i&#x02013;l</xref>). Introducing mutations into the RARA binding site (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>) led to loss of reporter activity in the embryo (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>), suggesting RARA is indeed required to activate <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2. To determine the potential significance of RARA-mediated regulation of <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 in vivo, we used the conventional dCas9-KRAB repressor to modify the endogenous enhancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. Two CRISPR guide RNAs (gRNA) designed to target the repressor to the <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 RARA binding site, or scrambled gRNA controls were electroporated together with dCas9-KRAB (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5g, h</xref>). Detection of <italic>TCF15</italic> expression by in situ showed that epigenome modification of the endogenous <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2 alone led to reduced <italic>TCF15</italic> expression and concomitantly a drastic truncation of the body axis (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x02009;6/8 embryos), whilst control scrambled gRNAs/dCas9-KRAB repressor has no effect on <italic>TCF15</italic> expression or axis elongation (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8/9 embryos, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5g&#x02013;i</xref>). These data suggest that RA signalling is crucial for <italic>TCF15</italic> gene expression as RARA binding site perturbation led to loss of reporter activity and epigenome editing of the endogenous CRE resulted in disruption of anterior&#x02013;posterior axis elongation. This is consistent with mouse mutants of <italic>TCF15</italic> or mutants affecting RA signalling, in which ES formation is disrupted and the embryonic axis truncated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Whilst it has been shown that Wnt signalling is important for <italic>TCF15</italic> expression in early somites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>, there is no evidence of direct regulatory interactions. However, we cannot exclude the possibility that Wnt signalling, via LEF/&#x003b2;-catenin, contributes to <italic>TCF15</italic> expression potentially via a different CRE, which alone is not sufficient. It is also worth noting that <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1 and Enh-2 are not conserved across mammalian species.</p><p id="Par21">MEOX1 is an important TF for early somite patterning and differentiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. We examined accessible regions of chromatin and selected an element that is evolutionary conserved at sequence level between chicken, Zebra finch, American alligator, Chinese softshell turtle, lizard, human and&#x000a0;mouse. We identified one candidate CRE of 1095&#x02009;kb, ~1&#x02009;kb upstream of <italic>MEOX1</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). This element displayed enhancer activity, with expression of the Citrine reporter restricted to the PSM and all somites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b, c</xref>). Expression in PSM was unexpected as chromatin was not accessible at that stage. It is possible that the citrine reporter is missing some repressive elements that are present endogenously. Time-lapse movies reveal Citrine fluorescence, which was first detected in the prospective paraxial mesoderm cells of a HH6 embryo. At HH7 signal was detected in the first somite and subsequently in all newly formed somites, as well as the PSM and prospective paraxial mesoderm cells. Overall the pattern was consistent with <italic>MEOX1</italic> gene expression detected in situ (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d, f</xref> and Supplementary Movie&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">2</xref>). We identified two TF footprints within the enhancer, one for FOXO1 and one for ZIC3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). We next determined their requirement for the activation of fluorescent reporter expression. Mutation of FOXO1 or ZIC3 sites individually had no effect and reporter activity was still observed (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6a, b</xref>). However, mutation of both sites led to loss of reporter activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6e</xref>). This suggests both TFs are able to activate this CRE and either FOXO1 or ZIC3 alone is sufficient. To investigate the significance of this element, we modified the endogenous enhancer using four gRNAs to target the dCas9-KRAB repressor to the <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh. Scrambled gRNAs with dCas9-KRAB were used as control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6f&#x02013;h</xref>). Using a probe to detect <italic>MEOX1</italic> transcripts showed that <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh enhancer perturbation led to loss of gene expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6g</xref>) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9/11). This was confirmed by RT-qPCR (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6j</xref>) and suggests the element is required.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Identification of a regulatory element for MEOX1.</title><p><bold>a</bold> ATAC-seq profile at <italic>MEOX1</italic> locus. Grey box indicates putative enhancer identified. FOXO1 and ZIC3 footprints identified within enhancer element. Mutant reporter sequence for <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh ZIC/FOXO mutant. <bold>b</bold>
<italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh reporter expression in presomitic mesoderm (Psm) and in somites (So) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13/13). <bold>c</bold> Transverse sections of embryo in <bold>b</bold> immunostained for Citrine showing <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh expression in epithelial somites, white dashed line in <bold>b</bold> indicates location of section, representative of (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4/4). Nuclei stained with DAPI (blue). <bold>d</bold> Still photographs from a time-lapse movie of <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh with the primitive streak (Ps) indicated. Fluorescent activity first observed in prospective paraxial mesoderm (Pm) at HH6 and continuous expression in the presomitic mesoderm (Psm) at HH7 prior to expression in somites (So) at HH8 and HH10 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3/3). <bold>e</bold> FOXO1 and ZIC3 binding site mutation in <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh Citrine reporter led to loss of expression (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/7). Epigenome engineering using dCas9-Krab with (<bold>f</bold>) control scrambled sgRNAs resulted in no change (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/7) and (<bold>g</bold>) sgRNAs targeting endogenous FOXO1 and ZIC3 binding sites led to loss of <italic>MEOX1</italic> expression (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9/11) as shown by wholemount in situ hybridisation. <bold>h</bold> Percentage of embryos with normal (blue) or reduced (orange) MEOX1 expression after injection and electroporation of control scrambled sgRNA with dCas9-Krab or sgRNAs targeting MEOX1 Enh FOXO1 and ZIC3 binding sites with dCas9-Krab. <bold>i</bold> Protein&#x02013;protein network analysis using STRING database. Interactions between genes identified with MEOX1 footprints in an accessible region, within 10&#x02009;kb upstream or downstream. Highlighted in red are genes correlated with anatomical structural development based on GO analysis. <bold>j</bold> RT-qPCR on somites dissected from wild-type (WT) embryos, or embryos electroporated with control scrambled sgRNA and dCas9-Krab, or sgRNAs targeting <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh FOXO1 and ZIC3 binding sites with dCas9-Krab. Statistical significance was determined by a two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test. **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.001&#x02013;0.01; *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01&#x02013;0.1; ns not significant. All scale bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;500&#x02009;&#x003bc;m except for <bold>c</bold> scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_Fig6_HTML" id="d32e1731"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">To determine the genes potentially regulated by MEOX1 in paraxial mesoderm, we identified accessible chromatin regions within 10&#x02009;kb of an expressed gene, which comprised a MEOX1 footprint (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6c&#x02013;e</xref>). STRING analysis of these putative MEOX1 regulated genes revealed PPI networks including genes enriched with the GO term anatomical structural development, and also included components of signalling pathways, such as Wnt and TGFbeta (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6i</xref>). To confirm that some of these genes are involved in mediating the function of MEOX1 in paraxial mesoderm, we used RT-qPCR to assess their expression in normal and epigenome edited somites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6j</xref>). First, we showed that <italic>MEOX1</italic> expression in wild-type somites was unaffected after introducing control gRNAs together with the dCAS9-KRAB repressor. However, electroporation of sgRNAs targeting the dCAS9-KRAB repressor to the <italic>MEOX1</italic> enhancer led to suppression of <italic>MEOX1</italic>. Expression of the closely related <italic>MEOX2</italic> gene was not affected, similarly <italic>PAX3</italic> expression remained unchanged. Next, we assessed a number of genes involved in chondrogenesis and setting up the polarity of the sclerotome. Epigenome editing of the endogenous <italic>MEOX1</italic> enhancer led to down-regulation of <italic>Uncx4.1</italic>, <italic>TBX18</italic>, <italic>FAT4</italic> and <italic>TGFb2</italic>, which are all associated with a MEOX1 footprint, indicating that they could be direct targets. Expression of <italic>NKX3-2</italic>, which is not associated with a MEOX1 footprint within 10&#x02009;kb up- or downstream of the gene, was also inhibited after negative regulation of <italic>MEOX1</italic> by epigenome editing of the <italic>MEOX1</italic> enhancer.</p><p id="Par23">As the <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh is highly conserved amongst amniote taxa&#x02014;birds, reptiles and mammals (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>), we next asked whether the homologous mammalian sequences are active in chick. We found that a human <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh, isolated from HeLa cells, was able to drive Citrine expression in somites. Activity was also detected in LPM and PSM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). The human <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh sequence included conserved FOXO1 and ZIC3 binding sites and mutation of both sites led to loss of reporter activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>). Therefore, we propose transcriptional regulation of the <italic>MEOX1</italic> enhancer is highly conserved in human and chick, with FOXO1 and ZIC3 binding sites required for enhancer activity. Interestingly, the <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh sequence was not found in fish or amphibians (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). However, when we injected the chick <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh reporter into one cell of <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> embryos at the 2-cell stage, we observed Citrine fluorescence in the paraxial mesoderm of early neurula stages (NF stage 14), where it overlapped with <italic>MYOD</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7b</xref>). At NF stage 25, Citrine expression was detected in mesoderm and by NF stage 33 and stage 42 Citrine was visible in elongated muscle fibres, which are somite derived (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7d</xref>). The <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh with mutations in the FOXO1 and ZIC3 binding sites showed no activity (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7a</xref>). This suggests that in amphibians the <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh can be activated by the same regulatory mechanism, even though the CRE is not conserved in the same location in the <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> genome.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Evolutionary conservation of MEOX1 enhancer and regulatory mechanism across vertebrates.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Genomic alignment of chick <italic>MEOX1</italic> locus, ~10&#x02009;kb. Exons and introns are represented by blue boxes and lines. Clustered green vertical lines indicate sequence identity between different species. The height of bars indicates extent of conservation in different species: turkey, zebra finch, American alligator, Chinese softshell turtle, Lizard, Human, Mouse, Zebrafish, Nile tilapia, Stickleback, Medaka, Fugu, Lamprey and <italic>Xenopus tropicalis</italic>, as indicated on the left of each row. Grey shading indicates the location of the <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh. <bold>b</bold> Expression of the conserved human <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh reporter in presomitic mesoderm, somites and lateral plate mesoderm in a HH9 chick embryo (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/6). <bold>c</bold> Mutation of FOXO1 and ZIC3 binding sites in the human <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh Citrine reporter led to loss of expression (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4/4). <bold>d</bold> Chick <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh reporter injected into 1 cell of a <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> 2-cell embryo shows Citrine expression in paraxial mesoderm (St14,&#x000a0;white arrowheads (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/6)) and in early somites and elongated myofibres (St25 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/6), St33 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/6), St42 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6/6), white arrowheads). A-P anterior&#x02013;posterior. Scale bars for <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> =&#x02009;500&#x02009;&#x003bc;m, <bold>d</bold> scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;250&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_Fig7_HTML" id="d32e1918"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par24">Extension of the vertebrate body axis is driven by the addition of new segments at the posterior end of the embryo. During avian gastrulation, presumptive paraxial mesoderm cells ingress through the primitive streak and their early migration patterns can be observed directly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. It has been shown that <italic>HOX</italic> genes are activated in a temporal colinear fashion, just prior to ingression when the precursors are still located in the epiblast<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, thus regional identity along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis is acquired at gastrula stages. Paraxial mesoderm formation continues as the main body axis forms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> and cells are added from a bi-potential population of NMP cells found in the tailbud. In response to high levels of Wnt3a and CDX family members, these progenitors commit to mesoderm fates and give rise to neck, trunk and tail structures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">Here we provide detailed molecular profiles of paraxial mesoderm of cranial and trunk regions by RNA-seq and ATAC-seq<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Using samples from along the axis we identify differential gene expression signatures consistent with axial patterning and differentiation, including the appearance of chondrogenic and myogenic markers in more anterior differentiating somites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c, d, j</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. We show that genes correlated with cell fate specification and muscle development are enriched in differentiating somites, and that the TF binding motifs found upstream of differentially expressed genes include the motif for myogenin consistent with its role in myogenic differentiation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2h, i</xref>). Components of signalling pathways involved in anterior&#x02013;posterior axis patterning are also differentially expressed, such as FGF, Wnt and RA pathways (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1g, k</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> and the motif for RXRA is enriched in differentiating somites (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2i</xref>). Furthermore, we uncover genome-wide dynamic changes in chromatin accessibility across the spatiotemporal series. Using HINT-ATAC, an improved method to predict TF binding sites with footprints<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, we show differential coverage of several binding sites along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis, including sites for RARA and LEF1, transcriptional effectors of the RA and Wnt pathways. Furthermore, we identify differential footprints for CDX2, a readout for WNT and a TF required for axial elongation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a&#x02013;h</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3j&#x02013;l</xref>). The observed coverage patterns correlate well with gene expression and with the known functions of RA and Wnt signalling in anterior&#x02013;posterior axis patterning. Interestingly, despite their similar function in posterior axis extension our network analysis shows that CDX2 and LEF1 footprints are largely correlated with different genes. Only four genes are associated with both CDX2 and LEF1 footprints, suggesting that posteriorization driven by Wnt signalling involves at least two parallel acting protein&#x02013;protein networks. Three of the shared proteins identified&#x02014;Msgn1, Sall4 and Spry1 are involved in posteriorization. Msgn1 is a master regulator of paraxial mesoderm formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>, Sall4 has recently been shown to regulate the balance between NMP maintenance and differention<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>, and Spry1 is a negative feedback regulator of FGF signalling. Our finding that Msgn1, Sall4 and Spry1 are associated with both CDX2 and LEF1 footprints in PSM is highly consistent with their known function. The fourth shared gene, DCC (aromatic amino acid decarboxylase) is mutated in a rare genetic disorder and deficiency of this enzyme affects neurotransmitter production. However, its possible role in axial elongation, indicated here, was previously not recognised.</p><p id="Par26">Notably, we observe the greatest differences between presegmented mesoderm and all somite samples, for both chromatin accessibility and differential gene expression signatures, compared to the differences seen between somites at different stages of maturation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d&#x02013;f</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1b</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2d&#x02013;f</xref>). This emphasises the complexity of the segmentation process, when paraxial mesoderm cells transition to generate somites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par27">We also observe differential chromatin accessibility along the anterior&#x02013;posterior axis in the <italic>HOXA</italic> cluster (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>) as well as differential expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>) and footprints (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c&#x02013;f</xref>) of <italic>HOXA</italic> family members. These patterns are also detected in <italic>HOXB</italic>, <italic>HOXC</italic> and <italic>HOXD</italic> clusters (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>) consistent with the role of <italic>HOX</italic> clusters in the regionalisation of axial structures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. As mentioned above, CDX2 is highly expressed in PSM and has greater coverage of footprints in PSM compared to somite samples (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a&#x02013;d</xref>) consistent with its role in posterior axis elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. PSM samples correspond to thoracic axial levels and this region is defined by central HOX genes, which are regulated by CDX proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. CDX2 footprints were found in intergenic accessible chromatin peaks within the <italic>HOXA</italic> cluster (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>).</p><p id="Par28">Predicting enhancer gene interactions remains challenging, although new computational methods are becoming available. For example, the recent activity-by-contact model indicates that very long-range interactions are rare<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. Thus, in our footprint analysis we selected accessible chromatin regions within 10&#x02009;kb of the transcription start site, or within 10&#x02009;kb downstream of the gene. This approach combined with experimental validation and time-lapse imaging in gastrula-stage chick embryos identified CREs for <italic>TCF15</italic> and <italic>MEOX1</italic>, both of which are in close proximity of the transcription start site (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). For <italic>TCF15</italic> we identified two separate elements, <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1 and <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2, which are both active in presegmented mesoderm and somites. <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-1 shows ectopic activity in the notochord. This expression was not seen when both elements were combined, suggesting that <italic>TCF</italic> Enh-2 may contain a repressor of notochord expression. However, both <italic>TCF</italic> Enh-2 and the combined CREs show ectopic activity in LPM, indicating additional repressive elements are missing. Alternatively, this CRE may interact with other gene(s) and direct their expression in the LPM. Footprint analysis identifies a RARA binding site as a highly relevant candidate TF binding site. Citrine activity is lost after mutation of the RARA site. Furthermore, dCas9-Krab epigenome modification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> leads to loss of <italic>TCF15</italic> expression. Although this is restricted to the region of the embryo that is targeted by electroporation at gastrula stages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, this finding suggests the endogenous CRE is essential. This element is not conserved at sequence level and might be chick specific. In contrast, the <italic>MEOX1</italic> enhancer identified here is conserved in avians, reptiles and mammals but not in amphibian or fish (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). In both chick and human CREs, TF binding sites for FOXO1 and ZIC3 are required for Citrine expression (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>e and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>). In vivo epigenome modification of the <italic>MEOX1</italic> enhancer causes axial elongation phenotypes in embryos (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6g, h</xref>). RT-qPCR shows that genes involved in chondrogenesis&#x000a0;and sclerotome polarity are affected in somites where expression of <italic>MEOX1</italic> is lost after targeting the dCas9-Krab repressor to the enhancer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6j</xref>). Furthermore, the elongation phenotypes observed are consistent with mouse mutants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> and human Klippel-Feil patients who display skeletal abnormalities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Thus, it could be of interest to determine whether the <italic>MEOX1</italic> enhancer is affected in patients, who do not have a coding mutation in MEOX1.</p><p id="Par29">Taken together we provide a resource of paraxial mesoderm samples across a spatiotemporal series. Our analysis focussed on PPI networks and CREs important for vertebrate anterior&#x02013;posterior axis formation. We assess evolutionary conservation and validate in vivo function to establish proof-of-principle, which underpins further interrogation and mining of this comprehensive data set.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Chicken embryos</title><p id="Par30">Fertilised chicken eggs (Henry Stewart &#x00026; Co.) were incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with humidity. Embryos were staged according to Hamburger and Hamilton<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. All experiments were performed on chicken embryos younger than 14 days of development and therefore were not regulated by the Animal Scientific Procedures Act 1986.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Embryo dissection</title><p id="Par31">HH14 embryos were dissected into Ringers solution in silicon lined petri dishes and pinned down using the extra-embryonic membranes. Ringers solution was replaced with Dispase (1.5&#x02009;mg/ml) in DMEM 10&#x02009;mM HEPES pH7.5 at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 7&#x02009;min prior to treatment with Trypsin (0.05%) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 7&#x02009;min. The reaction was stopped with Ringers solution with 0.25% BSA. The PSM, ES, MS and DS were carefully dissected away from neural and lateral mesoderm tissue using sharp tungsten needles.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>RNA extraction, library preparation and sequencing</title><p id="Par32">For ES, MS and DS, consecutive four somites were dissected. Tissues were placed into RLT lysis buffer. RNA was extracted using Qiagen RNAeasy kit (Cat no. 74104) and DNase treated (Qiagen Cat no 79254) for removal of DNA. Libraries were prepared and sequenced on the Illumina HiSeq4000 platform (75&#x02009;bp paired end) at the Earlham Institute. A minimum of three biological replicates for each stage were used for analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>ATAC, library preparation and sequencing</title><p id="Par33">PSM, ES, MS and DS samples were dissected as stated above. Cell dissociation was performed using a protocol adapted from<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Briefly, tissues were dissociated with Dispase at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;min with intermittent pipetting to attain a single cell suspension with 0.05% Trypsin at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for a final 5&#x02009;min at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The reaction was stopped, and cells were re-suspended in Hanks buffer (1X HBSS, 0.25% BSA, 10&#x02009;mM HEPES pH8). Cells were centrifuged at 500&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x02009;min at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, re-suspended in cold Hanks buffer, passed through 40&#x02009;&#x003bc;m cell strainers (Fisher Cat no. 11587522), and further centrifuged at 500&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x02009;min at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Pelleted cells were re-suspended in 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;l Hanks buffer, kept on ice and processed for ATAC library preparation. ATAC was performed using a protocol adapted from<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Briefly, cells were lysed in cold lysis buffer (10&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl, Ph7.4, 10&#x02009;mM NaCl, 3&#x02009;mM MgCl2, 0.1% Igepal) and tagmentation performed using Illumina Nextera DNA kit (FC-121-1030) for 30&#x02009;min at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C on a shaking thermomixer. Tagmented DNA was purified using Qiagen MinElute kit (Cat no. 28004) and amplified using NEB Next High-Fidelity 2X PCR Mast Mix (Cat no. M0543S) for 11 cycles as follows: 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 5&#x02009;min; 98&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 30&#x02009;s; 98&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 10&#x02009;s; 63&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 30&#x02009;s; 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 1&#x02009;min. Library preparation was complete after further clean up using Qiagen PCR MinElute kit (Cat no. 28004) and Beckman Coulter XP AMPpure beads (A63880). Tagmentation size was assessed using Agilent 2100 Bioanalyser. Libraries were quantified with Qubit 2.0 (Life Technologies) and sequenced using paired-end 150&#x02009;bp reads on the Illumina HiSeq4000 platform at Novogene UK. Three biological replicates for each stage were used for analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Enhancer cloning</title><p id="Par34">Chick genomic DNA (gRNA) was extracted from HH14 embryos using Invitrogen Purelink gDNA extraction kit (Cat no. K1820-00). Human genomic DNA was isolated from HeLa cells. Putative enhancers were amplified using primers with specific sequence tails to enable cloning into reporter vector using a modified GoldenGate protocol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> under the following conditions: 94&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 3&#x02009;min; 10 cycles of 94&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 15&#x02009;s; 55&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 15&#x02009;s; 68&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 3&#x02009;min, 25 cycles of 94&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 15&#x02009;s; 63&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 15&#x02009;s; 68&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 3&#x02009;min; and final step of 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 4&#x02009;min. Amplicons were purified using Qiagen PCR Cleanup (Cat no. 28104) and pooled with pTK nanotag reporter vector with T4 DNA ligase (Promega) and BsmBI (NEB) restriction enzyme. This reaction was prepared for T4-mediated ligation and BsmBI digestion under the following conditions: 25 cycles of 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 2&#x02009;min; 16&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 5&#x02009;min; a single step of 55&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 5&#x02009;min; and a final step of 80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 5&#x02009;min. For mutagenesis of specific sites in enhancers we utilised FastCloning methodology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>CRISPR-mediated enhancer repression</title><p id="Par35">sgRNAs specific for <italic>MEOX1</italic> Enh and <italic>TCF15</italic> Enh-2, or a scrambled control were cloned into a chicken pU6-3 vector using standard protocols<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. For enhancer repression, sgRNAs and dCas9-Krab were electroporated ex ovo<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. All primer sequences are detailed in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>RT-qPCR</title><p id="Par36">cDNA was synthesised from 500&#x02009;ng of RNA using a Maxima First Strand cDNA synthesis kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific). qPCR was performed on a 7500 Fast Real Time PCR machine (Applied Biosystems) using SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Thermo Fisher Scientific) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Primers (see Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) were designed with Primer3Plus software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://primer3plus.com/cgi-bin/dev/primer3plus.cgi">https://primer3plus.com/cgi-bin/dev/primer3plus.cgi</ext-link>). RT-qPCR was normalised to Gapdh mRNA. Three independent experiments each with replicate samples were performed for each RT-qPCR. The delta-delta CT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> method was used to analyse gene expression levels. Statistical&#x000a0;analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism (Version 6) software. Mann&#x02013;Whitney non-parametric&#x000a0;two-tail testing was applied to determine <italic>p</italic> values.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Embryo preparation and ex ovo electroporation</title><p id="Par37">Hamburger and Hamilton (HH3+) embryos were captured using the filter paper based easy-culture method. Briefly, eggs were incubated for ~20&#x02009;h, a window was created using forceps, the embryo and yolk were transferred into a dish and thin albumin above and around the embryo was removed using tissue paper. A circular filter paper ring was placed on top, excised and transferred into a separate dish containing Ringers solution and excess yolk was removed. The embryo was then transferred into a dish containing albumin-agar and ready for electroporation with the ventral side up<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Plasmid DNA was injected between the membrane and embryo to cover the whole epiblast, electroporated used five pulses of 5&#x02009;V, 50&#x02009;ms on, 100&#x02009;ms off. Thin albumin was used to seal the lids of dishes and embryos were cultured at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with humidity to the desired stage.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Cryosectioning and immunostaining</title><p id="Par38">Embryos were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) for 2&#x02009;h at room temperature (RT) or at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C overnight, washed 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x02009;min in PBS. Embryos were transferred into 30% sucrose/PBS overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C prior to 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x02009;min washes in OCT before final embedding of OCT in dry ice. Cryosectioning was performed at 15&#x02009;&#x003bc;m thickness. Sections were washed in 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15&#x02009;min PBS and 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;15&#x02009;min in PBS/0.5% Triton X-100 prior to blocking in 5% goat serum and 5% BSA in PBS for 1&#x02009;h at RT. Incubation with primary antibody for rabbit anti-GFP (1:200, Torrey Pines Biolabs Cat no. TP401) at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C overnight, followed by 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x02009;min washes in PBS and incubation with secondary antibody AlexaFluor-568-conjugated donkey anti-rabbit IgG (1:500, Thermo Fisher Cat no. A21206) for 1&#x02009;h at RT. Sections were washed 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10&#x02009;min in PBS and 1x wash with PBS and DAPI (Sigma-Aldrich) at 0.1&#x02009;mg/ml in PBS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Wholemount in situ hybridisation</title><p id="Par39">Wholemount in situ hybridisation using DIG-UTP labelled antisense RNA probes for <italic>MEOX1</italic> (a gift from Baljinder Mankoo, King&#x02019;s College London UK) and <italic>TCF15</italic> (a gift from Susanne Dietrich, University of Portsmouth UK) was carried out using standard methods. Briefly, following fixation in 4% PFA embryos were treated with Proteinase K, hybridised over night at 65&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. After post-hybridisation washes and blocking with BMB (Roche), embryos were treated with anti-DIG antibody, coupled to alkaline phosphatase (Roche). Signal was developed using NBT/BCIP.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Live imaging of enhancer reporter</title><p id="Par40">Embryos cultured in six-well cell culture plates (Falcon) were time-lapse imaged on an inverted wide-field microscope (Axiovert; Zeiss). Brightfield and fluorescent images were captured every 6&#x02009;min for 20&#x02013;24&#x02009;h, using Axiovision software as described in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. At the end of the incubation, most embryos had reached stage HH10-11.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Image analysis</title><p id="Par41">Sections were visualised on an Axioscope with Axiovision software (Zeiss). Wholemount embryos were photographed on a Zeiss SV11 dissecting microscope with a Micropublisher 3.5 camera and acquisition software or Leica MZ16F using Leica Firecam software. Live imaging datasets were analysed in FIJI/ImageJ.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>ATAC-seq processing</title><p id="Par42">Adaptors were removed from raw paired-end sequencing reads and trimmed for quality using Trim Galore! (v.0.5.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> a wrapper tool around Cutadapt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> and FastQC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. Default parameters were used. Quality control (QC) was performed before and after read trimming using FastQC (v.0.11.6)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> and no issues were highlighted from the QC process. Subsequent read alignment and post-alignment filtering was performed in concordance with the ENCODE project&#x02019;s &#x0201c;ATAC-seq Data Standards and Prototype Processing Pipeline&#x0201d; for replicated data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.encodeproject.org/atac-seq/">https://www.encodeproject.org/atac-seq/</ext-link>). In brief, reads were mapped to the chicken genome galGal5 assembly using bowtie2 (v.2.3.4.2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. The resultant Sequence Alignment Map (SAM) files were compressed to the Binary Alignment Map (BAM) version on which SAMtools (v.1.9)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup> was used to filter reads that were unmapped, mate unmapped, not primary alignment or failing platform quality checks. Reads mapped as proper pairs were retained. Multi-mapping reads were removed using the Python script assign_multimappers provided by ENCODE&#x02019;s processing pipeline and duplicate reads within the BAM files were tagged using Picard MarkDuplicates (v.2.18.12) [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://broadinstitute.github.io/picard/">http://broadinstitute.github.io/picard/</ext-link>] and then filtered using SAMtools. For each step, parameters detailed in the ENCODE pipeline were used. From the processed BAM files, coverage tracks in bigWig format were generated using deepTools bamCoverage (v 3.1.2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup> and peaks were called using MACS2 (v.2.1.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup> (parameters -f BAMPE -g mm -B -nomodel -shift -100 -extsize 200). Coverage tracks and peaks (narrow peak format) were uploaded to the UCSC Genome Browser<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup> as custom tracks for ATAC-seq data visualisation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Differential accessibility and footprinting</title><p id="Par43">Analysis of ATAC-seq for differential accessibility was carried out in R (v.3.5.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup> using the DiffBind package (v.2.8.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> with default parameter settings. Differential accessibility across samples was calculated using the negative binomial distribution model implemented in DEseq2 (v1.4.5)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. Computational footprinting analysis was conducted across samples using HINT-ATAC which is part of the Regulatory Genomic Toolbox (v.0.12.3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> also using default parameter settings and the galGal5 genome.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>RNA-seq differential expression analysis</title><p id="Par44">Adaptors were removed from raw paired-end sequencing reads and trimmed for quality using Trim Galore! (v.0.5.0) using default parameters. QC was performed before and after read trimming using FastQC (v.0.11.6) and no data quality issues were identified after checking the resultant QC reports. Processed reads were mapped to galGal5 cDNA using kallisto (v.0.44.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>. Resultant quantification files were collated to generate an expression matrix. Differential expression, GO term and pathway analyses were then conducted using DESeq2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup> and default settings within the iDEP (v.9.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup> web interface. GO term analysis used PGSEA method for GO Biological Process with a minimum of 15 and maximum of 2000 geneset and &#x0003c;0.2 FDR. For STRING analysis, version 11.0 was used<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup> to identify PPI networks with a high threshold (0.700) selected for positive interactions between pairs of genes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Xenopus embryo microinjection</title><p id="Par45">All experiments were carried out in accordance with relevant laws and institutional guidelines at the University of East Anglia, with full ethical review and approval, compliant to UK Home Office regulations. To obtain <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic>&#x000a0;embryos, females were primed with 100 units of PMSG and induced with 500 units of human chorionic gonadotrophin. Eggs were collected manually and fertilised in vitro. Embryos were de-jellied in 2% L-cysteine, incubated at 18&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and microinjected in 3% Ficoll into 1 cell at the 2 cell stage in the animal pole with 5&#x02009;nl of enhancer reporter plasmid at 400&#x02009;ng/&#x003bc;l or GFP capped RNA as control. Embryos were left to develop at 23&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Embryo stageing is according to Nieuwkoop and Faber normal table of Xenopus development. GFP capped RNA for injections was prepared using the SP6 mMESSAGE mMACHINE kit, 5&#x02009;ng was injected per embryo.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Reporting summary</title><p id="Par46">Further information on research design is available in the&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">Nature Research Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec27"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_MOESM2_ESM.mov"><caption><p>Supplementary Movie 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_MOESM3_ESM.mov"><caption><p>Supplementary Movie 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Reporting Summary</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="41467_2021_21426_MOESM6_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Description of Additional Supplementary Files</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Peer review information</bold>
<italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks Hector Escriv&#x000e0; and the other, anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work. Peer reviewer reports are available.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41467-021-21426-7.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank all members of the M&#x000fc;nsterberg and Wheeler labs for helpful discussion. Dr Timothy Grocott for discussions, Ronce Saputil and undergraduate project students for assistance with enhancer analysis. G.F.M., L.F., E.M. and V.M.H. were supported by BBSRC project grant (BB/N007034/1) to A.E.M. and G.N.W., and MRC project grant (MR/R000549/1) to A.E.M.; S.A.W. and A.M.G. were supported by studentships funded by the UKRI Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council Norwich Research Park Biosciences Doctoral Training Partnership to A.E.M. and G.N.W.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>G.F.M. and A.E.M. conceived and designed the study. G.F.M. generated and analysed RNA-seq and ATAC-seq data, performed and analysed chick reporter expression assays, in situ hybridisation, immunohistochemistry, QPCR experiments and assisted in bioinformatic analysis. L.F. performed bioinformatic analysis on RNA-seq and ATAC-seq data. E.M. and S.A.W. assisted in live imaging, chick embryo injections and in situ hybridisation. V.M.H. assisted with cloning reporter constructs. R.M.W. and T.S.S. shared electroporation setup, plasmids and expertise in NGS. A.M.G. performed injections into <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> and in situ hybridisation. G.N.W. discussed and supervised <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> experiments. S.M. helped oversee the computational analysis. G.F.M. and A.E.M. discussed ideas and interpretation of data and wrote the manuscript with input from all authors. A.E.M. supervised the study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The authors declare that all data supporting the findings of this study are available within the article and its supplementary information files or from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. Raw sequencing data for this study have been deposited in Sequence Read Archive (SRA) under the BioProject accession code: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/?term=PRJNA602335">PRJNA602335</ext-link>.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par47">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dormann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsterberg</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell movement patterns during gastrulation in the chick are controlled by positive and negative chemotaxis mediated by FGF4 and FGF8</article-title><source>Dev. Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1534-5807(02)00256-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12361604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Weijer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourquie</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual mode of paraxial mesoderm formation during chick gastrulation</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>2744</fpage><lpage>2749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0610997104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17299044?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17299044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benazeraf</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourquie</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation and segmentation of the vertebrate body axis</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-cellbio-101011-155703</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23808844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23808844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brent</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabin</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental regulation of somite derivatives: muscle, cartilage and tendon</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-437X(02)00339-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12200160?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12200160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scaal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amniote somite derivatives</article-title><source>Dev. Dyn.</source><year>2007</year><volume>236</volume><fpage>2382</fpage><lpage>2396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.21189</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17557304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17557304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Serralbo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcelle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WNT11 acts as a directional cue to organize the elongation of early muscle fibres</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>457</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07564</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18987628?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McColl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>4D imaging reveals stage dependent random and directed cell motion during somite morphogenesis</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>12644</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-31014-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30139994?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30139994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scaal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcelle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A two-step mechanism for myotome formation in chick</article-title><source>Dev. Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2004.05.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15177035?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15177035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kmita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Duboule</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organizing axes in time and space; 25 years of colinear tinkering</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>301</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1085753</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12869751?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12869751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noordermeer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temporal dynamics and developmental memory of 3D chromatin architecture at Hox gene loci</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e02557</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02557</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24843030?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24843030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neijts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>At the base of colinear Hox gene expression: cis-features and trans-factors orchestrating the initial phase of Hox cluster activation</article-title><source>Dev. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>428</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2017.02.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28728680?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28728680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourquie</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collinear activation of Hoxb genes during gastrulation is linked to mesoderm cell ingression</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>442</volume><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04838</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16760928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Denans</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourquie</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment of Hox vertebral identities in the embryonic spine precursors</article-title><source>Curr. Top. Dev. Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0070-2153(09)88007-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19651306?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19651306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aires</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deconstructing the molecular mechanisms shaping the vertebrate body plan</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2018.05.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30015151?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30015151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabaries</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cdx protein interaction with Hoxa5 regulatory sequences contributes to Hoxa5 regional expression along the axial skeleton</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1389</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.25.4.1389-1401.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15684390?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15684390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chawengsaksophak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>de Graaff</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cdx2 is essential for axial elongation in mouse development</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>7641</fpage><lpage>7645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0401654101</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15136723?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15136723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neijts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van Rooijen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Deschamps</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cdx is crucial for the timing mechanism driving colinear Hox activation and defines a trunk segment in the Hox cluster topology</article-title><source>Dev. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>422</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2016.12.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28041967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28041967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abou-Elhamd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Klhl31 attenuates beta-catenin dependent Wnt signaling and regulates embryo myogenesis</article-title><source>Dev. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>402</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2015.02.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25796573?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25796573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweetman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of myogenic regulatory factors in chicken embryos during somite and limb development</article-title><source>J. Anat.</source><year>2015</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joa.12340</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26183709?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26183709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Time course and side-by-side analysis of mesodermal, pre-myogenic, myogenic and differentiated cell markers in the chicken model for skeletal muscle formation</article-title><source>J. Anat.</source><year>2015</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joa.12353</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26278933?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26278933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawls</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Requirement of the paraxis gene for somite formation and musculoskeletal patterning</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>384</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/384570a0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8955271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8955271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cdx and Hox genes differentially regulate posterior axial growth in mammalian embryos</article-title><source>Dev. Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2009.08.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19853565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19853565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mankoo</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The concerted action of Meox homeobox genes is required upstream of genetic pathways essential for the formation, patterning and differentiation of somites</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2003</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>4655</fpage><lpage>4664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.00687</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12925591?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12925591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skuntz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lack of the mesodermal homeodomain protein MEOX1 disrupts sclerotome polarity and leads to a remodeling of the cranio-cervical joints of the axial skeleton</article-title><source>Dev. Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2009.06.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19520072?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19520072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayrakli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutation in MEOX1 gene causes a recessive Klippel-Feil syndrome subtype</article-title><source>BMC Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>95</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-14-95</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24073994?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24073994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutations in MEOX1, encoding mesenchyme homeobox 1, cause Klippel-Feil anomaly</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajhg.2012.11.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23290072?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23290072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamburger</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A series of normal stages in the development of the chick embryo</article-title><source>J. Morphol.</source><year>1951</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmor.1050880104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24539719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24539719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalcheim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Yair</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell rearrangements during development of the somite and its derivatives</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gde.2005.05.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15950454?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15950454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langfelder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WGCNA: an R package for weighted correlation network analysis</article-title><source>BMC Bioinforma.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>559</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-9-559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langfelder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining clusters from a hierarchical cluster tree: the Dynamic Tree Cut package for R</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm563</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18024473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buenrostro</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Giresi</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaba</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenleaf</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transposition of native chromatin for fast and sensitive epigenomic profiling of open chromatin, DNA-binding proteins and nucleosome position</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2688</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24097267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24097267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross-Innes</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential oestrogen receptor binding is associated with clinical outcome in breast cancer</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>481</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10730</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3272464?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22217937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DiffBind v.3.0.13&#x000a0;(Bioconductor, 2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TCF12 protein functions as transcriptional repressor of E-cadherin, and its overexpression is correlated with metastasis of colorectal cancer</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>2798</fpage><lpage>2809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.258947</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22130667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22130667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biesiada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamamori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myogenic basic helix-loop-helix proteins and Sp1 interact as components of a multiprotein transcriptional complex required for activity of the human cardiac alpha-actin promoter</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2577</fpage><lpage>2584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.19.4.2577</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10082523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10082523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunty</surname><given-names>WC</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalamalasetty</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional profiling of Wnt3a mutants identifies Sp transcription factors as essential effectors of the Wnt/beta-catenin pathway in neuromesodermal stem cells</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e87018</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24475213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24475213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CIZ, a zinc finger protein that interacts with p130(cas) and activates the expression of matrix metalloproteinases</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1649</fpage><lpage>1658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.20.5.1649-1658.2000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10669742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10669742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pokemon (FBI-1) interacts with Smad4 to repress TGF-beta-induced transcriptional responses</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2015</year><volume>1849</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2014.12.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25514493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25514493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambele</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepper</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of transcription factors potentially involved in human adipogenesis in vitro</article-title><source>Mol. Genet. Genom. Med.</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mgg3.269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delattre</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene fusion with an ETS DNA-binding domain caused by chromosome translocation in human tumours</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1992</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/359162a0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1522903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1522903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grunewald</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chimeric EWSR1-FLI1 regulates the Ewing sarcoma susceptibility gene EGR2 via a GGAA microsatellite</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3363</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26214589?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26214589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of transcription factor binding sites using ATAC-seq</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-019-1642-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30808370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30808370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metzis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nervous system regionalization entails axial allocation before neural differentiation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2018</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1118.e17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2018.09.040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30343898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30343898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsterberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic expression of Lef/Tcf family members and beta-catenin during chick gastrulation, neurulation, and early limb development</article-title><source>Dev. Dyn.</source><year>2004</year><volume>229</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.20010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14991726?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14991726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsterberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of (beta)-catenin in the developing chick myotome is regulated by myogenic signals</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2000</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>4105</fpage><lpage>4113</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10976043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10976043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhinn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinoic acid signalling during development</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2012</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.065938</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22318625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22318625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Akker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cdx1 and Cdx2 have overlapping functions in anteroposterior patterning and posterior axis elongation</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>2181</fpage><lpage>2193</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11959827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11959827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galceran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Farinas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Depew</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosschedl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wnt3a-/-like phenotype and limb deficiency in Lef1(-/-)Tcf1(-/-) mice</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.13.6.709</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10090727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10090727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Collignon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenwolf</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumsden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved method for chick whole-embryo culture using a filter paper carrier</article-title><source>Dev. Dyn.</source><year>2001</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0177(20010301)220:3&#x0003c;284::AID-DVDY1102&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11241836?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11241836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reconstruction of the global neural crest gene regulatory network in vivo</article-title><source>Dev. Cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>276.e7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2019.10.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31639368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31639368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bothe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular setup of the avian head mesoderm and its implication for craniofacial myogenesis</article-title><source>Dev. Dyn.</source><year>2006</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>2845</fpage><lpage>2860</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvdy.20903</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16894604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16894604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Williams, R. M. et al. Genome and epigenome engineering CRISPR toolkit for in vivo modulation of cis-regulatory interactions and gene expression in the chicken embryo. <italic>Development</italic><bold>145</bold>10.1242/dev.160333 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vermot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourquie</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinoic acid coordinates somitogenesis and left-right patterning in vertebrate embryos</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>435</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03488</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15889094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15889094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ghyselinck, N. B. &#x00026; Duester, G. Retinoic acid signaling pathways. <italic>Development</italic><bold>146</bold>10.1242/dev.167502 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>beta-Catenin-dependent Wnt signalling controls the epithelial organisation of somites through the activation of paraxis</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2005</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>3895</fpage><lpage>3905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.01961</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16100089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16100089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubrulle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourquie</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>fgf8 mRNA decay establishes a gradient that couples axial elongation to patterning in the vertebrate embryo</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>427</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02216</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14749824?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chalamalasetty</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mesogenin 1 is a master regulator of paraxial presomitic mesoderm differentiation</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2014</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>4285</fpage><lpage>4297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.110908</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25371364?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tahara, N. et al. Sall4 regulates neuromesodermal progenitors and their descendants during body elongation in mouse embryos. <italic>Development</italic><bold>146</bold>10.1242/dev.177659 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulco</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activity-by-contact model of enhancer-promoter regulation from thousands of CRISPR perturbations</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1664</fpage><lpage>1669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-019-0538-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31784727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31784727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaffney</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping and predicting gene-enhancer interactions</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1662</fpage><lpage>1663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-019-0540-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31784730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31784730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruetzner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandzia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marillonnet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Golden gate shuffling: a one-pot DNA shuffling method based on type IIs restriction enzymes</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e5553</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0005553</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19436741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19436741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FastCloning: a highly simplified, purification-free, sequence- and ligation-independent PCR cloning method</article-title><source>BMC Biotechnol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>92</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6750-11-92</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21992524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21992524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smad1 transcription factor integrates BMP2 and Wnt3a signals in migrating cardiac progenitor cells</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>7337</fpage><lpage>7342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1321764111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24808138?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24808138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Trim Galore v.0.6.5&#x000a0;(Babraham Institute, 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-throughput sequencing reads</article-title><source>EMBnet J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14806/ej.17.1.200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Andrews, S. FastQC: a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link> (2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3322381?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The sequence alignment/map format and SAMtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2723002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>deepTools2: a next generation web server for deep-sequencing data analysis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>W160</fpage><lpage>W165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw257</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27079975?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27079975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying ChIP-seq enrichment using MACS</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1728</fpage><lpage>1740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2012.101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22936215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The human genome browser at UCSC</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>996</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.229102</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12045153?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12045153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R. Core Team. R: A language and environment for statistical computing (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria, 2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 4302049?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Melsted</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Near-optimal probabilistic RNA-seq quantification</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3519</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27043002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>iDEP: an integrated web application for differential expression and pathway analysis of RNA-Seq data</article-title><source>BMC Bioinforma.</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>534</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-018-2486-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STRING v11: protein-protein association networks with increased coverage, supporting functional discovery in genome-wide experimental datasets</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>D607</fpage><lpage>D613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1131</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30476243?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30476243</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>