<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most members of the Hsp70 family belong to the Dnak family and they are recognized to play protective effects through several mechanisms, such as assisting for proper folding of misfolded proteins and degradation of damaged proteins [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The stress 70 protein chaperone (STCH), a member of the Hsp70 family, is constitutively expressed in all human cell types and shares a high degree of amino acid identity with Hsp70 [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Unlike other members of the DnaK subfamily, STCH contains a unique hydrophobic signal sequence and lacks a carboxyl-terminal peptide-binding domain [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Many studies have associated the 
 <italic>STCH</italic> gene to several brain diseases such as Alzheimer disease, epilepsy, autism but also to gastric cancer [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Despite these insights in STCH biological functions, the data relying on its role at the molecular level remain scarce. Kaye et al. has identified an interaction between STCH and the ubiquitin-like protein UBQLN2, termed CHAP1/DSK2, which is known to mediate the proteasomal targeting of misfolded proteins for degradation by binding to their polyubiquitin chains and by interacting (via ubiquitin-like domain) with the subunits of the proteasome [
 <xref rid="B54-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. UBQLN2 plays also a role in the ERAD pathway, providing a link between polyubiquitinated ERAD substrates and the proteasome. Although the precise molecular mechanisms remain unclear at this stage, the identification of ubiquitin-linked proteins that bind to a conserved peptide motif within the ‘core ATPase’ STCH molecule suggests a broader role for this Hsp70 like protein in regulating specialized cellular events. However, whether STCH has a direct role in ERAD of misfolded proteins has never been directly addressed. In the present study, we showed evidence for specific binding of STCH with NKCC2. Most importantly, we showed for the first time, that this interaction is required for efficient degradation of NKCC2 by the ERAD pathway.
</p>
