<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We previously demonstrated that ERAD and export from the ER constitute the limiting step in the maturation and cell surface expression of NKCC2 [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In the present work, the function of STCH in the ERAD of NKCC2 was first suggested by co-immunoprecipitation studies that demonstrated that the interaction involves mainly the immature, ER-resident form of NKCC2. Accordingly, immunocytochemistry studies showed that STCH mainly co-localizes with NKCC2 at the ER. To further support the role of STCH in the ERAD of NKCC2, we have shown that the overexpression of STCH or its inhibition using siRNA approach, was associated with an increase or a decrease in the expression and the degradation of the immature form of the co-transporter, respectively. It is important to note that Bae et al. [
 <xref rid="B41-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] have identified a positive role of STCH in the modulation of membrane trafficking of two acid/base transporters NBCe1-B and NHE1, by increasing their cell surface expression and activity. It is well known that a single chaperone might be involved in either folding or degrading a given substrate that travels through the ER [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]; STCH is no exception and its effect is substrate-dependent. Hence, it may have a protective role for NBCe1-B and NHE1 but a destructive one for NKCC2 during ERAD. Moreover, we have shown that STCH effects on the immature form of NKCC2 were predominantly prevented in the presence of the proteasome inhibitor MG132, indicating that STCH targets most of the immature form of the co-transporter to the proteasome-dependent ERAD pathway. Interestingly, full recovery of NKCC2 expression was achieved only by using MG132 combined with chloroquine, an inhibitor of lysosomal function. Thus, we show here for the first time that the lysosome machinery is also implicated in the proteolysis of NKCC2 by playing a complementary role with the proteasome in the degradation of misfolded NKCC2. The role of additional ER quality control mechanisms, defined as ER-to-lysosome-associated degradation (ERLAD) pathways, is progressively emerging, as some misfolded proteins evade the ERAD factors for quality control or they can form aggregates that cannot be dislocated across the membrane [
 <xref rid="B55-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. These misfolded ER clients, which are not suitable for ERAD must be cleared from the ER through the lysosome alternative by autophagic or non-autophagic pathways. It has been shown that Hsp70 chaperones have a dual function in protein degradation, as they can select misfolded proteins for either the general protein degradation pathways, the proteasome system, or the lysosome degradation machinery [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Our present data demonstrate that immature NKCC2 is recognized by STCH, a component of the Hsp70 system, and degraded by two different pathways that function in a complementary way to regulate NKCC2 turnover. We believe that our characterization for the first time of the ERLAD as another degradation pathway of NKCC2, as well as ERAD, supports and offers a new mechanistic explanation of the ER quality control of NKCC2. How this is regulated awaits further clarification.
</p>
