<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ERAD machinery has been reported to function primarily in the ER where ER α-1, 2-mannosidase I (ERManI) is capable of initiating the ERAD by promoting the first mannose trimming step of numerous misfolded N-glycosylated protein [
 <xref rid="B59-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. However, proteins that exhibit a severe misfolded conformation can traffic to post-ER compartments [
 <xref rid="B62-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. These findings suggest that the ER’s ability to retain misfolded proteins is limited and therefore requires a post-ER control system to prevent premature secretion of escaped misfolded immature proteins. Evidence obtained from several studies support the involvement of the Golgi complex as a component of ERAD. Indeed, it has been demonstrated that a number of ERAD substrates undergo vesicular cycling through early Golgi compartments, and that the three-traditional mammalian Golgi-localized α-1, 2-mannosidases (IA, IB, and IC) contribute to the intracellular degradation of misfolded glycoproteins [
 <xref rid="B63-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Furthermore, ERManI, which was predicted to function in the ER, was also localized to the Golgi complex in mammalian cells, where it contributes to a Golgi-based quality control checkpoint that facilitates the retrieval of captured ERAD substrates back to the ER [
 <xref rid="B65-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Interestingly, we have shown in our current study, that upon treatment with mannosidase I inhibitor kifunensine, the effects of STCH on NKCC2 expression were abolished. Given the fact that kifunensine inhibits trimming of mannose residues in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and in the Golgi compartment, these results suggest that the STCH-enhanced degradation of misfolded NKCC2 requires mannose trimming by α-mannosidase I to target ER misfolded NKCC2 as well as escaped misfolded NKCC2 in the Golgi for ERAD. STCH is expected to be mainly located in the ER, a prediction confirmed also by our experiments. However, in contrast to ER resident proteins, STCH does not encode a consensus ER retention signal such as the tetrapeptide KDEL [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] opening therefore the possibility that STCH may exit the ER. In support of this notion, Otterson et al. showed that STCH is localized to the cellular cytoplasm in a pattern that resembled, but was not identical to BiP, an ER resident protein [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Accordingly, we show here that not all STCH related immunofluorescence signal was found in the ER. In fact, the remaining staining was dispersed in a perinuclear Golgi like region. Most importantly, we found colocalization of STCH with GM130, strongly suggesting that in addition to its detection at the ER, this Hsp70-like protein is also present the cis-Golgi network. These findings are of great interest because they are consistent with the expression of STCH as a Man-6 phosphorylated glycoprotein [
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and its sensitivity to endo-H digestion (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-02207-f002">Figure 2</xref>B). Indeed, phosphorylation of mannose residues within the 1,6 branch prevents high mannose-type units from being converted to Endo H resistant structures by preventing mannosidase action [
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. However, despite being Man-6 P phosphorylated [
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], we did not detect any colocalization of STCH with the lysosome marker LAMP2, which clearly indicates that although some STCH proteins exit the ER and then become Man-6-phosphorylated in cis-Golgi apparatus, they were retained in the cis-Golgi network and/or retrieved back to the ER prior to encountering the MPRs in the trans-Golgi. In sum, these observations support a model in which STCH role in the ERAD of immature NKCC2 requires mainly its residence in the ER. Moreover, they open the possibility that STCH contributes not only in the retention and degradation of misfolded proteins at the ER, but also in the retention, the recycling, and ERAD of misfolded proteins that initially escape protein quality control surveillance within the ER.
</p>
