<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the members of 70 kDa heat shock proteins, Hsc70 (heat shock cognate protein, Hsp73/HSPA8) and Hsp70 (Hsp72/HSPA1A) have been extensively studied and have distinct biological functions despite their high sequence homology [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Consequently, the roles of Hsp70 and Hsc70 in the ERAD of several transmembrane proteins such CFTR, NCC, ENaC, and HERG have been thoroughly investigated [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Under cellular stress conditions, it is assumed in general that Hsc70 associates with newly synthesized misfolded proteins to induce their ER associated degradation by the proteasome. In contrast, Hsp70 seems to preferentially promote the biogenesis of newly synthesized proteins by facilitating their protein refolding after cellular stress [
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. In agreement with these notions, several reports demonstrated that Hsp70 and Hsc70 exert opposite effects on the stability and maturation of hERG and ENaC proteins through their association with their immature forms at the ER [
 <xref rid="B45-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. This is of great interest because similar to STCH, Hsc70 is also constitutively expressed [
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Hence, we hypothesized that STCH and the stress-inducible Hsp70 may also have differential effects on the stability and maturation of NKCC2. Importantly, we found indeed that similar to Hsc70, the effect of STCH was opposite to that of Hsp70 not only on WT NKCC2 but also on its disease-causing mutants i.e., STCH promotes NKCC2 degradation, whereas Hsp70 promotes the co-transporter maturation. Similar to STCH, the main site of action of Hsp70 appeared to be mainly the ER given that both chaperones associate only with the immature form of the co-transporter. Interestingly, our immunocytochemistry experiments revealed overlap of Hsp70 and STCH, which is consistent with the idea that these two chaperones exert opposite and antagonist effect on the same substrate, which in our case, is NKCC2. Obviously, further studies are required to determine the mechanisms underlying these differential effects and whether these effects are also observed native TAL cells. Of note, while under ER stress conditions, Hsp70 preferentially promotes, in general, the stabilization and proper protein folding of newly synthetized proteins, it promotes actually their degradation under non-stress conditions [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. This is of particular interest because our experimental setting i.e., heterologous overexpression of secretory and membrane proteins (NKCC2) causes ER stress which is therefore consistent with the protective role of Hsp70 during the ERAD of the co-transporter under these conditions [
 <xref rid="B70-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. With regard to the mechanisms underlying the effect of Hsp70 on protein maturation, it is worth mentioning that Chanoux et al. demonstrated that Hsp70 overexpression increases the association of ENaC with the Sec24D cargo recognition component of coat complex II, which carries protein cargo from the endoplasmic reticulum to the Golgi [
 <xref rid="B73-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. It is therefore tempting to speculate that Hsp70 overexpression stabilizes NKCC2 at the ER and promotes also its maturation and trafficking by increasing its association with Coat Complex II and its exit from Endoplasmic Reticulum. Undeniably, Hsp70 cannot work in isolation to promote NKCC2 biogenesis. Appropriately, one may reasonably postulate that Hsp70 works in concert, sequentially or simultaneously, with other NKCC2-binding proteins and ERAD components such as MAGE-D2 and Hsp40 to regulate the ER quality control and its associated protein degradation of the co-transporter. Indeed, it is well known that the function of Hsp70 in the ERAD pathway involves Hsp40 [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Most importantly, we previously provided evidence that MAGE-D2 protects the co-transporter against ER associated degradation and promotes its maturation and cell surface expression, an effect that is very likely to be mediated by Hsp40 [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Likewise, given that we previously showed the presence of OS9 mediated ER associated degradation of NKCC2 [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-02207" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], one may also postulate that STCH and OS9 work in concert to exert the opposite effect by promoting efficient degradation of the co-transporter and its folding mutants. Obviously, further experiments are needed to uncover the precise mechanisms behind these processes.
</p>
