<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interestingly, in this study, the greatest number of differentially expressed proteins from hemocytes was observed at 24 and 48 hpi (79 and 86, respectively), with a lower number of differentially expressed proteins at 96 hpi (only 28), whereas several plasma proteins were present at different levels throughout the study. According to a previous report on 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>siamensis goniomphalos</italic> infected with 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>viverrini</italic>, the majority of differentially expressed proteins on the whole snail’s proteome were observed at 28–56 days post infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. It is likely that the changes in the protein expression observed in these times could be linked to the parasite migration through digestive glands where asexual reproduction and parasite localization within the snail host take place. However, our findings could be indicating that the changes observed in the expression of hemocyte proteins could be a direct response against 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>viverrini</italic> infection in early infection. Within hours of infection, the miracidium hatches from the egg, penetrates the snail tissue and transforms into the sporocyst within 4 h [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic>, the snail’s immune system is directed towards the tegument and ciliated plates shed by the miracidium when it transforms into the sporocyst stage [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], followed by a strong up-regulation of a number of defense-related transcripts in early infection (12–48 hpi), and, a down-regulation at and beyond 4 days post-infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The results observed in the present study suggest that early stages of the infection are critical for the success or failure of parasite establishment.
</p>
