<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A GO analysis was also performed on proteins with significantly different expression patterns, which were classified into functional groups accordingly (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005104.g003">Fig 3</xref>). The main abundant GO term represented in biological process was the immune system process. Several immune-relevant proteins were identified in this group, such as C-type lectin, galectin-4, heat shock proteins (HSPs), glutathione-s-transferases (GSTs), hemocyanin (HMC), serpin and peroxiredoxin. HMC is significantly expressed in both hemocyte and plasma after infection, although at different times post-infection. The expression of HMC was strongly up-regulated at 24 hpi and particularly at 48 hpi in hemocyte, while, in plasma, it was down-regulated at 48 hpi but up-regulated at 96 hpi. HMC is the main protein component of hemolymph, and is found in both hemocyte and plasma. The function HMC in invertebrate is not only as a respiratory protein via oxygen transport, but it has also been strongly associated with different immunological processes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. HMC has been shown to participate in multiple roles of the immune response including phenoloxidase activity [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], antiviral [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] and antimicrobial activity [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In snails, a study on the transcriptional profile of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic> snails showed that a number of HMC transcripts were up-regulated after 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>mansoni</italic> and 
 <italic>Echinostoma paraensei</italic> infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. A previous study on 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>siamensis goniomphalos</italic> revealed that the expression of HMC was significantly up-regulated in uninfected snails compared to infected snails [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], however, this study was performed on the head-foot and the body of the snails and not on the cells or tissues involved in the immune response. In our case, hemocytes could be expressing more HMC to fight 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>viverrini</italic> infection in the early stages of the infection. Once the infection is cleared, HMC is no longer needed and its expression levels would be expected to decrease. In the case of plasma, the high levels of HMC found at 96 hpi could be related to lysis of hemocytes that would release their contents, although more studies should be done in this regard.
</p>
