<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Immunoglobulin superfamily (IgSF) proteins act as antibodies in mammals. While invertebrates do not have antibodies, some invertebrate molecules containing IgSF domain proteins are commonly associated with the immune system as they have the ability to specifically recognize pathogen molecules [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. In our study, 7 and 13 IgSF domain-containing proteins were identified in the hemocytes and plasma libraries, respectively. From these, 1 and 8 proteins had significantly up-regulated expression profiles in hemocytes and plasma, respectively, and the expression of only 1 protein (similar to IgSF DCC subclass member 4 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]) was down-regulated. These results suggest that the proteins containing an IgSF domain might play a role in 
 <italic>Bithynia</italic> snail defense responses against 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>viverrini</italic> infection. In a similar way, lectins are known to play a role in molecule recognition and are involved in both humoral and cellular immune response in molluscs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Recently, a comprehensive study reported different proteins involved in the immune response containing one or two IgSF domains and a multi lectin domain such as fibrinogen-related proteins (FREPs), C-type lectin-related proteins (CREPs) and galectin-related proteins (GREPs) in 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. FREPs are characterized as containing a C-terminal fibrinogen domain and one or two IgSF-like domains at the N-terminus, and are involved in 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic> immune responses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. CREPs and GREPs consist of one or two IgSF domains followed by a C-type lectin or a galectin domain, respectively [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], which are a family of glycan-binding proteins that are able to recognize and bind to the tegument of pathogens, and are usually up-regulated after infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. In our study, only 6 proteins in the hemocyte library contained a fibrinogen domain, of which 2 had a significantly down-regulated expression pattern in hemocytes, although none of these 6 proteins had an IgSF domain. Moreover, 2 proteins with a significantly regulated expression profile containing a C-type lectin domain (such as a protein similar to galactose-specific lectin nattectin [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and a protein having low similarity with macrophage manose receptor-1 like protein from 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic>) were identified. Furthermore, we identified a protein containing a galactoside-binding lectin domain that was similar to galectin-4. However, none of the proteins contained an IgSF domain. While we cannot rule out the possibility that these are partial sequences and the IgSF domain could be present, the fact that the expression of all of these lectin domain-containing proteins was down-regulated could indicate that they are not true FREPs, CREPs or GREPs, and, thus, would not be involved in the snail’s immune response against the parasite, or alternatively might be the result of parasite-induced immunosuppression. This is in disagreement with previously reported literature on other snails acting as trematode intermediate hosts such as 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic>. However, it is noteworthy that while 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic> is a pulmonate snail, 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>siamensis goniomphalos</italic> is a prosobranch. The two groups also show some physiological differences according to evolutionary distance that could affect the different responses of FREPs, CREPs and GREPs against parasitic infections. Despite the fact that several lectin families have been identified in other prosobranchs such as 
 <italic>Littorina littorea</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], there is no information published regarding the expression of these molecules following parasite infection. In order to unravel the functions of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>siamensis goniomphalos</italic> lectins in snail-fluke interactions, further studies are needed. In this sense, the snail’s genome sequence will be of great interest.
</p>
