<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, several proteins corresponding to enzymatic activity were characterized including glutathione-s-transferases (GSTs), fructose-bisphosphate aldolase, serpin and peroxiredoxin. Detoxifying enzymes such as GSTs and peroxiredoxins play an important role in removing harmful free radicals or cytotoxic compounds to protect the snail host during infection and the ensuing immune response, and their regulation could be linked to a survival strategy against infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. We detected significant down-regulation of the expression of GST whereas the expression of peroxiredoxins was up-regulated in plasma. In 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic> snails, it has been previously shown that the differential capability of host defense responses in susceptible and resistant snails could have different effects on enzyme activity due to the differences in the levels of these enzymes in each strain [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Serpin is a serine protease inhibitor that was only found expressed in plasma with an up-regulated expression profile at 24 and 48 hpi. This protein is strongly implicated in the innate immune response, and is likely to function by inactivating and clearing proteases such as those present in the ES of the parasite produced during invasion of the host [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The expression levels of several actin-related proteins (e.g. actin, filamin-4, tubulin, myosin and twitchin) were down-regulated in hemocytes and up-regulated in plasma. These proteins are involved in various types of cell motility and cell-cell interactions. Recent studies have revealed that actin-related genes and proteins were consistently up-regulated in infected 
 <italic>Bithynia</italic> snails, and it was hypothesized that these proteins could be associated with hemocyte chemotaxis and with the promotion of phagocytosis and encapsulation against parasite infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Moreover, we found fructose-1,6-bisphosphate aldolase, a glycolytic enzyme that can interact with cytoskeletal proteins and could play a role in the motility or adhesion of hemocytes. Fructose-1,6-bisphosphate aldolase has been identified in hemocytes of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>glabrata</italic> and has been shown to regulate hemocyte migration, implicating this protein in pathogen killing via cytotoxic reactivity and phagocytosis [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
