<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">We further identified the differential binding genes through integrating analysis ChIP-seq and RNA-seq data. For the differential genes associated LMNA alone with euchromatin, we obtained 5 candidate genes (EGR2, NMB, CREBBP, PRF1, and TENM4), of which EGR2 and NMB have been reported to involve in myocardial ischemia and heart failure, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Although there are currently no reports about PRF1 and TENM4 involved in heart disease, we noticed that they may be related to LMNA mutation-associated DCM in our research; therefore, they may be the potential biomarkers of DCM, which needs further verification. CREBBP was demonstrated to exert essential roles in the pathogenesis of DCM [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], which is consistent with our experimental results. In our study, CREBBP was discovered as the only key gene in the control groups, and the TF motif (SREBP1A) which is a novel lamin A interactor and the coactivator of CREBBP also had a significant change between control and DCM groups (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). Meanwhile, CREBBP has been widely reported to take part in WNT/β-catenin pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], but to our knowledge, the role of CREBBP participating in WNT/β-catenin pathway in LMNA mutation-associated DCM was still unclear. From our results, we proposed a possible link among CREBBP, WNT pathway and LMNA mutation-associated DCM, which helped to explain the mechanism of DCM caused by LMNA mutation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). CREBBP, a β-catenin-interacting protein functions as a coactivator in WNT signaling. Mutations in the LMNA gene may cause LMNA encoded protein to fail to bind to CREBBP DNA on the euchromatin, and our results showed that the expression of CREBBP was increased at the transcript level. We speculated that the increased CREBBP binds to the nuclear β-catenin and TCF, which led to excessive activation of WNT pathway, and promotes changes in transcription mechanism and causes the activation of several target genes, such as c-jun, c-Myc, Fos-Related Antigen-1, and COX2. Ultimately those changes contribute to the pathological phenotype of LMNA mutation-associated DCM. Although we could not obtain the enrichment results from the genes in DCM samples, we still carried out further analysis on its unique genes. We found that the expression of UCN3 gene was dysregulated in DCM patients, which is consistent with previous experimental data [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].
</p>
