<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par45">For the regulation of nucleoplasmic LAP2α-lamin A/C complexes, we eventually obtained 60 candidate genes (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table Sheet 15) in control groups. Some candidate genes have been reported to be related to the development of DCM, such as BMP4, BMP7, CREBBP, and NAMPT [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Furthermore, SLC9A1 and CACNA1E have been reported to regulate the development of other heart diseases, such as heart failure and arrhythmia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Based on our integrated analysis results, we considered that some key genes named BMP4, PPP2R2B, BMP7, and CREBBP might play the key roles in LMNA mutation-associated DCM, and they might be used to predict the diagnosis and prognosis of the disease. Similar to the change of CREBBP in the regulation of LMNA alone, there was also a significant change in TF motif (IRF4) related to CREBBP (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b); therefore, the role of CREBBP in the pathogenesis of DCM cannot be ignored. Increasing experimental data have been reported that bone morphogenetic protein 4 (BMP4), an important member of the TGF-β superfamily, leads to enhanced autocrine activation of TGF-β-responsive SMAD by regulating the activity of a series of downstream genes, which providing a context for the activation of TGF-β signaling in response to BMP during development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In addition, the abnormality of protein phosphatase 2 regulatory subunit Bbeta (PPP2R2B) has been confirmed to be involved in WNT pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. At the same time, we noticed that WNT/β-catenin signaling inhibitor TCF3 motif was not found in DCM in the study, which further verified the disorder of WNT/β-catenin pathway (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b and Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4). Although these genes have been associated with the pathway mentioned above, how dysregulation of these genes affects LMNA mutation-associated DCM is not understood. Previous research believed that PPP2R2B acts as a WNT signal antagonist, which is contrary to our study results [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Ishibashi et al. reported that the up-regulated PPP2R2B activates WNT pathway through promoting the dephosphorylation of β-catenin by PP2A [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]; our results were consistent with them (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). In this study, we speculated two possible mechanisms to explain how these genes that are regulated by the LAP2α-lamin A/C complexes on euchromatin lead to LMNA mutation-associated DCM. The LMNA mutations might be accompanied by the LAP2α-lamin A/C complexes not binding to BMP4 and CREBBP DNA on euchromatin and increasing the transcriptomic level of BMP4 and CREBBP. At the same time, the BMP4 ligand and the serine/threonine kinase receptor II (BMP receptor II, BMPR II) on the cell membrane excessively interacts to form a ligand receptor binary complex. The BMPR II can hyperactivate the type I receptor (BMPR I), and the activated BMPR I further phosphorylates the Smad protein (Smad1, Smad5, and Smad8) to promote the detachment of Smad molecules from the cell membrane receptor. The Smad1/5/8 protein forms heteromeric complexes with Smad4 (common Smad, Co-Smad) and translocates to the nucleus. In the nucleus, the Smad multiplex complex regulates the transcription of some specific target genes with the participation of CREBBP, which contributes to hyperactivate the TGF-β pathway and may further lead to LMNA mutation-associated DCM. Interestingly, we found that the dysregulation of bone morphogenetic protein 7 (BMP7) exerted similar effects with BMP4 on the regulation of TGF-β pathway. We discovered the increased binding between LAP2α-lamin A/C complexes and BMP7 DNA and decreased expression of BMP7 mRNA in DCM. BMP7 binds to the BMPR II, promoting phosphorylation of Smad1/5/8, which initiates downstream signal transduction pathways. Phosphorylated Smad1/5/8 binds to the Smad4 molecule in the cytoplasm and translocates to the nucleus to regulate the expression of some specific genes. The reduction of BMP7 expression level contributed to reducing Smad7 (an intracellular antagonist of TGF-β/Smad signaling) expression and the inhibitory effect on Smad3 DNA binding. Therefore, phosphorylated Smad2/3 and the heteromeric complexes were promoted, which exerted excessive positive regulation of TGF-β pathway with the participation of CREBBP (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). However, we also obtained 4 genes by GO and DAVID analysis in DCM groups, including TRABD2B, TLE3, CTNND2, and ROR2, but these genes were no significant difference at the transcriptomic level. However, previous reports have suggested that ROR2 played a distinctive role in signal transduction in human cardiomyocyte development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Although we predicted the detailed mechanisms on LMNA mutation-associated DCM, the results also need to further be validated by experiments. We also notice other limitations in our study; we could not obtain the enrichment results from the limited 15 unique genes in DCM (MACS). The three samples have different mutation sites, which may filter out some specific and unique genes related to distinct mutation sites. All the above problems need to be further solved in future studies.
</p>
