<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Electrochemical relithiation has been studied by several authors [
 <xref rid="B219-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>,
 <xref rid="B220-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>,
 <xref rid="B221-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">221</xref>]. Ra et al. proposed an electrochemical dissolution/deposition process for LCO batteries. This process, illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-00801-f020">Figure 20</xref>, involved the application of a small galvanostatic current (1 mA/cm
 <sup>2</sup>) in an aqueous slurry of spent LCO powder with 4 M LiOH and KOH at a temperature of 40–100 °C. During the process, LiCo(III)O
 <sub>2(s)</sub> dissolved as cobaltous oxyhydroxide (HCo(II)O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>) and oxocobaltic (Co(III)O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>) ions in the presence of OH
 <sup>-</sup>, which migrated towards the platinum working electrode (anode). Both Co complexes are oxidized in the presence of OH
 <sup>−</sup> and Li
 <sup>+</sup>. Then, they created a thin film of LiCoO
 <sub>2</sub>(s) on the electrode. This principle was evidenced by Li et al. following slightly different reactions [
 <xref rid="B180-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. According to Li et al., the cobalt oxyhydroxide ion (HCo(II)O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>) oxidized to solid oxyhydroxide (Co(III)OOH
 <sub>(s)</sub>). Then, a chemical transformation reaction formed LiCo(III)O
 <sub>2(s)</sub>. In both cases, the capacity of the refunctionalized material was close to the practical capacity of LCO (140 mAh/g [
 <xref rid="B21-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]), at approximately 130 mAh/g and 135 mAh/g, respectively, for Li and Ra [
 <xref rid="B180-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B219-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>]. Direct current electrochemical relithiation could also serve to regenerate spent LFP, as proven by Yang et al. [
 <xref rid="B222-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>], Ganter et al. [
 <xref rid="B217-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>], and Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B223-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>]. Yang et al. and Ganter et al. followed similar relithiation methods by discharging an LFP cell versus lithium metal negative electrode. However, the cathode preparation procedure diverged. While Yang et al. liberated the active material from the current collector and the binder, Ganter et al. coupled directly spent cathode with the lithium metal negative electrode. The initial capacities obtained from the first two studies reached 150 mAh/g and 140 mAh/g, respectively. Unfortunately, this simple relithiation process is difficult to scale up, as pointed out by Ganter et al. [
 <xref rid="B217-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>]. It did not repair the structural defect, nor did it remove contamination such as copper, which may plate on the positive electrode during cell over-discharge [
 <xref rid="B71-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. 
</p>
