<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar thermal reactivation processes were explored for LFP batteries, notably by Kim et al. [
 <xref rid="B69-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. In the process of Kim et al., after opening of batteries and sorting their components, the cathode was submitted to thermal treatment at 500 °C under nitrogen flow. This process decomposed the PVDF binder and liberated the active LFP from other components. Nevertheless, the recovered cathodic material exhibits low electrochemical capacity, reaching 136 mAh/g at 0.1 C (Refers to charging or discharging current rate. 1 C corresponds to full charge or discharge in 1 h.) versus Li
 <sup>0</sup> [
 <xref rid="B69-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. This process was improved by Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="B213-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>] and Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B97-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>] at pilot scale by introducing a lithium precursor and a reducing gas during the thermal treatment. In this way, the depleted cathodic material was replenished with lithium. This fully lithiated LFP exhibited electrochemical capacity of 145 mAh/g at 0.1 C versus Li
 <sup>0</sup>. The complete process flow chart is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-00801-f017">Figure 17</xref>. Similarly, Wang et al. developed a process integrating a cathode washing step with DMC for the removal of organic compounds before component separation, milling, and thermal treatment. This last step was performed at two different temperatures, namely, 200 °C and 500 °C under nitrogen atmosphere. It allowed carbonization of PVDF, refreshing the carbon layer around the LFP particles. Regenerated LFP exhibited good capacity (150 mAh/g at 0.1 C) even at a high discharge rate (100 mAh/g at 20 C) but showed a stability slightly lower than expected from LFP (95% capacity retention after 100 cycles). In addition, the chemical assay of regenerated LFP showed a contamination of aluminum at 0.5%. Although it did not seem to affect the capacity of refreshed material, the presence of this contamination has to be minimized to avoid their accumulation in the recycled active material. 
</p>
