<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We created a custom Python pipeline for automating RBHB searches between a single reference genome and multiple target genomes using a list of query sequences from the reference genome. For the query sequences in our search, we used the hg38 UniProt proteome (
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">The UniProt Consortium, 2017</xref>), which is a comprehensive set of protein sequences curated from a combination of predicted and validated protein sequences generated by the UniProt Consortium. Next, we excluded genes from downstream analyses for which assignment of homology was uncertain, including uncharacterized ORFs (991 genes), LOC (63 genes), HLA genes (402 genes), replication dependent histones (72 genes), odorant receptors (499 genes), ribosomal proteins (410 genes), zinc finger transcription factors (1983 genes), viral and repetitive-element-associated proteins (82 genes), and ‘Uncharacterized’, ‘Putative’, or ‘Fragment’ proteins (30,724 genes), leaving a final set of 37,582 query protein isoforms, corresponding to 18,011 genes. We then searched for all copies of 18,011 query genes in publicly available Afrotherian genomes (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Dobson, 2013</xref>), including African savannah elephant (
 <italic>Loxodonta africana</italic>: loxAfr3, loxAfr4, loxAfrC), African forest elephant (
 <italic>Loxodonta cyclotis</italic>: loxCycF), Asian Elephant (
 <italic>Elephas maximus</italic>: eleMaxD), Woolly Mammoth (
 <italic>Mammuthus primigenius</italic>: mamPriV), Colombian mammoth (
 <italic>Mammuthus columbi</italic>: mamColU), American mastodon (
 <italic>Mammut americanum</italic>: mamAmeI), Rock Hyrax (
 <italic>Procavia capensis</italic>: proCap1, proCap2, proCap2
 <italic>HiC</italic>), West Indian Manatee (
 <italic>Trichechus manatus latirostris:</italic> triManLat1, triManLat1HiC), Aardvark (
 <italic>Orycteropus afer</italic>: oryAfe1, oryAfe1
 <italic>HiC</italic>), Lesser Hedgehog Tenrec (
 <italic>Echinops telfairi:</italic> echTel2), Nine-banded armadillo (
 <italic>Dasypus novemcinctus:</italic> dasNov3), Hoffman’s two-toed sloth (
 <italic>Choloepus hoffmannii</italic>: choHof1, choHof2, choHof2HiC), Cape golden mole (
 <italic>Chrysochloris asiatica</italic>: chrAsi1), and Cape elephant shrew (
 <italic>Elephantulus edwardii</italic>: eleEdw1) (
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Dudchenko et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Palkopoulou et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Palkopoulou et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Foote et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
