<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Reconstructions from comparative genomics have established an overall pattern of conservation of endomembrane-system genes among all major lineages of eukaryotes including plants, protists, amoebae, animals and fungi, implying inheritance from a complex common ancestor [
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. It also suggests that a widely conserved, complex set of NEA proteins may exist, corresponding to the conservation of the NE itself. While 300–400 putative NEA proteins have been described in human and yeast cells, few orthologs of these proteins have been described across eukaryotic diversity to date. While the NEA protein datasets upon which we based our analysis are of high quality, we must emphasize the need for further experimental and 
 <italic>in silico</italic> work to define NEA protein cohorts with greater confidence. Inherent to any proteomics investigation are sources of error, including contaminants, mislocalized proteins and proteins evading detection by mass spectrometry. In the case of the NE, isolation of pure fractions for proteomic profiling is particularly challenging due to continuity of the NE with the ER, and due to fibrous connections between the NE and both the cytoskeleton and the nucleoplasm. Further complexities arise, as many NEA proteins have dual localizations at the NE and other organelles such as ER, cytoskeleton, mitochondria and peroxisomes, and some proteins are only identified in the NE while in the early stages of their biosynthesis [
 <xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. For some proteins, NE functions may be carried out by a minor fraction of the total cellular pool, as some of them can be detected in different organelles or even multiple localizations within the same organelle. Moreover, although orthologs tend to retain function [
 <xref rid="cit0118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>], many widely conserved NEA proteins are characterized in only one model organism, leaving their functions in distantly related eukaryotes uncertain. This, together with the apparent prevalence of lineage-specific NEA proteins revealed here warrants parallel experimentation efforts using multiple model organisms. Our present analysis is certainly not exhaustive and is intended to provide a broad overview of modes of NEA protein evolution. We are limited not only by uncertainty in experimental identification of NEA proteins but also sources of potential error inherent to sequence similarity search methods. For example, we are aware that highly divergent orthologs will not have been retrieved by our BLAST searches, but might be retrieved through further analysis with profile searching methods. Also, we have attempted to be conservative, preferring to exclude potential orthologs when there is reason for significant doubt. Thus, further analyses may reveal somewhat more (or less) extensive diversity in nuclear composition and hence, function. Certainly, examples of churning or backfilling would not be detected here. Nevertheless, considerable divergence in NEA protein cohorts between lineages is clear, with 50% or fewer proteins detected as broadly distributed, despite low stringency searching followed by manual validation. Ribosome biogenesis, RNA processing proteins and proteins with participation in transcription are highly conserved, unsurprisingly, followed by proteins involved in lipid biosynthesis [
 <xref rid="cit0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Regardless, the cohort is dominated by lineage-specific proteins, many of which, like nesprins, possibly have analogs in other lineages. Hence, when considering the NE, variations in the NPC, lamina systems, cytoskeletal anchoring and kinetochores, the nucleus provides an example of considerable diversity despite hosting a plethora of core functions (Figure 7). Indeed, these findings suggest a rather surprising level of divergence associated with a structure that, in a very real sense, defines the eukaryotic cell.
</p>
