<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">In the current study, high throughput RNA sequencing was used to quantify genome-wide DCVC-induced differential gene expression in two different first trimester placental models in vitro. The HTR-8/SVneo cells, with an extravillous trophoblast phenotype, were used to evaluate transcriptional responses in this specific critical cell type. Villous explants from first trimester placentae were used to evaluate transcriptional responses in intact villi tissue with multiple interacting cell types, including extravillous trophoblasts. Both of these placental models have been used extensively to study placental biology and pathophysiology (Huckle 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2017</xref>; Orendi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2011</xref>) and to study the effect of xenobiotics on the placenta (Kovo and Golan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2008</xref>). Subsequently, gene set enrichment testing was used to identify biological pathways and/or processes targeted by DCVC and re-evaluate previously identified pathways. The most notable pathway identified was the endoplasmic reticulum unfolded protein response (UPR), a cellular response designed to rid cells of accumulated misfolded proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). Upon further characterization of genes enriched in this pathway, the specific involvement of the integrated stress response (ISR), a condition triggered by the UPR and other stress stimuli, was revealed (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>). Because the ISR is characterized by eIF2α phosphorylation, causing protein synthesis restriction and selective activation of transcription factor 4 (ATF4)-mediated upregulation of amino acid biosynthesis and transport genes (Pakos-Zebrucka et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>), additional experiments were conducted to confirm ISR activation by measuring global protein synthesis, phosphorylation levels of eIF2α and protein concentrations of ATF4 as key regulators of ISR activation. Lastly, cell cycle progression and proliferation were determined in the cell model to evaluate functional consequences of DCVC treatment and ensure no acute cellular toxicity.
</p>
