<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">Differentially methylated loci between cutaneous and plexiform neurofibromas were identified using a hierarchical generalized linear mixed model (GLMM) approach with a logit link function as implemented in glmmTMB (v0.2.2) on the pre-processed beta-values. Partially repeated tissue sampling was modeled as a random effect with patient nested within methylation array slide unless specified otherwise. Group-level differences were determined using a likelihood ratio test (LRT) with a significance threshold of 
 <italic>q</italic> &lt; 0.05. False discovery rate adjustment was done using the Benjamini–Hochberg procedure. Models were filtered out for downstream analysis if they failed to converge. In total, 31,201 probes were found to be differentially methylated between cutaneous and plexiform neurofibromas. Differentially methylated regions were called using DMRcate (v1.18.0). Results from glmmTMB were wrangled into a suitable data structure as input for DMRcate by using the Wald statistic as the stat and a quasi-beta fold-change using the exponentiated model estimates for each probe. Default parameters were used for DMRcate with the bandwidth scaling factor (C parameter) set to 2. To identify differentially methylated loci associated with cutaneous neurofibroma size, a GLMM with a logit link was fitted, adjusting for age and sex differences and a random intercept term for partially repeated tissue sampling. Significant associations (
 <italic>q</italic> &lt; 0.05) between CNF size in millimeters and probe-level methylation were determined as described above. A total of 188 loci were found to be significant. Positive or negative correlations were computed on significant probes using Kendall’s Tau. False discovery rate was controlled using the Benjamini–Hochberg procedure and significant correlations were determined at a 
 <italic>q</italic> &lt; 0.05 threshold. Significantly correlated probes were filtered on a delta Beta-value (maximum Beta-value minus the minimum Beta-value) of 0.2, resulting in 34 loci.
</p>
