<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Fossil evidence shows that the earliest ancestors of baleen whales possessed complete dentitions without baleen (such as <italic>Janjucetus</italic> and <italic>Mammalodon</italic>), and then evolved the baleen with teeth (such as <italic>Aetiocetus</italic>), until the lineages only baleen existed (e.g., <italic>Eomysticetus</italic> and <italic>Micromysticetus</italic>) (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Fitzgerald, 2006</xref>, <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Meredith et al., 2011</xref>). However, the fact is all living baleen whales lack teeth and instead baleen (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Uhen, 2010</xref>). This implied that that mineralized teeth were lost or degenerated gradually in the common ancestors of all modern baleen whales (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Boessenecker &amp; Fordyce, 2015</xref>). In addition, the successive steps of vestigial tooth development was found in the fetal period of living baleen whales (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Davit-B&#233;al, Tucker &amp; Sire, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Thewissen, 2018</xref>), which was also confirmed by genetic evidence. Molecular sequences of some specific genes, such as <italic>AMBN</italic>, <italic>ENAM</italic>, <italic>AMELX</italic>, <italic>AMTN</italic>, <italic>C4orf26</italic> and <italic>ODAM</italic>, contain different types of inactivating mutations (e.g., stop codons, frameshift mutations, splice site mutations, etc.) in various mysticete species (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Dem&#233;r&#233; et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Meredith et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Alhashimi et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Gasse, Silvent &amp; Sire, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Meredith, Gatesy &amp; Springer, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Delsuc, Gasse &amp; Sire, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Springer et al., 2019</xref>), which is consistent with loss-of-teeth in this group. But none of the inactivating mutations are shared by all living mysticetes species. <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Meredith et al. (2011)</xref> found a common insertion of CHR-2 SINE retroposon in <italic>MMP20</italic> gene among all living baleen whales. Previous study has been confirmed that mutations or deletions of <italic>MMP20</italic> gene would result in thin and brittle enamel layer (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Caterina et al., 2002</xref>). Based on this result, they confirmed the hypothesis that mineralized teeth were lost or degenerated in the common ancestor of crown Mysticeti in the molecular level.</p>