<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We undertook a murine transplantational study using the dorsal skinfold chamber model. We saw, that there is a more severe change in gene expression profiles when comparing fat tissues gene expression before and after transplantation, than when comparing the gene expression profiles 7 days to 15 days after transplantation. This underlines the high impact transplantation has on the gene expression answer. Most changes were seen in the field of extracellular matrix and inflammation involved genes, being significantly upregulated, while energy metabolism linked gene and pathways were mostly downregulated. These findings substantiate the remodelling and inflammatory potential of adipose tissue and mirror genetic changes that have been described obese white adipose tissue showing an increased expression of genes encoding for ECM components [
 <xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Hence, there might be a similar development in obese white adipose tissue and transplanted lean adipose tissue. Studies revealed that an increased activation of ECM goes along with an increased adipocyte death due to a restricted space within the tissue. What conclusions can be set for the fate of transplanted adipose tissue, if it shows similar remodelling events than obese white adipose tissue? With an increase of ECM and inflammation encoding genes the constitution of the transplanted tissue would further shift to a fibrotic tissue, losing adipocytes. “Previous histologic examination with haematoxylin and eosin staining of transplanted fat tissue revealed increasing fibrosis within the fat transplant [
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41–44</xref>] and a decrease of the adipocytes’ size and shape [
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. We verified these changes in HE staining of samples of transplanted adipose tissue within the dorsal skinfold 1, 7, and 15 days after transplantation supporting our observation regarding the up-regulation of ECM and fibrosis-related genes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0009">Figure 9</xref>).
</p>
