<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Immunolabelling of GluN2A, GluN2B and GluN2D subunits in the SDH and DDH of male and female rats. The CGRP+ marginal region of the SDH as well as the remaining DDH was outlined as described in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>. For immunoreactive quantification in subsequent figures, SDH and DDH staining (per area) were normalized to background (BG) signal in a boxed region of the immuno-negative dorsal column. A, bottom) Representative confocal images (20x objective) illustrating the fluorescence staining patterns for GluN2A (left), GluN2B (middle) and GluN2D (right) in male juvenile rats. Scale bar: 200 μm. A, top) Higher magnification insets illustrating the distribution of immunoreactivity in the marginal SDH for all three GluN2 subtypes. GluN2A immunoreactivity is uniformly distributed across the neuropil of the SDH and DDH laminae, while GluN2B and GluN2D signal is also widespread but with differential expression in SDH versus DDH laminae, with staining of both neuropil and cell bodies. Scale bar: 50 µm. B, bottom) Representative confocal images (20x objective) illustrating the fluorescence staining patterns for GluN2A (left), GluN2B (middle) and GluN2D (right) in female juvenile rats. Scale bar: 200 μm. A, top) Higher magnification insets illustrating the distribution of immunoreactivity in the marginal SDH for all three GluN2 subtypes. GluN2A immunoreactivity is distributed mainly in the neuropil of the SDH and DDH laminae, while GluN2B and GluN2D signal demonstrates staining of both neuropil and cell bodies in the SDH and DDH. Scale bar: 50 µm
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KCHL_A_1871205_F0002_OC" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KCHL_A_1871205_F0002_PB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </alternatives>
</fig>
