<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Selenium (Se) has many effects on the growth and development of plants. It regulates photosynthesis, respiration, enhances stress resistance, and attenuates the damage of free radicals, while also mitigating the toxic effects of heavy metals [
 <xref rid="B1-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The absorption and accretion of Se by various plants varies greatly. Cruciferous plants have a relatively strong ability to accumulate Se, followed by legumes and then cereals [
 <xref rid="B4-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The Se enrichment of crop plant mainly focuses on two aspects: one is to improve the Se content in plants during physiological cultivation by fertilization; the other is to acclimatize and breed the Se-enriched parents. Foliar Se application, soil treatment and seed dressing methods can be deployed to enrich plants with Se. However, each method has its own restrictions. Soil is the main source of nutrition in plants, as far as Se application in soil is concerned. A number of methods are implemented to enrich plants with Se (i.e., soil Se treatment, seed dressing and foliar Se fertilization). The effectiveness in Se absorption by rice can be distorted by many factors, such as Se content in the soil, Se forms, alkalinity/acidity of soil, and metal-ion interaction [
 <xref rid="B5-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, the success rate by the seed dressing Se application method is limited, and dosage is difficult to control. Moreover, this method found a significant difference in Se distribution in the various organs of rice plants, and relatively low Se content in rice grains [
 <xref rid="B8-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The fertilizer efficiency by foliar spray method is short—it cannot be applied in rainy or windy conditions. It also results in easy leaching by rainwater, leading to contamination of the surrounding environment. Moreover, the amount of foliar spray is difficult to control, and it is quickly lost from the surface of hydrophobic leaves. As it is difficult to transfer the sprayed element from the absorption site of the leaf to other parts of the plant, the spraying effects are rather poor. In addition, over-spraying of Se may result in poisoning of the plant. These are the obstacles that rice breeders face when they attempt Se-enrichment of their plants. About half of the world’s population consumes rice (
 <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) as a staple food. Thus, its biofortification by means of breeding is a long-lasting and comparatively riskless process. Rice genome is sequenced and studied more than other crops [
 <xref rid="B9-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In addition, the molecular mechanism of Se-enrichment in rice is unclear. However, there are limited studies on differential proteinic expression in crop plants with response to Se. Therefore, the need of the hour is to assess the natural proteinic response of rice towards Se-enrichment and to compare it with non-Se food.
</p>
