<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MIA-induced outcomes in adult offspring have been well characterized; however, mechanisms of initiation and progression of NDD-related brain pathology remain poorly defined. Poly(I:C) increases proinflammatory cytokines such as IL-1β, IL-6, CXCL1, and TNF-α in the maternal circulation (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Ballendine et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Dahlgren et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Hsiao and Patterson, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Meyer et al., 2006b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Meyer et al., 2006a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2007</xref>). Downstream pathological changes in the brains of offspring have been reported across cell types, from neurons to microglia, and these changes have been linked to perturbations in proliferation, migration, and maturation in the developing brain (
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Haida et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Shin Yim et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Soumiya et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2019</xref>). Recent studies have identified acute transcriptomic changes in fetal brain in mice and rats at single time-points (3–4 hr) following MIA, with significant overlap between transcriptome changes in the cortices of MIA-exposed offspring and those altered in the brains of children with ASD (
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Lombardo et al., 2018</xref>). Although MIA could cause a dynamic sequence of transcriptional changes in the fetal brain following acute exposure, no integrated picture of MIA-associated transcriptomic pathology exists that maps changes spanning from the initial acute response to MIA through birth. Here, we combined time-course transcriptomics with neuroanatomy to map changes in prenatal mouse cortical development following MIA induced by poly(I:C) injection at E12.5.
</p>
