<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">To identify biological pathways and processes impacted by DCVC treatment, gene set enrichment analyses were performed using GSEA software (Mootha et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2003</xref>; Subramanian et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2005</xref>). For each gene set within a specified Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB, RRID: SCR_016863, version 7.0) curated collection, we used GSEA pre-ranked analyses to compute permutation-based tests that calculate a Normalized Enrichment Score (NES) and statistical FDR (Benjamini and Hochberg 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1995</xref>; Liberzon et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2011</xref>). Additionally, the GSEA analyses returned a list of enriched genes for each gene set based on differential gene expression. The enriched gene list for a gene set was derived from all genes annotated to that gene set. Here, the hallmark gene set collection was used in the analyses because it represents well-defined biological pathways, processes and states with strong gene expression concordance and reduced redundancy often seen within other collections (Liberzon et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2015</xref>). To conduct separate analyses for HTR-8/SVneo cells and placental villous explants, 12,855 (HTR-8/SVneo) or 13,972 (villous explants) genes included in the differential gene expression tests, respectively, were pre-ranked according to the logFC value for each gene. All genes (regardless of FDR or log
 <sub>2</sub>fold change values) thus, cutoffs do not impact the enriched pathways. We used 1000 permutations to test for enrichment within each of the hallmark gene sets. Because our genes were ranked based on logFC values, the magnitude of the NES above or below 0 corresponds directly with DCVC-induced up-regulation or down-regulation, respectively, of an enriched pathway or process. Gene sets representing an FDR &lt; 0.05 were considered significantly enriched (positive or negative).
</p>
