<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is well known that the boundary diffusion of elements is much faster than the volume diffusion [
 <xref rid="B36-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Cold deformation can produce seriously distorted ferrite grains containing either dense dislocations or dislocation cells [
 <xref rid="B37-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Cold deformation generates a large amount of thermal stress, which raises the temperature of the sample. Hence, the presence of these LAGBs is beneficial to the diffusion of elements, such as carbon and chromium, accelerating the coarsening of cementite [
 <xref rid="B37-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Several research groups [
 <xref rid="B38-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] reported that cementite has a tendency to precipitate and coarsen along the boundaries of pre-austenite, martensite, and sub-grain. Thus, the dissolution and coarsening of cementite occur simultaneously during cold deformation. In the current case, LAGBs with a high density had already been introduced into the region close to the surface of the cold rolled plate due to the inhomogeneous strain distribution throughout the normal direction of the plate (see the FE simulation results). With the propagation of deformation/strain, small cementite particles dissolved, while the larger ones became even larger, leaving the undissolved cementite at the ferritic LAGBs. The substantive characteristics of the coarsening process of cementite showed that large particles swallowed up small ones. Moreover, the coarsening process was associated with a decrease in interface energy between cementite and matrix, as the dissolution of cementite particles was useful to decrease the interface area per unit volume. However, carbon concentration in the matrix increased with the dissolution of cementite and reached a saturation state in the end [
 <xref rid="B21-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In order to reduce the interfacial energy, the remaining cementite particles were coarsened, and the coarsening process of cementite particles during cold deformation was similar to that of Ostwald ripening [
 <xref rid="B32-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In general, the coarsening of cementite was promoted by a long holding duration at high temperatures. Obviously, cold working accelerated this process so that it occurred at lower temperatures and short durations, as demonstrated in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot1dot2-materials-12-04136">Section 3.1.2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot1dot4-materials-12-04136">Section 3.1.4</xref>, and 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot1dot5-materials-12-04136">Section 3.1.5</xref>.
</p>
