<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">While not as important as microsite, burrow age also affected some vegetation properties. Fresh burrows supported simpler plant communities, with lower species richness and vegetation cover, than older burrows in the semi-arid savannah and in the mesic grassland. This likely reflects that at fresh burrows disturbances only recently ceased (or were possibly still occurring), and that few species were able to withstand the associated mechanical damage. Once burrowing (and all associated disturbances) stops, more species are able to establish and burrows start providing microhabitat benefits, reflected in species richness increasing after abandonment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, at fresh burrows the negative effects of constant disturbances (e.g. uprooting and burial) outweigh the positives provided by the burrows (e.g. through reduced competition and/or altered microclimatic conditions)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. As a result, the vegetation composition of abandoned burrows is expected to gradually become more similar to surrounding undisturbed vegetation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>, although, in some cases, as burrows get older differences in vegetation composition may persist
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. These changes in vegetation properties through time are probably not related to changing abiotic conditions as soil properties was not related to burrow age. In contrast, changes in vegetation with burrow age likely reflects successional processes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>, driven by differential colonization rates of different plant groups
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. Burrowing therefore, through small-scale biogemorphological disturbances, appears to create conditions that differ from undisturbed surrounding areas, driving a dynamic mosaic of microhabitats in the landscape differing in abiotic conditions and successional stage, thereby contributing to greater spatial and temporal heterogeneity within an environment.
</p>
