<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="Par32">This research suggests that biogeomorphic ecosystem engineers do not necessarily have a stronger impact in abiotically-extreme environments (also see ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>), and that the impacts of ecosystem engineers may be site-specific<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Indeed, it was expected that the impact of burrowing would be greater in drylands, where productivity is low<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> and resources are more limiting<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. However, in this study, burrowing mammals had a greater effect on vegetation in the mesic environment than in the semi-arid environment. Furthermore, in the same way that the impacts of aardvark are inconsistent across environments, other ecosystem engineers may potentially also have inconsistent effects across their geographical distribution and potentially even within individual habitats. Site-specific impacts of ecosystem engineers may be related to environmental conditions, with the magnitude of the impact of ecosystem engineers possibly being stronger in environments where ecosystem engineers alter abiotic conditions to a greater extent than other abiotic and biotic processes and where biotic communities respond strongly to abiotic changes as a result of ecosystem engineering<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup>. However, few studies have determined if the impacts of organisms with similar engineering roles vary across (or within) environments (although see ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>). As a result, there is a need to understand when ecosystem engineering is context-dependent or (relatively) context-independent, and therefore how predictable the ecological impacts of ecosystem engineering may be.</p>