<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Besides its effects on glucose metabolism, the insulin-sensitizing drug metformin displayed anti-cancer effects in various cancer types [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], including EC [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Metabolic diseases like type II diabetes mellitus and obesity, together with increased unopposed estrogen levels, as seen in anovulatory women with PCOS as well as in women with prolonged reproductive phases including early menarche and late menopause, are known risk factors for EC development [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Metformin sensitizes the body to insulin effects and decreases hepatic gluconeogenesis 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, consequently leading to a reduction and thus to a normalization of blood glucose levels [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In the present study, the direct effects of metformin on protein expression in the human EC cell line HEC-1A were investigated using an affinity proteomic approach. Insulin treatment was incorporated into the study in order to implement a model for insulin resistance, defined as normoglycemia reached by hyperinsulinemia, a condition often observed in obese and prediabetic patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Additionally, cells were treated in the presence of E2 to mimic increased estrogen levels, a common risk factor for EC development. Protein lysates of HEC-1A cells were collected 7 d after repeated administration of 0.5 mmol/L metformin or 100 ng/mL insulin and subjected to the scioDiscover antibody microarray targeting 1,300 different proteins. The aim of this study was to perform a proteomic screening after metformin as well as insulin treatment and to identify changes in protein expression that potentially contribute to the anti-cancer effects and the mechanism of action of the biguanide drug in EC.
</p>
