<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some proteins were regulated by metformin in a favorable way regarding tumor suppression and growth inhibition compared to untreated EC cells (
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), while they were not changed in regards to hyperinsulinemia. The following proteins were significantly downregulated by metformin, while no significant changes were detected in a hyperinsulinemic environment compared to the control: cyclin D2 (CCND2), cluster of differentiation 63 (CD63), CD81, interleukin-17A (IL17A), interferon regulatory factor 4 (IRF4), and V-set domain containing T cell activation inhibitor 1 (VTCN1, B7-H4). Downregulation of CCND2, a protein known to cause growth arrest in the G
 <sub>1</sub> cell cycle phase, and CD81, a protein relevant for membrane organization, protein trafficking, cellular fusion and cell-cell interactions, contributes to a decreased proliferation, tumor progression, migration, and invasion [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Downregulation of CD63, a tetraspanin involved in the regulation of membrane protein trafficking, leukocyte recruitment and adhesion, was found to reduce apoptosis inhibition as well as cell survival [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], and to suppress vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) signaling as well as related angiogenesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. In addition, metformin reduced the expression of several proteins related to immune responses, including VTCN1, a B7 family member involved in immune regulation, as well as IRF4, a regulator of lymphocyte growth and differentiation, leading to decreased tumor cell proliferation and metastasis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Furthermore, IL17A is involved in immune responses and inflammation [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], but also promotes migration and invasion in cancer cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Therefore, a metformin-induced downregulation of the cytokine has the potential to inhibit migration and invasion. Ambiguous results were obtained after metformin-induced downregulation of IL1B and IL2. IL1B not only activates antigen-presenting cells, thereby initiating an adaptive anti-tumor response, but also promotes tumor growth, metastasis as well as angiogenesis upon activation by tumor-infiltrating macrophages. Therefore, downregulation of IL1B may decrease carcinogenesis and metastasis, but may also be able to block adaptive anti-tumor responses. Hence, IL1B-blocking drugs such as anakinra and canakinumab are currently investigated as cancer therapeutics [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. The cytokine IL2 is important for growth of T cells and natural killer cells, despite its regulatory effect in cell cycle progression and tumor cell growth [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. On the one hand, downregulation of IL2 has been associated with decreased proliferation and carcinogenesis. On the other hand, no survival benefits were observed after administration of IL2 in metastatic renal cancer and melanoma, although the cytokine had led to a regression of metastatic tumors [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Therefore, the consequences of metformin treatment and hyperinsulinemia for the cellular fate are difficult to assess for these two interleukins and need to be further investigated to allow for clear conclusions.
</p>
