<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The following proteins were changed in a favorable way regarding tumor suppression and inhibition of invasiveness particularly under the influence of insulin (
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>) and to a lesser extent by metformin in comparison to untreated control cells: collagen type I alpha 1 chain (COL1A1), and insulin receptor substrate 2 (IRS2). COL1A1, the major component of collagen type I, which, in turn, constitutes the main structural ECM protein, promotes cell migration and metastasis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Thus, downregulation of the ECM component, as found to be induced by both insulin and metformin in the present study, is considered as a desired effect. IRS2, a cytoplasmic adaptor protein, mediates the effects of insulin as well as IGF1 and therefore plays a role in growth-promoting IGF1 receptor (IGF1R) signaling. Overexpression is associated with increased glucose metabolism and tumor invasion as well as decreased overall survival and disease progression in patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Therefore, the downregulation of IRS2 by hyperinsulinemia lowered tumor invasion and metastasis in the present study, which has also been proven in an obese and diabetic mouse model [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Ambiguous results were obtained for carcinoembryonic antigen-related cell adhesion molecule 8 (CEACAM8) that was expressed in higher amounts after insulin supplementation. CEACAM8, a cell adhesion molecule expressed on the surface of neutrophilic granulocytes, has been associated with poor prognosis and decreased survival in patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. However, when bound to CEACAM6, upregulation of the CEACAM6/8 complex has been related to inhibition of vascular invasion and cell proliferation [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Little is known about the role of CEACAM8 in cancer [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], making it hard to assess the consequences of an insulin-induced CEACAM8 upregulation.
</p>
