<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Besides the above-mentioned helpful effects observed in a hyperinsulinemic environment, elevated insulin levels also promoted a series of unfavorable changes (
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>) in EC cell protein expression, including the upregulation of autocrine motility factor receptor (AMFR), FAS-associated factor 1 (FAF1), membrane palmitoylated protein 3 (MPP3), enzyme 1-phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate (PIP
 <sub>2</sub>) phosphodiesterase gamma-2 (PLCG2, phospholipase Cγ2), sortilin-related receptor 1 (SORL1), secreted phosphoprotein 1 (SPP1, osteopontin (OSTP)), VEGFA, and wingless-type MMTV integration site family member 2B (WNT2B). AMFR, a cell surface receptor for AMF, is involved in many processes including cell motility, and AMFR upregulation has been related to enhanced tumor invasion and migration [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. WNT2B is involved in different cellular processes, including tumorigenesis, and WNT2B overexpression has been correlated with cancer progression and metastasis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Likewise, upregulation of MPP3, a membrane protein involved in cytoskeleton organization and regulation of cell proliferation, signal transduction, and intracellular tight junctions has been associated with enhanced cell migration and invasion [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. PLCG2 catalyzes the hydrolysis of PIP
 <sub>2</sub> to form diacylglycerol (DAG) and inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate (IP
 <sub>3</sub>), being important 2
 <sup>nd</sup> messenger molecules that activate protein kinase C (PKC). PKC, in turn, is involved in signal transduction related to proliferation, differentiation, growth, and motility, among others [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Downregulation of PLCG2 led to decreased cellular viability and proliferation in an 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> model [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>], and therefore it is likely that a hyperinsulinemia-mediated PLCG2 upregulation promoted cell proliferation. Overexpression of SPP1, a protein involved in ECM adhesion during wound healing, is also associated with cancer progression, metastasis, and apoptosis inhibition [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>], just like an upregulation of the transmembrane sorting protein SORL1 that promotes cell proliferation in cancer cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. VEGFA mediates angiogenesis and vasculogenesis by regulation of endothelial cells and acts as a pro-survival factor of endothelial cells during tumor angiogenesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. VEGFA overexpression, as seen after insulin supplementation in the present study, increased angiogenesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>], while downregulation of VEGFA was not only found to inhibit cell proliferation, migration as well as invasion, but also to promote apoptosis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. Another unfavorable effect of hyperinsulinemia was identified by a downregulation of FAF1 in the present study, which was found to increase tumorigenesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>], as FAF1 plays a role in various biological processes including apoptosis [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. As metformin reduces peripheral hyperinsulinemia 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, the drug might be able to counteract the observed negative insulin effects when administered to patients with high levels of the pancreatic hormone. In addition, metformin acted on the expression of the discussed proteins in the opposite, more favorable way in the present study.
</p>
