<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several proteins have been expressed significantly different during metformin treatment and hyperinsulinemia, of which AMFR, CCND2, CD63, CEACAM8, CTSL, GFAP, GUSB, IRF4, PI3, PLCG2, SORL1, TFRC, VEGFA, VTCN1, and WNT2B have already been discussed above. Further proteins, that did not show high changes compared to untreated control samples (|log
 <sub>2</sub>FC| &lt; 0.5), but displayed highly significant differences (
 <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.001) among both treatments will now be discussed in more detail (
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>). Changes in protein expression by metformin treatment displayed advantages over a hyperinsulinemic environment for the following proteins: erythroblastic oncogene B2 receptor tyrosine kinase 3 (ERBB3, human epidermal growth factor receptor 3 (HER3)), ezrin (EZR), and transmembrane 9 superfamily member 2 (TM9SF2). ERBB3 is a member of the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) family and is directly involved in the pro-proliferative PI3K signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. EZR is responsible for the linkage of the plasma membrane to the actin cytoskeleton and plays a key role in adhesion and migration [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Little is known about the functions of TM9SF2 to date, but it is proposed to act as a channel or transporter [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Overexpression of ERBB3, EZR, and TM9SF2 has been associated with cancer progression, increased proliferation and metastasis or poor survival [
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248103.ref125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. All three proteins were slightly downregulated after metformin administration, but upregulated in a hyperinsulinemic environment, with significant changes between both treatments. Therefore, metformin treatment is likely to promote anti-proliferative effects by the regulation of these proteins.
</p>
