<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f037">Figure 37</xref> shows a TEM bright-field micrograph of a rod-shaped precipitate embedded in an Al matrix. The corresponding SAED pattern of the [001] Al zone axis is shown in the inset. Additional superlattice reflections initiated from the rod precipitate in the SAED pattern are visible. Rod- and lath-shaped precipitates show similar diffraction patterns in the [001] Al zone axis. Since parts of the diffraction pattern initiated from the rod-/lath-shaped precipitates are located at the &lt;100&gt; positions of the aluminium matrix, these precipitates are coherent with the Al matrix along this direction. The diffraction pattern of the [001] zone axis of Al indicates superlattice reflections (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f037">Figure 37</xref>) that are very similar to those reported in the literature for the same kind of precipitates [
 <xref rid="B174-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>,
 <xref rid="B175-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B176-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>,
 <xref rid="B177-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>,
 <xref rid="B179-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>]. However, the interpretation of these results differs significantly between authors. While the authors of Refs. [
 <xref rid="B174-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>,
 <xref rid="B176-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>,
 <xref rid="B177-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>] suggest a hexagonal structure based on the TEM diffraction pattern, the authors of Refs. [
 <xref rid="B179-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>] report a monoclinic structure determined from similar diffraction images. Furthermore, it has been found that both the hexagonal and the monoclinic crystal structure of these precipitates build upon the same Si-based network structure [
 <xref rid="B179-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>]. Due to the coherence of the rod- and lath-shaped precipitates observed along the &lt;100&gt; direction of the aluminium matrix, at least one lattice parameter is known (0.405 nm), which is in agreement with the reported values of the hexagonal structure for β’ (a = 0.705 nm, c = 0.405 nm) and B’ (a = 1.03 nm, c = 0.405 nm) [
 <xref rid="B174-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>,
 <xref rid="B175-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B176-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>,
 <xref rid="B177-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>]. According to [
 <xref rid="B5-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], both types of precipitates, β’ and B’, can exist concurrently, although B’ occurs particularly at high Si:Mg ratios. Hence, it can be assumed that the low-temperature precipitates are β’ and/or B’. A recent work [
 <xref rid="B180-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>] confirms the quench-induced precipitation of the hexagonal β’ phase during the LTR due to a combination of cooling DSC, TEM, EDS and SAED in an Mn-rich dispersoid-containing model alloy with a composition of Al-0.67Si-0.84Mg-0.35Mn-0.25Fe (mass fraction in %).
</p>
