<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Al0.6Mg0.8Si, the HTRs are dominant over the entire range of cooling rates, and it can be concluded that the equilibrium phase β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si is primarily precipitated. However, the nucleation mechanism of β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si in the pure ternary Al0.6Mg0.8Si remains unclear. Compared to the commercial variant, substantially reduced LTRs are seen for the pure alloy, and this is probably due to the reduced number of nucleation sites. A direct comparison at about 0.1 K/s shows that for the commercial 6082
 <sub>I</sub>, quench-induced precipitation is clearly dominated by the LTR, while quench-induced precipitation for Al0.6Mg0.8Si is dominated by the HTR. For cooling rates higher than 0.5 K/s in Al0.6Mg0.8Si, barely any reaction can be seen in DSC, whereas for 6082
 <sub>I</sub> the LTRs are still well above the DSC detection limit and the total specific precipitation enthalpy still amounts to about 5 J/g for 0.5 K/s (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f042">Figure 42</xref>C). Although both alloys can achieve the same maximum hardness, this maximum is reached at substantially different cooling rates. A comparison of 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f042">Figure 42</xref>C,D shows that the UCCRs of these two alloys differ by a factor of ≈20, which quantifies the influence of an addition of an atomic fraction of ≈0.35% Fe+Mn to a medium AlMgSi alloy. This factor may of course may also depend in detail on the particular distribution size of the dispersoid particles and therefore on the homogenisation treatment [
 <xref rid="B48-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. It is also interesting to note from 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f042">Figure 42</xref> that the solvus temperature of these two alloys differs. For cooling at a rate of 0.003 K/s, the onset of quench-induced precipitation for Al0.6Mg0.8Si is about 510 °C, while for 6082
 <sub>I</sub> it is about 475 °C. It can be assumed that Si is partially bound in the eutectic primary phases and dispersoids, thus reducing the Si solute concentration at the end of the solution treatment and thereby the solvus temperature. This assumption is supported by the total specific precipitation enthalpy, for which Δh
 <sub>Al0.6Mg0.8Si</sub> &gt; Δh 
 <sub>6082I</sub> holds during very slow cooling. The abovementioned differences in the nucleation of the equilibrium β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si phase (commercial alloy: coarse primary particles enriched in Fe, Mn, Si; lab alloys: unclear) suggest that the HTR-quench-induced precipitates nucleate more easily in commercial alloys. However, the higher precipitation onset temperature for Al0.6Mg0.8Si hints at the dominating influence of a higher amount of solved alloying elements, particularly Si, on precipitation onset in the stable phases. The opposite behaviour is seen for the LTR, which is obviously much more strongly influenced by nucleation promoted in the presence of dispersoids. In other words, in the pure ternary alloy, quench-induced precipitation is clearly dominated by the precipitation of β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si, which precipitates as low aspect ratio particles at high temperatures and slow cooling rates (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f043">Figure 43</xref>). However, β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si particles are also found as high aspect ratio particles, which probably form during the second stage of the HTRs. As can be seen from 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f042">Figure 42</xref>B, the HTR peak during slow cooling has a shoulder at about 400 °C. This could indicate the separation of the precipitation regimes for these particle morphology types. A comparison of the OM image of the sample cooled at 0.01 K/s in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f043">Figure 43</xref> with the DSC cooling curve at the same rate in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f042">Figure 42</xref> indicates that both particle shapes are present after completion of the HTRs, as no LTRs occur during cooling at 0.01 K/s. The high aspect ratio particles identified after cooling at 0.01 K/s reach lengths of up to ≈50 µm.
</p>
