<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cavazos and Colás obtained a CCP diagram for 6063 from Jominy-like bar-end-quench tests [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. They measured the actual cooling rates achieved at different distances of the quench bar end (see the example in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f032">Figure 32</xref>A for a distance of 5.5 cm). The characteristic transformation temperatures were evaluated from the inflection points of the cooling rate curve shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f032">Figure 32</xref>B. Using this approach, these authors were able to construct a CCP diagram. The 6063 variant considered in Ref. [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] contained mass fractions of 0.50% Si, 0.52% Mg, 0.21% Fe and 0.022% Cu, i.e., very similar to our 6063 variant [
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. The CCP diagrams obtained in Refs. [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and [
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>] are compared in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f033">Figure 33</xref>. Although the 6063 variant in [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] showed slightly faster quench-induced precipitation, it can be seen that the nose temperature is very similar. Considering the sequence of HTR and LTR, it can be concluded that the DSC data are much more detailed, and cover a substantially wider cooling rate range. The authors of Ref. [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] found the UCCR of 6063 to be ≈10 K/s [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], while in Ref. [
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>] an UCCR of only 1 K/s was found. The higher UCCR of the 6063 variant analysed in Ref. [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] compared to that of Ref. [
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>] again shows that the quench sensitivity of different batches of alloys that are nominally the same may be substantially different.
</p>
