<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To identify these overlapping microstructural reactions, a relatively large body of work is available, e.g., [
 <xref rid="B23-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B170-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>,
 <xref rid="B171-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>,
 <xref rid="B172-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>,
 <xref rid="B173-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f035">Figure 35</xref> illustrates the authors’ own work on quench-induced precipitation in 6005A at different cooling rates, showing optical micrographs (A), SEM secondary electron images (B) and TEM bright-field images (C) after cooling from solution treatment to the ambient temperature at different rates. It can clearly be seen from 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f035">Figure 35</xref>A,B that precipitates with lower aspect ratio (appearing dark) become substantially smaller as the cooling rate rises. These HTR-quench-induced precipitates are β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si phase particles, which partially precipitate at grain boundaries and mainly precipitate inside the grains (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f035">Figure 35</xref>A,B). The fcc structure of β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si has been proven by electron backscatter diffraction (EBSD) and X-ray diffraction (XRD) analysis [
 <xref rid="B116-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. At a cooling rate of 0.16 K/s, hardly any quench-induced precipitation is seen in OM and SEM; however, at this cooling rate, a large number of rod-like quench-induced precipitates with much higher aspect ratios is found in TEM (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f035">Figure 35</xref>C). The lengths of these rod- and lath-shaped secondary precipitates were observed to decrease from about 600 nm after cooling at 0.16 K/s to about 300 nm at a cooling rate of 1.6 K/s.
</p>
