<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One class of commonly taken over the counter, and also widely prescribed, analgesics are non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), which inhibit cyclooxygenase (COX) enzymes to reduce prostaglandin production and thus relieve pain by preventing the sensitizing effects of prostaglandins upon sensory neurones. However, it has also been shown that COX-independent mechanisms exist that contribute to the analgesic effect of NSAIDs [
 <xref rid="cit0170" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. The Lazdunski lab observed that inflammation of rat hindpaws significantly upregulated the mRNA levels of some ASIC subunits (ASIC1a, ASIC2b, and ASIC3) in rat DRG neurones and that this could largely be suppressed by corticosteroids, as well as by some NSAIDS [
 <xref rid="cit0129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. They further investigated if there were any direct effects of NSAIDs on ASIC subunits when expressed in CHO cells and observed that certain NSAIDs, at high micromolar concentrations, could inhibit ASIC currents in a somewhat isoform-selective manner. Interestingly, salicylic acid (IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 260 ± 21 μM, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5a</xref>), aspirin (IC
 <sub>50</sub> not specified, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5b</xref>), and diclofenac (IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 92 ± 19 μM, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5c</xref>) inhibited the sustained current component of ASIC3 but not the transient component, whereas the ASIC1a current was inhibited by ibuprofen (IC
 <sub>50</sub> not specified) and flurbiprofen (IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 349 ± 40 μM) only. A range of other NSAIDs, namely piroxicam, etodolac, nimesulide, naproxen indomethacin and acetaminophen had no effect on either ASIC1a or ASIC3. However, subsequent work from Pless lab established that ibuprofen and some of its analogues could inhibit the transient currents of ASIC3 albeit with very weak potency, i.e. ibuprofen had an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 51.3 mM (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5d</xref>) at pH 6.4 [
 <xref rid="cit0171" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>]. Using site-directed mutagenesis, they identified a region comprising the upper of transmembrane helices and extracellular domain β9-α4 loop of rASIC1a to be the main site of ibuprofen binding. Most of the key residues identified for ibuprofen recognition are largely conserved across rASIC1a, rASIC1b, and rASIC2a, but rASIC3 has different residues in two key positions namely Thr in place of Lys76 (K76T) and has Ala in place of a critical Lys (K422A). It is intriguing to note that despite these amino acid differences, ibuprofen’s potency for inhibiting the ASIC3 peak current was comparable to that for inhibiting ASIC1a (IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 29.5 mM), which suggests that other binding regions are likely involved. 
</p>
