<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since ataxia-telangiectasia, mutated (ATM) protein kinase is required for optimal p53 induction after IR [
 <xref rid="B9-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], we asked whether ATM was involved in this IR-induced splicing event. Using an inhibitor of ATM kinase activity that had been characterized by our laboratory [
 <xref rid="B10-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], we found that exposure of cells to this kinase inhibitor induced, rather than inhibited, the generation of p53β. This observation led us to demonstrate that the induction of p53β after IR arose from the suppression of kinase activity of the ATM-related phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase-related kinase (PIKK) family member hSMG1. In addition, consistent with the observation that the binding of RPL26 to p53β RNA increases after IR, we found that RPL26 was also required for IR-induced alternative splicing of p53 pre-mRNA to p53β RNA. As RPL26 binds to p53 pre-mRNA after IR, it recruits the RNA splicing factor SRSF7, which is then able to induce the alternative splicing of p53 pre-mRNA to produce p53β mRNA. This series of protein–RNA binding changes is initiated by the IR-induced suppression of hSMG1 kinase activity and the selective release of hSMG1 from the exon/intron 9 region of p53 pre-mRNA. The release of hSMG1 from this site in p53 pre-mRNA then permits the binding of RPL26/SRSF7 to this same region of the RNA and leads to the alternative splicing that generates p53β mRNA. The induction of p53β after IR appeared to selectively regulate IR-induced cellular senescence (see below), establishing a specific physiologic signaling pathway and role for one of the p53 isoforms [
 <xref rid="B8-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This represented a novel arm of the DNA damage signaling pathway (DDR) and was consistent with reported links of alternative splicing to both cancer [
 <xref rid="B13-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and aging [
 <xref rid="B14-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A schema summarizing the steps involved in the IR-induced alternative splicing of p53 RNA to generate p53β RNA is illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cancers-13-00251-f001">Figure 1</xref>.
</p>
