<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The origin of the EXAFS signal is the interactions between the photoelectron excited from a deep core level of the absorbing atom by an incident X-ray photon, with the electrostatic potentials of neighboring atoms. The presence of neighboring atoms perturbs slightly the absorption probability, resulting in the oscillatory structure of the absorption coefficient μ(
 <italic>E</italic>) on top of smooth variations of the absorption probability μ
 <sub>0</sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>) that are not related to the sample structure, 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>a. Commonly, the normalization of the EXAFS component χ(
 <italic>E</italic>) is carried out as
 <disp-formula id="eq5">
  <graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m005" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>5</label>
 </disp-formula>where μ(
 <italic>E</italic>) is the experimentally measured spectrum, and μ
 <sub>0</sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>) is the smooth background function that can be constructed by smoothing the experimental signal via polynomial fitting or spline interpolation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> Δμ
 <sub>0</sub>(
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>) is the absorption jump value, calculated as the difference between two smooth functions that describe the background before the absorption edge (pre-edge region) and after the absorption edge (postedge region), respectively, calculated at the reference energy value 
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>
 </sup> As discussed above, 
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> corresponds to the minimal necessary energy required to excite the photoelectron to a delocalized state. Commonly, the maximum point of the first derivative of μ(
 <italic>E</italic>) is used as the approximation for the 
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> value, although other conventions also may be employed. Next, the EXAFS signal is converted from energy space to photoelectron wavenumber (
 <italic>k</italic>-) space by using the relation:
 <disp-formula id="eq6">
  <graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m006" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>6</label>
 </disp-formula>Here 
 <italic>ℏ</italic> is Planck’s constant, and 
 <italic>m</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub> is the electron mass. As an example, 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>b shows Cu K-edge EXAFS spectra for oxidized Cu NPs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>
 </sup> The choice of background fitting procedure and the 
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> value selected can affect the appearance of the EXAFS features significantly, especially at low 
 <italic>k</italic>-values, and therefore, it should be carried out systematically for all spectra in the analyzed series.
</p>
