<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The material-specific terms in 
 <xref rid="eq8" ref-type="disp-formula">eq 
  <xref rid="eq8" ref-type="disp-formula">8</xref>
 </xref> (
 <italic>S</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>
 <sup arrange="stagger">2</sup>, 
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>k</italic>,
 <italic>R</italic>), λ(
 <italic>k</italic>), ϕ
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>k</italic>,
 <italic>R</italic>)) describe the interactions of the X-ray-excited photoelectron with other electrons and atoms within the material and are discussed below. The key characteristics of the local structure of the material, however, are captured by 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>R</italic>), which expresses the probability density to find an atom of a given type at a distance 
 <italic>R</italic> from the absorbing atom. RDF contains information about the number of nearest neighbors, interatomic distances, and degree of structural disorder. In particular, the number of atoms of a given type within the distance interval between 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> is given by an integral:
 <disp-formula id="eq9">
  <graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m009" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>9</label>
 </disp-formula>Partial 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>R</italic>) functions corresponding to Cu–O and Cu–Cu RDFs in copper(II) oxide are shown in 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>d.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>
 </sup> The width of the 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>R</italic>) features is determined by the structural disorder. Note here that due to the very short lifetime of the excitation created by the incident X-ray photon (∼1 fs), which is much shorter than the characteristic atomic thermal vibration times (on the order of picoseconds), EXAFS probes the “frozen” snapshot of the structure (averaged over all absorbing atoms) and does not distinguish between atomic deviations due to static distortions and dynamic thermal motion.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
