<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">Cancer is one of the leading causes of human mortality; according to the World Health Organization (WHO), it ranked sixth among the top 10 causes of global death in 2016 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/the-top-10-causes-of-death" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/the-top-10-causes-of-death</ext-link>). Although a measurable number of cancers are both preventable and treatable, no anticancer drug or method has yet been developed to prevent and treat cancers effectively without affecting normal cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. Over many years, researchers worldwide have made extensive and rigorous efforts to identify and develop such drugs. Breast cancer is the most common cancer in women. It is estimated that more than 508,000 women worldwide died from breast cancer in 2011 (WHO, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/cancer/detection/breastcancer/en/index1.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/cancer/detection/breastcancer/en/index1.html</ext-link>), and about 42,170 women have died from the disease so far in 2020 in the USA (American Cancer Society, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/breast-cancer/about/how-common-is-breast-cancer.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cancer.org/cancer/breast-cancer/about/how-common-is-breast-cancer.html</ext-link>). The disease affects both developed and developing countries similarly
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>. The survival rates among breast cancer patients with the current remedies are low and vary by country, ranging from 40 to 80%
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>. The worldwide incidence has been increasing by 0.3% per year
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
