<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Insulin is well-characterized as a key regulator of blood glucose levels in vertebrates (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Insulin related peptides have also been identified in a number of other metazoan species and have been shown to contribute to various aspects of physiology in these species (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The discovery of insulin 100 years ago, led to a revolution in clinical medicine, as it allowed an effective treatment for diabetes (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Since its discovery, the treatment of diabetes using insulin, derivatives of insulin, and other peptides has and continues to evolve (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). There still is no cure. In addition to its critical role in the history of clinical medicine, insulin has played key roles in the development of many revolutionary technologies that are now commonplace in molecular biology, including protein sequencing (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) and the deduction of the three-dimensional structures of proteins (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). A key discovery made with insulin, but with important implications for many other bioactive peptides, is the role of proteolytic processing in regulating its biological action (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Since the sequencing of human insulin more than 60 years ago (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), a large number of insulin protein sequences have been determined due to its importance in medicine, as well as its small size and relative ease at isolation (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Over the past 20 years, as we entered the genomic era, an increasing number of insulin sequences have been predicted from the complete genome sequences of organisms. Genomic sequences have led to improvements of our understanding of not only human genetics and disease (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), but also nearly all other areas of biology (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The new insulin sequences identified from genome sequences have revealed an increased diversity in the number of insulin genes within species and has revealed that changes in the proteolysis processing of the proinsulin precursor likely contributes to the diversity of the biological actions of insulin.</p>