<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, the role of protein modifications in MtzR has been inferred through differential expression of their modifying enzymes [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] rather than modified substrates. Our results indicate that multiple proteins within MtzR lines are differentially modified by ubiquitination, phosphorylation, methylation, and acetylation on multiple protein substrates. These modification marks varied in intensity and detectability within MtzR lines (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). This is significant if increases in these modifications are in site occupancy unaccompanied by increased protein abundance, as it would indicate regulation independent of expression levels. Probes for ubiquitin revealed 3 common protein bands that increased in MtzR lines, including free ubiquitin, and a fourth band that increased in 713- and 106-MtzR lines only (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). Seven ubiquitination and proteasome-related proteins were differentially expressed across MtzR lines, 6 of which were in WB-MtzR. This correlates in WB-MtzR with significant differential expression of both ribosomal proteins as well as ribosomal transcripts [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], indicating a potential for heightened demand of protein production to compensate for turnover of damaged proteins. Ubiquitination blots were highly congruent between isolates and lines, although only major protein bands were detected and lower abundance proteins may not have been detected. As mono-ubiquitinated proteins are associated with proteasome-independent processes, including gene transcription, while poly-ubiquitinated proteins are more likely to be associated with proteolysis and proteasome-degradation [
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>], analysis of the states of ubiquitination in MtzR lines would allow further extrapolation of the role of this modification in resistance.
</p>
