<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Giardia</italic> has a uniquely reduced core kinome and a significantly expanded NEK kinome that consist of 80 and 278 kinases, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Our results indicated that both core and NEK kinases were differentially expressed and significantly enriched during functional clustering within MtzR lines. To survey changes to the phosphoproteome, we examined tyrosine phosphorylation and serine/threonine phosphorylation in the conserved 14–3-3 binding motif [(R/K)XX(s/t)XP] via Western blot. 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> has a single 14–3-3 homologue with 314 documented protein substrates [
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Immunodetection of the 14–3-3 motif revealed multiple novel and increased intensity protein features in MtzR lines relative to the isogenic parents (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). However, our protein expression data showed that although 60.8% of known 14–3-3 substrates were detected among identified proteins, only 18.2% were among differentially expressed proteins, implying that the stoichiometric balance between modified and unmodified protein isomers is more variable than substrate abundance. Western blots of pY reinforce observations of Manning et al. [
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] that despite the absence of canonical tyrosine kinases or tyrosine-kinase like (TKL) kinases in the 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> genome, pY is readily detectable and abundant across the proteome (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>, panel B). MtzR lines were quite congruent between isolates for pY and (excluding the unique pY profile of 106-MtzS) shared many features with their MtzS parents. With pY most likely to be catalyzed by dual-specificity serine-threonine kinases [
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], of which a wide range were differentially expressed in MtzR lines, including within the NEK kinase family, more work is required to define pY kinases in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic>.
</p>
