<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Acetylation (KAc) may be an important histone modification in MtzR; however our data reveal that KAc modifications occur and change on a wide range of protein substrates (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>, panel B). These changes appear linked to Mtz resistance, with all 3 MtzR lines showing increases in total KAc across a range of nonhistone proteins compared to their MtzS parents and cross-resistance to deacetylase inhibitor TSA (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>, panel A). This implies significant changes in lysine acetylase (KAT) or deacetylase (KDAC/HDAC) activity, which is further evidenced by differential KAc profiles and a lack of histone hyperacetylation in MtzR lines during TSA exposure (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>, panel B; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>). There are 5 lysine acetyltransferases (KATs) and 6 lysine deacetylases (KDACs) encoded by the 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> WB genome [
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], which include 5 nuclear (4 sirtuin [Sir2] KDACs and 1 NAD
 <sup>+</sup>-independent HDAC) and 1 cytostolic (a Sir2 KDAC) deacetylase in trophozoites [
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Although TSA is considered a class I and II, but not class III, (sirtuin) HDAC inhibitor, some 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> sirtuins have very low homology to mammalian families [
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] and more work is required to demonstrate that TSA specifically inhibits the single NAD
 <sup>+</sup>-independent HDAC in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic>. Furthermore, given changes in KAc in response to TSA were not confined to histone variants (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>, panel B; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>), HDAC substrates also require identification. In Ansell et al. [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], 4 of the 5 KATs were transcriptionally downregulated in 713-MtzR, along with numerous N-acetyltransferases. Among K/HDACs, the cytosolic Sir2 (10 708) is significantly upregulated at the transcript [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and protein levels in WB-MtzR, and the NAD
 <sup>+</sup>-independent deacetylase (HDAC) is upregulated at the protein level in 106-MtzR [
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Sir2 KDACs are linked to increased longevity, antioxidant gene expression, and cell cycle regulation in yeast during oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], while sirtuins in high eukaryotes are known to ameliorate oxidative stress by deacetylating enzymes and increasing their antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]; similar diverse KAc regulation may function in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> in MtzR lines.
</p>
