<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> genome encodes a highly reduced methylation network, with 6 histone lysine methyltransferases, but no canonical arginine methyltransferases or demethylases [
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>], and 3 methylation states (mono-, di-, and tri-methylation) observed on 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> histone variants [
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. This significant reduction of the methylation network may explain the high IC
 <sub>50</sub> of the broad-spectrum histone lysine methyltransferase chaetocin (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S6</xref>), which is significantly more effective in mammalian systems [
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Substrates of lysine methylation beyond histones are unknown, although our results have demonstrated K-MMe is an extensive modification network in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> trophozoites (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Fig. 5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>, panel B). Protein methylation modifications do not neutralize the substrate amino acid charge, as in acetylation and phosphorylation, or produce a significant mass shift as in ubiquitination. However, methylation still influences accessibility of protein–protein interactions and binding, particularly in gene regulation, where multiple methylation states are observed on histones, transcription factors, and DNA-modifying enzymes [
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. All 3 MtzR lines showed increases overall in total K-MMe (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>), with many features unique to each isolate or line. Three and 2 of the 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> histone methyltransferases, which were below detection in our proteomic dataset, are differentially transcribed in 713- and WB-MtzR relative to MtzS parental lines [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Conversely, in 106-MtzR, these enzymes are unchanged at the transcriptional level. However, at the protein level, these enzymes displays upregulation of a putative S-adenosylmethionine-dependent methyltransferase and 2 FtSJ rRNA methyltransferases. Although we can confirm lysine methylation as a correlate of MtzR across the proteome, substrate identities are now required.
</p>
