<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As described above, a comprehensive understanding of the microstructural changes in the alloys caused by cooling is crucial. As shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f012">Figure 12</xref>, the dimensions of quench-induced precipitates vary substantially and cover about five orders of magnitude. Thus, the use of a range of microscopes is required for imaging of the relevant precipitates. Coarse quench-induced precipitates originating from high temperatures and slow cooling rates can be imaged by OM [
 <xref rid="B112-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. OM images also allow us to evaluate the volume fractions of coarse quench-induced precipitation [
 <xref rid="B116-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B139-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>]. SEM (e.g., [
 <xref rid="B140-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]) allows imaging of coarser quench-induced precipitates. Imaging is typically done with either secondary electrons (SEs) or backscattered electrons (BSEs), the latter of which give better contrast for different atom masses. Analytical techniques integrated into SEM allow further valuable information to be acquired; for example, energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDS) enables the determination of the chemical composition of precipitates [
 <xref rid="B112-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>], while electron backscatter diffraction (EBSD) can reveal the crystal structure of coarse precipitates [
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. EDS always involves a compromise between spatial resolution and element-specific stimulation. A sufficient acceleration voltage is required for the EDS detection of alloying elements with heavier atomic masses; for example, the EDS detection of Zn typically requires an acceleration voltage of 25 kV [
 <xref rid="B112-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. However, this enlarges the interaction volume, and may make it larger than the particle of interest. Thus, in most cases, it is rarely possible to obtain EDS signals solely from the precipitate, and part of the stimulated and measured X-rays generally originates from the matrix [
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>].
</p>
