<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0230">Several multi-omic studies, including our previous trans-omic works, examined the effects of obesity on metabolism in human or animal models (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Kokaji et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Parks et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Soltis et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 2016</xref>). Soltis et al. performed epigenomic, transcriptomic, proteomic, and metabolomic analyses of liver from mice fed a normal or high-fat diet. Some of the differentially expressed molecules associated with high-fat diet in their study were consistent with our results from 
 <italic>ob</italic>/
 <italic>ob</italic> mice in previous study (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Kokaji et al., 2020</xref>) and the present study. In the amount of metabolite, GSH and lactate increased, and Gly decreased in the liver of both obese mice (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Kokaji et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Soltis et al., 2017</xref>). In the expression of genes, the increased DEGs in both obese mice were enriched in glycolysis/gluconeogenesis and steroid synthesis, whereas the decreased DEGs in both obese mice were enriched in 4 amino acid metabolic pathways such as Ala, Asp, and Glu metabolism and Gly, Ser, and Thr metabolism (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Kokaji et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Soltis et al., 2017</xref>). Besides, we compared our DETFs with TFs in liver of high-fat diet-induced obese mice (
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Soltis et al., 2017</xref>) (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>F and 
 <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S13</xref>). We found that more than half of the DETF were similarly regulated in the high-fat diet-induced mice (3 out of 4 increased DETFs and 3 out of 6 decreased DETFs). In particular, the increases of 
 <italic>Pparg</italic>, 
 <italic>Srebf1</italic>, and 
 <italic>Esr1</italic> and the decreases of 
 <italic>Zfx</italic>, 
 <italic>Gtf2ird1</italic>, and 
 <italic>Trim28</italic> consistently occurred both in their high-fat-diet-fed mice and in our 
 <italic>ob</italic>/
 <italic>ob</italic> mice fed with normal diet. Because these changes occurred in response to both high-fat diet and the absence of leptin (
 <italic>ob</italic>/
 <italic>ob</italic>), this result indicates that these DETFs are associated with obesity, not with leptin deficiency nor with the content of diet. The present study extends the previous multi-omic and trans-omic studies by including skeletal muscle and evaluating inter-organ metabolic cycles, thereby providing distinct insights into dysregulated metabolism in obesity.
</p>
