<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The details on the deduction of equation 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq25">(6)</xref> can be found in the Methods section, and the calculated 
 <inline-formula id="d33e1127">
  <inline-graphic id="d33e1128" xlink:href="srep19235-m26.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> are also listed in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>. The microstructures for the alloys BT15 to BT95 found in rods with a diameter of 10 mm are displayed in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4a–h</xref>. The crystalline volume fractions were extracted from these micrographs. While for BT15 and BT20 only a featureless micrograph is revealed, all other alloys exhibit the typical composite microstructure consisting of dendrites embedded in a featureless matrix. The crystalline volume fractions clearly increase with increasing 
 <italic>x</italic>. Starting from BT30 there is a satisfactory agreement between the estimated crystalline volume fractions and the measured values (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). The alloys BT10 up to BT15 are fully amorphous and apparently the lever rule does not describe the volume fractions properly. Obviously, the precipitation of β-Ti is aggravated as the composition of BT
 <italic>X</italic> shift towards BT100, due to the composition containing less Be, Cu and Co, which stabilize the undercooled liquid
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>. This means the 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>n</sub>–line as depicted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref> is shifted to larger times for these compositions and the entire melt hence vitrifies at the given cooling rate. Additionally, the compositions of β-Ti for 
 <italic>x</italic> ≥ 0.40 were measured by means of energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy attached in SEM and were found to be similar to Ti
 <sub>60.58</sub>Zr
 <sub>36.11</sub>Cu
 <sub>2.30</sub>Co
 <sub>1.01</sub> (BT100).
</p>
