<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another up-regulated protein that was identified in our proteomic analysis was ATP-dependent Clp protease, suggesting its contribution to the stationary phase survival by controlling protein quality. ATP-binding protein, which is pertinent to the anaerobic respiration process, is required after entering the stationary growth phase. This is concordant with a previous study performed on 
 <italic>M. smegmatis,</italic> showing that genes involved in anaerobic respiration have been up-regulated in the stationary phase [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Another protein obliquely involved in the anaerobic respiration and noted to be up regulated in our study is 6-phosphofructokinase 1, which aids in the conversion of fructose 6-phosphate and ATP to fructose 1,6-bisphosphate and ADP as a critical step of glycolysis that is deemed to be the base for both anaerobic and aerobic respiration. Interestingly, we found that one of the up-regulated proteins in the stationary phase, LprG protein, was associated with bacterial virulence and antibiotic resistance [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and this is unsurprising since the secreted virulence factors of most human pathogens are often increased in the stationary phase of growth [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. It has been proved that LprG involved in triacylglyceride levels, growth rate, and virulence regulation [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Its implication in mycobacterium virulence has appeared through the induction of mitochondrial fission, interference with complex I and complex II respiration, and modification of mitochondrial calcium uptake, which in turn proposes that LprG-stimulated cells are in a lower bioenergetics state, which could support its immunosuppressive capacity in infection [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The identification of LprG protein in 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> was previously confirmed as P27 in the Mycobacterium tuberculosis complex and its gene is conserved across several pathogenic and nonpathogenic Mycobacterium species [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].
</p>
