<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous transcriptomic studies of 
 <italic>M. avium</italic> have been focused on transcriptome during infection [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] or during the mid-exponential growth phase [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. We explored the expression of the dys-regulated proteins that were detected by proteomic analysis between the two phases at the transcriptional level. Our results showed a down-regulation of elongation factor and universal stress protein coherently with the proteomic results. Strikingly, universal stress protein was down- regulated at both levels, although previous study proved the up-regulation of genes that are implicated in responses to stress in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> in stationary growth phase [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. This could be attributed to the notion that responses to alterations in resource availability could vary between species [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Alternatively, the transcription of acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase in the stationary phase was down-regulated even when it had a 2.2 fold increase at the proteomic level. Additionally, ATP-dependent Clp protease ATP-binding protein and dibenzothiophene desulfurization enzyme C were down-regulated at the transcriptomic level during the stationary growth phase, although they were up-regulated at the proteomic level. These differences between transcriptome and proteome over the two growth phases could be attributed to several factors like the extremely low abundance of transcripts and the poor recovery of proteins due to its low solubility or the membrane attachment. Additional factor is the fact that a single transcript can be translated several times to protein, and protein is more stable than transcript, thus accumulating more than transcripts [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Another likely explanation for the transcriptome and proteome differences is post-transcriptional regulation. This slight difference between the transcriptomic and the proteomic results were also confirmed in our correlation graph (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-26-00305">Supplementary Figure S5</xref>). The weak correlation between the transcriptome and the proteome implies a major role for regulation at the post-transcription level in growth phase adaptation [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-00305" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].
</p>
