<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">Differential expression of seventeen transcripts observed in good-responders were validated in a small independent sample (
 <italic>n</italic> = 22) using OpenArray qPCR analysis. The validated transcripts were differentially expressed in the same direction as the initial discovery cohort and included 
 <italic>ENTPD1</italic> (otherwise known as CD39), which is primarily expressed on activated lymphoid cells. A previous study reported an expansion of CD39 positive regulatory T cells following successful treatment with methotrexate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], whilst a more recent study reported that a higher genetic score for CD39 expression on T cells at the 
 <italic>ENTPD1</italic> locus was associated with a poor response to TNFi [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Here, we observed relatively higher levels of 
 <italic>ENTPD1</italic> at pre-treatment in good-responders compared with the 3-month sample. However, in the current study, we cannot say whether the observed change in 
 <italic>ENTPD1</italic> expression is reflected at the protein level, if a particular cell type is prominently affected or if expression is modified by genotype. Further studies of 
 <italic>ENTPD1</italic> locus in relevant cell populations are now required in RA to resolve these interesting observations. In addition, this study identified increased expression of 
 <italic>CD40LG</italic> in good-responders. The 
 <italic>CD40LG</italic> gene encodes the complementary ligand for the CD40 transmembrane protein which is expressed on both B cells and antigen-presenting cells (APCs) and has been associated with increased TNF expression. Furthermore, transcription of both genes is reportedly elevated in the synovial tissue of RA patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. More recently, increased CD40 transcription and lower CD40 methylation in whole blood were associated with improved TNFi response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].
</p>
