<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to their enhanced proliferation and differentiation ability, 
 <italic>me</italic>_SWH-treated MSCs served as a good model for the study of signaling conduction in MSC differentiation. In this work, 
 <italic>me</italic>_SWH-treated MSCs were induced to differentiate into neuronal cells 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> using a neurobasal medium supplemented with B27, SHH, bFGF and FGF8. After 5 days of differentiation, the length of me_SWH hMSCs increased 1.52 times in comparison to undifferentiated cells. The results indicate that in the presence of an inhibitor of the phosphoinositide 3-OH kinase (PI3K)/Akt pathway, cell viability decreased significantly to 60% of its original value 1 day after induction. Two signaling pathways, the PI3K/Akt and MAPK/ERK pathways, could play important roles in the neuronal differentiation of MSCs. The PI3K/Akt pathway serves to maintain cell survival during neural differentiation; whereas the function of the MAPK/ERK pathway is probably to enhance the maturation of differentiated MSCs. Blocking of the PI3K/Akt pathway by the Akt inhibitor caused significant cell death. We found that the expression of TrkB correlated well with the secretion of BDNF during differentiation. The differentiated cells secreted BDNF to activate TrkB via the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway in order to maintain cell survival. During neuronal differentiation, sustained ERK activity was achieved by activation of the MAPK/ERK pathway due to the binding of growth factors bFGF and FGF in the early phase and then later by the binding of BDNF to TrkB. In addition, the conventional proteomic method was used to investigate the change in cellular protein expression as a result of neuronal differentiation. Three proteins—nucleoside diphosphate kinase A (NM23-H1), kinesin-1 heavy chain (KIF5B, UKHC), and protein kinase C epsilon type (PKC-ε)—were found to be differentially expressed by the neuronal differentiation. Via the secretion and binding of BDNF, there is cross-talk between PKC-ε and the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway, which is essential for the survival of differentiated neurons.
</p>
