<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Generally, 10–20 wt% of ceramic fillers is the critical addition content in SCEs. However, the severe agglomeration behavior of the particles greatly lowers the volume fraction of interphase, destroys the percolated network of interphase, and thus reduces the ionic conductivity.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">55</xref> In addition, since the nanoparticles and nanowires are randomly mixed within polymer matrix, the Li ion transport channels constructed in SCEs are disordered. If the ceramic fillers distribute linearly along the current direction in SCEs, the migration of Li ions would become more targeted and efficient. Therefore, various methods have been adopted to obtain SCEs with aligned ceramic fillers for larger ICEs/polymer interphase and high‐efficient Li ion transportation. Liu et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">76</xref> induced the LATP particles coated with poly(ethylene glycol) diacrylate (PEGDA) to distribute orderly into the poly(dimethylsiloxane) (PDMS) matrix by an external alternating‐current electric field, which architects 3D lithium‐ion conductive networks in SCE (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). The ionic conductivity of the aligned LATP@PEGDA@PDMS is three times that of unaligned LATP@PEGDA@PDMS under the same condition. Yang co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0077" ref-type="ref">77</xref> reported an easy and simple ice‐templating‐based method to prepare PEO‐based composite electrolyte with vertically aligned and connected LATP nanoparticles. Both of the PEO and PEO/polyethylene glycol (PEG) polymer electrolytes with ice‐templated LATP nanoparticles show higher ionic conductivity than those without filler or with randomly dispersed LATP nanoparticles (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c). Furthermore, Cui co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref> also proved the significance of alignment of ceramic nanowires for the enhancement of ionic conductivity of SCEs, including the angles among the nanowires. They embedded the aligned LLTO nanowires in PAN‐LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> polymer host with various orientations to fabricate SCEs. The ionic conductivity of the PAN‐LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> electrolyte with randomly dispersed LLTO nanowires at 30 °C is 5.40 × 10
 <sup>−6</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup>. Whereas, for the case of nanowires aligned at 90°, 45°, and 0°, the ionic conductivities are 1.78 × 10
 <sup>−7</sup>, 2.24 × 10
 <sup>−5</sup>, and 6.05 × 10
 <sup>−5</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup>, respectively. The activation energies for electrolyte with random nanowires and electrolytes with 0° aligned nanowires are respectively 0.84 ± 0.02 and 0.94 ± 0.04 eV, indicating faster ion conductive pathway contributed by the aligned nanowires. The ion‐conducting pathway without crossing junctions can further improve the ionic transportation efficiency (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). Therefore, the significant enhancement of ionic conductivity of SCEs with aligned ceramic nanoparticles and nanowires is attributed to the continuous and aligned lithium‐ion conductive pathways facilitating the lithium‐ion motion in SCEs. In addition, the alignment of the ceramic could further shorten the transfer distance of Li ions and enhance the ionic conductivity of SCEs.
</p>
