<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">For food calories, nearly half of the seven billion people on earth depend on rice
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. Majority of the rice consumers live in the low income countries of tropical Asia and for them rice accounts for more than 76% of caloric intake
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>. Improvement of yield potential of the irrigated IR8-parented semi-dwarf rice has accounted for the food grain surplus in the rice growing nations and ensured food security since 1960s. However, the yield potential has almost stagnated in the last 2–3 decades and on farm yield seldom has gone beyond 10 t ha
 <sup>−1</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup> in spite of improved management practices. Currently speculation is ripe for a shortage of food in the absence of another quantum jump of yield potential in near future
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. For gain in yield potential, breeders have targeted on improvement of panicle grain number. Using advanced technologies and accessing improved breeding populations, several new large panicle rice cultivars bearing numerous spikelets, such as, hybrid rice, super rice, new plant type rice have been developed
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> but the intended matching benefit of grain yield is not accrued. The increase of spikelet/grain number without corresponding increase of size makes the panicle compact/dense, where a trade off between grain number and filling derides commensurate advancement of yield benefit
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. Consequently the failing spikelets located especially on the proximal part of panicle become barren or poorly filled
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Spikelets compromised for accommodation within crammed space of panicle rachis produce high concentration of ethylene at anthesis to the detriment of starch synthesis and filling of the developing grains
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
