<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ability of the Pir toxin proteins to enter primary shrimp hemocytes was explored using immunocytochemical analysis. First, recombinant His-tagged PirA and PirB proteins (designated as His-rPirA or His-rPirB) were cloned, expressed, and purified as described previously [
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Brieﬂy, the nucleotide sequence encoding PirA (GenBank #: KU145400.1) and PirB (GenBank #: KU145400.1) were ampliﬁed using the AHPND strain of 
 <italic>V. parahaemolyticus</italic> (PD-2) (a kind gift from Dr. Chu Fang Lo of National Cheng Kung University) as template, with gene-specific primers (
 <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) designed with Primer Premier 5. The PCR product was cloned into pET-28a and transformed into 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) (TransGen Biotech, Beijing, China). The expressed recombinant proteins were puriﬁed using Ni-NTA beads (GE Healthcare, CT, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The recombinant proteins were identified via sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and Western blot analysis as described previously [
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The purified proteins (His-rPirA and His-rPirB) were separated on SDS-PAGE, before being transferred onto polyvinylidene ﬂuoride membranes (PVDF, Millipore, MA, USA). The PVDF membranes were blocked with 5% skimmed milk dissolved in TBST (20 mM Tris, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% Tween 20, pH 7.4) for 1 h at room temperature. The membranes were incubated overnight at 4°C with mouse anti-His primary antibody (1:3000, Transgen BioTech, Beijing, China) followed by washing 3 times (15 min) with TBST. The membranes were then incubated for 1 h at room temperature with HRP-linked goat anti-mouse secondary antibody (1:3000, Sigma-Aldrich, MO, USA) and then washed 3 times (15 min). Protein bands on blots were detected with the Amersham Imager 600 system (GE Healthcare, CT). 
</p>
