<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Since their first commercialization in the 1990s, rechargeable lithium-ion batteries (LIBs), which are characterized by high voltage, high energy density, and long cycling stability, have been widely used as portable power source in many aspects of our daily life during the past three decades, in particular in the field of personal electronics (
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2019</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2015</xref>). The state-of-the-art LIBs use organic-based electrolytes, which, however, can introduce serious safety concerns for large-scale applications, such as electrochemical energy storage for electric grid and power source for electric vehicles (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hu and Xu, 2014</xref>). In addition, the limited resource of lithium also brings a big concern about the cost of LIBs when their widespread application is realized. Therefore, battery systems with higher safety and lower cost are highly demanded (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Lukatskaya et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Ming et al., 2019</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Zhong et al., 2019</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2019</xref>). Compared with conventional organic electrolytes, inorganic, aqueous electrolytes usually have improved ionic conductivity, higher safety, and lower fabrication cost (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Fang et al., 2018</xref>). Aqueous batteries based on different metal ions, e.g., Li
 <sup>+</sup>, Na
 <sup>+</sup>, Zn
 <sup>2+</sup>, Mg
 <sup>2+</sup>, and Al
 <sup>3+</sup>, have been developed and intensively studied over the past decades (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Verma et al., 2019</xref>). In particular, zinc-ion (Zn-ion) batteries have attracted increasing attention owing to the abundance of Zn resource and the relatively high electrochemical potential of Zn metal in neutral or mildly acidic aqueous electrolytes, which is beneficial to the stable performance (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Konarov et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2019</xref>). The concept and the fundamental chemistry of the rechargeable Zn-ion batteries based on the migration of Zn
 <sup>2+</sup> between cathode and anode was first proposed by Kang and co-workers in 2011 (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2019a</xref>). In recent years, intensive efforts have been made to the investigation of the composition of aqueous electrolytes, the preparation and protection of Zn anodes, and the development of high-performance and stable cathode materials (
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2019</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2019</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
