<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">Confluent IPEC-J2 cells were washed three times with PBS. After infected with GDS01 at 5 MOI for 1 h, the supernatant was replaced by fresh medium. Mock infection was used as control. Cells were collected at 4, 7, 10, 13, 16, 19 hpi. In total, fourteen samples were used for library preparation. Briefly, total RNA was extracted from samples using TRIzol (Invitrogen). Genomic DNA was removed by using Turbo DNA-free Kit (Ambion) following manufacturer’s instruction. Approximately 2 μg total genomic DNA-free RNA of each sample was randomly fragmented by heating at 94℃ for about 20 min. The first-strand cDNA was synthesized by SuperScript III Reverse Transcriptase Kit (Invitrogen) using an anchored oligo d (T) primer with a 5′ template switching adaptor. Using an anchored oligo dT primer for first-strand synthesis cannot avoid obtaining polyA-rich regions, but this sequence would be filtered out in the reads processing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Then the second-strand cDNA was synthesized by using cDNA synthesis Kit (M-MLV version) (Gubler-Hoffman) according to the manufacturer’s instruction. The cDNA product was purified with Agencourt RNA Clean XP kit (Beckman Coulter). In vitro transcription was done by using RiboMAX™ Large Scale RNA Production System-T7 (Promega). After removing template cDNA with RQ1 RNase-Free DNase (Promega), the RNA product was purified with Agencourt RNA Clean XP kit (Beckman Coulter). Illumina adaptor B with 6-mer barcode and modified oligo d(T) tagged illumine adaptor A were used for PCR amplification following the instruction of High Fidelity Platinum Taq DNA Polymerase Kit (Invitrogen). Then fragments of 250–500 bp in size of the PCR products were selected and purified by Agencourt Ampure magnetic bead (Beckman Coulter) according to the manufacturer’s instruction. The average size was determined by Agilent 2100 bioanalyzer (Agilent Genomics). Then the final pooled fragments were quantified and sequenced from the 3′ end with Hiseq 2500 (Illumina). The details of primers were shown in Additional file 1.
</p>
