<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par74">Two of the main ontology classes previously associated with apomixis in 
 <italic>Paspalum</italic> corresponded to transcription factors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] and hormones [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. Here, we identified a number of transcriptional regulators showing differential expression in reproductive organs of apomictic and sexual plants. Some of them, like MYB family members, show heterochronic upregulation in the apomictic and sexual libraries, with expression reaching peaks at different developmental stages. MYB proteins share the conserved MYB DNA-binding domain that is crucial to the control of proliferation and differentiation in several cell types [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Besides, upregulation in the apomictic libraries was observed for members of the bHLH, ERF, WRKY, B3, ARF and AP2 family, all of them previously related to plant development through cell division, proliferation and differentiation control [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. We also identified numerous members of different hormonal pathways, especially the auxin and jasmonate routes, that show differential regulation during apomixis, a fact that had been anticipated when analyzing the representation of miRNAs in reproductive organs of sexual and apomictic plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. Currently several members of these pathways are under functional characterization to determine its role in apomixis development. Besides, the expression characterization for several transcripts previously associated with apomixis provided information on the specific stages these transcripts are modulated and a proof of concept that the use of the catalogue presented here might contribute to a thorough comparison of both reproductive pathways.
</p>
