<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par75">The Illumina sequence database reported here represents a detailed chronological characterization of the sense/antisense gene expression landscape in reproductive organs of sexual and apomictic counterparts of the same species. The derived information could be of use in 
 <italic>Paspalum</italic> research programs dealing with gene expression during sexual and asexual seed formation, as well as the molecular breeding of apomixis. Moreover, it will allow the identification of apomixis candidate genes, which could be further characterized in expression and function in other apomictic species. The reported information could not be completely systematized in a single scientific article, since a number of different analyses can be conducted, depending on the need of each specific research project. However, the main use for this tool no doubt will be the comprehensive identification of candidate genes that can be used as molecular markers in apomixis-based breeding programs or to induce asexuality from sexual genetic backgrounds through genetic engineering. In particular, it will allow for rapid discrimination of some of the sequences controlling apomeiosis and parthenogenesis, due to its potential to expose differential expression at specific stages. Such discrimination was impracticable when using the formerly-produced apomictic vs. sexual transcriptomic databases, since their construction invariably involved only one reproductive stage or a bulk of stages. Currently, the 
 <italic>Paspalum</italic> genome is in process of sequencing and assembly in our laboratory and the apospory controlling locus (ACL) is being identified by positioning markers that were fully linked to the trait in former genetic mapping experiments. In this context, mapping the stage-specific candidate sequences exposed here onto the 
 <italic>Paspalum</italic> ACL will help to identify the genomic controllers of apomixis, while RNA in situ hybridization will reveal the precise site of expression in reproductive tissues. Eventually, functional analysis will disclose the reproductive phenotypes that can be induced after up- or down- regulation in precise cell types pointed by the in situ analysis. Moreover, genetic engineering will allow the harnessing of these candidates to reproduce the desired reproductive phenotypes in species of interest, using the appropriate promoters. On another note, an additional application of this database, among many others, will be aimed at clarifying the functionality of the expression originated from the heterochromatic non-recombinant ACL, since mapping the antisense transcripts identified here onto the 
 <italic>Paspalum</italic> genome will reveal which of these transcripts emerge from this particular region.
</p>
