<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Using freshly isolated CD11b
 <sup>+</sup> cells, which consist of both CNS infiltrating macrophages and brain resident microglia from the brains of mice that had been systemically treated with LPS in the presence and absence of the K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 blocking peptide ShK-223, Rangaraju 
 <italic>et al</italic>. confirmed that K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 inhibition reduces expression of inflammatory cytokines like IL-1β but showed that K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 inhibition also reduced expression of TAP1 and prevented upregulation of EHD1 in CD11b
 <sup>+</sup>CD45
 <sup>low</sup> microglia as measured by flow cytometry [
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Both TAP1 and EDH1 are proteins that are involved in MHC class-I assembly and trafficking to the cell surface. The authors therefore next investigated the effect of ShK-223 treatment on MHC class-1 expression on acutely isolated microglia, and, based on reduced MHC expression, hypothesized that LPS-induced increases in the antigen presenting capacity of microglia are K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3-dependent processes, suggesting that K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 inhibition could reduce antigen presentation to CD8
 <sup>+</sup> cytotoxic T cells. In a subsequent weighted co-expression network analysis applied to microglial transcriptomic datasets from neuroinflammatory and neurodegenerative disease mouse models the same group identified K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 as part of a pro-inflammatory gene signature that also included Tlr2, Ptgs2, Il12b, Il1b, CD44, NFκB, Stat1, and RelA [
 <xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 blockade with ShK-223 could shift this pro-inflammatory signature to one with increased expression of anti-inflammatory genes in disease associated microglia. What is interesting in this context, is that Kv1.3 inhibitors have been reported in other studies to further increase the migration of cultured microglia stimulated with the anti-inflammatory cytokines IL-4 and IL-10 [
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and to not affect microglial phagocytosis of microbeads [
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] or to even increase phagocytosis of amyloid-β [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
