<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Animal welfare is defined as the collective physical, mental, and emotional states of an animal over time [
 <xref rid="B1-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Each individual experiences different welfare depending on their natural and individual history, personality, and environment [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Methods to assess animal welfare consist of behavioral measures, including specific behaviors such as stereotypies or social behaviors, (see [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] for review) or aggregate measures like behavioral diversity [
 <xref rid="B3-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Physiological indicators can also be used to measure welfare, with glucocorticoids being the most commonly employed in zoo studies [
 <xref rid="B4-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Integrated measures of glucocorticoid activity, such as fecal glucocorticoid metabolites (FGM), can summarize activity of the hypothalamic–pituitary–adrenal (HPA) axis over a period of time (usually 24–48 h for fecal samples). Longitudinal profiles of individual adrenal activity can then be compared as the animal experiences different husbandry conditions as an indication of how those conditions affect animal welfare. However, it should be noted that adrenal activity can sometimes increase during positive experiences, as well as in response to environmental threats, so careful analysis of individual hormone profiles in relation to behavioral data is needed to interpret results. Social interactions [
 <xref rid="B5-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and rates of abnormal behaviors, such as pacing [
 <xref rid="B6-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], have also been linked to changes in adrenal activity and are considered indicators of animal welfare in their own right; for that reason, these factors should also be taken into account when analyzing FGM profiles. These complexities are why multiple indicators are preferable when examining the impact of an event on the welfare of an animal. One type of husbandry event that is commonly evaluated using these types of welfare indicators is the provisioning of environmental enrichment.
</p>
