<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to their nocturnal and semi-fossorial nature, research on the natural history of aardvarks (
 <italic>Orycteropus afer</italic>) has been scarce. In the wild, aardvarks have been tracked traveling 1–2 km a night [
 <xref rid="B19-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] to find food, burrow sites, and mates [
 <xref rid="B20-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Although predated items vary throughout the year, an aardvark can have up to 200 foraging bouts per night [
 <xref rid="B21-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. There is also little research available on aardvark welfare in captivity. Allard, Fuller, and Hamilton [
 <xref rid="B22-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] used infrared cameras to assess activity budgets and collected fecal samples for hormone analysis to compare the welfare of aardvarks over time and in different habitat spaces at the Detroit Zoo. The data showed that FGM concentrations were lower when the aardvarks spent more time exploring their habitat [
 <xref rid="B22-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], suggesting that enrichment designed to encourage investigation may be a way to positively influence the welfare of aardvarks in captivity. Based on our previous research and aardvark natural feeding and traveling behaviors, we therefore chose to focus this study on the behavioral goals of increasing rates of foraging and exploring the environment. This exploratory study addressed two primary issues: the extent to which different types of enrichment promote their intended behavioral goals and their subsequent effects on indicators of animal welfare. We asked the following specific questions:
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>(1)</label>
   <p>How did the amount and rate of use vary depending on the stated enrichment goal?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(2)</label>
   <p>Which enrichment items better achieved their stated goals based on use throughout the night? What about throughout the study (i.e., was habituation observed)?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(3)</label>
   <p>Following this logic, we developed the following question post hoc. Which enrichment items better achieved their stated goal based on promoting overall rates of goal behaviors, including behaviors directed towards non-enrichment as well as enrichment items?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(4)</label>
   <p>Did certain enrichment types or increased enrichment use correspond to positive changes in specific welfare indicators, including FGM concentrations, behavioral diversity, pacing, or social behaviors?</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
