<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is important to note that XAS is an ensemble-averaging technique and that for heterogeneous samples with absorbing species coexisting in different environments, caution is needed in the interpretation of XAS data and the CNs extracted. In the simplest case of a sample where metallic particles of different sizes coexist, the analysis of particle sizes by XAS will yield only an effective mean particle size averaged over all species. Nonetheless, knowledge of such effective particle size and tracking its evolution under reaction conditions can provide important clues about particle segregation/fragmentation trends, as demonstrated by Matos et al., who used the CNs extracted from the fitting of EXAFS data of Pt NPs to follow 
 <italic>in situ</italic> their coarsening under high temperature treatments in different chemical environments (
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>
 </xref>b). However, in the samples with broad particle size distributions, the contribution of larger particles to the measured spectrum is effectively larger due to a larger fraction of atoms involved. Thus, the effective particle size obtained from XAS will be slightly larger than the true average particle size. See ref (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref268">268</xref>) for more details. If additional information about the particle size distribution is available (e.g., from TEM measurements), such information can be included in the interpretation of the coordination numbers; see ref (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref212">212</xref>). Another important case of heterogeneous samples, especially relevant for 
 <italic>in situ</italic> catalysis studies, includes those with coexisting metallic and oxide phases. The interpretation of CNs here needs to be carried out with especial care, as discussed in 
 <xref rid="sec5.9" ref-type="other">Section 
  <xref rid="sec5.9" ref-type="other">5.9</xref>
 </xref>.
</p>
