<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The novelty of this multigene panel is also attributed to its component genes. Among the 10 individual genes, 5 genes have not been reported or with articles published in PC, including C1orf106 and FBXO6 (
 <xref rid="genes-12-00257-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Downregulations of C1orf106 occur in PCs compared to prostate tissues, PCs with TMPRSS2-ERG fusion compared to those without the fusion, and mPCs compared to primary PCs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f003">Figure 3</xref>A, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f004">Figure 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f005">Figure 5</xref>). C1orf106 plays a role in activating innate immunity in breast cancer [
 <xref rid="B65-genes-12-00257" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], suggesting that its downregulation contributes to the evasion of immune checkpoints during PC initiation and progression. In view of the emerging roles of escaping immune surveillance in all stages of tumorigenesis, the potential contributions of C1orf106 to this aspect of PC certainly warrants further investigation in future. Reductions in ARFGEF2 expression in mPCs compared to primary tumors were observed in two independent cohorts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f003">Figure 3</xref>B and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f005">Figure 5</xref>). In both TCGA PanCancer and MSKCC cohorts, ARFGEF2 downregulations increased the risk of PC relapse (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f007">Figure 7</xref>) and this biomarker value is independent of age at diagnosis, tumor stage, WHO PC grade, and surgical margin status. The oncogenic actions of ARFGEF2 remain unclear not only in PC but also tumorigenesis in general with 
 <italic>n</italic> = 4 articles in PubMed under “ARFGEF2 and Cancer”. Our research here indicates that ARFGEF2 downregulation may facilitate PC progression. FBXO6 was upregulated in mPCs over primary PCs in two independent datasets (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f003">Figure 3</xref>B and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f005">Figure 5</xref>). FBXO6 can induce Chk1 degradation [
 <xref rid="B66-genes-12-00257" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Chk1 plays an essential role in maintaining genome stability via contributing to activation of cellular DNA damage response [
 <xref rid="B67-genes-12-00257" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. FBXO6 might contribute to genome instability during PC progression; genome instability is an essential oncogenic factor of PC and other cancer types [
 <xref rid="B68-genes-12-00257" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p>
