<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Owing to the lack of a cell wall, the mycoplasma cell membrane is composed of a single lipid bilayer with many embedded membrane proteins. These membrane proteins are divided into three categories: integral, peripheral, and lipid-anchored proteins. Most mycoplasmas membrane lipoproteins belong to the lipid-anchored proteins. Like bacterial lipoproteins, mycoplasma lipoproteins contain a conserved S-diacylglyceryl-cysteine residue at the N-terminus. In most mycoplasmas, the NH
 <sub>2</sub> in cysteine exists in a free terminal form, yielding a diacylated lipoprotein (in bacterial lipoproteins, there is an additional acyl group in the amino group of the diacylated cysteine residue, i.e. triacylated lipoprotein), which may be one of the reasons why its immune-modulatory mechanism is different from that of bacteria. Mycoplasma membrane lipoproteins are abundantly present in the cell membrane and are pivotal proinflammatory substances of mycoplasmas. In 2018, an elaborate review summarized the effects of membrane lipoproteins on lymphocytes, epithelial cells, neutrophils, and myeloid cells as well as the regulation of the immune system [
 <xref rid="cit0268" ref-type="bibr">268</xref>]. However, the true function of lipoproteins is far from that; in addition to the function of immunomodulation, membrane lipoproteins are also essential for cell adhesion; biofilm formation (i.e., Vsa protein); cytotoxicity; colonization and invasion of host cells; degradation of host DNA or NETs; and functioning of ABC transporters [
 <xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0269" ref-type="bibr">269</xref>]. Christodoulides [
 <xref rid="cit0268" ref-type="bibr">268</xref>], Shimizu [
 <xref rid="cit0207" ref-type="bibr">207</xref>] and May [
 <xref rid="cit0270" ref-type="bibr">270</xref>] have provided complete details regarding these functions. Herein, we will discuss new insights into membrane lipoproteins of pathogenic mycoplasmas.
</p>
