<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ureaplasmas are associated with human genitourinary tract diseases and perinatal diseases. Multiple banded antigen (MBA) is the major surface-exposed lipoprotein of ureaplasmas, which undergoes phase and size variation both 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. The characteristics and functions of MBA have been described extensively in other studies [
 <xref rid="cit0103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0139" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. MBA may be linked to the severity of human placental inflammation 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0271" ref-type="bibr">271</xref>], although controversial results exist [
 <xref rid="cit0272" ref-type="bibr">272</xref>]. The current evidence indicates that a potent host humoral immune response may be a key determinant in explaining adverse pregnancy outcomes and that the degree of MBA/mba variation increases with the duration of gestation 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0273" ref-type="bibr">273</xref>]. Additionally, Huang and colleagues have indicated that the lipid-associated membrane proteins of 
 <italic>U. parvum</italic> and 
 <italic>U. urealyticum</italic> induce U937 cell cycle arrest in the G1 phase through a p21-dependent but p53-independent pathway [
 <xref rid="cit0274" ref-type="bibr">274</xref>], suggesting that this signaling pathway is highly correlated with the inflammatory and protective effects in ureaplasmal diseases. Interestingly, a recent report has indicated that the lipid moiety of 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> lipoprotein is a causative factor of vaccine-enhanced disease, which overcomes the roadblock of vaccine development [
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. This suggests that the development of a vaccine should balance the maintenance of its immune-stimulatory activity and reduce the side effects caused by the lipid moiety. Furthermore, the lipoproteins of 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> and 
 <italic>M. salivarium</italic> can translocate to the cytosol via an unidentified mechanism, which causes NLRP3 inflammasome activation and IL-1β maturation in macrophages [
 <xref rid="cit0275" ref-type="bibr">275</xref>]. This illustrates the complexity of the proinflammatory mechanism of lipoproteins.
</p>
