<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The absence of triacylated lipoprotein in mycoplasma has long been a consideration. Although there have been dispersed reports of the possibility that triacylated lipoproteins may exist in some strains, evidence remains lacking. First, neither N-acyltransferase (
 <italic>Lnt</italic>) nor its homologous gene has been characterized in the mycoplasma genome [
 <xref rid="cit0280" ref-type="bibr">280</xref>]. Second, when TLR recognizes mycoplasma lipoproteins, not only the lipid moiety, but also the amino acid sequence and spatial structure may affect the recognition of TLRs [
 <xref rid="cit0281" ref-type="bibr">281</xref>]. Although Shimizu et al. have claimed the existence of triacylated lipoproteins in 
 <italic>M. genitalium</italic> since they were recognized by TLR1 and TLR2, they did not perform any chemical analyses such as the ratio of N-amide and O-ester bonds, and the Edman degradation experiments [
 <xref rid="cit0282" ref-type="bibr">282</xref>]. Therefore, TLR1 and TLR2 recognition is only a necessary condition for triacylated lipoprotein rather than a sufficient condition. To date, mass spectrometry and nuclear magnetic spectroscopy are more reliable for the identification of triacylated lipoproteinsthan TLR-based estimation. Kurokawa et al. have successfully identified three triacylated lipoproteins in 
 <italic>M. genitalium</italic> (MG_040) and 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> (MPN052 and MPN415), and one novel peptidyl form of lipoprotein in 
 <italic>M. fermentans</italic> (MBIO_0319 and MBIO_0661) by mass spectrometry [
 <xref rid="cit0280" ref-type="bibr">280</xref>], suggesting that lipoprotein structures vary among mycoplasmas and even within individual proteins of 
 <italic>M. fermentans</italic>. Given that mycoplasmas lack 
 <italic>Lnt</italic> or its homologues as that in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, the existence of the triacylated lipoproteins indicates that the yet to be discovered Lnt enzyme may have distinct enzymatic properties.
</p>
