<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The poor contact between Li anode and ICEs induces the high impedance and heterogeneous Li ion deposition that causes the inferior rate performance and uncontrollable lithium dendrite growth.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0094" ref-type="ref">94</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0095" ref-type="ref">95</xref> Inheriting the advantages of both SPEs and ICEs, the SCEs show good stability with Li metal and satisfactory performance in the suppression of lithium dendrite growth. The polymer hosts not only provide continuous ion‐conducting pathway and isolate ceramic particles from electrodes to avoid side reactions, but also offer soft contact with electrodes to reduce Li ion transfer resistance, which could achieve a uniform Li ion flux to suppress lithium dendrite growth.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">50</xref> Meanwhile, the rigid ceramic particles offer fast highways for the migration of lithium ions and enhance the mechanical strength of the electrolyte to suppress lithium dendrites.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">96</xref> For instance, Zhao et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">43</xref> incorporated slight LGPS into P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiTFSI matrix to fabricate a contact amelioration SCE membrane. The interfacial resistance of symmetrical cell assembled with 1% LGPS‐P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiTFSI membrane is 26 Ω cm
 <sup>2</sup> and remains constant after storage for 7 days, while the interfacial resistance of P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiTFSI membrane obviously increases from 38 to 80 Ω cm
 <sup>2</sup> at the same condition. The LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/Li cell using the incorporated membrane also shows excellent cycling performance (capacity retention of 92.5% after 50 cycles at 0.5 C rate and 60 °C) and good rate property. The interfacial resistance remains steady around 113 Ω after 20 cycles, while that of LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiTFSI/Li increases from 203 to 270 Ω. In addition, the ceramic fillers could also reinforce the mechanical properties of the solid electrolyte to inhibit lithium dendrite growths. An SCE with high mechanical property was obtained by reinforcing the P(EO)
 <sub>8</sub>/LiTFSI polymer substrate with LATP/PAN fiber (FCSE) (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0008" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>8</bold>
 </xref>a), which has an enlarged tensile strength (10.72 MPa).
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0097" ref-type="ref">97</xref> The Li/Li cell with FCSE exhibits excellent stability in both bulk and interface resistance after 12 days.
</p>
