<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In terms of the intended evaluation of solid-solid phase transitions, the zero level of the considered DSC measurement is of outstanding importance, particularly when the enthalpy changes are to be determined quantitatively. The measured signal of excess 
 <italic>c</italic>
 <sub>p</sub> can still be curved, and may particularly deviate from zero in temperature regions in which no reactions are occurring (the excess c
 <sub>p</sub> should be zero here). This zero-level curvature can have multiple reasons. To ensure a reliable and straight signal close to zero level, only adequately calibrated calorimeters should be used (for calibration details, see [
 <xref rid="B113-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B124-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]). It is also reasonable to check each DSC run and its corresponding baseline measurement using the following quality attributes: (i) the heat flow difference between the high- and low-temperature isothermal section (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f007">Figure 7</xref>A); and (ii) the heat flow difference between the heat flow values of the sample and baseline measurements of the high-temperature isothermal section (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f007">Figure 7</xref>B). The acceptable values of the heat flow difference depend on both the specific device and their continuity with time; for instance, the heat flow difference between the isothermal sections at high and low temperatures depends mostly on the symmetry and adjustment of the device. More important than the absolute values of these differences is the reproducibility. An unfavourable value may be acceptable as long as it is constant with time [
 <xref rid="B83-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], but for highest accuracy, the values of heat flow differences should be small, i.e., in case (i) within the range of few tenths of mW, and in case (ii) within the range of a few mW for the PerkinElmer power-compensated differential scanning calorimeter.
</p>
