<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The behavior of AISI 4340 steel under various temperature and deformation conditions was investigated in this paper. Dilatometry analysis was designed to construct the CCT diagram of a high-strength steel from eight dilatation curves. The cooling rate was set from 100 °C/s to 0.01 °C/s. Further analysis examined hot deformation behavior at various deformation temperatures from 900 ° C to 1200 °C and strain rates from 0.001 s
 <sup>−1</sup> to 10 s
 <sup>−1</sup>. The following conclusions can be drawn from the present work:
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Transformation temperatures have values of 
    <italic>Ac</italic>
    <sub>1</sub> = 725 °C to 
    <italic>Ac</italic>
    <sub>3</sub> = 763 °C. The selected austenitizing temperature thus guarantees full austenitizing throughout whole material bulk since it was set at 850 °C and holding time at this temperature was 30 min.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Average martensitic transformation start temperature is 
    <italic>Ms</italic> = 282 °C. The temperature is calculated from five dilatation curves (100, 10, 5, 1 and 0.5 °C/s) with martensitic transformation presence only. The 
    <italic>Ms</italic> temperature softly decreases with reduction of cooling rate.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The highest Vickers hardness value of 850 was reached at the highest cooling rate of 100 °C/s and, conversely, at the lowest cooling rate of 0.01 °C/s the Vickers hardness of approximately half was reached, namely 423. The hardness decreases with decreasing of cooling rate, and this result is associated with the formation of individual structures.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Deformation rate has also significant effect on peak stress, which increases exponentially with increase in deformation rate. The highest value of peak stress (
    <italic>σ
     <sub>p</sub>
    </italic> = 328 MPa) was measured with a combination of the highest strain rate (
    <italic>φ</italic>´ = 10 s
    <sup>−1</sup>) and the lowest temperature (
    <italic>T</italic> = 900 °C). The Arrhenius-type constitutive model can be used for prediction flow stress values of this type of steel with high prediction accuracy.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Microstructure investigations show that dynamic recrystallization takes a place at higher temperature (1200 °C), and grain coarsening occurs regardless of strain rate. Furthermore, high strain rate causes grain refinement. This effect is most noticeable at lower temperatures (900 °C) where the recrystallization is not present, and grains remain deformed with the result of very fine grains even after transformation of austenite to martensite or other phases.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The most noticeable effect on microstructure was observed with combination of the highest strain rate 
    <italic>φ</italic>´ = 10 and the lowest temperature 
    <italic>T</italic> = 900 °C. This combination of deformation rate and temperature shows the most grain-refined microstructure.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The basic conclusion of the deformation analysis is that the peak stress decreases linearly with increasing deformation temperature and increases linearly with the deformation rate. The peak stress σ
    <sub>p</sub> is very closely related to Vickers hardness where their dependence is linear.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
