<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par80">Intracellular Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup> levels, known as calcium transients, regulate neuronal subtype and neurotransmitter specifications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Our global transcriptome data showed activation of genes regulating Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup> entry, specifically voltage-sensitive calcium channels and ionotropic glutamate receptors, not sooner than at the eMN developmental stage (D18 vs D13, Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup> signaling comprises a cascade of molecular interactions and biophysical events, which translate extracellular signals to intracellular responses via increase of cytoplasmic Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup>. This can be activated by neurotransmitters, hormones, and growth factors, chemical and electrical stimuli, causing membrane excitation. Two fundamental mechanisms regulate Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup>entry through protein channels: voltage-dependent Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup> channels and ligand-gated channels. The latter are highly diverse, non-Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup>-specific, and greatly represented by the family of guanine-binding GPCR [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Significant upregulation in differentiated MN of high-voltage activated Cavs genes, such as 
 <italic>CACNB3</italic>, is responsible for tight control on intracellular Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup> signaling through regulation of calcium (Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup>) entry and direct interaction with phospholipase C-coupled (PLC) and inositol trisphosphate (IP3) receptors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Upregulation of 
 <italic>CXCR4</italic> by 16-fold at D0-D7 underlines the importance of intracellular Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup> signaling inhibition as the neuronal cell lineage commitment process begins. The CXCR4/CXCR7 complex recruits β-arrestin to trigger the canonical GPCR pathway activating ERK1/2, p38, and SAPK, while inhibiting both Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup> mobilization and cAMP signaling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Upregulation of neuromedin and apelin receptors (
 <italic>NMUR2</italic> and 
 <italic>APLNR</italic>) in NSCs suggest a role for phosphoinositide (PI) signaling pathways that inhibit cAMP production upon Ca
 <sup>
  <italic>2+</italic>
 </sup> mobilization and possibly in regulating cytoskeleton dynamics, cell growth, and hormone release [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].
</p>
