<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A myriad of industrial catalytic processes, ranging from petro- and fine-chemical to environmental processes, depend on crystalline zeolites such as H-ZSM-5 owing to their unique and yet versatile physical and chemical properties, which render not only high catalytic activity and product selectivity but also catalyst stability under harsh reaction conditions.
 <xref rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Environmental processes like exhaust after-treatment utilise zeolites to adsorb/convert toxic pollutants, especially at the cold start of engines, which may originate from the unburnt fuel itself (
 <italic>e.g.</italic>, methanol and/or ethanol blended fuels
 <xref rid="cit3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) or from the combustion process.
 <xref rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The petro-chemical processes include conversion of methanol, which can be derived from renewable resources, into hydrocarbons (MTH) over H-ZSM-5. MTH promises to mitigate the growing global demand for gasoline, polymer grade olefins and aromatics through carbon neutral paths.
 <xref rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Since its first development in 1976 (
 <xref rid="cit6" ref-type="bibr">ref. 6 and 7</xref>) the potential impact of MTH on the energy and environment landscapes has stimulated interest in both industry and academia, and has triggered extensive research to understand the underlying reaction mechanism using experimental and computational tools.
 <xref rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> There is clear evidence that the catalytic activity arises from Brønsted acidic sites
 <xref rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and that a hydrocarbon pool formed during the reaction in the zeolite pores plays an important role in the activity, product selectivity and zeolite lifetime.
 <xref rid="cit17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> However, there is long standing uncertainty concerning the initial methoxylation, which is not only the first step in the process but also a key step in hydrocarbon (pool) growth through methylation.
 <xref rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Methoxylation occurs on the reaction of methanol with Brønsted acidic sites (H
 <sup>+</sup>–O–Si/Al) of H-ZSM-5 giving rise to methoxy species,
 <xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> which is represented by:
 <disp-formula id="eqn1">
  <label>1</label>
  <graphic xlink:href="d0sc01924k-u1.jpg" id="ugr1" position="float" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
