<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Studies based on solid state nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) and infrared (IR) conclude that methoxylation occurs only at elevated temperatures (&gt;150 °C).
 <xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> In line with these observations, several computational studies, usually examining configurations with only one methanol molecule per unit cell (
 <italic>i.e.</italic> one methanol molecule per Brønsted acidic site) suggest that methoxylation could have a significant activation energy (typically reported values are around 200 (±20) kJ mol
 <sup>–1</sup>) and hence require higher temperatures for the reaction.
 <xref rid="cit15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In a marked contrast, our recent inelastic neutron scattering (INS) and 
 <italic>operando</italic> diffuse reflectance infrared Fourier transformed spectroscopy (DRIFTS) and mass spectrometry (MS) studies show the occurrence of methoxylation, to some degree, also under ambient conditions on H-ZSM-5 with a saturation level of methanol loading (7 molecules per Brønsted acidic site).
 <xref rid="cit29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Such a room temperature methoxylation reaction was indeed not ruled out in an earlier study.
 <xref rid="cit32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> These observations are at least partially consistent with computational studies that report decreased energy barrier (reported values are varied; 130 (±30) kJ mole
 <sup>–1</sup>) for methoxylation with 2 methanol molecules per Brønsted acidic site, as compared to that with one methanol molecule.
 <xref rid="cit20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> The calculated energy barrier, although greatly reduced, remains considerable for room temperature methoxylation.
</p>
