<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The PyroMark® Q96 ID Pyrosequencing System (Qiagen, Seoul, South Korea) was used to determine the methylation status of six CpG sites within 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> which was differentially expressed in VAT. 
 <italic>Slc27a3</italic> pyrosequencing primers (Rn_Slc27a3_01_PM PyroMark CpG assay) were pre-designed and purchased from Qiagen (Hilden, Germany). Prior to pyrosequencing, quantity and quality of amplicons were assessed by agarose gel electrophoresis. Visceral (100 µg) adipose samples were bisulphite converted using the EpiTect DNA kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) as per the manufacturer’s recommendations. A thermal cycler was used to convert the DNA with two cycles of denaturation at 95°C for 5 minutes and incubation at 60°C for 10 minutes, followed by column-based DNA clean-up. PCR of 25 ng bisulphite converted DNA was carried out using the PyroMark PCR Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA, USA) under the following PCR conditions: 95°C for 15 minutes; 45 x (95°C for 30 seconds; 56°C for 30 seconds; 72°C for 30 seconds) and 72°C for 5 minutes. PCR reactions were carried out in a Veriti 96-well Thermal Cycler (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, USA) and the quality and size of amplicons were assessed by agarose gel electrophoresis. Pyrosequencing was carried out using the PyroMark Gold Q96 Reagents (Qiagen, Valencia, USA) on a PyroMark ID pyrosequencer (Qiagen, Seoul, South Korea), and the methylation level was calculated using the PyroMark Q96 software (Version 1.0.10; Qiagen) program. All pyrosequencing assays were validated using different ratios of methylated:unmethylated bisulphite converted DNA (0, 10, 25, 50, 75, 90 and 100%) (Qiagen, Valencia, CA, USA), from which standard curves were constructed to determine primer sensitivity (Figure S1). Each pyrosequencing run contained no template negative controls and bisulphite conversion controls were incorporated within each assay sequence to assess conversion efficiency.
</p>
