<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Catalyst–support interactions can also be used to control the stability of the catalysts, as demonstrated by Oh et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref563">563</xref>
 </sup> In their work, the oxidation state of Ir NPs supported on antimony-doped tin oxide (ATO) after electrochemical oxidation was monitored by XAS. The observed shift of the Ir L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge XANES features to lower energy values and lower area under the Ir L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge WL for the ATO-supported catalyst with respect to that for carbon-supported suggested a different oxidation state of Ir in these two cases, namely ∼+ 3.3 and +4, correspondingly. The lower oxidation state of Ir in the ATO-supported catalyst was confirmed also by EXAFS analysis, which yielded a larger Ir–O interatomic distance. Note that an Ir–O bond length of ∼2.20 Å is expected for Ir
 <sup>3+</sup> oxides, while for IrO
 <sub>2</sub> the corresponding interatomic distance is 1.98 Å.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref564">564</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref565">565</xref>
 </sup> While no significant difference in OER activity was observed for the catalysts considered, ATO-supported Ir showed higher stability toward corrosive dissolution, which was attributed to particle-support interactions contributing to sustain a lower oxidation state of Ir.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref563">563</xref>
 </sup> The evolution of the oxidation state of Ir-based catalysts under OER conditions was demonstrated by Minguzzi et al. by using 
 <italic>in situ</italic> time-resolved X-ray absorption measurements at a fixed energy, where the largest difference between the XAS spectra of Ir species in different oxidation state is expected.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref566">566</xref>
 </sup> Alternatively, energy-dispersive XAS can be used,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref567">567</xref>
 </sup> where subsecond time resolution was achieved while collecting 
 <italic>operando</italic> Ir L
 <sub>3</sub>-ege data for IrO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> catalysts.
</p>
