<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The ribosome structure organization in yeast requires a fine-tuning in the gene expression of many of its components, involving ∼200 assembly factors. The 60S ribosomal subunit contains three rRNAs (25S, 5.8S, and 5S) and ∼46 ribosomal proteins, while the 40S subunit is composed of a single rRNA (18S) and ∼33 proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. The yeast genome is reported to encode 137 ribosomal protein genes (RPGs), ∼150 rDNA repeats, and 76 small nucleolar RNAs (snoRNAs), that are mainly involved in the post-transcriptional modifications of the rRNAs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. Changes in the expression of each single components participating in the overall process may affect the ribosome biogenesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. RPGs in yeast are characterized by couples of paralogs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. In particular, among the 137 RPGs annotated in the 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genome, 116 were identified to be ohnologs, i.e., duplicated genes, or paralogs, originated by a whole genome duplication
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. In 2019, Ghulam et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. demonstrated that the stoichiometry of ohnolog RPGs changes in response to variations of environmental conditions. In particular, under physiological conditions, the ribosome population is dominated by the presence of one of the two paralogs that was defined as the major paralog. When cells are exposed to stress conditions, decreased expression of the major paralog and/or overexpression of the minor one, in ohnolog pairs of ribosomal proteins, reduce the relative proportion of the major versus the minor paralog content in the cell
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
