<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">The strong activity of ribosome-targeting macrolides against many gram-positive microorganisms indicates that they effectively inhibit protein production. Like the antibiotics chloramphenicol and puromycin, macrolides stop protein synthesis in the elongation phase of translation. However, instead of directly binding to the PTC and disrupting its structure, macrolides bind in the exit tunnel one or more nanometers from the PTC
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. These macrolides decrease the diameter of the exit tunnel, leading to steric clashes with nascent peptides
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. For instance, the 
 <sup>64</sup>KVE
 <sup>62</sup> segment of the MarR peptide clashes with the cladinose and lactone moieties of both erythromycin (ERY) and Azithromycin (AZ) causing ribosome stalling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. In the case of the EngD peptide, only AZ induces ribosome stalling while ERY does not. The mechanism of ribosome stalling by macrolides is not limited to a narrowing of the exit tunnel. Vázquez-Laslop and coworkers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> showed that when the cladinose sugar group of ERY is replaced by substituents that are as bulky as cladinose, the resulting macrolide cannot stall protein synthesis. While Vázquez-Laslop
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>, Johansson
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>, and Arenz
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> and their coworkers observed that mutating amino acids in the region 
 <sup>6</sup>IFVI
 <sup>9</sup> of the peptide ErmCL can relieve stalling and allow synthesis of the nascent protein. These results demonstrate that the ability of macrolides to inhibit protein synthesis involves a combination of excluded volume interactions and attractive inter-molecular interactions between the nascent protein and antibiotic.
</p>
