<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">The exit tunnel can act synergistically with macrolides to inhibit protein synthesis, and altering the ribosomal nucleotides and residues that line the tunnel can lead to macrolide-resistant bacteria
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Mutations of the 23S ribosomal RNA (a component of the 50S ribosomal subunit) can confer macrolide resistance
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. The mutations at A2058 and A2059, which are located on the surface of the tunnel mediate ERY resistance in multiple species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. The C2610U mutation in 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>’s (
 <italic>E. coli</italic>) ribosome reduces ERY-dependent ribosome stalling of ErmCL peptide twofold
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>, implying that the interaction between the exit tunnel and macrolide plays an important role in inhibition. Mutations in other components of 50S subunit can also contribute to macrolide resistance
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. The mutation Δ
 <sup>82</sup>MKR
 <sup>84</sup> in ribosomal protein L22, for example, confers antibiotic resistance in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Thermus thermophilus</italic> and 
 <italic>Haloarcula marismortui</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Distinct amino acids and peptides attached to macrolide derivatives can establish interactions with components of the ribosomal tunnel that enhance the ribosome binding and inhibitory properties of macrolides
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. For example, attaching Ala-Ala to the C20 aldehyde position of tylosin prevents covalent bonding between tylosin and A2062 of the ribosomal tunnel, but establishes a new interaction with the tunnel that improves inhibitory properties of tylosin.
</p>
