<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An instructive example of the importance of 
 <italic>operando</italic> methods in studies of TMNCs is the recent study by Karapinar et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref448">448</xref>
 </sup> of Cu-based catalysts. While in general the Cu–N
 <sub>4</sub> motif in Cu-based TMNCs materials is not considered active for CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR, the former study reported a surprising selectivity of this catalyst for CO
 <sub>2</sub> conversion to ethanol. 
 <italic>Ex situ</italic> EXAFS data analysis for the as-prepared sample, as well as for the sample after reaction confirmed the presence of the Cu–N
 <sub>4</sub> moiety, and the lack of Cu clusters. However, when 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS measurements were performed, EXAFS data collected under applied potential showed the clear formation of Cu clusters and the disappearance of the Cu–N
 <sub>4</sub> species (
 <xref rid="fig31" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig31" ref-type="fig">31</xref>
 </xref>e). The latter, thus, cannot be responsible for the ethanol production. The observed catalytic activity hence should be attributed to the 
 <italic>in situ</italic> formed Cu clusters, with sizes of at least 4 nm, as determined from EXAFS-yielded coordination number analysis. Intriguingly, the collected data suggested that after reaction and upon exposure to air, the Cu clusters could be dissolved, and the Cu–N
 <sub>4</sub>-like motif returned to be the dominant Cu-containing species in the material.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref448">448</xref>
 </sup> While the reversibility of the Cu cluster formation certainly requires additional investigations, a similar process was previously observed by Weng et al. in the study of Cu(II)phthalocyanine-based catalysts under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref447">447</xref>
 </sup> Here the catalysts demonstrated selectivity toward CH
 <sub>4</sub>. On the basis of 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS data, it was established that the actual active species were the 2 nm Cu nanoclusters formed under reaction conditions and disappearing after the potential was removed.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref447">447</xref>
 </sup> These intriguing examples clearly indicate the importance of 
 <italic>operando</italic> studies for the identification of active species in TMNC materials and working electrocatalysts in general.
</p>
