<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The catalytic activity and selectivity of TMNC materials is in a large part determined by the chosen transition metal, although other factors, such as the microstructure of carbon, also can play a role.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref441">441</xref>
 </sup> Ni-based TMCN catalysts show the highest selectivity toward CO
 <sub>2</sub> conversion into CO but are efficient only at high overpotentials. Therefore, Fe-based catalysts are often considered as the most promising catalysts in this class of materials, by ensuring the high selectivity to CO production at low overpotentials, and also due to their ability to convert CO
 <sub>2</sub> to small amounts of CH
 <sub>4</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref441">441</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref443">443</xref>
 </sup> Significantly lower selectivity toward CO production is usually reported for highly dispersed Co and Cu-based TMCN materials, which exhibit high HER reactivity, although examples of highly active Co-based TMNCs and related single-site materials were also reported.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref441">441</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref445">445</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref446">446</xref>
 </sup> Regarding Cu-based (and, similarly, Zn-based) materials, the main issue seems to be the low stability of the metal–nitrogen structural motifs, which results in the formation of metallic clusters.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref441">441</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref447">447</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref448">448</xref>
 </sup> For example, surprising selectivity toward ethanol formation was observed for Cu-based TMNC catalysts. However, further investigations attributed it to the significant transformation of the catalyst under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR conditions leading to Cu cluster formation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref448">448</xref>
 </sup> Selectivity toward formate production is observed with Sn-based TMNC materials.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref449">449</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
