<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Myocardial ischemia-reperfusion injury (MIRI) is a significant problem in clinical cardiology, and refers to a more serious myocardial injury caused by blood recanalization after a period of myocardial ischemia, as compared with injury caused by vascular occlusion. The spinal cord, as the primary afferent and efferent center of cardiac sensory and sympathetic nerve fibres, has received increased attention in recent years with regards to the regulation of MIRIs. Previous studies have revealed that MIRI has a strong correlation with the abnormal expression of long non-coding (lnc)RNAs in the myocardium; however, there are limited reports on the effects of the altered expression of lncRNAs in the spinal cord following MIRI. To investigate the expression patterns of lncRNAs in the spinal cord after MIRI and their potential role in the early stage of reperfusion, a MIRI model was established in rats. After 30 min of myocardial ischemia and 2 h of reperfusion, the upper thoracic spinal cord tissues were immediately dissected and isolated. lncRNAs and mRNAs in spinal cord tissues were screened using transcriptome sequencing technology, and the expression of several highly deregulated mRNAs, including Frs3, Zfp52, Dnajc6, Nedd4l, Tep1, Myef2, Tgfbr1, Fgf12, Mef2c, Tfdp1 and lncRNA, including ENSRNOT00000080713, ENSRNOT00000090564, ENSRNOT00000082588, ENSRNOT00000091080, ENSRNOT00000091570, ENSRNOT00000087777, ENSRNOT00000082061, ENSRNOT00000091108, ENSRNOT00000087028, ENSRNOT00000086475, were further validated via reverse transcription-quantitative PCR. The number of altered expressed lncRNAs was 126, among which there were 41 upregulated probe sets and 85 downregulated sets. A total of 470 mRNAs were differentially expressed, in which 231 probe sets were upregulated and 239 were downregulated. Gene Ontology analysis indicated that dysregulated transcripts related to biological processes were mainly associated with ‘cell-cell signaling’. Moreover, pathway analysis demonstrated significant changes in the ‘PI3K/Akt signaling pathway’ and the ‘p53 signaling pathway’. Thus, the altered expression of lncRNAs in the spinal cord may be of considerable importance in the process of MIRI. The present results could provide an insight into the potential roles and mechanism of lncRNAs during the early stage of reperfusion.</p>
</abstract>
