<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">One of the ways to make salt stress tolerant crop plants is to genetically engineer them to sustain their growth and productivity in challenging environments. This requires exploring gene pool of wild relatives of crop plants. This can be achieved by analysing global gene expression of salt tolerant species to reveal the underlying regulatory and metabolic mechanisms. Glenn et al. (1999)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> have suggested a number as high as 6000 species of halophytes and additionally, the eHALOPH
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>, Halophyte Database currently identifies more than 1500 species as salt tolerant, without labelling them as halophyte. The main halophytes explored for physiological and molecular studies for salt tolerance mechanism include 
 <italic>Sueda</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic>Spartina species</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic>Salicornia brachiate</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> and 
 <italic>Atriplex </italic>etc
 <italic>.</italic> Still the salt tolerant grasses (STGs) that have not been explored for gene network analysis may be utilised to elucidate their mechanisms of survival at high salt concentrations. 
 <italic>Urochondra setulosa</italic> (Poaceae) is a rhizomatous perennial grass that grows in dune slacks, banks of salt-water creeks and saline flats. It is distributed in Northern Africa through Arabia, southern coast of Pakistan (Sindh) and Northwest India
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. It can survive up to 1000 mM NaCl but genomically, its mechanism of survival in high saline environment has not been explored. Next-generation sequencing coupled with bioinformatics tools provides a platform for high-throughput analysis of key metabolic pathways involved in stress response and adaptation. Here, we used RNA sequencing to identify the genes present in a highly salt tolerant non-model plant species, 
 <italic>Urochondra setulosa</italic> and identify the genes associated with salt tolerance.
</p>
