<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Comparing groups 2, 4, and 5 could potentially demonstrate differences between effects of ibuprofen monotherapy, antiviral monotherapy and the dual ibuprofen and antiviral and ibuprofen therapy as these groups began their treatments on day 5 post infection. It was group 4 (FPI only) that was associated with differences from the placebo that were similar to the changes in lung lesions of group 6 and were characterized by neutrophil chemotaxis, cell migration and cytokine production. In lung tissue without lesion of group 4, innate antiviral and antibacterial responses were predominant, but in group 6 the proinflammatory response-related GO terms and pathways predominated. Both treatment modalities and initiation times varied between these groups. More tissue damage-associated functions and oxidative stress in both tissue types were observed when only FPI was administered (group 4). Notably, there was no ibuprofen involved in the treatment, but prostaglandin biosynthesis was enriched in lung lesions when group 4 and placebo were compared. However, expression of prostaglandin E synthase, most important in this context, had no difference between group 4 and the placebo. Genes: PTGDS, PTGS1 and prostaglandin F synthase II-like had the highest differences in expression. Pathogen response pathways and complex immunological processes were identified for group 6, using the Kegg enrichment pathway. As discussed above, expression of genes, related to these pathways is decreased in group 6 and it is, most likely, a result of the lower viral load in this group. This difference in viral shedding distinguishes group 6 from placebo and thus makes it stand out in the category of response to pathogens, when compared to the placebo. In contrast group 5 received the same drugs but did not begin therapy until 2 days later on day 5. This is an important difference as our previous experience with this infection model for BRSV infection of young calves viral replication is well underway and clinical signs are usually apparent by day 5. There was some small difference in enhanced expression in immune response and chemotaxis pathways when group 5 was compared with placebo, but overall there was no significant benefit of these therapies for viral shedding or lung pathology. However, there was a significant benefit for decreased clinical signs, although less significant than for group 6 [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Based on these results of the transcriptome analysis we can predict that to be most effective dual therapy with FPI and ibuprofen must be initiated by day 3 or earlier if possible. Administration prior to or on day 3 is difficult both for human infants and bovine calves in natural infection cases as this timepoint is prior to the initiation of clinical signs. Potentially the use of FPI alone or with ibuprofen on day 3 (previously shown to be effective) could be initiated in cases of known or suspected exposure to BRSV/RSV [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs can cause ulceration of the gastrointestinal tract; and it has been shown that these chemicals are able not only to generate profound changes in physical and biochemical properties of the cell membrane [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], but also to affect tight junctions and intercellular connections through overexpression of prostasin caused by ibuprofen [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Cell adhesion tight junction KEGG pathways enrichment analysis showed the “Tight junction” pathway enriched when placebo was compared to groups treated with ibuprofen only and the group treated with FPI only. This enrichment of the "Tight junction" KEGG pathway in lung with lesion, most likely was not an effect of ibuprofen treatment, because this pathway was enriched in group 4, in which was not used. Cell damage and stress are likely the major factors involved here, because enrichment of this pathway was observed only in lung lesions.
</p>
