<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Gas vesicles are gas-filled prokaryotic organelles that function as flotation devices [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. A range of bacteria and archaea produces intracellular gas-filled proteinaceous structures to maintain a suitable depth in an aqueous environment [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Under conditions of nitrogen-replete conditions, cyanobacterial filaments consisted of only vegetative cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0248155.g001">Fig 1A</xref>); under nitrogen deprivation conditions, these filaments consisted of both vegetative cells and heterocysts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0248155.g001">Fig 1B</xref>). These results suggest that nitrogen deprivation induced heterocyst differentiation, which is consistent with previously reported findings [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In total, we identified eight DEGs encoding the gas vesicle protein (
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In the comparison of NVs vs. NDVs, six DEGs were highly downregulated, suggesting that nitrogen deprivation inhibits the expression of gas vesicle genes in vegetative cells; these results are consistent with most of the results obtained previously on gas vesicle protein regulation [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Furthermore, in the NDV vs. NDH comparison, three DEGs encoding gas vesicle genes were upregulated, suggesting that the expression of gas vesicle genes is higher in heterocysts than in vegetative cells under nitrogen deprivation conditions (
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Thus, the density of vegetative cells increases via inhibition of gas vesicle protein expression under nitrogen deprivation conditions. Our results are consistent with the phenomenon of water bloom under eutrophication conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and improve the understanding of the formation mechanism of water blooms at the transcription level.
</p>
