<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cooling curves corresponding to the BT48 rods with a diameter of 2 mm and 6 mm intersect the 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>n</italic>
 </sub>–line but not the 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>–line and thus go through the phase regions I, II, IV, and VI (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>). Once the 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>n</italic>
 </sub>–line is crossed β-Ti precipitates in the supercooled liquid. Before the composition of the supercooled liquid or the dendrites reaches the equilibrium composition, 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>f</italic>
 </sub> is traversed and the compositions and volume fractions are frozen in due to the limited mobility of atoms. At the glass transition temperature the supercooled liquid finally vitrifies and a BMGC is the outcome. In this cooling rate regime the composition and the volume fractions depend on the cooling rates. For this reason one obtains identical phases in case of rod with 6 mm in diameter but dendrites are Ti-richer and the glass is Ti-poorer compared to the rods with smaller diameters (ϕ2 mm). At the same time the crystalline volume fraction is somewhat larger because the system has a larger time window for β-Ti to precipitate and the dendrite size increases as well. In contrast, the cooling curves representing the larger rods (ϕ10 mm and ϕ20 mm) as well as the 100 g ingot of BT48 intersect the 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>n</italic>
 </sub>– and 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>–lines, and go through regions I, II, III, V, and VII (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>) before the microstructure evolution is effectively halted at 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>f</italic>
 </sub>. This in turn results in BMGCs in which the composition of the Ti dendrites and the glassy matrix and consequently also the respective volume fractions reach a quasi-equilibrium (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). Owing to the steep slopes near 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>f</italic>
 </sub> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>) the compositions of β-Ti and the supercooled liquid remain virtually constant near 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>f</italic>
 </sub>. The same holds for the volume fractions because of the conservation of mass. Instead, the main microstructural change in region III is the coarsening of the dendrites driven by the interfacial energy, known as Ostwald ripening
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. The cylindrical arm with a smaller diameter has a higher chemical potential. During the precipitation of β-Ti dendrites, the outer parts of the dendrite arms have larger diameters than the inner root parts. During ripening the root parts of β-Ti dissolve and then re-precipitate on the head parts, leading to a more particle-like morphology. Similarly, smaller particles have a higher chemical potential than the larger ones, causing large particles to become larger and more spherical, and smaller ones to become smaller and eventually to vanish
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. In other words, the lower cooling rates mean more time for ripening of the dendrites. The ripening process in region III also provides the possibility to design BMGCs with various shapes and sizes of β-Ti (without altering the volume fractions) by simply changing the cooling rates in this regime.
</p>
