<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent surveys of fish and mammalian insulin coding sequences have identified several species that have accumulated increased amounts of sequence change (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). However, in contrast to the sequences from the rodent suborder of Hystricomorpha and New World monkeys, the striking changes in these sequences were at sites involved in proteolytic processing. Insulin is composed of two peptide chains linked by disulphide bonds, with both peptide chains generated from a single precursor protein (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Studies on insulin emphasized the importance of proteolytic processing in the generation of bioactive peptides (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The insulin precursor undergoes two types of proteolytic processing to generate a functional hormone: 1) removal of its signal peptide, which is necessary for secretion, and 2) removal of the C-peptide to generate the two-chain molecule linked by disulphide bonds (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Evolutionary changes have occurred at all of these proteolytic sites. Changes in the sites of proteolytic processing of the insulin precursor had previously been observed, especially at the signal peptidase cleavage site and at the B-chain/C-peptide processing site (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). While some earlier studies have suggested altered proteolytic processing of proinsulin in some species of the most divergent classes of vertebrates, jawless and cartilaginous fish (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), recent studies of insulin gene sequences obtained from the genomic sequences of some species of bony fish and mammals predict amino acid replacements that abolish proteolytic processing at both the B-chain/C-peptide and the C-peptide/A-chain processing sites of insulin (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Almost all of the proinsulin sequences predicted by teleost fish 
 <italic>ins</italic> genes encode sequences that can be processed into two-chain insulin hormones, except for those encoded by 
 <italic>insab</italic> genes (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Most proinsulin sequences encoded by the 
 <italic>insab</italic> genes contain amino acid substitutions at their B-chain/C-peptide processing site that likely prevent proteolytic cleavage, with many of them also having substitutions that should impair processing at the C-peptide/A-chain site (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
  <bold>Figure 2</bold>
 </xref>), thus leading to improperly processed insulin molecules (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Similarly, insulin gene sequences from two bats (
 <italic>Myotis brandtii</italic> and 
 <italic>M. lucifugus</italic>) predict substitutions at both the A-chain/C-peptide and C-peptide/B-chain processing sites that should prevent processing (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
  <bold>Figure 2</bold>
 </xref>), while the insulin sequences from several species of Afrotheria [e.g., aardvark (
 <italic>Orycteropus afer</italic>)] likely have altered C-peptide/A-chain processing (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
  <bold>Figure 2</bold>
 </xref>) (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Thus, it is likely that the insulin genes of many vertebrate species generate a final protein product that is composed of either a single protein chain or are two-chain protein molecules that have an A- or a B-chains that is extended to include the complete C-peptide sequence (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Intriguingly, all of these insulin sequences with altered protein processing retain conserved cysteine residues that are important for disulphide bridging, thus, these proteins potentially retain three-dimensional structures that are similar to insulin and are also biologically functional.
</p>
