<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The aim of this work was the development of a reliable method to record isothermal time-temperature-precipitation diagrams of aluminum alloys by 
 <italic>in situ</italic> differential scanning calorimetry (DSC). Those diagrams may be used as a database for heat treatment simulations of the cooling step within the age hardening procedure, by applying Scheil’s additivity principle or Quench Factor Analysis, respectively [
 <xref rid="b2-materials-07-02631" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="b3-materials-07-02631" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In particular, in this work, the whole heat treatment cycle, containing solution annealing, overcritical quenching to a certain temperature and isothermal soaking, was performed in one single DSC device. Thereby, the dead time, in which precipitation might take place, but could not be recorded, was reduced to a minimum. Aluminum alloy EN AW-6005A was chosen, because its continuous cooling precipitation diagram is available for the particular batch investigated here. Thereby, the critical cooling rate, sufficient to suppress any precipitation during cooling, is known. Moreover, the here-used Perkin-Elmer Pyris 1 DSC in its applied configuration is able to cool faster than this critical cooling rate in the relevant temperature range. By this work, a data evaluation, suitable for revealing the reliable heat flow curves during isothermal soaking, is presented. Furthermore, a procedure suitable for determining the characteristic times of precipitation reactions is described. This procedure is based on peak values, but also on different fractions of the released amount of heat. Short periods of time, which were not measureable, due to device limitations, were approximated in a defined way. Additionally, the zero point of time for evaluation was defined. The time-temperature-precipitation diagram shows a general “C-curve” with three underlying weak noses. The first nose is located at 440 °C after about 135 s, the second at 370 °C after only about 22 s and the third at 300 °C after 80 s. At high temperatures, the precipitation of β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si was found. At medium temperatures, the precipitation of phases, like β’ and B’, and, at low temperatures, the precipitation of β” is assumed, based on literature data. The new method enables a very detailed 
 <italic>in situ</italic> analysis of precipitation during isothermal soaking. As one drawback, we admit that this procedure in its current state is only valid for medium or low concentrated aluminum alloys. As the cooling rate of the DSC device is limited at some K/s, only those medium- or low-alloyed compositions with a critical cooling rate low enough to be quenched over-critically in the Perkin Elmer Pyris 1 DSC can be studied. Nevertheless, the method developed here shows the way to go for high alloyed compositions with faster DSC devices, e.g., fast scanning chip calorimeters [
 <xref rid="b30-materials-07-02631" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="b41-materials-07-02631" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].
</p>
