<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our analysis highlighted several genes that appear to be clonally variantly expressed that are involved in invasion and located in euchromatic regions of the genome. This is in contrast to patterns of heterochromatin observed in asexual blood stages and transmission stages, where multigene families and some invasion pathways are clonally variant and regulated by heterochromatin (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Flueck et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Rubio et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Salcedo-Amaya et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Crowley et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Brancucci et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Fraschka et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Witmer et al., 2020</xref>). None of the genes we identified overlapped with those found to be heterochromatic regions in either 
 <italic>P. berghei</italic> asexual blood stages or ookinetes (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Fraschka et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Witmer et al., 2020</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">
  <bold>Figure S8</bold>
 </xref>). In general, we find that heterochromatic genes are largely silenced in ookinetes. In contrast, we find that in ookinetes variant gene expression is not necessarily a yes or no decision (as seen with heterochromatic genes in other life stages) but manifests as variable expression levels of non-heterochromatic genes. This is in stark contrast to how variegated gene expression is driven by heterochromatin in asexual blood stages. One limitation of this study is that clonally variant expression of preceding or subsequent stages for each experiment is unknown as we only sampled ookinetes. However, we do know that heterochromatic 
 <italic>pir</italic> genes are highly variable in male gametocytes (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Reid et al., 2018</xref>) and both male and females show higher expression of heterochromatic genes (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">
  <bold>Figure S8</bold>
 </xref>), but notably these data are from a different experimental infection and should be carefully interpreted. Still, the majority of the genes detected in our study are ookinete-specific and euchromatic, supporting a model of variegated expression in the invasive ookinete stage that is not driven/controlled by heterochromatin formation.
</p>
