<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In our analyses we identify some components of the IMC supporting invasion and invasion proteins themselves to be variably expressed. Remarkably, we found variation in response to the species of mosquitoes in which ookinetes develop. In the wild, parasites can encounter many vector species, for instance 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> can infect more than 70 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> species (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Sinka et al., 2012</xref>). Our observation raises the possibility that there exists some invasion plasticity to cater for the host environment, such a phenomenon would be an important consideration in the development of transmission blocking vaccines. For example, 
 <italic>P. berghei</italic> infections in 
 <italic>An. stephensi</italic> are more intense (
 <italic>i.e.</italic> have more oocysts) than in 
 <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alavi et al., 2003</xref>). The differentially expressed genes identified here may be actively involved in modulating infection intensity or may be differentially expressed 
 <italic>via</italic> selection on the parasite population. Secondly, we found invasion related variation in response to the mosquito environment within the same species suggesting that there is also fine tuning in response to more minor variations in the mosquito environment to potentially enhance transmission. A particularly interesting transcript identified in several of our analyses is CelTOS, a protein essential for invasion that actively takes part in membrane disruption during pore formation of the midgut epithelial cells in order for the ookinete to reach the basal lamina (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kariu et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Jimah et al., 2016</xref>). Although CelTOS is essential for ookinete invasion, lysis of the enterocyte can also have a deleterious effect on epithelial integrity of the gut and vector survival. It may therefore be advantageous for the parasite to modulate such lytic factors to maximize invasion whilst limiting host death in response to environment or as a population wide bet-hedging strategy to limit the number of invasion events within a single gut. Although such hypotheses would require much deeper validation, our data is suggestive of adaptive phenotypic plasticity of the parasite invasion machinery in response to environmental changes.
</p>
