<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">One group of transcripts strongly associated with the cytosol was the nuclear-encoded mitochondrial transcripts. The biogenesis of the mitochondria relies on dual genetic origins; the nuclear and the mitochondrial genomes, but 99% of the mitochondrial proteins are encoded in the nucleus
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. This imposes the need for tight coordination between the two compartments to regulate gene expression. The detailed mechanisms that regulate gene and protein expression coordination between the nucleus and the mitochondria are not well understood. Nevertheless, it is believed that this coordination occurs both at mRNA and protein levels. Previous reports demonstrated that many mRNAs encoding NEMPs are localized to the outer membrane of mitochondria and it is believed that these mRNAs are translated locally
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. It has also been demonstrated that mRNAs coding for NEMPs localize to and are translated by ribosomes in the cytoplasm
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. However, an accurate estimation of the fraction of NEMP mRNAs that localize to the mitochondrial-membrane and cytosol is still an open question, particularly in humans as most of the current knowledge thus far is based on drosophila and yeast
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, we demonstrate, for the first time, that NEMP mRNAs in the human brain are significantly enriched in the cytosol as compared to the rest of the protein-coding genes. We validated this observation in ENCODE cell lines, where independent extraction protocols were employed. We also showed that the cytosolic localization of NEMP mRNAs was not a result of their association to the mitochondrial membrane since the mitochondria end up in the nuclear fraction in our cellular fractionation procedure. NEMPs have previously been assigned to classes based on their location of translation in relation to mitochondria (MLR class)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>, but we found no correlation between increased cytosolic localization and MLR class (data not shown). We were also unable to find any correlation with the strength of the mitochondrial localization signal or scores based on evidence for mitochondrial localization (TargetP score or MitoCarta2.0 score) from the MitoCarta database
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup> (data not shown). We further determine that NEMP mRNAs on average have a longer half-life than the rest of protein-coding genes. Thus, our data suggest that NEMP mRNAs are rapidly transported from the nucleus after transcription and accumulate in the cytoplasm until their translation is required by the mitochondria. In line with our results, a recent study in yeast sought to monitor nuclear and mitochondrial gene expression during mitochondrial biogenesis. The study demonstrated that the synchronization between the two compartments does not occur on the transcriptional level. Instead, they are rapidly synchronized on protein translation level
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
