<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">A recent study by Lake et al
 <italic>.</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. found high concordance between single nuclei and whole-cell data and concluded the efficiency of single nuclei sequencing to interpret cellular diversity. We found on average more than 50% of cytosolic-enriched and nuclear-enriched transcripts from their study overlap with cytosolic and nuclear-enriched transcripts found in our data, despite the fact that the studies were performed in different species and with different RNA preparation and sequencing protocols. We also found overlap, particularly for the metabolic processes, between the two data sets for the list of ontology categories enriched in both the cytosol (or whole cell in the Lake et al. study) and nucleus. While we find a large overlap in genes identified as differentially expressed between samples using comparisons of cytosolic vs cytosolic and nuclear vs nuclear RNA, respectively, our data also highlight that certain categories of genes will give rise to differences in results depending on the cellular compartment used. This includes lncRNA, which are generally overrepresented in the nucleus, but primarily thought to be located in the compartment where they are functional. We further find many genes to be exclusively found in either cyto vs cyto or nuc vs nuc analysis, with e.g. differential expression of genes involved in translational processes and ribosomal function to be better assayed using cytosolic RNA. In single-cell analysis, there are now different protocols ranging from those employing very mild lysis that will primarily interrogate cytosolic RNA, to harsh lysis and single nucleus sequencing that will capture the whole cell or only nuclear RNA, respectively. Our results show important differences that may arise depending on the protocol used, and highlight the importance of which subcellular fraction that is analyzed in interpreting and comparing results from single-cell studies.
</p>
