<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order to reduce the interfacial impedance between cathode and SCEs, special structures of cathode and battery were designed. For example, Chen et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0100" ref-type="ref">100</xref> stacked the composite LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> cathode, PEO filled with Al‐LLZTO particles, and lithium foil layer by layer and then hot‐pressed to form a monolithic all‐solid‐state battery (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>9</bold>
 </xref>a). Ascribed to the relatively high viscosity and ductility of both composite cathode and electrolyte, no pores and voids were observed in the interfacial regions, which contribute to tight contact of cathode with SCE and quite less interfacial resistance. The as‐prepared all‐solid‐state battery demonstrates an ultrahigh surface discharge capacity of 10.8 mAh cm
 <sup>−2</sup> and an average specific discharge capacity of 155 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> at the current density of 100 µA cm
 <sup>−2</sup> at 60 °C. Similar method was also employed by Zha et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0101" ref-type="ref">101</xref> to fabricate all‐solid‐state Li/LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> battery with 90 wt% LLZTO/PEO electrolyte (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>b). The interfacial resistance of the cathode/electrolyte largely reduces from ≈248 to ≈62 Ω cm
 <sup>−2</sup> after wet coating and hot pressing. Our group reported a low resistance‐integrated all‐solid‐state battery using PEO‐based electrolyte embedded with LLZO nanowires (PLLN) and PEO/LITFSI as cathode binder (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>c).
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">57</xref> The PEO in both cathode and PLLN are fused at high temperature to form a stable integrated all‐solid‐state battery structure for high‐efficient ion transportation. The integrated LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/Li cell presents a specific capacity of 158.8 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> after 70 cycles under 0.5 C at 60 °C and a specific capacity of 158.7 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> after 80 cycles at 0.1 C and 45 °C. Therefore, the monolithic and integrated structures can greatly improve structure stability and reduce the interfacial resistance of the all‐solid‐state battery, which are promising all‐solid‐state battery structures for future practical application.
</p>
