<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Except good interfacial contact and well‐developed mixed conducting network, the wide electrochemical window of SCEs is indispensable for constructing a stable interface between cathode and SCE, which is quite significant for the application of high‐voltage cathode in high energy density system. Generally, the electrochemical window of polymer electrolyte is below 5 V versus Li/Li
 <sup>+</sup>, while that of ceramic electrolyte could be up to 9 V or even higher.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> For SCEs, the ceramic filler could widen the electrochemical window beyond 5 V to satisfy the most cathode materials with high working voltage.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">54</xref> Generally, the larger ceramic content could result in higher electrochemical stability.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">54</xref> The enhancement of electrochemical stability might be attributed to the following reasons. First, the dipole–dipole interaction between polymer chains and ceramic fillers can elevate the oxidation decomposition potential of polymer.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0099" ref-type="ref">99</xref> Second, the acidic surface sites of ceramic complex with the salt anions can suppress the migration of anions and thus limit their irreversible oxidation.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">42</xref> Third, the inorganic ceramic fillers can remove the impurities such as water in SCE from the interface.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">47</xref>
</p>
