<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Target analysis identified a number of potential lncRNA regulatory targets. Certain targets were previously reported to play an important role in the pathogenesis of osteoarthritis, although their potential function as regulatory targets for lncRNA shad not previously been suggested (
 <xref rid="b36-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="b37-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). For example, in the present study, integrin-α5 (ITGA5) was found to be a potential target of lncRNA ENSG00000257477, which is expressed at a 2.2787-fold higher level in normal cartilage than in osteoarthritis chondrocytes. ITGA5 can mediate mutual adhesion and two-way signal transduction between chondrocytes and the extracellular matrix (
 <xref rid="b38-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). ITGA5 is also involved in physiological processes including inflammation, differentiation and migration (
 <xref rid="b39-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), and the dedifferentiation of chondrocytes leads to a reduction in ITGA5(
 <xref rid="b40-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Another example is JNK, a potential target of lncRNA ENSG00000261496, which was found in the present study to be expressed at a 4.4304-fold higher level in osteoarthritis than in normal chondrocytes. Elevated levels of JNK and activation of the JNK signaling pathway may aggravate chondrocyte inflammation and cause cartilage degradation (
 <xref rid="b41-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Mice overexpressing JNK are more susceptible to osteoarthritis compared to normal mice (
 <xref rid="b42-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). In the present study, certain targets that have not previously been reported to play a role in osteoarthritis were identified as having a potential regulatory role in osteoarthritis. For example, high mobility group protein B1 (HMGB1), a late inflammatory regulator, has been studied for its role in coronary atherosclerosis and diabetes (
 <xref rid="b43-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="b44-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). However, results from the present study suggested that the expression level of HMGB1 was higher in articular cartilage tissue than in normal cartilage (~42.0320-fold), indicating that it may be a regulatory target of lncRNA ENSG00000272825, which plays a proinflammatory role (
 <xref rid="b45-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Interferon induced transmembrane protein 3 (IFITM3), a member of the IFITM gene family, is involved in cell adhesion, immune cell regulation and stem cell differentiation and maturation (
 <xref rid="b46-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). IFITM3also plays a role in tumor proliferation and viral infection (
 <xref rid="b47-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Microarray data suggested that IFITM3 may be the regulatory target of lncRNA ENSG00000277310. The expression level of IFITM3 was lower in arthritic cartilage than in normal cartilage, which may be related to the continuous dedifferentiation of chondrocytes [(
 <xref rid="b48-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), (
 <xref rid="SD1-etm-0-0-09796" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig S1</xref>)].
</p>
