<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Primary skin fibroblast cultures exhibit a patient-specific phenotype that recapitulates the PD chronological and epigenetic aging pattern, and are used as study models of several gene variants associated with PD (
 <xref rid="b17-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="b20-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="b40-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Therefore, skin fibroblast cultures of patients with PD and healthy controls were used in the present study to explore proteins affected by these two variants. Based on quantitative proteomics and PPI analysis, the top 25 proteins with expression levels affected by 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variants belong to three categories, including negative regulation of macromolecule metabolic processes (12 proteins, GO:0010605), an mRNA metabolic process (7 proteins, GO:0016071) and protein targeting to the membrane (4 proteins, GO:0006612). ANXA2 was the most highly upregulated gene in the fibroblasts of patients with PD exhibiting 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variants. ANXA2 is involved in calcium signalling and is associated with S100A11 and TAGLN, which were also highly upregulated in the GBA fibroblasts of patients with PD. ANXA2 and S100A11 are Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-dependent binding proteins, whereas TAGLN is an actin cross-linking protein involved in Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> interactions and regulates contractile properties (
 <xref rid="b41-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). It has been reported that several PD-associated proteins, including GBA, are associated with Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> homeostasis (
 <xref rid="b42-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Kilpatrick 
 <italic>et al</italic> (
 <xref rid="b43-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) demonstrated that the GBA fibroblasts of patients with PD exhibited an increase in cytosolic Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>, whereas the lysosomal Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> store content was reduced. The authors suggested that accelerated remodelling of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> stores by GBA may be involved in PD pathogenesis. ANXA2 is a multicompartmental protein that serves important roles in a range of intracellular membrane-related functions, including organization of specialized membrane microdomains, recruitment of peripheral membrane proteins, and regulation of membrane fusion and repair events (
 <xref rid="b44-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). It has been reported that single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) of ANXA2 were associated with an increased risk of stroke (
 <xref rid="b45-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), and were a risk factor of avascular necrosis of the bone (osteonecrosis (
 <xref rid="b46-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). ANXA2 is involved in numerous biological processes, including stress responses. It was reported that ANXA2 expression is increased after starvation, and this increase is associated with autophagy (
 <xref rid="b47-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). ANXA2 is considered to be a brain pathology-associated protein, since its expression is increased under pathological conditions in various brain diseases (
 <xref rid="b48-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="b49-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), but it was undetectable in the neurons and glial cells of a normal healthy brain (
 <xref rid="b50-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Furthermore, another study showed that skin fibroblasts of patients with PD exhibiting 
 <italic>GBA</italic> variants have altered GCase activity and impaired autophagic flux (
 <xref rid="b40-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). S100A11 is implicated in membrane and cytoskeletal dynamics. It can interact with multiple cytoskeletal proteins, including tubulin, actin, ANXA1 and ANXA2(
 <xref rid="b51-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Scherzer 
 <italic>et al</italic> (
 <xref rid="b52-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) reported that the S100A11 level was upregulated in peripheral blood samples of patients with PD. In addition, the S100A11 level was increased in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, a neurodegenerative disease affecting motor neurons in the spinal cord and motor cortex (
 <xref rid="b53-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). These data suggest that aberrant expression of ANXA2 and S100A11 may contribute to PD pathogenesis; however, further studies are required to clarify the mechanism(s) by which decreased GCase activity affects autophagic flux and the roles of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> in the function of ANXA2 and S100A11 in the cells of patients with PD.
</p>
