<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>PARK2</italic> variants are involved in the alteration of proteins via three mechanisms, including regulation of biological quality (16 proteins, GO:0065008), cytoskeleton organization (8 proteins, GO:0019674) and NAD metabolic process (4 proteins, GO:0019674). The levels of TUBB showed the highest degree of upregulation in the PARK2 group. TUBB was directly linked to TUBA1B and GAPDH, which are involved in cytoskeleton organization (GO:0019674). It has been reported that the expression of several cytoskeletal proteins is altered in neurodegenerative diseases (
 <xref rid="b17-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="b57-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="b58-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Microtubules, composed of α and β forms, are essential components of neurons, and defects in tubulin genes are likely to cause neuronal diseases (
 <xref rid="b59-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). It was reported that 
 <italic>de novo</italic> mutations in TUBB5 (M299V, V353I and E401K) were found in microcephalic patients with structural brain abnormalities. These mutants were observed to affect the chaperone-dependent assembly of tubulin heterodimers, and to disrupt neurogenic division and/or migration 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="b60-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Generally, α and β-tubulins can polymerize as heterodimers that join to form microtubules. The correct folding of tubulin monomers and the formation of functional α/β heterodimers require a series of cellular chaperonins and co-factors (
 <xref rid="b61-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). It was reported that parkin protein binds to α/β tubulin, and increases their ubiquitination as well as the degradation of misfolded tubulins in order to prevent cytotoxicity (
 <xref rid="b62-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). Cartelli 
 <italic>et al</italic> (
 <xref rid="b57-br-0-0-01412" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>) showed an increased level of β-tubulin and actin in skin fibroblasts of patients with PD carrying 
 <italic>PARK2</italic> variants. These data are consistent with our results. Nevertheless, further investigation is required to determine why the β-tubulin found in skin fibroblasts of patients with PD carrying 
 <italic>PARK2</italic> variants is upregulated, and whether these increased levels are related to misfolding and malfunctions of ubiquitination.
</p>
