<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For rare functional variants analysis, we defined rare SNVs as minor allele frequency &lt;1% in East Asian population from multiple public databases, including 1000 Genomes Project (release in 2013 May), Exome Aggregation Consortium (ExAC r0.3.1) and Genome Aggregation Database (exome samples data). Then, we classified those coding rare SNVs based on their functional annotation: loss of function (LOF, including start loss, stop loss and splicing site) and missense SNVs. From these annotations, we created two rare variants sets for single gene testing: (1) all functional SNVs (both LOF and missense), (2) only LOF SNVs. Both analyses mentioned above were used optimal sequencing kernel association test (SKAT-O, with parameter: number permutation = 10,000, alpha = 0.05, beta1 = 1, beta2 = 20) in KGGseq software (v1.0) [
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. We defined the genes with 
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 statistically significance as candidate loci. In order to identify most potential risk loci, we used influenza A pathway genes from KEGG database (hsa05164) as training gene set and performed a further ranking analysis of all the candidate genes using the ToppGene software [
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. ToppGene is a one-stop portal for gene list enrichment analysis and candidate gene prioritization based on their functional annotations and protein interactions network. In addition, we used STRING software (v 11.0, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://string-db.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://string-db.org/</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] to build the protein interaction networks (combined sore &gt; 0.4) of these candidate genes. Then, Cytoscape (v3.5.1) software [
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] was used to visualize the largest network diagram and speculate the hub genes through the cytoHubba plug-in.
</p>
