<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The CARDS TX, both produced by natural infection and the recombinant form (rCARDS TX), can elicit profound inflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="cit0217" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0218" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>]. In a murine model of 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> infection, the level of CARDS TX in bronchiolar lavage fluid was positively correlated with pathological changes in the lungs and the severity of the disease [
 <xref rid="cit0218" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>]. Moreover, a clinical study assessing children with refractory 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> pneumonia demonstrated that CARDS TX and TNF-α co-expression is associated with enhanced pulmonary inflammatory infiltration and mucus secretion [
 <xref rid="cit0219" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>]. The exposure of rCARDS TX to the pulmonary compartment in both mice and baboons causes a prolonged inflammatory response, infiltration of inflammatory cells around the bronchus and blood vessels, and airway dysfunction. Such inflammation is characterized by rapid expression of proinflammatory cytokines and chemokines with the concurrent development of lymphocytic inflammation [
 <xref rid="cit0220" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>]. In addition, intratracheal instillation of rCARDS TX is sufficient to elicit allergic-type pulmonary inflammation or to exacerbates ovalbumin-induced asthma-like inflammation in mice, and is characterized by eosinophilia, mucus metaplasia, airway hyperreactivity, and T-helper-2 type cytokine and chemokine expression [
 <xref rid="cit0217" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0221" ref-type="bibr">221</xref>]. The inflammatory pathology and lung dysfunction are largely dependent on CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells. However, Maselli et al. confirmed that the kinetics of the T cell response of primates to CARDS TX or 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> is delayed than that of murines [
 <xref rid="cit0222" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>]. Both single- and double-dose rCARDS TX are equally sufficient to increase the total IgE and rCARDS TX-specific IgE levels in serum [
 <xref rid="cit0223" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>]. The latter can bind to the N-terminal peptide of CARDS TX and cause mast cell degranulation. The N-terminal peptide of CARDS TX can also cause mast cell degranulation [
 <xref rid="cit0223" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>], indicating that CARDS TX generates functional lgE and that the mast cell-lgE axis is critical for CARDS TX-mediated allergic inflammation. Furthermore, CARDS TX not only causes inflammation of the respiratory system but can also mediate the deterioration of ciliary movement of the respiratory tract, epithelial cell damage, and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
