<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">The hundred- to hundred-million-fold reductions in intrinsic cancer risk associated with the evolution of large body sizes in some Afrotherian lineages, in particular Elephantimorphs such as elephants and mastodons, suggests that these lineages must have also evolved remarkable mechanisms to suppress cancer. While our initial hypothesis was that large-bodied lineages would be uniquely enriched in duplicate tumor suppressor genes compared to other smaller-bodied lineages, we unexpectedly found that the duplication of genes in tumor suppressor pathways occurred at various points throughout the evolution of Afrotheria, regardless of body size. These data suggest that this abundance of tumor suppressors may have contributed to the evolution of large bodies and reduced cancer risk, but that these processes were not necessarily coincident. Interestingly, pervasive duplication of tumor suppressors may also have contributed to the repeated evolution of large bodies in hyraxes and sea cows, because at least some of the genetic changes that underlie the evolution of reduced cancer risk were common in this group. It remains to be determined whether our observation of pervasive duplication of tumor suppressors also occurs in other multicellular lineages. Using a similar reciprocal best BLAST/BLAT approach that focused on estimating copy number of known tumor suppressors in mammalian genomes, for example, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Caulin et al., 2015</xref> found no correlation between copy number or tumor suppressors with either body mass or longevity, whereas <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Tollis et al., 2020</xref> found a correlation between copy number and longevity (but not body size) (<xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Tollis et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Caulin et al., 2015</xref>). These opposing conclusions may result from differences in the number of genes (81 vs 548) and genomes (8 vs 63) analyzed, highlighting the need for genome-wide analyses of many species that vary in body size and longevity.</p>