<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F0006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 6.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Lipid-stimulated ATPase activity of PcATP2/PcCdc50B complex. The apparent ATPase activity of the PcATP2/PcCdc50B complex was measured by spectrophotometric quantification of the released inorganic phosphate in the absence (no lipid) and in the presence of the indicated lipids. POPS, 1-palmitoyl-2-oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phospho-L-serine, and POPE, 1-palmitoyl-2-oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphoethanolamine. As indicated, ATPase assays were also performed in the presence (+) or in the absence (-) of phosphatidylinositol-4-phosphate (PI4P). Gray bars and white bars represent, respectively, the activity of the wild-type (WT) and the functionally-impaired D596N mutant (DN) at each experimental condition. The reaction was performed at 37°C during 25 min, and initiated by the addition of 1 mM ATP-Mg
   <sup>2+</sup>. The bars display the average value of 
   <italic>n </italic>= 3 or 
   <italic>n </italic>= 4 experimental datapoints, and the indicated error is the standard deviation. The upper panel displays the SDS-PAGE of the acid-eluted content of the immobilized wild-type (WT) or D596N mutant (DN) agarose beads used for this experiments. (
   <italic>A</italic>) Coomassie-stained, (B) western blot using the antibody against the GFP to detect PcATP2-GFP, and (
   <italic>C</italic>) western blot using the HisProbe
   <sup>TM</sup> to detect the 10xHis tag fused to PcCdc50B 
   <italic>.</italic>* 
   <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.05 (paired t-test). Note that the DN mutant of PcATP2 runs slightly faster because it lacks the BAD domain.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="TEMI_A_1870413_F0006_OC" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="TEMI_A_1870413_F0006_PB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </alternatives>
</fig>
