<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently, DIscBIO provides limited options for normalization, clustering, differential analysis and cell type identification. However, its open, versatile and dynamic structure enables users with programming skills to fully edit the pipeline and include other methods. Through the Jupyter notebook, we showcase how additional methods, such as Leiden clustering, can be added to the pipeline. The Leiden clustering algorithm has the ability of identifying high-quality partitions [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. It does not require a cluster number a priori. The notebook is available at 
 <uri xlink:href="https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ocbe-uio/DIscBIO/blob/dev/notebook/DIscBIO-CTCs-Binder-Leiden-Clustering.ipynb" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ocbe-uio/DIscBIO/blob/dev/notebook/DIscBIO-CTCs-Binder-Leiden-Clustering.ipynb</uri>. Importantly, the features of DIscBIO can be expanded in future work to include other methods, such as SCDE and scTyper. SCDE is an alternative tool for differential analysis [
 <xref rid="B54-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. It was developed by the Kharchenko lab specifically for single-cell RNA-seq data. SCDE uses Bayesian probability and can handle the technical artifacts of single-cell RNA sequencing. RaceID, which is the fundamental tool in DIscBIO, is well known for identifying rare cell types with limited efficiency in the absence of rare cell populations [
 <xref rid="B55-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. On the other hand, scTyper is an R package for reproducible and comprehensive cell typing, equipped with 213 cell marker sets collected from the literature [
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Incorporating such tools in DIscBIO can enable users to compare the differential analysis outcome from tools designed for bulk RNAseq (SAMseq) and scRNAseq (SCDE) in addition to identifying cell types in heterogeneous cell populations, with and without rare cell populations.
</p>
