<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A sensitive tool to probe particle interactions with adsorbates and supports is XANES data analysis and, in particular, the analysis of the shape and intensity of the white line and shifts in the position of the absorption edge. Both are known to respond to the changes in the electronic structure or charge transfer between the catalyst and its environment. In particular, by performing XAS measurements at different temperatures for Al
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>-supported Pt NPs with different sizes and shapes in H
 <sub>2</sub> and He atmospheres, Behafarid et al. associated the blue shift and an increase in the integrated area of the differential Pt L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge XANES spectrum with an increase in the hydrogen coverage.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref357">357</xref>
 </sup> The same approach was used by Mistry et al. to quantify the increase of the hydrogen coverage per surface Pt atom with increasing H
 <sub>2</sub> pressure, which was found to be in a good agreement with the predictions from theoretical models (
 <xref rid="fig22" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig22" ref-type="fig">22</xref>
 </xref>a–c).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref287">287</xref>
 </sup> Interestingly, the observed shift of the Pt L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge XANES with increasing hydrogen coverage correlates with the shift of the center of the unoccupied d-band states, as obtained in DFT simulations by Behafarid et al. (
 <xref rid="fig22" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig22" ref-type="fig">22</xref>
 </xref>d).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref357">357</xref>
 </sup> The same method was used by Small et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref343">343</xref>
 </sup> to monitor temperature- and pressure-dependent CO and H
 <sub>2</sub> coverages on Pt NPs. During the last decades, the analysis of the shape and intensity of the Pt L-edge has turned to be a crucial tool for monitoring the catalyst interaction with adsorbates and reaction intermediates in 
 <italic>operando</italic> studies of Pt-based catalysts for ORR,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref141">141</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref358">358</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref359">359</xref>
 </sup> as discussed in more detail in 
 <xref rid="sec6.2.2" ref-type="other">Section 
  <xref rid="sec6.2.2" ref-type="other">6.2.2</xref>
 </xref>.
</p>
