<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic> adhesin P97 is a cilium adhesin that can undergo antigenic variation and is thus involved in evasion of the host immune response [
 <xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. P68 is another 
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic> cilium adhesin that mediates the occurrence of inflammatory response and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Wherease, recent documents indicated that some surface-exposed adhesins, such as P216, P159, P146, P116, Mhp271, Mhp107 and Mhp683, are generated through endoproteolytic cleavage of the P97/P102 paralog family, and all of which are ECM-binding adhesins [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40–46</xref>]. The P146 cilium adhesin bind to Plg through the C-terminal lysine and arginine residues [
 <xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Moreover, the EF-Tu and GAPDH of 
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic> are Fn-binding adhesins and the ciliary border of the airway is the target for EF-Tu adhesion [
 <xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. With the gradual advancement in the study on mycoplasma pathogenicity, some multifunctional enzymes have been considered as adhesins, for example, 
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic> expresses fructose-1, 6-bisphosphate aldolase (FBA) and L-lactate dehydrogenase [
 <xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The function of FBA is similar to that in 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic>, including invasion and persistent infections [
 <xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Moreover, both MHJ_0125, a glutamyl aminopeptidase, and MHJ_0461, a leucine aminopeptidase, have moonlighting roles as adhesins on the surface of 
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic>; MHJ_0461 also binds to foreign double-stranded DNA [
 <xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Eno in 
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic> and 
 <italic>M. suis</italic> also play crucial roles in adherence, invasion, and infections [
 <xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
</p>
