<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep19235</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep19235</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Two-phase quasi-equilibrium in &#x003b2;-type Ti-based bulk metallic glass composites</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M. Q.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H. F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Shenyang National Laboratory for Materials Science, Institute of Metal Research, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, 110016 Shenyang, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>IFW Dresden, Institute for Complex Materials</institution>, P.O. Box 27 01 16, D-01069 Dresden, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>TU Dresden, Institute of Materials Science</institution>, D-01062 Dresden, <country>Germany</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>hfzhang@imr.ac.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c2"><label>b</label><email>s.pauly@ifw-dresden.de</email></corresp><fn id="n1"><label>*</label><p>Present address: Erich Schmid Institute of Materials Science, Austrian Academy of Sciences, Jahnstra&#x000df;e 12, A-8700 Leoben, Austria; Department Materials Physics, Montanuniversit&#x000e4;t Leoben, Jahnstra&#x000df;e 12, A-8700 Leoben, Austria.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>01</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>19235</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>07</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016, Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The microstructural evolution of cast Ti/Zr-based bulk metallic glass composites (BMGCs) containing &#x003b2;-Ti still remains ambiguous. This is why to date the strategies and alloys suitable for producing such BMGCs with precisely controllable volume fractions and crystallite sizes are still rather limited. In this work, a Ti-based BMGC containing &#x003b2;-Ti was developed in the Ti-Zr-Cu-Co-Be system. The glassy matrix of this BMGC possesses an exceptional glass-forming ability and as a consequence, the volume fractions as well as the composition of the &#x003b2;-Ti dendrites remain constant over a wide range of cooling rates. This finding can be explained in terms of a two-phase quasi-equilibrium between the supercooled liquid and &#x003b2;-Ti, which the system attains on cooling. The two-phase quasi-equilibrium allows predicting the crystalline and glassy volume fractions by means of the lever rule and we succeeded in reproducing these values by slight variations in the alloy composition at a fixed cooling rate. The two-phase quasi-equilibrium could be of critical importance for understanding and designing the microstructures of BMGCs containing the &#x003b2;-phase. Its implications on the nucleation and growth of the crystalline phase are elaborated.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Bulk metallic glasses (BMGs) are metastable alloys, which are commonly produced through rapid solidification of metallic melts<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. They generally exhibit high strengths, a large elastic limit, and good corrosion resistance because the lack of translational symmetry does not permit lattice defects such as grain boundaries or dislocations, which their crystalline counterparts usually contain<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. However, BMGs generally do not exhibit any significant macroscopic plasticity in tension<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref> since the plastic deformation is highly localized in narrow regions termed shear bands<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>. In order to enhance the ductility, bulk metallic glass composites (BMGCs) composed of (a) soft crystalline phase(s) and a glassy matrix have been developed<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>. The ductile crystalline particles act as obstacles for shear bands and hence hamper the rapid propagation of a detrimental shear band. Instead, these heterogeneities often even multiply the number of shear bands<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>. Depending on the nature of the crystalline phase, the currently widely-studied <italic>in-situ</italic> BMGCs can be classified into two main groups<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>: (i) CuZr-based BMGCs containing B2 CuZr<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, which precipitates during cooling and (ii) Zr/Ti-based BMGCs, in which &#x003b2;-Zr/Ti dendrites are embedded in a glassy matrix<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>. However, CuZr-based BMGCs have two drawbacks: they are relatively poor glass formers, which severely restricts the dimensions of the samples and, simultaneously, it is rather difficult to control the morphology (volume fraction, size and distribution of the B2 phase) of the microstructure<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. Both factors negatively affect the reproducibility of microstructures and the respective mechanical properties<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>.</p><p>Similarly, the glass-forming ability (GFA) of the glassy matrices of Zr/Ti-based BMGCs is often also limited and the critical casting thicknesses are known to be generally below 20&#x02009;mm<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. More importantly, the volume fraction of the &#x003b2;-phase can be only adjusted in a relatively small range of cooling rates during Bridgman solidification<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. An alternative route to tailor the microstructure is to modify the Be content of the glass-forming alloys, whose microstructure is then designed in the course of a semi-solid treatment<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. Therefore, developing novel BMGCs comprising a glassy matrix with an exceptional high GFA is needed from a practical point of view and, simultaneously, a more advanced and detailed understanding of the solidification process in these particular BMGCs is required in order to produce novel BMGCs with custom-made microstructures.</p><p>In this work, a Ti<sub>45.7</sub>Zr<sub>33.0</sub>Cu<sub>5.8</sub>Co<sub>3.0</sub>Be<sub>12.5</sub> (at.%) alloy was developed consisting of &#x003b2;-Ti dendrites embedded in a glassy matrix. The Be-rich matrix (Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub>) can congeal into glassy ingots with a weight of up to 150&#x02009;g. A two-phase quasi-equilibrium between two metastable phases, i.e. the supercooled liquid and &#x003b2;-Ti dictates the compositions of both phases as well as the according volume fractions. Based on the lever rule, a series of BMGCs with precisely controllable fractions of &#x003b2;-Ti was successfully produced for alloys with crystalline volume fractions above 30%. The influence of the cooling rates on the microstructures of these BMGCs is also elucidated. The two-phase quasi-equilibrium has strong implications on designing and understanding the evolution of typical microstructures found in cast BMGCs containing the &#x003b2;-phase.</p><sec disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><p>In order to avoid listing a vast number of multicomponent alloys with only slightly varying compositions, we will use a special abbreviation for all alloys investigated in this work. The sample name indicates the expected crystalline mole fraction. &#x0201c;BT48&#x0201d; for example represents a composition, which contains 48%&#x02009;mole of crystals and 52%&#x02009;mole of glass. This estimation is based on the lever rule for the quasi-equilibrium phase diagram <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1"/><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2"/>(cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). This can then be converted into volume fractions (see methods). BT0 (Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub>) hence labels the composition of the glassy phase and BT100 represents the composition of the &#x003b2;-Ti dendrites (Ti<sub>60.58</sub>Zr<sub>36.11</sub>Cu<sub>2.30</sub>Co<sub>1.01</sub>) as determined by means of wavelength-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (WDS, see <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1"/><xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). As we will see below the volume fraction of these alloys is constant for a wide range of cooling rates. Therefore we do not need to specify a particular cooling rate for these alloys.</p><sec disp-level="2"><title>Microstructures of the alloy BT48 cast at different cooling rates</title><p>The microstructures of the as-cast rods of the alloy BT48 (Ti<sub>45.7</sub>Zr<sub>33.0</sub>Cu<sub>5.8</sub>Co<sub>3.0</sub>Be<sub>12.5</sub>) with diameters of 2&#x02009;mm, 6&#x02009;mm, 10&#x02009;mm, and 20&#x02009;mm, as well as of a 100&#x02009;g ingot are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1a&#x02013;e</xref>, respectively. All five samples show a similar two-phase microstructure containing dendrites and a featureless matrix. The bright-field transmission electron microscopy (TEM) image of the rod with a diameter of 6&#x02009;mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1f</xref>) depicts the dendritic phase and the matrix at a much higher magnification. Very sharp interfaces are visible and the selected area electron diffraction image can be indexed according to &#x003b2;-Ti. A halo is superimposed on the diffractions spots, which indicates the presence of an amorphous phase. The differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) traces of all samples are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1g</xref>. A glass transition (marked with arrows) precedes the exothermic crystallization events and it can be concluded that the matrix is indeed glassy. At high temperatures (above 850&#x02009;K) the endothermic transformation from &#x003b1;-Ti to &#x003b2;-Ti is detectable.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1a&#x02013;e</xref> proves that the morphology of the dendrites changes with cooling rate. The faster the cooling, the finer the dendrites become. In the case of the ingot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1e</xref>) the dendrite arms are almost circular in the cross-sectional cut. Based on these micrographs we analyzed the particle size and crystalline volume fraction as a function of cooling rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1h</xref>). In this work, &#x0201c;particle size&#x0201d; refers to the diameters of the secondary dendrite arms as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1b</xref> to facilitate the comparison. The average particle sizes gradually increases from 1.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 &#x003bc;m (&#x003d5;2&#x02009;mm) to 3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 &#x003bc;m (&#x003d5;6&#x02009;mm) to 5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 &#x003bc;m (&#x003d5;10&#x02009;mm) to 8.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3 &#x003bc;m (&#x003d5;20&#x02009;mm) and eventually to 15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5 &#x003bc;m in the case of the 100&#x02009;g ingot. The volume fractions (for the conversion please see Methods) of &#x003b2;-Ti in the &#x003d5;2&#x02009;mm and &#x003d5;6&#x02009;mm rods are about 41.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5% and 48.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5%, respectively. While the crystalline volume fraction initially increases it remains constant within the experimental uncertainty for the rods with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm and 20&#x02009;mm as well as for the 100&#x02009;g ingot (52.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9&#x02009;vol.%). This suggests that only coarsening of the &#x003b2;-Ti dendrites occurs above a critical cooling rate.</p><p>From secondary ion mass spectrometry (SIMS) conducted for the rod with a diameter of 20&#x02009;mm (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>), it is clear that the dendrites are Ti-rich, Cu&#x02013; and Co-lean. The Be-signal in &#x003b2;-Ti is very week, suggesting that only a very small amount of Be is dissolved in &#x003b2;-Ti, a phenomenon commonly observed in Be-containing BMGCs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. Since it is impossible to accurately determine the content of a light element like Be in the glass or the dendrites by microscopic techniques, we shall assume in the following that all Be is dissolved in the glassy matrix. This approximation of course has an impact on the estimated compositions of the glass and the Ti dendrites. But the SIMS results imply that this error in composition should be rather small and, after all, should not affect the concept of a quasi-equilibrium we want to put forward here. The other elements dissolved in the dendrites were measured by means of electron probe micro analyzer (EPMA) with WDS for all samples excluding the 2&#x02009;mm rod due to its small particle size. The values are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>. The composition of &#x003b2;-Ti in the rods with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm and 20&#x02009;mm as well as in the 100&#x02009;g ingot are almost identical. The concentration of Ti and Zr is higher and that of Cu and Co is lower compared with the composition of &#x003b2;-Ti in the &#x003d5;6&#x02009;mm rod.</p><p>These compositional differences of the constituent phases in the case of the &#x003d5;6&#x02009;mm rod and the other samples also reflect in the DSC traces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1g</xref>). The second crystallization event (~740&#x02009;K) is about 3&#x02009;K lower for the 6&#x02009;mm rod compared to the 10&#x02009;mm, 20&#x02009;mm rods and the 100&#x02009;g ingot. This indicates that the composition of the matrix in the 6&#x02009;mm rod might be slightly different. In addition, the &#x003b1; &#x02192; &#x003b2; transformation peak (~860&#x02009;K) detected in the rod having a diameter of 6&#x02009;mm shifts by about 4&#x02009;K to lower temperatures (marked by a rectangular). A lower &#x003b1;-to-&#x003b2; transformation temperature generally indicates that the &#x003b2;-Ti dendrites in the 6&#x02009;mm rod contain a slightly higher amount of &#x003b2;-stabilizers (Cu and Co) than the other samples<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. This is indeed consistent with the EPMA results obtained for the other samples (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). Similar differences are also observed for the DSC curve of the &#x003d5;2&#x02009;mm rod. However, the almost identical DSC traces of the larger rods (&#x003d5;10 and &#x003d5;20&#x02009;mm) and of the 100&#x02009;g ingot suggest that the glass and dendrites are chemically identical in these samples. The composition of the glassy matrix in the 100&#x02009;g ingot was also obtained by EPMA, which does not allow for the concentration of Be (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). The EPMA results was further verified by considering the mass conservation for each element:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e411" xlink:href="srep19235-m1.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <inline-formula id="d33e414"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e415" xlink:href="srep19235-m2.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="d33e417"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e418" xlink:href="srep19235-m3.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="d33e420"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e421" xlink:href="srep19235-m4.jpg"/></inline-formula> are the concentrations of each element <italic>i</italic> (<italic>i</italic>: Ti, Zr, Cu, Co) in &#x003b2;-Ti, in the glassy matrix and in the nominal composition, respectively. 0.125 and <italic>x</italic> are the Be content in the overall composition and the mole fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti, respectively, which has been measured from the micrographs in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>. The estimation based on all four elements (Ti, Zr, Cu and Co) yield very similar values with regard to the &#x003b2;-Ti mole fraction, <italic>x</italic>, in the 100&#x02009;g ingot (Ti: <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;47.91%, Zr: <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;47.85%, Cu: <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;47.88%, Co: <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;48.02%). In other words, the EPMA results seem to be consistent. We used the mean value of <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;47.9% as the mole fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti phase, which is in good agreement with the measured volume fraction of 52.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1h</xref>). Applying the approximation discussed above we recalculated the composition of the glassy matrix by assuming that all Be is dissolved in the glass (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). The estimated compositions of the glassy matrix and &#x003b2;-Ti are Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub> (at.%, BT0) and Ti<sub>60.58</sub>Zr<sub>36.11</sub>Cu<sub>2.30</sub>Co<sub>1.01</sub> (at.%, BT100), respectively.</p><p>The present results imply that the glassy matrix is an exceptional glass former because it does not crystallize even in the 100&#x02009;g ingot and it even restricts the growth of &#x003b2;-Ti. In order to evaluate the glass-forming ability of BT0, a Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub> ingot with a weight of 150&#x02009;g was produced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref>). It has a mirror-like surface and the corresponding XRD pattern (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2b</xref>) proves that it is fully amorphous. Because the cooling rate at which a 100&#x02009;g ingot solidifies is equivalent to that of the cylinder with a diameter of 50&#x02009;mm quenched in water<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref> or in a copper mould<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>, BT0 is one of the best BMG formers developed so far<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>, comparable to Vitreloy 1.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Two-phase quasi-equilibrium</title><p>As suggested by Lin and Johnson<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>, the typical cooling rate during copper mould casting can be estimated by the following equation:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq5"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e532" xlink:href="srep19235-m5.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>R</italic> and <inline-formula id="d33e538"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e539" xlink:href="srep19235-m6.jpg"/></inline-formula> are the sample radius and the cooling rate, respectively. This estimation yields the following cooling rates for the various samples: 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;Ks<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (&#x003d5;2&#x02009;mm), 1.1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;Ks<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (&#x003d5;6&#x02009;mm), 40&#x02009;Ks<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (&#x003d5;10&#x02009;mm), 10&#x02009;Ks<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (&#x003d5;20&#x02009;mm) and 1.6&#x02009;Ks<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (100&#x02009;g ingot). It is known that the cooling rate usually has a strong influence on the volume fraction of the &#x003b2;-phase in Zr/Ti-based BMGCs and the volume fractions tend to increase with lowering the cooling rates<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. Because the cooling rate in the 100&#x02009;g ingot is more than 20 times lower than in the case of the rod with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm, there is much more time for the precipitation of &#x003b2;-Ti. Consequently, the crystalline volume fraction should be much higher in the ingot than in the &#x003d5;10&#x02009;mm rod. Contrary to expectation, the volume fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti does not change when the cooling rate is between 40 and 1.6&#x02009;K s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and only the dendrites become coarser (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1h</xref>).</p><p>A possible mechanism to explain the current findings is to assume that the system attains a quasi-equilibrium between two metastable phases during cooling. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3a</xref> depicts the schematic binary phase diagram for the present alloy system. The green solid lines indicate the equilibrium phase diagram. Next to the complex mixture of equilibrium phases (e.g.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> Be<sub>2</sub>Zr and Cu<sub>10</sub>Zr<sub>7</sub>) at Cu-Co-Be-rich compositions, only &#x003b2;-Ti and the liquid phase have to be considered. As observed for most glass-forming Zr/Ti-based alloys<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>, the present system is a eutectic one. Besides the equilibrium lines, the red dotted lines belonging to a metastable phase diagram are displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>. The left two red dashed lines describe the temperatures at which nucleation of &#x003b2;-Ti or the other crystalline phases (Be<sub>2</sub>Zr and Cu<sub>10</sub>Zr<sub>7</sub>) sets in. The degree of undercooling for a given composition is then determined by the temperature difference between the equilibrium liquidus line and the metastable liquidus line. For higher cooling rates, the degree of undercooling will increase and thus the red dashed liquidus lines will shift to lower temperatures. The red dotted line at high Ti concentrations reflects the solubility of Cu, Co and Be in &#x003b2;-Ti during fast cooling. Quenching of metallic melts generally results in supersaturation by solute trapping at the early stages of crystallization<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref> and therefore the red dotted line is placed left of the equilibrium solidus line (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p>At the specified composition BT48 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>), &#x003b2;-Ti begins to precipitate when the melt is cooled down and intersects the red dotted line at <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>. The liquid&#x02019;s composition is <inline-formula id="d33e620"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e621" xlink:href="srep19235-m7.jpg"/></inline-formula> and that of &#x003b2;-Ti is <inline-formula id="d33e623"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e624" xlink:href="srep19235-m8.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Growth of the &#x003b2;-phase nuclei is controlled by atomic diffusion<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. When the temperature falls below <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>, the volume fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti increases quickly due to the fast atomic diffusion in the slightly undercooled liquid. The contribution of the element <italic>i</italic> to the growth velocity, <italic>g</italic><sup><italic>i</italic></sup>, is given by<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq9"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e648" xlink:href="srep19235-m9.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <inline-formula id="d33e651"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e652" xlink:href="srep19235-m10.jpg"/></inline-formula> is the molar chemical potential difference of the element <italic>i</italic> between the undercooled liquid and crystalline phase (here: &#x003b2;-Ti), <inline-formula id="d33e657"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e658" xlink:href="srep19235-m11.jpg"/></inline-formula> is a constant at temperature <italic>T</italic>, and <italic>R</italic> is the ideal gas constant. Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq9">(3)</xref> is generally applied to isothermal processes. Here, we regard the continuous cooling process during solidification as a sequence of short isothermal treatments at varying temperatures<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. Therefore, equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq9">(3)</xref> is believed to also describe the crystallization process under non-isothermal conditions. Atomic diffusion is pronounced at high temperatures and thus the volume fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti should increase quickly. This is accompanied by a relatively fast change of the composition of the supercooled liquid from <inline-formula id="d33e675"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e676" xlink:href="srep19235-m12.jpg"/></inline-formula> to the equilibrium value, <inline-formula id="d33e678"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e679" xlink:href="srep19235-m13.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Simultaneously, the dendrites alter their composition from<inline-formula id="d33e681"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e682" xlink:href="srep19235-m14.jpg"/></inline-formula> to the equilibrium composition, <inline-formula id="d33e685"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e686" xlink:href="srep19235-m15.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>), which effectively lowers the undercooling of the melt. The composition-dependent chemical potential in both phases also changes and reduces the driving force for crystallization, <inline-formula id="d33e691"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e692" xlink:href="srep19235-m16.jpg"/></inline-formula>. There exists a temperature, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>, where the driving force for the precipitation of &#x003b2;-Ti vanishes:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq17"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e702" xlink:href="srep19235-m17.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>i.e. the chemical potentials of element <italic>i</italic> in both phases (supercooled liquid and &#x003b2;-Ti) are equal, and the system establishes a two-phase equilibrium (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). At <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>, the compositions <inline-formula id="d33e717"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e718" xlink:href="srep19235-m18.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e720"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e721" xlink:href="srep19235-m19.jpg"/></inline-formula>of both phases are located on the equilibrium lines of the phase diagram (green lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). Below the eutectic temperature, the glass should decompose into various crystalline phases (e.g.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> Be<sub>2</sub>Zr and Cu<sub>10</sub>Zr<sub>7</sub>) if the system is given sufficient time. Due to the relatively fast cooling, which we apply here, this process is suppressed as is the transformation of &#x003b2;-Ti to &#x003b1;-Ti. These two metastable phases are retained and the green dotted lines describe their compositional changes on further cooling. Since diffusion is rather limited at these relatively low temperatures, these lines are rather steep (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref> a). This is also a result of the negligible changes in the Gibbs free energy differences of both phases at very low temperatures<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref>. Once a certain temperature, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>, is crossed, the compositions of the constituent phases can be assumed constant and temperature-independent. As a final step, the supercooled liquid vitrifies at the glass transition temperature, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>.</p><p>The resulting microstructure consists of two metastable phases and therefore we use the term &#x0201c;quasi-equilibrium&#x0201d; in this context. The mole ratio of both phases should then be governed by the lever rule and the composition of the supercooled liquid, which then transforms into a glass, should be <inline-formula id="d33e758"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e759" xlink:href="srep19235-m20.jpg"/></inline-formula>. This corresponds to alloy BT0 (Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub>). Two-phase equilibria are usually only established for phases in their equilibrium states<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. However, a two-phase quasi-equilibrium can also occur between two metastable phases when their chemical potentials are identical. Metastable phase diagrams have been used to understand the formation of metastable phases via solidification<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref> or solid-state amorphization<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>, for instance. Lee <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref> have also constructed a pseudo-binary equilibrium phase diagram by measuring the melting points of several Zr-based BMGCs containing &#x003b2;-Zr and used the metastable phase diagram to explain the evolution of the different microstructures in their samples. However, they did not address the influence of the cooling rate on volume fractions and compositions as well as they did not focus on the underlying mechanism. The current concept of a two-phase quasi-equilibrium successfully reveals the influence of cooling rates and designed mole fractions of &#x003b2;-Ti on the microstructures of BMGCs as we discuss below.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Continuous cooling transformation (CCT) curves</title><p>The precipitation of &#x003b2;-Ti in the present system can be captured by continuous cooling transformation (CCT) curves. We use the quasi-equilibrium phase diagram to construct a CCT curve for the present alloys (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>). It is also the basis for discussing the differences in the crystalline volume fractions and compositions of the glass and &#x003b2;-Ti for BT48 samples produced with different cooling rates (see above). The following temperatures are crucial here: <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> (the equilibrium liquidus temperature), <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> (the temperature when nucleation commences), <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub> (the temperature when the compositions of the supercooled liquid and &#x003b2;-Ti reach the equilibrium values), <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> (the temperature when diffusion stops and the composition are effectively frozen in), <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub> (the glass transition temperature) and finally the temperatures at which the supercooled liquid crystallizes into Be<sub>2</sub>Zr and Cu<sub>10</sub>Zr<sub>7</sub>. The cooling curves (constant cooling rate given by equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq21">(2)</xref>) for the rods having a diameter of 2&#x02009;mm, 6&#x02009;mm, 10&#x02009;mm, and 20&#x02009;mm as well as the cooling rate for the 100&#x02009;g ingot of BT48 are displayed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>).</p><p>CCT curves are difficult to obtain, and are often calculated from isothermal temperature-time-transformation (TTT) curves by the Grange and Kiefer method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref>. Due to the resemblance of CCT curves and the upper parts of TTT curves<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>, TTT curves are widely used to schematically describe the crystallization process of a melt during continuous cooling<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>. TTT curves of alloys with various GFA were experimentally constructed by Johnson <italic>et al.</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref>, and the &#x0201c;nose&#x0201d; temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>nose</italic></sub>) of the C-shaped curve has been found to be linked to the glass transition temperature, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>: <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>nose</italic></sub> &#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;1.3&#x02009;<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref>. Due to its propensity to precipitate &#x003b2;-Ti, BT48 is a poor glass former (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>/<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;0.5) and between its equilibrium liquidus temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1546&#x02009;K) and its glass transition temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;773&#x02009;K), the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> curve with a nose temperature <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>nose</italic></sub>&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;1.3&#x02009;<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;1040&#x02009;K can be drawn. Similarly, the temperatures at which the glassy matrix (with the composition BT0) crystallizes into Be<sub>2</sub>Zr and Cu<sub>10</sub>Zr<sub>7</sub> among other phases<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> (orange curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>) is also drawn between <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;990&#x02009;K and <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;602&#x02009;K with a <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>nose</italic></sub>&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;1.3&#x02009;<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;783&#x02009;K. The measured times are modified by adding (2000&#x02009;K &#x02013; 990&#x02009;K)/(1&#x02009;Ks<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) for the comparison with the cooling curves from 2000&#x02009;K, because the critical cooling rate of BT0 for glass formation is estimated about 1&#x02009;K s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Now that the different phase fields are established, the solidification behaviour under different cooling rates can be discussed qualitatively.</p><p>The cooling curves corresponding to the BT48 rods with a diameter of 2&#x02009;mm and 6&#x02009;mm intersect the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;line but not the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;line and thus go through the phase regions I, II, IV, and VI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>). Once the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;line is crossed &#x003b2;-Ti precipitates in the supercooled liquid. Before the composition of the supercooled liquid or the dendrites reaches the equilibrium composition, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> is traversed and the compositions and volume fractions are frozen in due to the limited mobility of atoms. At the glass transition temperature the supercooled liquid finally vitrifies and a BMGC is the outcome. In this cooling rate regime the composition and the volume fractions depend on the cooling rates. For this reason one obtains identical phases in case of rod with 6&#x02009;mm in diameter but dendrites are Ti-richer and the glass is Ti-poorer compared to the rods with smaller diameters (&#x003d5;2&#x02009;mm). At the same time the crystalline volume fraction is somewhat larger because the system has a larger time window for &#x003b2;-Ti to precipitate and the dendrite size increases as well. In contrast, the cooling curves representing the larger rods (&#x003d5;10&#x02009;mm and &#x003d5;20&#x02009;mm) as well as the 100&#x02009;g ingot of BT48 intersect the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013; and <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines, and go through regions I, II, III, V, and VII (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>) before the microstructure evolution is effectively halted at <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>. This in turn results in BMGCs in which the composition of the Ti dendrites and the glassy matrix and consequently also the respective volume fractions reach a quasi-equilibrium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). Owing to the steep slopes near <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>) the compositions of &#x003b2;-Ti and the supercooled liquid remain virtually constant near <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>. The same holds for the volume fractions because of the conservation of mass. Instead, the main microstructural change in region III is the coarsening of the dendrites driven by the interfacial energy, known as Ostwald ripening<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. The cylindrical arm with a smaller diameter has a higher chemical potential. During the precipitation of &#x003b2;-Ti dendrites, the outer parts of the dendrite arms have larger diameters than the inner root parts. During ripening the root parts of &#x003b2;-Ti dissolve and then re-precipitate on the head parts, leading to a more particle-like morphology. Similarly, smaller particles have a higher chemical potential than the larger ones, causing large particles to become larger and more spherical, and smaller ones to become smaller and eventually to vanish<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. In other words, the lower cooling rates mean more time for ripening of the dendrites. The ripening process in region III also provides the possibility to design BMGCs with various shapes and sizes of &#x003b2;-Ti (without altering the volume fractions) by simply changing the cooling rates in this regime.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Producing BMGCs with precisely controlled volume fractions of &#x003b2;-Ti</title><p>In order to test our hypothesis of a quasi-equilibrium for the present alloy system, we have synthesized a variety of alloys with compositions ranging from BT0 up to BT95 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). If the quasi-equilibrium as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref> exists than for a rod diameter above 10&#x02009;mm, the volume fraction of the glassy phase and &#x003b2;-Ti should be predictable by applying the lever rule. The composition of the glass should be Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub> (BT0) and that of the dendrites Ti<sub>60.58</sub>Zr<sub>36.11</sub>Cu<sub>2.30</sub>Co<sub>1.01</sub> (BT100). Therefore, the crystalline mole fraction, <italic>x</italic>, in the BMGCs should be given by:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq21"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1091" xlink:href="srep19235-m21.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <inline-formula id="d33e1094"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1095" xlink:href="srep19235-m22.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e1097"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1098" xlink:href="srep19235-m23.jpg"/></inline-formula> are the compositions of the glassy matrix (BT0) and &#x003b2;-Ti (BT100), respectively. These alloys are abbreviated BT<italic>X</italic> (<italic>X</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100<italic>x</italic>) and their compositions are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>. The expected volume fractions, <inline-formula id="d33e1113"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1114" xlink:href="srep19235-m24.jpg"/></inline-formula>, can be calculated from the mole fractions, <italic>x</italic>, by:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq25"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1121" xlink:href="srep19235-m25.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>The details on the deduction of equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq25">(6)</xref> can be found in the Methods section, and the calculated <inline-formula id="d33e1127"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1128" xlink:href="srep19235-m26.jpg"/></inline-formula> are also listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>. The microstructures for the alloys BT15 to BT95 found in rods with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm are displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4a&#x02013;h</xref>. The crystalline volume fractions were extracted from these micrographs. While for BT15 and BT20 only a featureless micrograph is revealed, all other alloys exhibit the typical composite microstructure consisting of dendrites embedded in a featureless matrix. The crystalline volume fractions clearly increase with increasing <italic>x</italic>. Starting from BT30 there is a satisfactory agreement between the estimated crystalline volume fractions and the measured values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). The alloys BT10 up to BT15 are fully amorphous and apparently the lever rule does not describe the volume fractions properly. Obviously, the precipitation of &#x003b2;-Ti is aggravated as the composition of BT<italic>X</italic> shift towards BT100, due to the composition containing less Be, Cu and Co, which stabilize the undercooled liquid<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>. This means the <italic>T</italic><sub>n</sub>&#x02013;line as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref> is shifted to larger times for these compositions and the entire melt hence vitrifies at the given cooling rate. Additionally, the compositions of &#x003b2;-Ti for <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.40 were measured by means of energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy attached in SEM and were found to be similar to Ti<sub>60.58</sub>Zr<sub>36.11</sub>Cu<sub>2.30</sub>Co<sub>1.01</sub> (BT100).</p><p>The XRD patterns of the as-cast rods with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm of various BT<italic>X</italic> alloys are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4i</xref>. As <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.15, no crystalline diffraction peaks were detected in the 10&#x02009;mm rod of BT15, indicating a fully amorphous structure. Weak reflections of &#x003b2;-Ti begin to become detectable in the 10&#x02009;mm rod of BT20 and its intensities increase with increasing <italic>X.</italic> This suggests an increasing volume fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti. These results are corroborated by TEM micrographs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>), which prove the fully glassy nature of the BT15 rod with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm and in the &#x003d5;10&#x02009;mm rod of BT20 TEM reveals the presence of small &#x003b2;-Ti dendrites.</p><p>Finally, the CCT curves for the BT<italic>X</italic> shall be discussed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>). For several alloys the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013; and <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines are drawn. Two cooling rates are also depicted, one for a rod with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm and for an ingot with a weight of 100&#x02009;g. As <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.3, the cooling curve of the rod intersects the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines of these alloys and the outcome is a microstructure, which has attained a two-phase quasi-equilibrium: The compositions of both phases are identical in all alloys and crystalline volume fraction can be predicted (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). As <italic>x</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.2, however, the cooling curve of the 10&#x02009;mm rod crosses the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;line at a temperature close to its nose temperature, and then quickly reaches the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>&#x02013;line, generating a non-equilibrium BMGCs with a very small fraction (&#x0003c;5%) of &#x003b2;-Ti (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). When <italic>X</italic> is even smaller (e.g. <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;15), the cooling curve of the 10&#x02009;mm rods does not cross the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;line and a fully glassy rod can be obtained. At slower cooling (100&#x02009;g ingot of BT15), yet, &#x003b2;-Ti precipitates with a volume fraction less than 5% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Information</xref>) because the cooling curve representing the 100&#x02009;g ingot intersects the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>). Since the cooling rate of the 100&#x02009;g ingot approaches the critical cooling rate for the formation of a glassy matrix, BT10 and BT15 can never achieve the quasi-equilibrium BMGCs due to decomposition of the supercooled liquid into Be<sub>2</sub>Zr and Cu<sub>10</sub>Zr<sub>7</sub> at even lower cooling rates.</p><p>The discussion above unravels that there are two cooling-rate dependent critical &#x003b2;-Ti mole fractions: <inline-formula id="d33e1287"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1288" xlink:href="srep19235-m27.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e1290"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1291" xlink:href="srep19235-m28.jpg"/></inline-formula>. As <inline-formula id="d33e1293"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1294" xlink:href="srep19235-m29.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the cooling curves cut through the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines and as <inline-formula id="d33e1302"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1303" xlink:href="srep19235-m30.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the cooling curves intersect the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013; and <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines. At the same cooling rate, fully amorphous states, &#x0201c;non-quasi-equilibrium&#x0201d; BMGCs, and &#x0201c;quasi-equilibrium&#x0201d; BMGCs can be achieved as <inline-formula id="d33e1318"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1319" xlink:href="srep19235-m31.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="d33e1321"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1322" xlink:href="srep19235-m32.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="d33e1324"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1325" xlink:href="srep19235-m33.jpg"/></inline-formula>, respectively. In the current as-cast 10&#x02009;mm rods of BT<italic>X</italic>, <inline-formula id="d33e1331"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1332" xlink:href="srep19235-m34.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e1334"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1335" xlink:href="srep19235-m35.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Both <inline-formula id="d33e1337"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1338" xlink:href="srep19235-m36.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e1340"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1341" xlink:href="srep19235-m37.jpg"/></inline-formula> decrease with lowering the cooling rate.</p><p>In summary, a Ti-based BMGCs containing &#x003b2;-Ti was developed in the Ti-Zr-Cu-Co-Be system, and its glassy matrix can solidify into fully glassy ingots up to 150&#x02009;g. A two-phase quasi-equilibrium is established during continuous cooling and determines the microstructural evolution in terms of composition of the constituent phases as well as their volume fractions. Also its dependence on the cooling rate can be understood by assuming this quasi-equilibrium between two metastable phases. The nature of the two-phase quasi-equilibrium and a steep liquidus line near the temperature at which diffusion is effectively suppressed, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>, account for the identical volume fractions and compositions of &#x003b2;-Ti in the rods with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm, 20&#x02009;mm rods as well as in the 100&#x02009;g ingot of the alloy BT48 (Ti<sub>45.7</sub>Zr<sub>33.0</sub>Cu<sub>5.8</sub>Co<sub>3.0</sub>Be<sub>12.5</sub>). The influence of designed &#x003b2;-Ti mole fractions on the microstructures of BMGCs can also be understood based on the two-phase quasi-equilibrium. By carefully modifying the composition the respective volume fractions of the composite can be predicted and composite microstructures can thus be tailored. Moreover, the size of the dendrites can be adjusted by choosing the appropriate cooling rate for a given alloy while the volume fractions remain constant. In this way, one has a large degree of freedom in designing BMGCs. We envision that the two-phase quasi-equilibrium has scientific significance for the understanding of BMGCs with various microstructures.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Sample preparation</title><p>The 100&#x02009;g ingots of all alloys listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref> and the 150&#x02009;g ingot of BT0 were prepared by arc melting Ti, Zr, Cu, Co, and Be pure metals (purities are over 99.9&#x02009;wt. %) under a Ti-gettered high-purity argon atmosphere. As the chemical homogeneity was achieved after re-melting four times, the melts solidified into semi-spherical ingots within the water-cooled copper crucibles. The as-cast rods with diameters of 2&#x02009;mm, 6&#x02009;mm, 10&#x02009;mm, and 20&#x02009;mm of BT48 and the as-cast rods with diameters of 10&#x02009;mm of other BT<italic>X</italic> were prepared by copper-mould casting after re-arc melting the master ingots in high-purity argon atmosphere.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Characterization</title><p>The specimens were transversely cut from the as-cast rods and from the upper central part (the lowest cooling rate) of the 100&#x02009;g or 150&#x02009;g ingots for the characterization by means of X-ray diffraction (Philips PW1050, Cu-K&#x003b1;), scanning electron microscopy (Zeiss Supra 55) combined with energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (Oxford) and differential scanning calorimetry (DSC, Netzsch 204F1) at a constant heating rate of 20&#x02009;K min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The liquidus temperatures of BT0 and BT100 were measured claorimetrically (Netzsch 404). The DSC isothermal time before crystallization was obtained by heating at rates of 60&#x02009;K min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to and then holding at different temperatures between 610&#x02009;K and 640&#x02009;K using a Netzsch 204F1. The elemental mapping of the 20&#x02009;mm rod of BT48 was carried out by secondary ion mass spectroscopy (ION-TOF, SIMS5). The composition of the constituent phases in BT48 samples cooled at different rates were quantitatively acquired by an electron probe micro analyzer (Shimadzu 1610) with a wavelength-dispersive spectroscopy (WDS). The microstructure of the &#x003d5;6&#x02009;mm rod of BT48, the &#x003d5;10&#x02009;mm rods of BT15 and BT20 were investigated in a transmission electron microscope (FEI Tecnai F20) with an electron energy loss spectrum (EELS) system attached. The TEM samples were prepared by ion-milling with the cooling of liquid nitrogen using a Gatan 691.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Measurement of volume fractions and particle sizes of &#x003b2;-Ti</title><p>We used the software Image J (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://imagej.nih.gov">http://imagej.nih.gov</ext-link>) to directly measure the area fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti from the SEM micrographs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. Supposing the area fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti in the cross section at height of <italic>h</italic> in a unit cubic is <italic>A</italic>(<italic>h</italic>), then the volume fraction can be obtained by the relation: <inline-formula id="d33e1412"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1413" xlink:href="srep19235-m38.jpg"/></inline-formula>. In the current BMGCs, &#x003b2;-Ti precipitates within the liquid by homogenous nucleation which is then followed by diffusion-controlled growth. Thus &#x003b2;-Ti is distributed homogeneously on the micrometer-scale in the BMGCs, causing that the <italic>A</italic>(<italic>h</italic>) slightly fluctuates near the measured average volume fraction <inline-formula id="d33e1421"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1422" xlink:href="srep19235-m39.jpg"/></inline-formula>. In this case <inline-formula id="d33e1424"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1425" xlink:href="srep19235-m40.jpg"/></inline-formula>. This method shows good accuracy, because the fluctuations of <italic>A</italic>(<italic>h</italic>) are quite small (within 1.5%, seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1h</xref>). Particle sizes were also measured using Image J by directly measuring the diameters of secondary arms or particles of &#x003b2;-Ti. We also estimate the volume fractions of &#x003b2;-Ti in the 10&#x02009;mm rod of BT20 and the 100&#x02009;g ingot of BT15 by comparing their intensities of diffraction peak (110) of the XRD patterns with that of BT95, i.e.<inline-formula id="d33e1437"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1438" xlink:href="srep19235-m41.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Converting mole fraction <italic>x</italic> into volume fraction <italic>x&#x02019;</italic></title><p>For convenience we accept that there is one mole atoms of BMGCs and the mole fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti phase is <italic>x</italic>. The volume of &#x003b2;-Ti and glassy matrix (BT0) are given by <inline-formula id="d33e1453"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1454" xlink:href="srep19235-m42.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e1456"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1457" xlink:href="srep19235-m43.jpg"/></inline-formula>, respectively, where <inline-formula id="d33e1459"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1460" xlink:href="srep19235-m44.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e1462"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1463" xlink:href="srep19235-m45.jpg"/></inline-formula> are the molar weight of BT100 and BT0 (listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>), respectively. <inline-formula id="d33e1469"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1470" xlink:href="srep19235-m46.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e1472"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1473" xlink:href="srep19235-m47.jpg"/></inline-formula> are densities of single-crystal &#x003b2;-Ti and BT0, respectively. <inline-formula id="d33e1475"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1476" xlink:href="srep19235-m48.jpg"/></inline-formula> was obtained by the Archimedes method, and <inline-formula id="d33e1478"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1479" xlink:href="srep19235-m49.jpg"/></inline-formula> was calculated using <inline-formula id="d33e1481"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1482" xlink:href="srep19235-m50.jpg"/></inline-formula> and XRD measured volume size <inline-formula id="d33e1485"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1486" xlink:href="srep19235-m51.jpg"/></inline-formula> of the unit cell of &#x003b2;-Ti by <inline-formula id="d33e1488"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1489" xlink:href="srep19235-m52.jpg"/></inline-formula>. The relationship between <italic>x</italic> and <inline-formula id="d33e1494"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1495" xlink:href="srep19235-m53.jpg"/></inline-formula> is given by <inline-formula id="d33e1497"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1498" xlink:href="srep19235-m54.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and then equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq25">(6)</xref> was obtained by substituting corresponding values.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Additional Information</title><p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Zhang, L. <italic>et al.</italic> Two-phase quasi-equilibrium in &#x003b2;-type Ti-based bulk metallic glass composites. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic>
<bold>6</bold>, 19235; doi: 10.1038/srep19235 (2016).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d33e100" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Information</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep19235-s1.doc"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science of Foundation of China (Grant No. 51434008), the Strategic Priority Research Program on Space Science, the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Grant No. XDA04020411, XDA04020202-11), the Program of &#x0201c;One Hundred Talented People&#x0201d; of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, and the Chinese Scholarship Council (CSC). J.E. acknowledges additional support from the German Science Foundation (DFG) under the Leibniz Program (grant EC111/26-1), the European Research Council under the ERC Advanced Grant INTELHYB (grant ERC-2013-ADG-340025).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Metallic glasses</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>267</volume>, <fpage>1947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1953</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17770105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Bulk glass-forming metallic alloys: science and technology</article-title>. <source>MRS Bull.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Stabilization of metallic supercooled liquid and bulk amorphous alloys</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>306</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schroers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Bulk metallic glasses</article-title>. <source>Phys. Today</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gorantla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Transformation-mediated ductility in CuZr-based bulk metallic glasses</article-title>. <source>Nat. Mater.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>477</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20473286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sarac</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Schroers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Designing tensile ductility in metallic glasses</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>2158</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23863967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y. Q.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Shear bands in metallic glasses</article-title>. <source>Mater. Sci. Eng. R</source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schuh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hufnagel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Ramamurty</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mechanical behavior of amorphous alloys</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>4067</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4109</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rainforth</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<article-title>New compositional design for creating tough metallic glass composites with excellent work hardening</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Bulk metallic glass composites with transformation-mediated work-hardening and ductility</article-title>. <source>Adv. Mater.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>2770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2773</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20422654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Strategy for pinpointing the formation of B2 CuZr in metastable CuZr-based shape memory alloys</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>6620</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6630</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Formation of Cu&#x02013;Zr&#x02013;Al bulk metallic glass composites with improved tensile properties</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>2928</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2936</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z. Q.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Microstructural tailoring and improvement of mechanical properties in CuZr-based bulk metallic glass composites</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>3128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3139</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gargarella</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Ti-Cu-Ni shape memory bulk metallic glass composites</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Microstructural heterogeneities governing the deformation of Cu47.5Zr47.5Al5 bulk metallic glass composites</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>5445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5453</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Bulk metallic glass composite with good tensile ductility, high strength and large elastic strain limit</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Microstructure controlled shear band pattern formation and enhanced plasticity of bulk metallic glasses containing <italic>in situ</italic> formed ductile phase dendrite dispersions</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>2901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2904</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mattern</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>ZrNbCuNiAl bulk metallic glass matrix composites containing dendritic bcc phase precipitates</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>2478</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2480</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Development of tough, low-density titanium-based bulk metallic glass matrix composites with tensile ductility</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source>
<volume>105</volume>, <fpage>20136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20140</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19074287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Designing metallic glass matrix composites with high toughness and tensile ductility</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>451</volume>, <fpage>1085</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1089</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18305540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liaw</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Large plasticity and tensile necking of Zr-based bulk-metallic-glass-matrix composites synthesized by the Bridgman solidification</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>151905</fpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Large-sized Zr-based bulk-metallic-glass composite with enhanced tensile properties</article-title>. <source>Intermetallics</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Innovative approach to the design of low-cost Zr-based BMG composites with good glass formation</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>2097</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23807140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Correlation of the microstructure and mechanical properties of Zr-based <italic>in-situ</italic> bulk metallic glass matrix composites</article-title>. <source>Intermetallics</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>2425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2430</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>High tensile ductility of Ti-based amorphous matrix composites modified from conventional Ti-6Al-4 V titanium alloy</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>3012</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3026</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M. Q.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>TiZr-base bulk metallic glass with over 50 mm in diameter</article-title>. <source>J. Mater. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>486</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X. H.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>An improved tensile deformation model for <italic>in-situ</italic> dendrite/metallic glass matrix composites</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Duhamel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mechanical properties of bulk metallic glasses and composites</article-title>. <source>J. Mater. Res.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title><italic>In-situ</italic> dendrite/metallic glass matrix composites: a review</article-title>. <source>J. Mater. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>685</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>701</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Designing Bulk Metallic Glass Composites with Enhanced Formability and Plasticity</article-title>. <source>J. Mater. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>566</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>575</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> in <source>Phase transformations 1st edn</source>, Vol. 12 (eds <name><surname>Cahn</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>) Ch. 1, <fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage> (Elsevier, <year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Compressive plastic metallic glasses with exceptional glass forming ability in the Ti&#x02013;Zr&#x02013;Cu&#x02013;Fe&#x02013;Be alloy system</article-title>. <source>J. Alloys Comp.</source>
<volume>638</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>355</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>73 mm-diameter bulk metallic glass rod by copper mould casting</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>051910</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>A Ti36.2Zr30.3Cu8.3Fe4Be21.2 bulk metallic glass with exceptional glass forming ability and remarkable compressive plasticity</article-title>. <source>J. Alloys Comp.</source>
<volume>562</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>The world&#x02019;s biggest glassy alloy ever made</article-title>. <source>Intermetallics</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A highly processable metallic glass: Zr41.2Ti13.8Cu12.5Ni10.0Be22.5</article-title>. <source>Appl. Phys. Lett.</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>2342</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2344</lpage> (<year>1993</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X. H.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Formation of Ti-Zr-Cu-Ni bulk metallic glasses</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Phys.</source>
<volume>78</volume>, <fpage>6514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6519</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Gahn</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Solute trapping by rapid solidification</article-title>. <source>Acta Metall.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>575</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>578</lpage> (<year>1969</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<source>Fundamentals of solidification 3rd edn</source>, Ch. 7, <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>, Appendix 6, <fpage>220</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage> (Trans Tech Publications, <year>1992</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Spaepen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Homogeneous crystal nucleation in binary metallic melts</article-title>. <source>Acta Metall.</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>2021</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2027</lpage> (<year>1983</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Thermodynamics and kinetics of the undercooled liquid and the glass transition of the Zr41.2Ti13.8Cu12.5Ni10.0Be22.5 alloy</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Phys.</source>
<volume>77</volume>, <fpage>4039</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4043</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Understanding the glass-forming ability of Cu50Zr50 alloys in terms of a metastable eutectic</article-title>. <source>J. Mater. Res.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>2307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2313</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Highmore</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Eutectics and the formation of amorphous alloys</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>339</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>365</lpage> (<year>1989</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Pseudo-binary phase diagram for Zr-based <italic>in situ</italic> beta phase composites</article-title>. <source>J. Mater. Res.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>538</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>543</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Critical cooling rate for the glass formation of ferromagnetic Fe40Ni40P14B6 alloy</article-title>. <source>Mater. Lett.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>3323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3328</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Supercooling investigation and critical cooling rate for glass formation in Pd&#x02013;Cu&#x02013;Ni&#x02013;P alloy</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1495</lpage> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schroers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Processing of bulk metallic glass</article-title>. <source>Adv. Mater.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1566</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1597</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20496386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schroers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Rhim</surname><given-names>W. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Influence of kinetic and thermodynamic factors on the glass-forming ability of zirconium-based bulk amorphous alloys</article-title>. <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>245501</fpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> H.F.Z. conceived the project. L.Z. and H.F.Z. carried out the experiments. L.Z. and H.F.Z. proposed the two-phase quasi-equilibrium, and S.P. and J.E. provided insightful suggestions to improve it. T.M.Q. and H.F.Z. generated the idea to design BMGCs by using the lever rule on quasi-equilibrium compositions. L.Z. and S.P. drew the schematic illustrations and wrote the manuscript. All authors contributed to data analysis and discussion.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Characterizations of the samples of BT48 obtained at different cooling rates.</title><p>(<bold>a&#x02013;e</bold>) The back-scattered scanning electron microscopy (SEM) micrographs of the as-cast rods with diameters of 2&#x02009;mm, 6&#x02009;mm, 10&#x02009;mm, and 20&#x02009;mm, and the ingot of 100&#x02009;g, respectively. The different cooling rates have a strong influence on the volume fractions, the shapes, and the size of &#x003b2;-Ti. (<bold>f</bold>) The transmission electron microscopy (TEM) micrograph of the rod with a diameter of 6&#x02009;mm with an inset of diffraction pattern from the two-phase interface, showing a two-phase microstructure containing a glassy matrix and &#x003b2;-Ti with a body-centered cubic (<inline-formula id="d33e1538"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1539" xlink:href="srep19235-m55.jpg"/></inline-formula>) symmetry. (<bold>g</bold>) Differential scanning calorimetry (DSC) traces of the samples. The differences between the rods with a diameter of 2&#x02009;mm or 6&#x02009;mm and other samples are marked by circles (arising from the glassy matrices) and rectangulars (arising from &#x003b2;-Ti), indicating the compositions of both phases in the rods with a diameter of 2&#x02009;mm or 6&#x02009;mm are slightly different with other samples. The exothermic events at about 540&#x02009;K before <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub> arise from the metastable &#x003b2;-Ti. (<bold>h</bold>) The summary of the measured volume fractions and particle sizes (herein refer to the diameters of the secondary arms, as shown in (<bold>b</bold>)) of &#x003b2;-Ti in different samples. Error bars (s.d.) of the fluctuations of the measured volume fractions and particle sizes of &#x003b2;-Ti are given. Although particle sizes increase with lowering the cooling rates, the volume fractions of &#x003b2;-Ti are identical in the rods with diameters of 10&#x02009;mm, and 20&#x02009;mm, and the ingot of 100&#x02009;g.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep19235-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The as-solidified 150&#x02009;g ingot.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) The appearance of the 150&#x02009;g ingot of Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub> (at.%, BT0). The mirror-like surface and the diffraction humps in its X-ray diffraction pattern (<bold>b</bold>) indicate that it is fully amorphous.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep19235-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Schematic illustrations of the two-phase quasi-equilibrium.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic binary phase diagram. The green solid lines represent the equilibrium liquidus line, the solution limit of &#x003b2;-Ti and the eutectic line. The left two red dashed lines describe the beginning stage at which &#x003b2;-Ti or other crystalline phases begin to precipitate in the undercooled melt at the cooling rate representing the ingot with a weight of 100&#x02009;g. &#x003b2;-Ti begins to precipitate as the melt is cooled down and intersects the red dashed lines, and the composition of &#x003b2;-Ti is <inline-formula id="d33e1594"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1595" xlink:href="srep19235-m56.jpg"/></inline-formula>. It is slightly richer in solute (Cu and Co) than its equilibrium composition (the far right green line). For higher cooling rates, the degree of undercooling increases<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref> and thus the red dashed lines shift to lower temperatures. As the fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti increase, the compositions of both phases change from <inline-formula id="d33e1599"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1600" xlink:href="srep19235-m57.jpg"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula id="d33e1602"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1603" xlink:href="srep19235-m58.jpg"/></inline-formula>. When the quasi-equilibrium is established between the (undercooled) liquid and &#x003b2;-Ti, the compositions of both phases change along the liquidus and the solution limit of &#x003b2;-Ti (green lines) from <inline-formula id="d33e1606"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1607" xlink:href="srep19235-m59.jpg"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula id="d33e1609"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1610" xlink:href="srep19235-m60.jpg"/></inline-formula>. (<bold>b</bold>) Schematic continuous cooling transformation curves (CCT) for BT48. The &#x003b2;-Ti begin curve (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;line), the two-phase quasi-equilibrium curve (<italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;line), and the crystallization TTT curve of BT0 are drawn between their <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> and <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>g</italic></sub>, respectively. (<inline-formula id="d33e1640"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1641" xlink:href="srep19235-m70.jpg"/></inline-formula>) are DSC measured times before crystallization of BT0 plus (2000&#x02009;K-990&#x02009;K)/(1&#x02009;K s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The cooling curves starting from 2000&#x02009;K are indicated by the different sample diameters (calculated from equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq21">(2)</xref>). Phases in regions with different colours are: I, liquid; II, liquid&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x003b2;-Ti (non-equilibrium compositions, changeable microstructure); III, liquid&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x003b2;-Ti (equilibrium compositions, changeable microstructure); IV, supercooled liquid&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x003b2;-Ti (non-equilibrium compositions, unchangeable microstructure); V, supercooled liquid&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x003b2;-Ti (quasi-equilibrium compositions, unchangeable microstructure); VI, non-equilibrium BMGCs; VII, quasi-equilibrium BMGCs; VIII, crystallized matrix&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x003b2;-Ti. If cooling curves intersect <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;line (not crystallization curve of BT0), quasi-equilibrium BMGCs will be achieved, otherwise, non-equilibrium BMGCs will be obtained. The sketches of thermodynamic views are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep19235-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Characterization of as-cast BT<italic>X</italic> rods with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm.</title><p>(<bold>a&#x02013;h</bold>) The back-scattered scanning electron microscopy (SEM) micrographs of BT15, BT20, BT30, BT40, BT60, BT80, BT90, and BT95, respectively. BT15 shows a fully amorphous structure, and other samples have a two-phase microstructure. The growing intensities of the diffraction peaks (110) of &#x003b2;-Ti from BT20 to BT95 suggest an increasing volume fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti. (<bold>i</bold>) The X-ray diffraction patterns of BT<italic>X</italic>. The compositions of BT<italic>X</italic> are designed using the lever rule and calculated by equitation (5), as listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>. The designed mole fractions, <italic>x</italic>, of &#x003b2;-Ti have a strong influence on the final microstructure and the measured volume fractions of &#x003b2;-Ti are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep19235-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Influence of designed mole fractions, <italic>x</italic>, on the two-phase quasi-equilibrium.</title><p>The precipitation of &#x003b2;-Ti is more difficult as <italic>x</italic> becomes smaller and the liquidus temperature also decreases, causing the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines and <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines to shift to larger times and lower temperatures. The <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines, and <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub>&#x02013;lines of BT95, BT60, BT30, BT20, and BT15 and the crystallization curve of the remaining liquid of BT15 are drawn. The cooling curves (indicated by the diameter or the weight of the samples) of the as-cast rod with a diameter of 10&#x02009;mm and the ingot of 100&#x02009;g obtained by equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq21">(2)</xref> are also plotted. There are two cooling-rate dependent critical values: <inline-formula id="d33e1736"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1737" xlink:href="srep19235-m61.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="d33e1739"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1740" xlink:href="srep19235-m62.jpg"/></inline-formula>. If the cooling curves do not intersect the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;line (<inline-formula id="d33e1749"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1750" xlink:href="srep19235-m63.jpg"/></inline-formula>), fully amorphous are the outcome. If the cooling curves intersect the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>&#x02013;line but not the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;line (<inline-formula id="d33e1765"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1766" xlink:href="srep19235-m64.jpg"/></inline-formula>), non-equilibrium BMGCs will be obtained; if the cooling curves intersect the <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x02013;line (<inline-formula id="d33e1774"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1775" xlink:href="srep19235-m65.jpg"/></inline-formula>), quasi-equilibrium BMGCs will be achieved, and then the fraction of &#x003b2;-Ti can be precisely controlled by the lever rule. In the as-cast rods with diameters of 10&#x02009;mm of current BT<italic>X</italic>, <inline-formula id="d33e1780"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1781" xlink:href="srep19235-m66.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="d33e1784"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1785" xlink:href="srep19235-m67.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep19235-f5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Chemical compositions of the constituent phases in the samples BT48 cooled at different rates.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Samples</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Phases</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Compositions</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">6&#x02009;mm</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x003b2;-Ti</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>59.51</sub>Zr<sub>35.16</sub>Cu<sub>3.49</sub>Co<sub>1.84</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">10&#x02009;mm</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x003b2;-Ti</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>60.59</sub>Zr<sub>36.13</sub>Cu<sub>2.27</sub>Co<sub>1.01</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">20&#x02009;mm</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x003b2;-Ti</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>60.54</sub>Zr<sub>36.17</sub>Cu<sub>2.29</sub>Co<sub>1.00</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x003b2;-Ti</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>60.58</sub>Zr<sub>36.11</sub>Cu<sub>2.30</sub>Co<sub>1.01</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">100&#x02009;g</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">glassy matrix</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>42.12</sub>Zr<sub>39.65</sub>Cu<sub>11.86</sub>Co<sub>6.37</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">glassy matrix</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub>&#x0003e;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t1-fn1">*</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>The estimated compositions of the glassy matrix and &#x003b2;-Ti in the 100 g ingot are the quasi-equilibrium compositions and are denoted BT0 (<inline-formula id="d33e1923"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1924" xlink:href="srep19235-m68.jpg"/></inline-formula>) and BT100 (<inline-formula id="d33e1926"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1927" xlink:href="srep19235-m69.jpg"/></inline-formula>), respectively. *This composition is calculated from the EPMA obtained compositions and the nominal composition by assuming that Be is totally in the glassy matrix.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>The compositions, designed &#x003b2;-Ti volume fractions, and measured &#x003b2;-Ti volume fractions in the as-cast 10&#x02009;mm rods of BT<italic>X</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Alloys No.</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Mole Fraction x (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Compositions (at.%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Expected Vol. Fraction x&#x02019; (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Measured Vol. Fraction (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>32.02</sub>Zr<sub>30.13</sub>Cu<sub>9.01</sub>Co<sub>4.84</sub>Be<sub>24.00</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>34.88</sub>Zr<sub>30.73</sub>Cu<sub>8.34</sub>Co<sub>4.46</sub>Be<sub>21.60</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">11.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>36.30</sub>Zr<sub>31.03</sub>Cu<sub>8.00</sub>Co<sub>4.27</sub>Be<sub>20.40</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">17.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT20</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>37.73</sub>Zr<sub>31.33</sub>Cu<sub>7.67</sub>Co<sub>4.07</sub>Be<sub>19.20</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">23.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x0003c;5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT30</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>40.59</sub>Zr<sub>31.92</sub>Cu<sub>7.00</sub>Co<sub>3.69</sub>Be<sub>16.80</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">33.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">35.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT40</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">40</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>43.44</sub>Zr<sub>32.52</sub>Cu<sub>6.33</sub>Co<sub>3.31</sub>Be<sub>14.40</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">44.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">45.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT48</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">47.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>45.7</sub>Zr<sub>33.0</sub>Cu<sub>5.8</sub>Co<sub>3.0</sub>Be<sub>12.5</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">52.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">52.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT60</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">60</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>49.16</sub>Zr<sub>33.72</sub>Cu<sub>4.98</sub>Co<sub>2.54</sub>Be<sub>9.60</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">64.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">65.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT70</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">70</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>52.01</sub>Zr<sub>34.32</sub>Cu<sub>4.31</sub>Co<sub>2.16</sub>Be<sub>7.20</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">73.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">74.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT80</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">80</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>54.87</sub>Zr<sub>34.91</sub>Cu<sub>3.64</sub>Co<sub>1.78</sub>Be<sub>4.80</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">82.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">83.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT90</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">90</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>57.72</sub>Zr<sub>35.51</sub>Cu<sub>2.97</sub>Co<sub>1.39</sub>Be<sub>2.40</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">91.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">91.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT95</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>59.15</sub>Zr<sub>35.81</sub>Cu<sub>2.64</sub>Co<sub>1.20</sub>Be<sub>1.20</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">95.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">96.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BT100&#x0003e;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="t2-fn1">*</xref></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Ti<sub>60.58</sub>Zr<sub>36.11</sub>Cu<sub>2.30</sub>Co<sub>1.01</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02013;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2-fn1"><p>*BT100 is the quasi-equilibrium composition of &#x003b2;-Ti in the 100 g ingot of BT48.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>