<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">The apical and basal spikelet samples of the panicle from the main shoot of the plants were collected at 5 day intervals from day of anthesis (0 day) up to 30 days post-anthesis period and dried inside an oven at 80 °C for 1 h and kept as such at 37 °C for 72 h till constant weight. The dry weight was recorded in an electronic balance and the results were presented in the form of a logistic growth curve
 <disp-formula id="Equa">
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ {\text{W}}\left( {\text{t}} \right)= {\text{ Wo M }}/ [{\text{Wo }} + \left( {{\text{M }} - {\text{ Wo}}} \right)^{{{-}{\text{kt}}}} ], $$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M2" display="block">
    <mrow>
     <mtext>W</mtext>
     <mfenced close=")" open="(">
      <mtext>t</mtext>
     </mfenced>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mspace width="0.333333em"/>
      <mtext>Wo M</mtext>
      <mspace width="0.333333em"/>
     </mrow>
     <mo stretchy="false">/</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mo stretchy="false">[</mo>
      <mrow>
       <mtext>Wo</mtext>
       <mspace width="0.333333em"/>
      </mrow>
      <mo>+</mo>
      <msup>
       <mfenced close=")" open="(">
        <mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mtext>M</mtext>
          <mspace width="0.333333em"/>
         </mrow>
         <mo>-</mo>
         <mrow>
          <mspace width="0.333333em"/>
          <mtext>Wo</mtext>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
       </mfenced>
       <mrow>
        <mo>-</mo>
        <mtext>kt</mtext>
       </mrow>
      </msup>
      <mo stretchy="false">]</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo>,</mo>
    </mrow>
   </math>
   <graphic xlink:href="41598_2021_84663_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>where W (t), grain weight at a particular time ‘t’; Wo, initial grain weight; M, maximum grain weight; k, growth rate constant calculated from Microsoft Excel solver, 2007; t, time. The ‘k’ values in apical and basal spikelets of SR-157 are 0.196397 and 0.170065 whereas the values in apical and basal spikelets of SR-159 are 0.209456 and 0.197954, respectively (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The dried samples were subsequently converted into powder form and boiled in aqueous methanol for 10 min and the extract was collected in a volumetric flask. The residue was boiled for second time in 50% methanol and both the extracts were pooled together and volume was adjusted to mark with distilled water. Aliquot of the extract was used for estimation of soluble sugars using Phenol–Sulfuric acid reagent measuring absorbance at 490 nm
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. The residue after methanolic extraction was boiled with 3% HCl for 3 h in a water bath to convert the starch into glucose and the glucose released was measured quantitatively
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. The results were expressed in terms of starch by multiplying a factor of 0.9 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).
</p>
