<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">For a schematic representation of the sample preparation process, please see Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1
 <italic>.</italic> The dissected tissue was frozen (− 80 °C) and pulverized in liquid nitrogen using a ball grinder, after which the pulverized tissue was weighed. The proteins were extracted from the pulverized tissue using 15 volumes of chaotropic buffer (4 M GdnHCl, 50 mM NaAc, 100 mM 6-aminocaproic acid, 5 mM benzamidine, 5 mM 
 <italic>N</italic>-ethylmaleimide, pH 5.8) for 24 h on an orbital shaker at + 4 °C. Extracts were collected after centrifugation at 13200 x g at + 4 °C for 30 min. The pellet was frozen and saved. Fifty μL of the extracts were reduced, using 4 mM DTT for 30 min shaking at + 56 °C. The extracts were alkylated using 16 mM iodoacetamide for 1 h at room temperature in the dark. In order to remove residual salts the extracts were precipitated with nine volumes of ethanol for 4 h at − 20 °C, after which the precipitate was dried in a SpeedVac and suspended in 100 μL of 0.1 M AMBIC, pH 8.5. The samples were then digested using 2 μg trypsin gold on a shaker at + 37 °C for approximately 16 h. The peptide concentrations of the digests were determined using Pierce Quantitative Colorimetric Peptide Assay (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Rockford, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Samples (50 μg) were diluted to 200 μL with a final concentration of 50 mM AMBIC and 0.5 M sodium chloride (to minimize ionic interactions). In order to remove peptides with glycosaminoglycan (GAG) chains from the samples, they were centrifuged through Nanosep® 30 K Omega Centrifugal Devices (Pall Life Sciences, Ann Arbor, USA. The samples were subsequently desalted and fractionated into two fractions (eluted with 10 and 50% acetonitrile respectively) using Pierce High pH Reversed-Phase Peptide Fractionation Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Rockford, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions.
</p>
