<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bacteria degrading long-chain alkanes frequently contain proteins homologous to AlkB a membrane-bound non-heme di-iron monooxygenases found in 
 <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> GPo1 which utilizes a terminal oxidation pathway for alkane degradation. For example, 
 <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. M1 contains genes that code for membrane-bound oxygenase complexes involved in long-chain alkane degradation (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Tani et al., 2001</xref>). This includes 
 <italic>alkMa</italic>, which was induced by long-chain 
 <italic>n-</italic>alkanes greater than 
 <italic>n-</italic>C
 <sub>22</sub>, and 
 <italic>alkMb</italic>, which was preferentially induced by 
 <italic>n</italic>-alkanes with chain lengths of 
 <italic>n-</italic>C
 <sub>16</sub> to 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>22</sub>. 
 <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sp. DSM 1784 was first reported to have an enzyme involved in the degradation of 
 <italic>n</italic>-alkanes longer than 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>30</sub>, which was named AlmA (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Throne-Holst et al., 2007</xref>). AlmA homologs have been detected in other OHCB such as 
 <italic>Alcanivorax borkumensis</italic> SK2, 
 <italic>Alcanivorax hongdengensis</italic> A-11-3 and 
 <italic>Alcanivorax dieselolei</italic> B-5 (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Rojo, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2011</xref>). In addition to AlmA, other alkane hydroxylases involved in long-chain 
 <italic>n</italic>-alkane degradation have also been reported, such as a thermophilic soluble long-chain alkane monooxygenase (LadA), which exerts terminal oxidation of alkanes ranging from 
 <italic>n-</italic>C
 <sub>15</sub> to 
 <italic>n-</italic>C
 <sub>36</sub> in 
 <italic>Geobacillus thermodenitrificans</italic> NG80-2 (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Ji et al., 2013</xref>). However, 
 <italic>almA</italic> and 
 <italic>ladA</italic> homologs are not present on the 
 <italic>T. oleivorans’</italic> genome, suggesting an alternative mechanism of long-chain alkane degradation. Several proteins upregulated during growth on 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>28</sub> (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) provided strong evidence of a potential subterminal long-chain alkane oxidation pathway. This involves the initial hydroxylation of one of the subterminal carbon atoms in the alkane chain by an alkane monooxygenase (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Kotani et al., 2007</xref>). Whilst expression of a specific subterminal alkane monooxygenase was not observed during growth on 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>28</sub>, the same monooxygenase that was highly upregulated during terminal oxidation of 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>14</sub> was also expressed. This suggests the possibility that this enzyme may act in a non-specific regioselective manner and can activate alkanes at either the terminal or sub-terminal position. Such enzymatic non-specificity can result in both primary and secondary alcohols from initial alkane oxidation at both terminal and subterminal carbons (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Fredricks, 1967</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Markovetz and Kallio, 1971</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Singer and Finnerty, 1984</xref>).
</p>
