<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>More distantly related BVMOs have been isolated from 
 <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> species such as 
 <italic>Acinetobacter radioresistens</italic> S13 (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Minerdi et al., 2012</xref>), which was induced during growth in the presence of long-chain alkanes (
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>24</sub>, 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>36</sub>) and shown to subterminally oxidize alkanes. Both 
 <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> MIL-1 and 
 <italic>Acinetobacter radioresistens</italic> S13 are capable of growth on either short- and/or long-chain alkanes as the sole carbon source. They both possess genes coding for terminal alkane hydroxylases homologous to 
 <italic>alkB</italic> and BVMOs homologous to EthA (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">van Beilen et al., 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Minerdi et al., 2012</xref>). As seen in 
 <italic>Acinetobacter radioresistens</italic> S13 (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Minerdi et al., 2012</xref>), 
 <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> MIL-1 appears to differentially express either AlkB or BVMO according to the presence of medium- or long-chain alkanes. Both terminal and subterminal oxidation can coexist in some microorganisms (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Rojo, 2009</xref>). Subterminal oxidation has been described for both short- and long-chain alkanes as well as for fatty acids (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ashraf et al., 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">Wentzel et al., 2007</xref>). In fatty acids, chain length determines the rate and position of hydroxylation (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Van Bogaert et al., 2007</xref>). The longer the chain the more the terminal/subterminal oxidation ratio declines. For example, palmitic acid (C
 <sub>16</sub>H
 <sub>32</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>) and heptadecanoic acid (C
 <sub>17</sub>H
 <sub>34</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>) are predominantly hydroxylated at the terminal position, whereas no terminal oxidation is observed for oleic acid (C
 <sub>18</sub>H
 <sub>34</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>). This may also be the case for 
 <italic>n</italic>-alkanes and explain why the subterminal oxidation pathway may potentially is only occur during growth on 
 <italic>n-</italic>C
 <sub>28</sub>. The production of ketones and esters are impossible in the terminal oxidation pathway so the upregulation of a BVMO and esterase, which catalyze ketone and ester metabolism respectively, and the lack of a primary alcohol metabolite during growth on 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>28</sub> strongly suggests 
 <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> is using a subterminal oxidation pathway during growth on long-chain alkanes.
</p>
