<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Venous thromboembolism (VTE), including deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism, is a highly prevalent and potentially fatal disease that causes 3 million deaths worldwide every year [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. VTE is a common cancer complication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The risk of venous thrombosis in cancer patients is as high as 7% due to their hypercoagulability or surgical intervention [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], which has become the second leading cause of death in cancer patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Compared with healthy people, the incidence of VTE in malignant tumor patients is 4–7 times higher, with a high incidence of morbidity and mortality [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. From 2004 to 2016, the incidence of VTE in China was on the rise, increased from 34.8% in 2005 to 60.9% in 2014 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In etiology, the most common cause of VTE is active malignant tumors. Therefore, it is important to study the pathogenesis of VTE to reduce the risk of postoperative death in cancer patients. Previous studies have generally believed that the occurrence of VTE is mainly related to the activation of coagulation function, slow blood flow, vascular wall injury, and its treatment uses anticoagulants, and thrombolytic drugs to prevent thrombus expansion and reduce thrombus. Nevertheless, in many VTEs, tissue factors reflecting vascular endothelial cell injury, P selectin activated by platelets did not rise significantly, which is difficult to explain with the traditional theory. It is reported that VTE is a complex disease influenced by environment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], genetics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and epigenetics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], which play important roles in the occurrence of VTE. A number of genes have been found to be susceptible to VTE occurrence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Recently, some scholars have shown that immune gene mutations may provide new insights into the pathogenesis of VTE [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, the specific pathogenesis of VTE is still unclear.
</p>
