<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the factors controlling AS in RSV-infected epithelial cells are likely complex and will require additional research, full-length mRNA sequencing studies have linked AS to the control of transcriptional initiation [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In this seminal study, Anvar et al. showed a marked interdependency between transcription and mRNA-processing events, including AS and APA, in MCF-7 breast carcinoma cells. Although the factors coupling transcriptional initiation to AS were not investigated in that study, a great deal of understanding has been developed for how transcriptional initiation is linked to mRNA processing in IIR gene expression. Chromatin immunoprecipitation and siRNA depletion studies have shown that the process of transcriptional elongation is responsible for activating the immediate–early IFN response by a chromatin remodeling complex known as positive transcription elongation factor-b (PTEF-b). PTEF-b is a multisubunit protein complex whose core regulators are cyclin-dependent kinase 9 (CDK9) and bromodomain-containing protein 4 (BRD4) recruited to immediate–early innate response genes by the sequence specific binding of IRF and RelA transcription factors [
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Once recruited to an innate-inducible gene, the PTEF-b complex phosphorylates the carboxy terminal domain of RNA polymerase II, stimulating RNA polymerase II processivity and dissociating transcriptional elongation inhibitors from the promoter [
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Quantitative proteomics of the effect of innate activation on the CDK9 complex has found that this complex dynamically associates with the DDX5/17 family of RNA helicases. DDX5/17 play a role in co-transcriptional alternative splicing of redox regulatory genes [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], an essential component of the antiviral response to RSV [
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Collectively, these data indicate that highly inducible immediate–early genes are co-transcriptionally spliced and processed via dynamic changes in the transcriptional elongation complex.
</p>
