<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Nocturnal species already are active at the cooler time of day, so one might predict less change in their activity patterns in response to increasing heat and aridity. By contrast with diurnally active mammals that might need to increase evaporative water loss to keep cool, mammals active during the night might need to increase their metabolic rates to keep warm, which may impose an extra demand for energy during cold nights. Indeed, increasing air temperatures at night, as a result of climate change, might benefit nocturnal species by reducing the energetic costs of maintaining homeothermy (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Levy et al., 2019</xref>), a benefit that might help offset the reduced nutritional quality or availability of food resulting from climate change (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Durant et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Post et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Birnie-Gauvin et al., 2017</xref>). In environments with clear night skies, substantial heat loss occurs through passive radiant cooling to the night sky, which acts as a heat sink with an effective temperature of between &#8211;10 and &#8211;30&#176;C (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Mitchell et al., 2018</xref>). Because the radiant heat sink of the night sky is unlikely to change much with climate change, warmer air temperatures at night are unlikely to offset the energetic cost of reduced resource availability. Instead, as resources become limited, the ability to keep warm at night using metabolic heat might be compromised, such that some nocturnal species may increase their diurnal activity to reduce the energy cost that would have been incurred through being active at night (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Van der Vinne et al., 2019</xref>). The trade-off then is that they have to acquire sufficient resources while exposed to daytime heat loads, with air temperatures increasing under climate change.</p>