<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One species that exhibits increased heterothermy in the face of heat and aridity is the aardvark, 
 <italic>Orycteropus afer</italic> (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Rey et al., 2017</xref>). Aardvarks are solitary, burrowing mammals that occur in non-desert habitats of sub-Saharan Africa. They extract ants and termites, on which they depend for energy and water, by digging them out of their underground hives (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Taylor, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Weyer, 2018</xref>). Aardvarks generally emerge from their burrows at night to forage, but demonstrate flexibility in behaviour and activity patterns in response to environmental fluctuations. Aardvarks in the semi-arid Karoo region of South Africa displayed an increased amplitude of their 24-h body temperature rhythm during winter when it was cold, as a result of low minimum 24-h body temperatures (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Skinner, 2004</xref>), whereas aardvarks in the more-arid Kalahari region of South Africa displayed an increased amplitude of the 24-h body temperature rhythm during a summer drought, as a result of low minimum 24-h body temperatures (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Rey et al., 2017</xref>). In both studies, the low body temperatures were accompanied by an increase in diurnal activity. In the Kalahari, many aardvarks (including five out of six study aardvarks) died during the drought, presumably from starvation, and survivors were in poor condition (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Rey et al., 2017</xref>). It remains unclear whether the shift to diurnal activity resulted from aardvarks being intolerant of the cold night-time temperatures in winter (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Skinner, 2004</xref>), or from an attempt to reduce the energetic costs of homeothermy when resources were limited (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Rey et al., 2017</xref>). Here, we expand our previous study to investigate the key drivers of changes in body temperature and activity in aardvarks.
</p>
