<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Carbohydrates were extracted from samples that were composed of three to four shoots grown in the same culture container; five samples were taken per treatment and per species, amounting to five biological replicates. Each replicate was adjusted to about 100 mg of fresh matter and was ground in an Eppendorf tube of 2 mL (automatic grinder for 1 min at 22 Hz) with two metallic beads and 1 mL of a water/ethanol mixture (20/80, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>). After vortexing and shaking for 30 min at 4 °C with an Eppendorf Thermomixer at 1400 rpm, samples were centrifuged at 17,000× 
 <italic>g</italic> at 4 °C for 10 min. The supernatant was collected and the pellet extracted again with 0.5 mL water/ethanol (20/80, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>). The resulting supernatant was pooled with the first one and dried at reduced pressure (Speedvac). The final dried extract was re-suspended in 1 mL Milli-Q water and filtered at 0.45 μm (PVDF filters) prior to analysis using High Performance Anion Exchange Chromatography coupled to a Pulsed Amperometric Detector (HPAEC-PAD) (Dionex ED 40, Dionex Corp., Sunnyvale, CA, USA), according to Guignard 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b93-ijms-14-04912">93</xref>]. Briefly, the analytical column was a Dionex Carbopac PA-20 (3 mm × 150 mm) with a PA-20 guard column (3 mm × 50 mm) kept at 35 °C. The mobile phase was on-line generated KOH at 0.5 mL min
 <sup>−1</sup>. The PAD detection was achieved with a gold working electrode and an Ag/AgCl reference electrode, with a data collection rate of 2 Hz. Carbohydrates were quantified using seven-points calibration curves with custom-made external standard solutions (based on stock solution of arabinose, galactose, glucose, sucrose, xylose, fructose, melibiose, raffinose, stachyose, maltose, cellobiose and rhamnose), ranging 1 to 100 μmol L
 <sup>−1</sup>, respectively, and every 10 injections, a check standard solution was used to confirm the calibration of the system.
</p>
