<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With regard to specific musculoskeletal conditions, RA is an autoimmune disease often marked by intra-articular decreases in pH, aberrant hyaluronan regulation and destruction of bone and cartilage [
 <xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Under control conditions, it has been shown that mice express ASIC3 in knee joint synoviocytes, but not in primary afferent neurones innervating the knee joint synovium, whereas post-inflammation (induced by carrageenan), ASIC3 coexpression was observed with protein gene product (PGP) 9.5 and calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP) in synovium-innervating primary afferent fibers; furthermore, unlike WT mice, ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice do not develop secondary mechanical analgesia (in response to von-Frey filaments), but like WT mice do develop primary mechanical hyperalgesia (in response to response to tweezers) [
 <xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. It should be noted that a further study using retrograde tracing has found that ~30% of knee-innervating afferents express ASIC3 under control conditions, which rises to ~50% during inflammation [
 <xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], thus afferents innervating non-synovium regions (e.g. bone, menisci, ligaments, etc.) of the knee likely express ASIC3 under control conditions with synovium-innervating neurones also expressing ASIC3 during inflammation. Considering the expression of ASIC3 in both synoviocytes and sensory neurones, development of synovial fluid acidity has the potential to modulate multiple cell types in an ASIC3-dependent manner. Indeed, in fibroblast-like synoviocyte (FLS) cultures isolated from WT mice, exposure to pH 5.5 for 1 hour increased hyaluronan release, by 1.5-fold compared to (physiological) pH 7.4, via increased intracellular calcium [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> [
 <xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. This could be a potential protective mechanism to compensate for the enhanced ASIC3 expression observed in these cells during inflammation. In addition to ASIC3 expressing FLS cells mediating increased [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> in response to acidic pH, the addition of inflammatory mediators such as interleukin 1β (IL-1β) caused an ASIC3-dependent increase in the levels of phospho-extracellular signal-regulated kinase (p-ERK), IL-6 and matrix metalloproteinase mRNA, and ultimately FLS cell death, a cascade that was significantly muted in ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice [
 <xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. This observation of IL-1β modulating ASIC3 function is further confirmed in studies in mice showing that induction of ischemia-related myalgia caused an increase in mechanical hypersensitivity and defensive behaviors, which were both attenuated by knock-down of ASIC3 or the IL-1 receptor 1 [
 <xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
</p>
