<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are many models used to simulate inflammatory pain in rodents, three key acute models being: complete Freund’s adjuvant (CFA), which produces a cell-mediated immune response [
 <xref rid="cit0074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]; carrageenan via a nonimmune-mediated response [
 <xref rid="cit0075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]; and zymosan via an innate immune response [
 <xref rid="cit0076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Carrageenan and CFA intra-plantar paw injections have been shown to produce similar degrees of inflammation in WT and ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice, however, the inflammation does not directly correlate to the degree of hyperalgesia. Whereas both inflammation models produced a statistically significant difference for mechanical hyperalgesia between genotypes (after 24 hours, i.e. ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice showed less hyperalgesia compared to WT), only carrageenan produced a statistically significant thermal hyperalgesia difference (after 24 hours, i.e. ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice showed less hyperalgesia compared to WT); furthermore, the ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> displayed a reduction in the inflammatory features (granuloma and vasculitis) of muscle compared to WT by ~65% [
 <xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>], which may perpetuate differences in hyperalgesia between genotypes. In support of these findings, carrageenan-induced muscle inflammation in WT mice is associated with an increase in ASIC3 mRNA in lumbar DRG neurones, and in the same model, ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice develop only primary, but not secondary, muscle hyperalgesia [
 <xref rid="cit0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. In a different model of muscle pain, repeated acid injections into the gastrocnemius muscle caused mechanical hyperalgesia in WT mice, but not ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice, furthermore, ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice did not develop cutaneous mechanical hyperalgesia after muscle inflammation whilst heat hyperalgesia occurred at similar levels to in WT mice [
 <xref rid="cit0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Interestingly, the importance of ASIC3 in muscle mechanical hyperalgesia was reinforced by results showing that injecting an ASIC3-encoding virus (and administration of carrageenan) into the muscle of ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice resulted in rescuing of the development of muscle mechanical hyperalgesia like that observed in WT mice, thus demonstrating a key role for ASIC3 in muscle-innervating sensory neurones in this model [
 <xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Mechanical hyperalgesia is also a prominent consequence of nerve injury. It has been shown that whilst ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice showed greater sensitivity to mechanical stimulation compared to WT, in post-spinal nerve ligation of ASIC3
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice showed comparable development of mechanical and heat hyperalgesia to WT mice; thus, ASIC3 appears to play a limited role in neuropathic pain [
 <xref rid="cit0081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The role of ASIC3 in neuropathic pain has been further evaluated using the cisplatin model of chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy, which causes hyperalgesia and allodynia in rodents [
 <xref rid="cit0082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], increased expression of ASIC3 being observed in DRG neurones innervating the gastrocnemius muscle, alongside mechanical hyperalgesia, which was ameliorated by the ASIC inhibitor amiloride [
 <xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>].
</p>
