<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There have been many efforts made to further improve the performance of Li-ion batteries, which achieved certain significant progress. At first, lithium metal was used as the anode, but it contains dendritic Li growth during cycling processes which is known to possess serious safety hazards [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Later, in 1991, Sony [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] discovered that pyrolytic carbon can effectively insert lithium ions, so they introduced the first commercial Li-ion battery based on C/LiCoO
 <sub>2</sub> [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Li-ion cells have higher operating voltage and lower self-discharge compared to some conventional secondary cells, such as nickel-cadmium and nickel-metal hydride. Despite the effort made in recent years, a further increase in energy densities (Wh l
 <sup>−1</sup>) and mass capacities (Wh kg
 <sup>−1</sup>) are still required to make Li-ion cells usable for low- or zero-hybrid and electric vehicles, energy-efficient cargo ships, locomotives, aerospace, and power-grid applications [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. By replacing lithium cobalt oxide cathode and carbon anodes with higher performance electrode materials, the devices can be improved [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. A few alternatives to cathode material have been developed. Many of them are either olivine type phosphates [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] layered compounds with hexagonal symmetry based on a α-NaFeO
 <sub>2</sub> structure, such as LiNiO
 <sub>2</sub>, LiNi
 <sub>x</sub>Co
 <sub>y</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, etc. Various elements such as Co, Mn, Ni, Cr, Al, or Li can be substituted into the α-NaFeO
 <sub>2</sub> structure and influence on stability and electronic conductivity [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The enhancement in the morphology of anode materials leads to better capacitance properties. Nanostructure design is an effective way to improve battery cycling because nanostructures provide short diffusion length for Li
 <sup>+</sup> ions and electrons with better resistance to fracture. Si (4200 mAh/g)-, Sn (992 mAh/g)-, and SnO2 (782 mAh/g)-based anodes have high gravimetric and volumetric capacities, so they are the most attractive and widely investigated candidate materials among the different alloys [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The most widely used anode is graphite, whose lithiated compounds have stable phases up to the LiC
 <sub>6</sub> stoichiometry, corresponding to a theoretical specific capacity of 372 mAh/g [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In contrast, silicon possesses a very high theoretical capacity of 4200 mAh/g and can intercalate 4.4 Li into Si at high temperatures to form Li
 <sub>15</sub>Si
 <sub>4</sub> [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Silicon also features a working potential around 0.4 V vs. Li/Li
 <sup>+</sup>, which is safer than operating potential of graphite (0.05 V vs. Li/Li
 <sup>+</sup>) [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Although silicon possesses all of these advantages, silicon-based anodes suffer from huge volume expansion upon cycling (≈400%) causing electrode fracture and electrical isolation during repeated cycling (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-00891-f002">Figure 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Continuous volume changes cause the breaking-reformation of the solid electrolyte interphase (SEI) film, which leads to the consumption of lithium ions and electrolyte. Passivating SEI layer usually contains non-cyclable lithium ions (LiF, Li
 <sub>2</sub>O), which are trapped by irreversible side reactions. Liquid electrolytes reductively decompose at the working potential of Si (&lt;0.4 V vs. Li/Li
 <sup>+</sup>), forming the SEI layer on a conductive surface. Solvent exhaustion causes the degradation of conductivity and induces fast capacity loss [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-00891" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
