<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Reproductive division of labor is characteristic of social insects, in which only some of the members are fully endowed with reproductive capacity, while others are not. As one of the highly developed social insects, the honeybee (
 <italic>Apis mellifera</italic> L.) also exhibits reproductive division of labor. This trait is not determined by genetic difference, but rather by complex sequential events occurring at early larval development stages. This complex sequence of events determines the fate of young and genetically identical larvae to switch into either reproductive a queen or infertile worker honeybee castes. According to the literature, larvae that are raised as queens or workers vary to a great extent in their gene and metabolic enzyme expression patterns, which are directly linked to caste determination 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Corona1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Hartfelder1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. A number of studies have been conducted on the differences between honeybee workers and queens, mainly focusing on the core causes of caste divergences. For instance, physiological and anatomical differences between the two castes 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Amdam1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Severson1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, environmental or early larval feed factors 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Hartfelder1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Groh1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Scharlaken1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, differential gene expression
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Corona1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Evans1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Hepperle1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, influence of juvenile hormone on caste determination 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Rueppell1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Barchuk1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Seehuus1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, and comparisons of hemolymph protein composition
 <xref rid="pone.0013455-Randolt1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> have been reported. There is an existing notion that 3 day old larva is bipotent and can grow into either queen or worker depending on epigenetics. Therefore, our hypothesis is that there will be very slight differences in protein profiles of day 3 larvae from the queen and the worker. On the other hand, despite the aforementioned studies on the mechanisms of honeybee caste differentiation, little is known about the roles of primary proteins expressed at the early post embryonic stage. Therefore, the aim of this study is to investigate the specific time and the influences of primary proteins on post embryonic caste determinations in honeybee by using proteomic analysis in combination with bioinformatics.
</p>
