<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0125">Another protein that showed increased expression in FV-PTC lesions was IQGAP2. To the best of our knowledge, structural and functional information regarding IQGAP2 is very limited 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Taken together with the features of FV-PTC and new classification of noninvasive FV-PTC as NIFTP lesions, higher expression of this protein in these samples can indicate a potential protective role. Notably, this potential protective role of IQGAP2 has also been shown in gastric cancer cell lines and primary gastric cancer tissues. Jin et al. studied IQGAP2 silencing through methylation and showed inverse correlation between IQGAP2 expression and gastric cancer progression 
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Same hypothesis is supported by Tamura et al., in which hormone-refractory prostate cancer demonstrated decreased expression of IQGAP2 
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Altogether, these studies highlight the potential of IQGAP2 as a tumor suppressor. Although evolutionary conserved IQGAP proteins share similar structure and sequence homology, IQGAP1 has been proposed to be an oncogene 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. It has been well known that IQGAP1, which has important roles in regulation and modulation of cytoskeleton and participate in cell adhesion by binding to specific molecules, is over-expressed in certain cancer types 
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Several reports suggest the involvement of IQGAP1 in thyroid tumorigenesis 
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. For example, Liu et al. assessed IQGAP1 copy number gain in different types of thyroid cancer, suggesting that IQGAP1 copy gain has a crucial role in thyroid tumorigenesis 
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Our results indicated that IQGAP1 was found at increased levels in CV-PTC (fc ≥ 2), while the expression of this protein was not changed in benign and FV-PTC samples. Generally speaking, increased level of IQGAP1 protein in CV-PTC can support the oncogenicity; while the higher levels of IQGAP2 protein in FV-PTC favor the tumor suppressor features. However, there seems to be a gap in the literature between the mechanism that either triggers the up-regulation of IQGAP1 and down-regulation of IQGAP2 in different neoplasms 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>.
</p>
