<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IFNγ is a potent proinflammatory cytokine and the key effector for differentiation of Th1 adaptive immune responses [
 <xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. IFNγ antiviral properties are complementary to those of type I IFN or are derived from the protective effects of Th1 adaptive responses in many viral diseases studied to date. A direct antiviral effect of type II IFN needs to be further characterized, such as in hepatitis C virus and HIV infection in which IFNγ interferes with several steps of the viral life cycle [
 <xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. It is still unclear why IFNγ
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice are slightly protected after SLEV intracranial challenge when compared to WT mice. Populations of innate and adaptive lymphocytes, which participate in related arboviral infections such as West Nile and Japanese Encephalitis, could be modulated by IFNγ and somewhat participate in early disease pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. We also considered that RIG-I could be at an elevated baseline expression level in the tissue of IFNγ
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice when compared to WT, explaining the marginal protection of IFNγ
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice to lethal SLEV challenge (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0010">Figure 10</xref>). Nonetheless, the role of IFNγ in the brain is different from the essential role of type I IFNs and indicates that IFNγ may be dispensable for the control of SLEV replication in the brain. Susceptible animal models of Dengue, Yellow fever and Zika virus infections are often based on the AG129 mouse strain, which lacks both type I and II IFN receptors [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. These studies, and others, have confirmed the protective role of IFNγ in the periphery [
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In contrast, our mouse model of St. Louis encephalitis was established as a model of severe neurological disease. Direct inoculation of SLEV in the brain allowed us to study IFNs from a different perspective [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Thus, IFNγ may be protective in initial phases of flavivirus infection by controlling or preventing virus dissemination in the periphery. Once in the CNS, IFNγ would be secondary to a type I IFN-driven antiviral response.
</p>
