<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The expression levels of certain proteins were validated by western blot analysis. These included annexin A2 (ANXA2), 60S ribosomal protein L18 (RPL18), tubulin β chain (TUBB) and collagen α-1 chain (COL1A1). Protein lysates of pooled fibroblasts from healthy controls and patients with PD carrying 
 <italic>GBA</italic> and 
 <italic>PARK2</italic> variants were resuspended in the same lysis buffer, as previously described in the sample preparation for MS. Equal protein quantities (10 µg) from four pooled healthy controls and individual patient samples were separated by 10% SDS-PAGE and then transferred to 0.20-µm PVDF (Pall Life Sciences). The membranes were blocked with 3% (w/v) BSA in TBST [50 mM Tris, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl and 0.1% Tween-20 (v/v)] for 1 h. Next, the membranes were incubated at 4˚C overnight in 3% BSA/TBST with the following antibodies: Anti-ANXA2 (cat. no. ab54771; Abcam; 1:1,000), anti-RPL18 (cat. no. ab241988; Abcam; 1:2,000), anti-TUBB (cat. no. 2128; Cell Signaling Technology, Inc.; 1:1,000), anti-COL1A1 (cat. no. ab138492; Abcam; 1:1,000) or anti-β-actin (cat. no. 3700; Cell Signaling Technology, Inc.; 1:20,000). After washing with TBST, the membranes were incubated with the appropriate secondary antibodies conjugated with horseradish peroxidase (cat. no. P0217, anti-rabbit and cat. no. P0260, anti-mouse; Dako, Agilent Technologies, Inc.; 1:2,000 except for anti-β-actin where 1:20,000 was used) at room temperature for 1 h. After washing with TBST, the bands in the membranes were detected by chemiluminescence using a WesternBright ECL detection kit (Advansta, Inc.). β-actin (ACTB) was used as a protein loading control. The immunoblot signals were detected and analysed using an ImageQuant LAS 4000 mini system (GE Healthcare). Densitometry analysis was performed using ImageQuant TL 1D version 7.0 (GE Healthcare) based on the band intensity of certain proteins divided by the band intensity of the respective ACTB, and normalized to those of the pooled healthy control fibroblasts.
</p>
