<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">In many plants, a larger number of DEMs have been identified in the developing seed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In this study, we identified 76 DEMs during Tartary buckwheat seed development. Expression profiles analysis revealed that these DEMs possessed stage-specific highly expressed patterns during Tartary buckwheat seed development, suggesting that these DEMs might perform their regulatory roles in a specific stage during Tartary buckwheat seed development and miRNAs with the same expression pattern might have a similar regulatory role in the developing Tartary buckwheat seed. Notably, some DEMs such as miR156, miR160, miR166, miR167, miR168, miR395, miR396, miR397, miR398, miR399, and miR408 were also found to be differentially expressed during seed development in many seed plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In rice, miR156, miR160, miR167, miR396, miR397, miR389, and miR408 have been functionally verified to regulate the rice seed development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. These suggested that these known miRNAs were the key and conserved miRNAs in different plant seed development regulation and could also be used as candidate miRNAs for Tartary buckwheat seed development. In addition, 37 novel miRNAs and several conserved miRNAs, including miR530, miR828, and miR858, were found to be specifically differential expression in developing Tartary buckwheat seed when compared with other seed plants. This indicated that these miRNAs might have a specific regulatory function in Tartary buckwheat seed development. Furthermore, all these information indicated that conserved and diverse miRNA-mediated regulatory mechanisms in seed development might exist in different seed plants.
</p>
