<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mixed fungal-bacterial infections tend to be the most complex and challenging to treat; however, the impact of these interactions on therapy remains largely understudied. 
 <italic>Candida</italic> and 
 <italic>s</italic>taphylococci species are the most common etiological agents isolated from device-associated nosocomial infections, and co-infection with these species poses a significant therapeutic challenge [
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Therefore, it has become crucial to understand the mechanisms of inter-species interactions within the context of polymicrobial infections. However, a major challenge in investigating polymicrobial biofilm-associated infections is the development of suitable animal models that account for host factors, and allow for evaluation of efficacy of treatment strategies under 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> conditions. Therefore, to substantiate our 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> findings on enhanced 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> antimicrobial tolerance in mixed biofilms with 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>), we modified the established mouse subcutaneous catheter model, which proved to be suitable for sustaining polymicrobial biofilm formation, as demonstrated by SEM analysis of explanted catheters (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Fig. 2</xref>, 3) [
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Vancomycin therapy was implemented at clinically relevant therapeutic doses over a period of five days in mice with single-species or mixed-species infected catheters. Comparative assessment of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from explanted catheters demonstrated inefficacy for vancomycin against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> in mice with co-infected catheters (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4</xref>). Vancomycin is one of the few antibiotics that have remained effective against methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, and development of resistance to vancomycin is relatively rare [
 <xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Therefore, the demonstration of failure of vancomycin against mixed 
 <italic>C. albicans-S. aureus</italic> device infection carries significant clinical implications. Notably, although single-species 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms were statistically susceptible to vancomycin treatment, the level of response was variable among the experimental sets. It is important to note however, that although the subcutaneous catheter infection model is an appropriate and reproducible model to evaluate foreign device biofilm infections and anti-biofilm strategies [
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], one disadvantage is lack of blood flow, which can result in inefficient drug delivery to the biofilm within the catheter. In fact, an initial pilot study indicated no effect for vancomycin on 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from single-species biofilms, supporting this concern (data not shown), and therefore, to circumvent this problem, for the therapy experiments, the catheters were cut longitudinally prior to inoculation and implantation in the animals. Neverthelss, despite this limitation, the findings from using the model for 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>-grown polymicrobial biofilms serve as a proof-of-principle underscoring the challenges associated with treatment of device-associated fungal-bacterial infections.
</p>
