<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To provide insights into the mechanisms contributing to the observed therapeutic implications of mixed biofilm infections, we performed RNA-seq analysis to delineate changes in gene expression during polymicrobial infections. The most significant finding from the comparative transcriptome analysis of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> was the down-regulation of the repressors of autolysis, lrgA and lrgB (
 <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and Table S1), during mixed catheter infection. eDNA is essential for bacterial biofilm formation and stability, and the majority of eDNA in the biofilm matrix is a result of cell lysis, which are critical for biofilm attachment during the initial stages of development [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Regulatory mechanisms in 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> controlling cell death and lysis during biofilm development are mediated by the opposing functions of the cid and lrg operons encoding holin- and antiholin-like proteins, respectively, [
 <xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The lrg operon encoding LrgA and LrgB proteins are the inhibitory counterparts to cid, and a repressor of murein hydrolase activity that hydrolyzes components of the cell wall involved in autolysis. Therefore, down-regulation of lrgAB promotes the activity of the cidA-encoded holin allowing increased activity of murein hydrolases, cell lysis and eDNA production. In fact, the lrgAB mutant was shown to exhibit increased biofilm matrix-associated eDNA, consistent with its role as an inhibitor of cidA-mediated lysis [
 <xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Similarly, staphylococcal thermonuclease (nuc), which was down-regulated during mixed catheter infection, was also shown to be involved in biofilm development, and a nuc mutant was reported to form thicker biofilms containing increased levels of eDNA [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Therefore, cell lysis and genomic DNA release during biofilm development is regulated 
 <italic>via</italic> opposing activities of the cid and lrg gene products, while staphylococcal thermonuclease functions to degrade the eDNA, possibly as a mean to promote biofilm dispersal.
</p>
