<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is well established that biofilms are physiologically different from planktonic cells and cells in a biofilm have altered metabolic activity. In a comparative transcriptome analysis to determine which genes are up-regulated in 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm, a study by Resch 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] found that, although the cell envelope appeared to be a very active compartment in biofilm cells as indicated by up-regulation of PIA, virulence factors such as toxins and proteases were up-regulated under planktonic growth conditions but not during biofilm growth. These findings are in line with ours, where a set of host cell-damaging proteins were found to be down-regulated during mixed species infection including gamma-hemolysins (γ-hemolysin) HlgAB and HlgCB. Interestingly, staphylococcal alpha-hemolysin (α-hemolysin) encoded by the gene 
 <italic>hla</italic>, also plays a major role in the biofilm formation and appears to be primarily required for cell-to-cell interactions. In fact, a mutant allele of 
 <italic>hla</italic> was shown to initially aid in colonizing a substratum. In addition to hemolysins, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> secretes bi-component cytotoxins, Panton-Valentine leukocidins, encoded by the genes 
 <italic>lukSF-PV</italic> composed of two co-transcribed open reading frames (
 <italic>lukS-PV</italic> and 
 <italic>lukF-PV</italic>), which were also found to be down-regulated during mixed catheter infection [
 <xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Expression and secretion of these factors play specific roles in certain 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> life stages and diseases, and are tightly controlled by a number of regulatory systems. Most notable is the accessory gene regulator (agr), a well-characterized two-component regulatory system that plays a critical role in the up-regulation and down-regulation of protease and exotoxins, respectively, [
 <xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60–62</xref>]. Interestingly, SarU, a positive activator of agr expression, is a member of the SarA family proteins; sarA is a transcriptional regulator that represses extracellular proteases and therefore, the observed elevated sarU expression during mixed catheter infection may result in additional amplification of agr signal, and explain the observed down-regulation of exotoxins in our infection model [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>].
</p>
