<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is important to note that previous studies by Peters 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] exploring the mechanism by which 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> augments 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> infection during polymicrobial intrabdominal infection, correlated lethal outcomes with exacerbation of host inflammatory responses. These findings are interesting as our transcriptome analysis of mixed-species catheter infection seemed to indicate potential dampening of host immune responses 
 <italic>via</italic> down-regulation of super-antigen like proteins in 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, such as the immunodominant surface antigen B (IsaB) which was shown to elicit immune response during septicemia [
 <xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. These findings are in line with the overall perception that biofilms tend to be resistant to host immune defense system [
 <xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Interestingly, in addition to contributing to biofilm matrix, PIA molecules, which we found to be up-regulated during mixed catheter infection, also serve to shield cells from neutrophil phagocytosis, thus significantly contributing to biofilm resistance from elimination by innate host defense [
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Most significantly however, was the noted up-regulation of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> capsular polysaccharide biosynthesis during mixed catheter infection. The production of capsular polysaccharide by 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> has been proposed as an anti-phagocytic evasion strategy by inhibiting neutrophil phagocytosis [
 <xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Serotype 5 and 8 capsular polysaccharides predominate among clinical 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates and animal studies have revealed that staphylococcal capsules enhance virulence by impeding phagocytosis. Furthermore, the capsule was also shown to modulate 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> adherence to surfaces 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, suggesting that it also promotes bacterial colonization, and persistence in the infected host [
 <xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]
</p>
