<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In light of the findings from the transcriptional analysis indicating enhanced 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> autolysis in mixed biofilms, and given the implication of biofilm eDNA on staphylococcal resistance to antimicrobials, as follow-up studies, we comparatively evaluated the accumulation of eDNA in single- and mixed-species biofilms. Additionally, the effect of eDNA on 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> response to vancomycin was also evaluated using DNA enzymatic digestion, and mutant strains lacking lrg operon genes. Quantification of eDNA in biofilms indicated a comparable level of eDNA produced by each species in their respective biofilms. In comparison, the total amount of eDNA in the mixed-species biofilms was significantly higher (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6a</xref>). Given that both species produced eDNA and the assay is not specific, it remains speculative at this time to confirm increase in 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> eDNA specifically in mixed biofilm. It is noteworthy however that eDNA level in mixed biofilms was greater than the combined eDNA concentrations from single-species biofilms (0.2350 ± 0.0046 versus 0.216 ± 0.00989; p = 0.2592; data not shown). Nevertheless, DNAse treatment of mixed biofilms significantly sensitized 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> to vancomycin, but had little impact on 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> susceptibility in single-species biofilm (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6b</xref>). The impact of DNAse on mixed biofilms was further demonstrated using confocal laser scanning microscopy where fluorescently-labeled vancomycin diffusion through DNAse treated biofilms caused significant disruption to the mixed biofilm structure, resulting in a more dispersed and accessible distribution of vancomycin (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6c,D</xref>). Comparative evaluation of biofilm formation using the lrg mutant strains paradoxically demonstrated reduced metabolic activity in lrgB mutant biofilm, but no reduction in biofilm biomass, indicating decrease in cell viability due to increase in cell lysis, without impacting biofilm due to increase in eDNA content (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5a-C</xref>). Theses findings were substantiated by the reduced susceptibility of the lrgB mutant to vancomycin, which was reversed upon DNAse treatment (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5c</xref>). It is important to mention that the down-regulation of the lrg operon during 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> grown mixed staphylococcal-
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm and inc12qqrease in biofilm eDNA content was previously reported by Pammi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], using a similar model. However, in that study, microarrays were used to delineate changes in 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> gene expression induced by 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Although the authors posited that the enhanced release of eDNA due to increased autolysis would affect antibiotic tolerance, antimicrobial susceptibility assays were not performed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> or 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. However, the key role for eDNA in mediating staphylococcal tolerance to antimicrobials in single-species biofilm was clearly demonstrated by subsequent studies by Doroshenko 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] and Brackman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In terms of therapeutic implications of the findings from our study, it is important to note an interesting study by Siala 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] demonstrating that the antifungal caspofungin improves the activity of fluoroquinolones against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> as well as in a similar subcutaneous biofilm model system as used in our study. Subsequent sequence analysis revealed a shared homology for IcaA with β-1-3-glucan synthase, the enzyme responsible for synthesis of β-1-3-glucan in 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, and the target for caspofungin. The findings from the study did in fact show that caspofungin treatment destructured the 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm, and reduced polymerization of matrix polysaccharides increasing drug penetration into biofilms. Hence, the authors proposed that IcaA inhibitors could be useful in the treatment of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm infections, substantiating the significance of our findings demonstrating up-regulation of the ica operon in mixed biofilms. However, as caspofungin is the drug of choice for treatment of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>-biofilm infections, the findings from the study are of even more significance in light of ours identifying an important role for eDNA in the 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>-mediated enhanced 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> tolerance to antimicrobials. In fact, eDNA has been described as a promising new target for staphylococcal anti-biofilm treatments [
 <xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and therefore, it is conceivable to speculate that the application of combination DNase-caspofungin treatment may prove effective against mixed 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>-staphylococci biofilm infections.
</p>
