<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">As economical traits, food habits domestication can reduce production cost in aquaculture. However, the molecular mechanism underlying food habits domestication has remained elusive. Mandarin fish (
   <italic>Siniperca chuatsi</italic>) only feed on live prey fish and refuse artificial diets. In the present study, we domesticated mandarin fish to feed on artificial diets. The two groups were obtained, the fish did not eat artificial diets or ate artificial diets during all of the three domestication processes, named Group W or X, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par2">Using transcriptome and metabolome analysis, we investigated the differentially expressed genes and metabolites between the two groups, and found three common pathways related to food habit domestication, including retinol metabolism, glycerolipid metabolism, and biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids pathways. Furthermore, the western blotting and bisulfite sequencing PCR analysis were performed. The gene expression of 
   <italic>TFIIF</italic> and histone methyltransferase 
   <italic>ezh1</italic> were significantly increased and decreased in the fish of Group X, respectively. The total DNA methylation levels of 
   <italic>TFIIF</italic> gene and tri-methylation of histone H3 at lysine 27 (H3K27me3) were significantly higher and lower in the fish of Group X, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par3">It was speculated that mandarin fish which could feed on artificial diets, might be attributed to the lower expression of 
   <italic>ezh1</italic>, resulting in the decreased level of H3K27me3 and increased level of DNA methylation of 
   <italic>TFIIF</italic> gene. The high expression of 
   <italic>TFIIF</italic> gene might up-regulate the expression of genes in retinol metabolism, glycerolipid metabolism and glycerophosphoric metabolism pathways. Our study indicated the relationship between the methylation of DNA and histone and food habits domestication, which might be a novel molecular mechanism of food habits domestication in animals.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
