<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Collectively, we found that immune response and cytoskeleton remodeling in pathway maps, response to organic substance and response to organic cyclic compound in GO processed, and cytoskeleton and cell adhesion in process networks are common in EASCs and PASCs. Interestingly, cytoskeleton remodeling was the most enrichment of upregulated DEGs both in EASCs and PASCs, while immune response was the most enrichment of downregulated DEGs both in EASCs and PASCs. Also, KEGG analysis (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS4">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>) showed ASCs derived from different deposits of VAT were both involved in cytokine–cytokine receptor interaction, Rap1 signaling pathway, regulation of actin cytoskeleton, PI3K-Akt signaling pathway, lysosome, and focal adhesion. The PI3K-Akt signaling pathway has been reported to primarily regulate the transcription, translation, proliferation, growth, survival, and other basic functions of extracellular signals. These new findings proved that the functions of ASCs derived from different deposits of VAT were similar, while different functions of immune response and extracellular matrix remodeling vary compared with the ASCs derived from SAT. As reported previously, the adipose tissue from subcutaneous and visceral showed a significant difference in immune response in obesity and other metabolic diseases (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Klimcakova et al., 2011</xref>). Compared with our studies, these differences may be most relevant to the different ASCs from SAT and VAT. Whereas, further studies on this point are required for confirmation. Furthermore, the function of extracellular matrix remodeling was reported as a critical microenvironment in different sites of adipose tissue (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Mori et al., 2014</xref>), and, by standard 2D culture or 3D culture, Strieder-Barboza et al. proved that adipocytes from different sites of adipose tissues have different metabolic profiling in murine obesity (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Strieder-Barboza et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
