<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The MnO
 <sub>2</sub> structure of birnessite is formally composed of stacked sheets of edge-sharing MnO
 <sub>6</sub> octahedra (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>
 </sup> and forms ultrathin nanoplatelets with a surface dominated with its basal face.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>
 </sup> It has a formal average oxidation state (AOS) of 4.0, but synthetic and natural forms commonly contain a mixture of Mn oxidation states (Mn
 <sup>IV</sup>, Mn
 <sup>III</sup>, and Mn
 <sup>II</sup>).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>
 </sup> In nature, birnessite or vernadite with AOS values as low as ∼3.5 is probably more common because natural organic matter has a strong propensity to reduce Mn
 <sup>IV</sup>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>
 </sup> Cationic vacancies represent an additional source of charge imbalance with, for example, previously reported populations of 12% in birnessite prepared in acidic and 6% in alkaline media.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>
 </sup> Countercations (
 <italic>e.g.</italic>, Na
 <sup>+</sup>, K
 <sup>+</sup>, and Mn
 <sup>2+</sup>) in the interlayer region counterbalance the missing charges resulting from the mixed Mn-oxidation states and vacancies. These can collectively alter the structure and the chemical reactivity of intercalated water. For example, manganese oxides with well-defined crystallographic sites host structured water layers, while those of lower crystallinity host relatively more disordered water.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>
 </sup> Understanding the forms of water trapped in the interlayer region when birnessite is exposed to moist air is especially central for understanding how they mediate reactions of natural and technological importance. Of note, resolving this chemistry can also be challenged by the coexistence of water condensed in pores between particles.
</p>
