<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Apart from particle size of ICEs, the shape of ICEs also presents significant influence on the Li ion conduction in SCEs. The direction and length of Li ion pathway provided by ICEs are directly determined by their shape. Cui and co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref> compared the effect of LLTO nanoparticles and nanowires on the electrochemical properties of PAN/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> solid electrolyte. It was found that the PAN/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> with 15 wt% LLTO nanowires displays a much higher ionic conductivity of 2.4 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at room temperature than that of PAN/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> and PAN‐LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> with 15 wt% LLTO nanoparticles (2.1 × 10
 <sup>−7</sup> and 0.5 × 10
 <sup>−5</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup>, respectively) (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>5</bold>
 </xref>a). The enhancement of ionic conductivity could be mainly attributed to the construction of continuous 3D ion‐conducting network pathway, providing long‐range fast Li‐ion lithium transfer channels; whereas, the LLTO nanoparticles were isolated in polymer matrix to form discontinuous pathways. Hu and co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">41</xref> fabricated a fiber‐reinforced polymer composite membrane (FRPC) by filling the PEO/LiTFSI hybrid into a Li
 <sub>6.4</sub>La
 <sub>3</sub>Zr
 <sub>2</sub>Al
 <sub>0.2</sub>O
 <sub>12</sub> 3D nanofiber network. The FRPC membrane displays an ionic conductivity of 2.5 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at room temperature, one or two orders of magnitude higher than that of PEO‐based electrolytes with LLZO nanoparticles.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">53</xref> The symmetric Li/FRPC/Li cell could steadily cycle for about 500 h at a current density of 0.2 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup> and over 300 h with a current density of 0.5 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup>. Recently, Wang et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">70</xref> developed a novel lithium‐salt‐rich PEO/Li
 <sub>0.3</sub>La
 <sub>0.557</sub>TiO
 <sub>3</sub> interpenetrating SCEs with 3D ceramic nano‐backbone by hot‐pressing and quenching, in which the concentration of LiTFSI reaches 40 wt%. This SCEs achieves an ionic conductivity of 1.8 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at room temperature and an electrochemical window of 4.5 V versus Li/Li
 <sup>+</sup>. More importantly, the as‐prepared symmetric Li/Li cell using above novel SCEs can steadily cycle for over 800 h at a current density of 0.1 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup>. Furthermore, some other researches[qv: 24b,71–73,104] also demonstrated that the ceramic nanowires can really enhance the Li ion conduction in polymer electrolyte. Except nanowire, the ceramic nanosheet also plays a similar role that offers continuous and high‐efficient ion‐conducting pathway. Song et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">74</xref> fabricated Li
 <sub>6.5</sub>La
 <sub>3</sub>Zr
 <sub>1.5</sub>Nb
 <sub>0.5</sub>O
 <sub>12</sub> nanosheets with GO as a template and then developed the PEO‐based composite electrolyte with 15 wt% Li
 <sub>6.5</sub>La
 <sub>3</sub>Zr
 <sub>1.5</sub>Nb
 <sub>0.5</sub>O
 <sub>12</sub> nanosheets, which exhibits a conductivity of 3.6 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at room temperature. Moreover, the mesoporous LiAlO
 <sub>4</sub> nanosheets were filled into P(EO)
 <sub>16</sub>/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> polymer matrix to fabricate SCEs with enhanced ionic conduction and transfer efficiency.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0075" ref-type="ref">75</xref> Therefore, compared to the nanoparticles of ceramic fillers, the nanowires, fiber, and nanosheets in polymer host are able to provide continuous Li ion transport channels and thus higher ionic conductivity could be obtained. In addition, the nanowire, fiber, and nanosheet of ceramic fillers can construct the 3D or 2D Li ion transport channels and network for high‐efficient long‐range Li ion transportation.
</p>
