<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Finally, to further explore the potential regulatory role of DEL on muscle development. We generated the MDRPTG-DEL co-expression network and studied PTG related to muscle development. The growth of skeletal muscle depends on muscle fiber hypertrophy, and the size of muscle fibers is increased when the rate of protein synthesis is higher than the rate of degradation. Under normal physiological conditions, the IGF-1-Akt-mTOR pathway plays a key regulatory role in skeletal muscle protein synthesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. After IGF-1 binds to the membrane receptor IGFR1, it promotes protein synthesis by activating Akt-mTOR
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. The Akt–mTOR pathway is also a meeting point for other signaling pathways known to promote muscle growth. For example, Wnt7a can participates in this pathway to induce muscle fiber hypertrophy by activating its receptor Fzd7
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. Correspondingly, it has been reported that 5′-adenosine monophosphate-activated protein kinase (AMPK) can inhibit the activity of mTOR complex 1 (mTORC1), thereby inhibiting protein synthesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, the WNK1-FOXO4 axis has been reported to affect muscle fiber hypertrophy. With-no-lysine (K) (WNK) kinases, which can mediate the nuclear localization and transcriptional activity of forkhead box protein O4 (FOXO4) to promote skeletal muscle cell hypertrophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. But in general, the most well-studied pathway is still the IGF-1-Akt-mTOR pathway. A large number of studies have confirmed that it is a core pathway that affects muscle fiber hypertrophy and is essential for myotube formation and muscle hypertrophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
