<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Interestingly, we comprehensive analysis found that multiple DELs may participate in the IGF-1-Akt-mTOR signaling pathway by regulating their PTGs. Mitochondrial calcium unidirectional transporter (
 <italic>MCU</italic>) is a highly selective channel for Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> transport into the mitochondria. Mammucari et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup> reported that 
 <italic>MCU</italic> participates in IGF-1-Akt-mTOR signaling by increasing Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> level in the mitochondria, activating the PGC-1α4, which is a transcriptional coactivator; the 
 <italic>IGF-1</italic> gene is activated through the PGC-1α4, leading to muscle hypertrophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. In the present study, our analysis showed that compared with the TP group, the LW group had higher 
 <italic>MCU</italic> expression level (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), which may be associated with the growth characteristics of Yorkshire pig breeds. More importantly, we found that DEL-MSTRG.8035 is positively related to the expression of 
 <italic>MCU</italic> and highly expressed in the LW group. Insulin-like growth factor 2 (
 <italic>IGF-2</italic>) is a maternal blotting growth factor that regulates prenatal skeletal muscle development
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. It can be involved in the IGF1-Akt-mTOR signaling pathway by activating the 
 <italic>IGF1</italic> receptor
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. A significant positive correlation exists between the DEL-MSTRG.12010 and 
 <italic>IGF-2</italic>, which were upregulated in the LW group. Interestingly, MSTRG.12010 was significantly negatively correlated with the troponin T-3 (
 <italic>TNNT3</italic>) gene. Wang et al
 <italic>.</italic> It is predicted that 
 <italic>TNNT3</italic> can regulate muscle growth and muscle fibers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>TNNT3</italic> is an important part of pig skeletal muscle filaments, which can affect the taste and tenderness of pork
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. Its expression level was low in the LW group. This may, on the other hand, find the reason for the decrease in meat quality as the growth rate increases. In addition, a potential target gene, serum response factor (
 <italic>SRF</italic>), plays an important role in controlling muscle fiber hypertrophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>SRF</italic> can control the transcription of miR-486, which as a potential regulator of PI3K/Akt signal transduction in muscle cells, can phosphorylate Akt and activate the IGF-1-Akt-mTOR signaling pathway, leading to muscle fiber hypertrophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. The co-expression network, suggests that DEL-MSTRG.21771 is significantly positively correlated with 
 <italic>SRF</italic> expression and highly expressed in the LW group. It is speculated that MSTRG.21771 regulates the high expression of its potential target gene 
 <italic>SRF</italic>, in the LW group, which possibly useful in maintaining the fast skeletal muscle rate in Yorkshire pig. 
 <italic>PLD1</italic> is an isoform of phospholipase D (
 <italic>PLD</italic>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>, which can stimulate phosphatidylcholine (
 <italic>PC</italic>) to produce phosphatidic acid 
 <italic>(PA</italic>), which can bind to mTOR and participate in the IGF-1-Akt-mTOR signaling pathway
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. The substrate 
 <italic>S6K1</italic> of 
 <italic>mTORC1</italic> is phosphorylated to enhance protein translation, resulting in muscle fiber hypertrophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, DEL-MSTRG.6293 was positively correlated with its expression, and highly expressed in the LW group. QTL results indicated that MSTRG.8035, MSTRG12010, MSTRG21771, and MSTRG.6293 were all mapped to the QTL loci, such as Loin weight QTL, Loin muscle area QTL, and backfat above muscle dorsi QTL, which are related to muscle development. It is speculated that these DELs may be related to skeletal muscle development, and participate in the IGF-1-Akt-mTOR signaling pathway by regulating the expression of its potential target genes, thereby affecting the muscle fibrous hypertrophy process. However, the specific molecular regulation of this phenomenon remains unclear, and further studies are needed. We speculate that DEL may affect muscle protein synthesis by regulating its PTG to participate in the IGF-1-Akt-mTOR pathway (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).
</p>
