<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effect of the catalyst oxidation state for CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR was also investigated for other metal catalysts. For example, in ref (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref338">338</xref>), the possible role of oxidized silver species was studied. Silver is a popular catalyst for CO
 <sub>2</sub> conversion to CO. Similarly to Au, Ag binds CO too weekly, thus limiting the further reduction of the intermediate products, and exclusively CO and H
 <sub>2</sub> are produced.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> In CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR to CO conversion, Ag is less active than Au but is cheaper and can achieve nearly 100% selectivity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref338">338</xref>
 </sup> Exceptional activity and selectivity for CO production at low overpotential was observed for Ag foils treated with oxygen plasma (
 <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">27</xref>
 </xref>a,b).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref338">338</xref>
 </sup> Such samples showed an enhanced surface roughness, 
 <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">27</xref>
 </xref>b, and an oxidized surface. Thus, both the rough and defect-rich structure as well as the oxidized species could explain the enhanced catalytic properties. As mentioned above, XAS is a good tool to distinguish between them. XANES and EXAFS spectra collected at the Ag K-edge in the as-prepared sample confirmed the presence of oxidized silver species. 
 <italic>Operando</italic> XAS measurements, however, showed that the AgO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> species are reduced within 35 min after the onset of the reaction, ruling out the role of AgO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> in the improved reactivity observed for this sample during the first 1–2 h (
 <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">27</xref>
 </xref>a).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref338">338</xref>
 </sup> Also, the reduction of the AgO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> species could not be responsible for the observed decrease in the selectivity from making CO in favor of making H
 <sub>2</sub> with increasing reaction time since the AgO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> species were gone well before the change in the selectivity was detected. Decreased coordination numbers, as obtained from EXAFS, could be linked to the enhanced structure roughness observed in microscopy measurements.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref338">338</xref>
 </sup> The former XAS results were also in agreement with 
 <italic>quasi in situ</italic> XPS data. The latter, being a surface-sensitive technique, showed that oxidized species on the surface are depleted within 3 min under reaction conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref338">338</xref>
 </sup> Importantly, no decrease in catalytic activity or selectivity was observed when the O
 <sub>2</sub>-plasma treated Ag foil was subsequently exposed to a H
 <sub>2</sub>-plasma, contrary to the Cu foil case in ref (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref364">364</xref>). This confirms that the activity and selectivity trends in the case of Ag are not related to the presence of residual AgO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> species but to the roughness and defects created by the O
 <sub>2</sub>-plasma exposure. A similar enhancement of CO
 <sub>2</sub> conversion in preoxidized and then reduced Au catalyst was also observed and assigned to disorder effects.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref407">407</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
