<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the catalysts that convert CO
 <sub>2</sub> to formate or formic acid, Sn and SnO
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>-derived catalysts have been investigated. The oxidation state of Sn seems to be one of the factors that significantly affects the observed catalytic activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref254">254</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref405">405</xref>
 </sup> In particular, a correlation between the formate production and the thickness of the oxide layer in the as-prepared catalysts was reported by Chen et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref405">405</xref>
 </sup> However, the reduction of the tin oxide is also expected under reaction conditions, with Sn
 <sup>4+</sup> species undergoing a transformation to Sn
 <sup>2+</sup> and then to the Sn
 <sup>0</sup> state.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref254">254</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref406">406</xref>
 </sup> The possibility to monitor the oxidation state of the Sn species under the catalyst actual working conditions, as provided by 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS, is very helpful. For instance, 
 <italic>in situ</italic> XAS measurements at the Sn K-edge were used to monitor changes in the Sn oxidation state of SnO
 <sub>2</sub> NPs supported on graphene.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref254">254</xref>
 </sup> The potential-dependent shift of the Sn K-edge XAS was observed under reaction conditions and is consistent with a gradual reduction of the Sn species (
 <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">27</xref>
 </xref>c). Linear combination analysis of the XANES spectra showed the presence of Sn
 <sup>0</sup> and Sn
 <sup>4+</sup> species, with the fraction of Sn
 <sup>0</sup> increasing for more negative applied potentials. EXAFS data analysis, 
 <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig27" ref-type="fig">27</xref>
 </xref>d, showed that the Sn–O coordination number decreased with increasing applied potential. The Sn–O bond length remained the same, ∼2.0–2.1 Å, which was also consistent with SnO
 <sub>2</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref254">254</xref>
 </sup> It is worth mentioning here that Sn
 <sup>2+</sup> species were detected in complementary 
 <italic>operando</italic> Raman measurements carried out for this sample. The difference between XAS and Raman results arises from the fact that XAS was probing the bulk phase of a relatively thick catalyst layer, while Raman was more sensitive to the interface between the catalyst and the electrolyte.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref254">254</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
