<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The latter aspect, namely, the role of the catalyst oxidation state, was especially debated in the recent literature and exemplifies a case where insight from 
 <italic>in situ</italic> XAS may play a decisive role. While it is generally assumed that the active species for CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR is metallic copper, it was observed that oxide-derived Cu catalysts have different catalytic properties than bulk metallic Cu.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref263">263</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref414">414</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref419">419</xref>
 </sup> In particular, lower reaction onset potential and higher selectivity toward C
 <sub>2+</sub> products were observed on oxide-derived catalysts.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref418">418</xref>
 </sup> The reduction of the oxidized copper species to metallic copper under the typical CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR conditions (e.g., −1.0 V vs RHE) is energetically favored, and therefore, the distinct catalytic properties of oxide-derived copper catalysts were explained by changes in the catalyst morphology and defect-rich structure.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref414">414</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref417">417</xref>
 </sup> However, 
 <italic>in situ</italic> grazing incidence Cu K-edge XAS studies by Mistry et al. on O
 <sub>2</sub>-plasma-treated Cu foils suggested that oxidized copper species can survive under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR conditions and may influence the formation of ethylene and alcohols.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref364">364</xref>
 </sup> In this study, a significantly enhanced selectivity toward ethylene production, as compared to an electropolished Cu foil, was observed for the plasma-treated sample. XANES and EXAFS spectra analysis of the as-prepared sample confirmed the presence of Cu(I) species and Cu–O bonds, respectively, in the oxygen-plasma treated Cu foils. 
 <italic>Operando</italic> XAS measurements carried under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR reaction conditions showed that the Cu–O contribution gradually diminished but was still evident at least 15 min after the potential was applied. After 1 h under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR, the Cu–O contribution could not be discerned (
 <xref rid="fig25" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig25" ref-type="fig">25</xref>
 </xref>a). However, due to the fact that the XAS signal in this case was dominated by the underlying bulk copper after the expected significant reduction of the thickness of the Cu oxide layer under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR, the presence of oxidized species in the near-surface layers cannot be excluded. The importance of the residual oxidized species was confirmed based on catalytic selectivity studies. In particular, the catalytic performance of the O
 <sub>2</sub>-plasma treated Cu foil was compared to that of an identical Cu foil similarly treated by O
 <sub>2</sub>-plasma but subsequently exposed to a hydrogen plasma to reduce the oxidized species. Although the latter sample had a similarly rough morphology as the nonreduced sample, a drastic decrease in the ethylene selectivity was obtained.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref364">364</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
