<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nonetheless, the stability of oxidized Cu species during CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR strongly depends on the nature of the investigated catalyst, its morphology, and support. Grosse et al. used 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS to monitor the evolution of the oxidation state and structure of 100 nm large Cu cubes electrochemically grown on carbon supports in the presence of chloride that stabilizes their cubic form.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref148">148</xref>
 </sup> As-prepared cubes showed the presence of Cu
 <sub>2</sub>O and CuCl
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>. However, the chloride contribution disappeared in the EXAFS spectra upon contact with the KHCO
 <sub>3</sub> electrolyte. After 1 h of CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR, however, oxidized copper species were reduced and only metallic Cu was observed both by XANES, as well as by EXAFS analysis, including the wavelet transform analysis to enhance the chemical sensitivity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref148">148</xref>
 </sup> Here, the changes in the oxidation state were accompanied by significant changes in the catalyst morphology under CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR, namely, the reduction of the nanocube sizes and an increase of their porosity. The large disorder in the final catalyst structure was observed also in the XAS data, where reduced coordination numbers for Cu–Cu bonds were obtained from the fitting of the EXAFS spectra for the metallic catalyst phase. Findings from XAS regarding catalyst oxidation state supported by 
 <italic>quasi in situ</italic> XPS/Auger measurements confirmed the lack of Cu(I) species in the Cu nanocube/C samples. In contrast, in the case where similar Cu cubes were grown on a copper foil (Cu cube/Cu), Cu-Auger data showed the presence of residual Cu(I) species after 1 h reaction. For this sample, enhanced production of C
 <sub>2+</sub> products (ethylene) was observed as compared for the Cu cube/C samples, which mainly generated CH
 <sub>4</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref148">148</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref420">420</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
