<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pulpal repair in response to dental tissue damage caused by caries or trauma is a complex inflammatory process [
 <xref rid="B3-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. As caries progresses from the tooth surface toward the dentin-pulp complex, activation of both the innate and adaptive immunities occurs [
 <xref rid="B4-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. For a relatively mild stimulus, such as slowly progressing caries or tooth wear, the dentin-pulpal complex produces tertiary dentin. In contrast, under conditions of more rapidly progressing disease, a more intense immune and inflammatory response occurs, resulting in pulp tissue death [
 <xref rid="B5-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. During healing after dental tissue injury, induction of necrosis of pulp tissue, including odontoblasts, occurs followed by reparative dentinogenesis, a result of continuous and interrelated processes, including chemotaxis, proliferation, angiogenesis, extracellular matrix remodeling, and cell differentiation [
 <xref rid="B6-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Wei et al. [
 <xref rid="B6-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] reported that after tissue injury, the unique dentin-pulp complex might undergo complete regeneration, including the differentiation of various cell types and induction of new proteins. Smith et al. [
 <xref rid="B7-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] reported the presence of a broad spectrum of bioactive molecules in the dentin-pulp complex. Eckhardt et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] pointed out that identifying the bioactive proteins may facilitate a better understanding of their potential involvement in regenerative and other tissue responses. Therefore, elucidation of differences in the protein expression between healthy and diseased pulp tissue may help assess whether these differences offer novel clinical therapeutic methods [
 <xref rid="B7-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-jcm-08-01234" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
