<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>FTIR and DSC have been employed to investigate the possibility of incidence of interaction between loratadine and sulpiride. The existence of the characteristic FTIR absorption bands of both loratadine and sulpiride in the spectrum of the corresponding physical mixture (at the same positions compared to the spectra of the individual drugs) refers to the absence of drug/drug interaction. The presence of the melting endotherms of loratadine in the physical mixture DSC thermogram revealed the nonexistence of drug interaction supporting the FTIR results. The absence of melting endotherm of sulpiride could be attributed to the dissolution of the drug in the melt of loratadine as the two drugs have close melting temperatures. The less cloudy appearance of F1, F2 and F3 compared to other formulations could be related to diminished droplet size resulting in reasonably weak scattering rendering the nanoemulsion system optically translucent (McClements, 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; McClements, 
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The higher viscosity values of F6 and F7 relative to other formulations might be ascribed to the higher concentration of lecithin or glycerol respectively. Similarly, Zhou et al., have revealed a rise in the viscosity of a lecithin nanoemulsion by the increase in the concentration of lecithin or glycerol (Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). The high entrapment efficiency of loratadine and sulpiride in the prepared nanoemulsions could be attributed to increased drug solubility in the crude olive which contains a combination of unsaturated fatty acids that provide a cosolvent effect (Balata et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). This result could also be ascribed to the high ester value of olive oil (190.86) indicating high percentage of ester groups (Zambiazi et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). This value is an indication for the proportion of glycerol existing in the oil that gives high solubilizing capacity for the oil (Azeem et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). In a recent study, olive oil has been reported to have the uppermost solubilizing capacity for the hydrophobic drug gliclazide relative to other screened oils (Balata, 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). These results are also in accordance with a preceding work that revealed that olive oil has a good solubilizing ability for the hydrophobic drug resveratrol (Balata et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). In addition, the hydrophilic nonionic surfactant, Tween 80, having HLB 15 might maximize the solubilizing power, which is essential for affording a uniform emulsion. Furthermore, lecithin as a natural emulsifying agent might enhance the solubilization of both drugs in the oil and hence entrapment efficiency. The resulted small droplet size is important for drug bioavailability as it leads to greater surface area for drug absorption. The small droplet size of F3 compared to F1 and F2 could be ascribed to the higher total concentration of the used surfactants (Tween 80 and sodium cholate) that might jacket the surfaces of the new droplet produced throughout homogenization and lower the oil/water interfacial tensions (Samson et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). It has been reported that the average droplet size of nanoemulsion reduces with the increase in concentration of surfactant due to the formation of larger water-oil interface (Joung et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Furthermore, combination of hydrophilic surfactant Tween 80 and lecithin (natural emulsifying agent) decreases the interfacial tension during emulsification process and consequently reduces the nanoemulsion droplet size (Guttoff et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The small PDI values of F2 and F3 indicates narrow globule size distribution, which reflects uniformity in the size distribution and droplet diameter of both formulations (Balakumar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The measured zeta potentials reflect good stability of the selected systems with F2 having the highest stability. Generally, it has been reported that zeta potential of ± 30
 <bold> </bold>mV was appropriate for nanoemulsion stability; (Müller et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Balakumar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Formulations with high zeta potential have higher stability, as they resist coalescence of oil droplets through enhancing the electrostatic repulsion between the charged globules (Balakumar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The electrical conductivity of the selected nanoemulsions revealed good quality nanoemulsions and support stability (Sari et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The enhanced release of loratadine and sulpiride from F2 and F3 compared to the corresponding raw rugs could be ascribed to the small droplet size of the investigated nanoemulsions which imparts large surface area for release (Alshehri et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Thus, both drugs existed in solubilized micellar solution which greatly enhanced their release from the selected nanoemulsions (Balata, 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Kinetic of release of loratadine and sulpiride from F2 and F3 obeyed the Higuashi Diffusion model denoting that there was a direct proportional relationship between the amount of drug release and either the square root of the total amount of the drugs or the drug solubility in the nanoemulsion formulation (Sarpal et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Also, the release kinetics followed the model of Baker–Lonsdale that was established from Higuchi model and described the release of drugs from the sphere-shaped matrices. Analogous findings have been documented for the release of chlorehexidine HCL from a promising antibacterial root canal irrigant nanoemulsion (Abdelmonem et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Stability study revealed that F3 maintained excellent physical stability at 4 °C and 25 °C for one month.
</p>
