<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the biggest challenges of current times is to feed the ever-growing population amidst a changing climate with limited available resources. Abiotic stresses such as salinity, water (drought and flooding), and heat are a few of the many factors that directly impact the agronomical traits and yield of crops [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Potato (
 <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.) is one of the most important food crops, third-largest after rice and wheat in terms of human consumption [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This crop can also be used commercially as a health food because it is rich in antioxidants, minerals, and dietary fibers [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, as a consequence of global warming, a continuous increase in temperature leads to multiple stresses, including heat and salinity. Consequently, excess reactive oxygen species (ROS) are generated inside the cells, which, if not scavenged, can lead to severe oxidative stress to plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. ROS can be scavenged using an array of enzymatic [such as superoxide dismutase (SOD), ascorbate peroxidase (APX), and catalase] [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and non-enzymatic mechanisms (glutathione, α-tocopherol, carotenoids, flavonoids) [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Impaired function or decreased activity of any of these ROS scavenging activities can also have a devastating impact on the plant’s growth and yield [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Stress also affects the quality of potato tubers by altering sugar and solid content [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. A limited understanding of heat and salt tolerance regulation mechanisms through TFs (transcription factors) hinders elite cultivars’ development with higher stress tolerance [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The complete genome sequence data of potato (haploid genome content of 840 Mb) offers an excellent opportunity to explore gene families, their downstream pathways, and regulation mechanisms under stress conditions.
</p>
