<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the current study, we mined and functionally annotated the basic leucine zipper family (bZIP) of TFs in potato using its genome information and previous annotation [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Generally, the bZIP proteins contain an essential region that consists of a DNA-binding part and a leucine zipper dimerization motif [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Structurally, the bZIP family is highly conserved among the species with signature sequences of the domains (60–80 amino acids long). These bZIPs can be subdivided further into two essential parts depending on their structure: the basic region and the leucine zipper region. The basic region has an invariant motif N-X7-R / K-X9, which links nuclear localization to the target DNA [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The leucine zipper region consists of Leu heptad repeats, and often with Ile, Val, Phe, or Met [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Recent findings of bZIP TFs in specific plant families have shown that they are involved in diverse biological roles in plant physiology [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The functions of bZIP TFs are well characterized in various plants during stress conditions, such as salt, heat, and hormone signaling [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. To date, genome-wide analysis has led to the identification of the 
 <italic>bZIP</italic> gene family in several plants, including 75 in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana (AtbZIPs)</italic>, 89 in 
 <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> (
 <italic>OsbZIPs</italic>), 160 in 
 <italic>Glycine max</italic> (
 <italic>GmbZIPs</italic>), 166 in 
 <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> (
 <italic>SbbZIPs</italic>), 125 in 
 <italic>Zea mays</italic> (
 <italic>ZmbZIPs</italic>), 136 in 
 <italic>Brassica napus</italic> (
 <italic>BrbZIPs</italic>), and 370 in 
 <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> (
 <italic>TabZIPs</italic>), and 41 in 
 <italic>Ipomoea trifida</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Recently, 65 
 <italic>bZIPs</italic> were identified in the potato genome using a single database source viz. Spud DB [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In our current study, we used the previous genome sequence databases available in SpudDB [
 <xref rid="pone.0247864.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] as well as the latest genome assembly in the Ensembl plants database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plants.ensembl.org/Solanum_tuberosum" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://plants.ensembl.org/Solanum_tuberosum</ext-link>) of potato for a comprehensive investigation of the 
 <italic>StbZIP</italic> family that includes transcripts and genes. The present work led to the identification of 25 more 
 <italic>bZIPs</italic> at the genome-wide scale.
</p>
