<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, we found that retinol metabolism is associated with CE infection in sheep. After CE infection, 38 DEGs associated with retinol metabolism, including 
 <italic>ADH</italic> [
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], 
 <italic>RDH</italic> [
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], 
 <italic>UGT</italic> [
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and 
 <italic>LRAT</italic> [
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], were significantly higher in CE-resistant sheep than in non-resistant sheep. These genes are already known to be associated with the binding, metabolic process, and transport of retinol. Reports have shown that retinol plays an important role in maintaining host immune function. Cotton rats lacking retinol had a significantly higher infection rate of filarial worms compared with normal cotton rats [
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and a similar finding was reported in research of human infection with filarial worms [
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Parasites may take retinol preferentially from the host at the infected site for their own development, differentiation, growth, and reproduction. High concentrations of retinol in worms have a significant effect on their growth rate. Other studies have suggested that retinol is critical to defense against parasite infections, and this is due to the fact that a lack of retinol damages the epithelial tissue barrier and helps filariae to penetrate and migrate in the host, and local immune response of the mucosal surface thereby decreases [
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Retinol is, therefore, vital in host resistance to parasitic infections. Based on these findings, we speculated that the high expression of these genes in the CE-R group might play an important role in intestinal defense against 
 <italic>E. granulosus</italic> infection, by hindering parasite damage to the epithelial tissue barrier, as well as penetration and migration to the host organ. These types of inhibitory effects might be related to the artificial infection resistance in the small intestinal tissue of Kazakh sheep reported by us previously [
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This is the first finding of a relationship between retinol metabolism and CE resistance in the host.
</p>
