<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For all of the precipitation hardening Al alloys investigated, it holds that if the alloy is cooled sufficiently slowly, quench-induced precipitation occurs at relatively high temperatures [
 <xref rid="B117-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. During the HTRs, essentially stable equilibrium phase particles form in the shape of coarse precipitates with a low aspect ratio, and their dimensions can reach more than 10 µm [
 <xref rid="B117-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. If the grain size of the alloy is considerably larger than this, precipitation will predominantly occur inside the grains [
 <xref rid="B31-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B195-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>]. However, quench-induced precipitation also occurs on the grain boundaries [
 <xref rid="B31-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. In commercial wrought alloys, nucleation of these equilibrium phase particles at high temperatures takes place on relatively coarse primary particles comprised of elements such as Fe, Mn and Si [
 <xref rid="B118-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. In addition, pre-existing particles from the same phase that were not dissolved during the solution treatment (i. e. stable equilibrium phase particles in the shape of coarse precipitates) can also act as nucleation sites [
 <xref rid="B148-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. These undissolved particles start to grow instantly with the onset of cooling. This is obvious from 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f078">Figure 78</xref>, which compares DSC cooling curves for aluminium alloys after incomplete dissolution with those after full dissolution. A comparison of 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f078">Figure 78</xref>D and F is particularly illuminating, as these show DSC cooling curves for the same alloy and the same cooling rate but with different solution treatments. The obvious difference in the precipitation behaviour during cooling is attributed to incomplete dissolution of β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si after solution treatment at 540 °C for 20 min, while a full solution was achieved in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f078">Figure 78</xref>F at 560 °C. In Ref. [
 <xref rid="B148-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>], we showed that this incomplete dissolution strongly increases the quench sensitivity and that the UCCR is increased by about a factor of three.
</p>
