<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The kinetics of quench-induced reactions are accelerated by an increased concentration of alloying elements [
 <xref rid="B118-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. At medium cooling rates, which are particularly relevant for gas cooling, for instance, more highly concentrated alloys may lose a large amount of their age-hardening potential by quench-induced precipitation. Applying the same gas cooling rates to leaner alloys might still achieve sufficient supersaturation, allowing these alloys to exploit nearly their full age-hardening potential. Leaner alloys might therefore achieve higher hardness and strength after medium-slow cooling, as compared to more highly concentrated alloys. This aspect was demonstrated for AlMgSi and AlZnMgCu wrought and AlSiMg cast alloys (compare 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f041">Figure 41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f056">Figure 56</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f073">Figure 73</xref>, respectively). Particularly for the latter, the applied solution treatment makes a substantial impact, since the coarsening of the eutectic, which increases with soaking duration, influences the density of nucleation sites. In all cases, the lower concentrated alloy after medium-slow cooling at approximately 1 K/s and additional ageing achieved a hardness of about 150% of the highest alloy concentration considered. This aspect has particular technological relevance if the aim is to retain high dimensional stability of the quenched parts, or to limit their residual stresses, which is often associated with reduced cooling rates. The knowledge obtained of the kinetics of quench-induced precipitation now allows us to choose either an appropriate cooling process for a certain fixed alloy and/or an appropriate alloy for a certain fixed cooling process.
</p>
