<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Given the limited options for treating microaerophilic parasites, Mtz resistance is a major obstacle in the control of giardiasis and a widespread issue for metabolically related pathogens treated with nitroheterocyclics. To our knowledge, our study provides the first quantitative proteomic data for any MtzR pathogen. Further, we performed the first exploration of protein PTM networks in MtzR parasites and identified substantial changes in 4 major protein modification networks (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). This indicates that PTM and differential protein expression may both contribute to Mtz resistance phenotypes. Further, we demonstrated trends of increased protein acetylation in MtzR lines, as well as cross-resistance to the histone deacetylase inhibitor TSA (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>, panel A), which also produced divergent KAc profiles in exposed MtzS and MtzR lines (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>, panel B; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>). Perhaps most significantly, this study documented changes in Mtz susceptibility in 2 MtzR lines upon cessation of drug selection, and we observed IC
 <sub>50</sub> variation between isolates and widespread fluctuations in 3 PTM networks (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>). However, a key aim of this 3-way, isogenic analysis of MtzR lines was to reconcile observed inconsistencies of passive and active MtzR traits and isolate-dependent variation [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Our results show that although there was some equivalency at the functional level, differentially expressed proteins diverged considerably between isolates (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">1</xref>, panel A), within protein families (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>, panel B and C), networks (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>), and pathways (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>). When interrogating post-translational networks, again multiple isolate-specific features differentiated each MtzR line (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>), including some preexisting, unique features in parental MtzS lines. Last, isolate variation was evident in Mtz sensitivity and PTM profiles upon exposure to TSA (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>, panel B) and cessation of Mtz selection (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>). Overall, we believe this study confirms that MtzR is polygenic, plastic, and likely post-translationally regulated, with particularly strong links between Mtz resistance and protein acetylation. Our data therefore support earlier hypotheses that suggest links between MtzR and epigenetic regulation [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], expand previously limited data concerning post-translation modifications in MtzR [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and highlight for the first time that changes in post-translational modifications in MtzR are widespread.
</p>
