<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par60">GO enrichment analysis showed that the biological processes (BPs) of the differently expressed RBPs were mainly enriched for ncRNA processing, tRNA metabolic processes, RNA splicing, regulation of mRNA metabolic processes, ribosome biogenesis, and translational regulation. Calo et al. reported that DExD-box helicase 21 (DDX21), a member of the DEAD-box RNA helicase family, was required for pre-rRNA processing; occupied the transcribed rDNA locus; directly contacted both rRNA and snoRNAs; and promoted rRNA transcription, processing, and modification in the nucleolus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Protein quaking (QKI), a splicing factor frequently downregulated in lung cancer and correlated with poor prognosis, selectively suppressed the inclusion of NUMB mRNA exon 12 to promote the expression of a NUMB isoform, thereby inhibiting proliferation and the Notch signalling pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Another study reported that DEAH-box helicase 37 (DHX37), an ATP-dependent RNA helicase, was essential for ribosome biogenesis by facilitating small ribosomal subunit maturation. The cellular component analysis in the present study showed that the differential RBPs were primarily enriched for cytoplasmic ribonucleoprotein granule, ribonucleoprotein granule, mitochondrial ribosome, and P-body. Recently, Rozanska et al. demonstrated that ribosome binding factor A (RBFA) was a mitochondrial RBP that played important roles in mitoribosome biogenesis. RBFA combined with helices 44 and 45 of the 12S rRNA in the mitoribosomal small subunit promoted the dimethylation of two highly conserved consecutive adenines, necessary for completing mitochondrial rRNA maturation and promoting the formation of a functional mitoribosome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. P-body, a cytoplasmic ribonucleoprotein granule, reportedly played a crucial role in translational repression and mRNA decay [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. NBDY (NoBody), a recently identified P-body protein, inhibited mRNA turnover, as the silencing of NBDY expression destabilized a reporter of nonsense-mediated decay [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. YTH N6-methyladenosine RNA binding protein 2 (YTHDF2), another recently discovered P-body protein, is specifically bound to N-methyladenosine and promoted the destabilization of mRNAs with this modification [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Regarding molecular function, the differential RBPs in the present study were largely enriched for catalytic activity, acting on RNA, ribonuclease activity, translation factor activity, and RNA and ribonucleoprotein complex binding. For example, mex-3 RNA binding family member C (MEX-3C) is a MEX-3-homologous protein with E3 ubiquitin ligase activity mediated by a RING domain and critical for RNA degradation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Cano et al. demonstrated that MEX-3C regulated 
 <italic>HLA-A2</italic> expression by binding to its 3′-UTR, thereby inducing the ubiquitin-dependent degradation of this mRNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].
</p>
