<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par62">Subsequently, we established a PPI network of these differentially expressed RBPs and constructed a module containing 104 key RBPs. Most of these key RBPs have been reported to play important roles in cancer initiation, development, and metastasis. Cancer susceptibility candidate 3 (CASC3), also known as metastatic lymph node 51 (MLN51), is a splicing factor that regulates long intron-containing genes splicing. CASC3 overexpression significantly promoted hepatocellular carcinoma cell proliferation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. EFTUD2, an alternative splicing factor, may regulate the innate immune response in macrophages. Silencing of EFTUD2 expression significantly inhibited chronic intestinal inflammation and tumorigenesis, which was related to the reduced production of inflammatory cytokines and tumorigenic factors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. DDX39, a DEAD-box RNA helicase, was upregulated in hepatocellular carcinoma tissues and cells and negatively correlated with patient OS. Furthermore, DDX39 overexpression promoted hepatocellular carcinoma cell proliferation and invasion through the Wnt/β-catenin pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Block of proliferation 1 (BOP1), which reportedly participates in 28S and 5.8S ribosomal RNA processing and 60S ribosome biogenesis, was down-regulated in patient-derived melanoma samples [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. A loss of BOP1 also resulted in acquired resistance to BRAF kinase inhibitors in melanoma by increasing MAPK signalling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Importin 4 (IPO4) belongs to the importin β family, which is responsible for transporting histones H3 and H4 into the nucleus for chromatin assembly [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Xu et al. reported IPO4 overexpression in gastric cancer tissues and cell lines and demonstrated that IPO4 knockdown suppressed gastric cancer cell proliferation and migration [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. This brief overview highlights the role of RBPs in tumorigenesis and development. Thus, the regulation of RBPs may represent an important breakthrough in tumour diagnosis, therapy, and prognostic prediction.
</p>
