<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par63">In this study, we finally identified eight independent prognosis-associated RBPs and used them to construct a prognostic prediction model. Moreover, the prognostic ability of this model was validated in the test dataset, which also showed a good predictive performance. Although five of the eight hub RBPs did not have statistically significant differences in the multivariate Cox regression analysis, these hub genes were found to be associated with OS in BLCA patients through survival analyses, which means these genes can be used to predict the prognosis of BLCA patients. Therefore, these five hub genes were also included when we constructed prognostic model. Among these hub RBPs, high expression levels of GEMIN7, OAS1, APOBEC3H, and YTHDC1 were associated with favourable prognosis in BLCA patients, while high expression levels of DARS2 and RBMS3 predicted poor prognosis. A previous study reported that GEMIN7, a component of the survival motor neuron complex, is involved in the biogenesis of the small nuclear ribonucleoprotein complex [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]; however, its role in cancers is rarely reported. OAS1, initially identified as an interferon-induced antiviral enzyme, was recently associated with 5-azacytidine (AZA) sensitivity, the deficiency of which resulted in the NCI-60 set of cancer cell lines resistant to AZA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. APOBEC3H is a single-stranded DNA cytosine deaminase that can induce mutations in tumour cells, resulting in immune recognition or cancer cell death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. YTHDC1, a N
 <sup>6</sup>-methyladenosine binding protein localized in YT-bodies adjacent to nuclear speckles, regulates mRNA splicing by recruiting splicing factors to the targeted mRNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. DARS2 promoted cell cycle progression and inhibited hepatocellular carcinoma cell apoptosis via the miR-30e-5p/MAPK/NFAT5 pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Wu et al. demonstrated that the loss of RBMS3 in epithelial ovarian cancer not only induced chemoresistance to platinum but also promoted recurrence via miR-126-5p/β-catenin/CBP signalling. Moreover, the loss of RBMS3 was associated with poor overall and relapse-free survival in epithelial ovarian cancer patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Another study found that RBMS3 inhibited breast cancer cell proliferation, migration, and invasion through the Wnt/β-catenin signalling pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The loss of EFTUD2 repressed colonic inflammation and tumorigenesis via inactivation of NF-κB signalling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. TRIM71, an E3-ubiquitin ligase, induced ubiquitination and degradation of mutant p53 by binding to its transactivation domain in ovarian cancer, leading to decreased ovarian cancer cell growth [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. However, the functions and molecular mechanisms of these hub RBPs in BLCA remain poorly understood; thus, functional experiments are needed to further explore their potential roles and mechanisms. Moreover, large sample and multi-centre clinical studies are expected to verify the results.
</p>
