<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As above mentioned, ferrite and brittle twisted cementite lamellae were alternately arranged (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04136-f002">Figure 2</xref>). During cold deformation, soft ferrite deformed in priority, but the limited deformation of cementite restricted deformation of the ferritic matrix, leading to an inhomogeneous distribution of strain in the lamellar pearlite. Moreover, a hard and brittle network of the pre-eutectoid cementite precipitated at grain boundaries, splitting the continuity of the matrix. Thus, an obvious cleavage surface formed during deformation [
 <xref rid="B41-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Subsequently, cracks initiated at the network of brittle cementite, which aggravated the failure of the brittle cleavage. Hence, the plasticity of the lamellar pearlite structure was poor, and the stress-strain curve showed an insignificant yield point accordingly (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04136-f009">Figure 9</xref>). In contrast, the stress-strain curve of the specimen (with lamellar pearlite structure) after spheroidizing annealing showed obvious yield points, which was attributed to dislocation accumulation on the ferritic grain boundaries and dislocation activation in ferrite according to the polycrystalline yield theory [
 <xref rid="B42-materials-12-04136" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. After heat treatment, the strength of the steel decreased, and the elongation increased. The fundamental reason must be related to the dispersed cementite particles in the fine-grained ferritic steels. In contrast, the strength of the 0.10C-1.50Cr steel increased, and the elongation decreased after cold rolling and cold drawing. The decreasing strain after the cold drawing was due to the fact that the average size and the ratio of larger cementite particles were larger than that after cold rolling (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04136-f003">Figure 3</xref>g). On the other hand, the increasing strength was associated with the high dislocation density in the cold drawn steel (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04136-f008">Figure 8</xref>b).
</p>
