<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The quench sensitivity of Al alloys has been researched for about 70 years (e.g., [
 <xref rid="B10-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]). Within the existing substantial body of work, the definitions of the term “quench sensitivity” differ, and this term generally refers to a reduction in the final properties (e.g., strength; ductility/toughness; corrosion-resistance) in the as-quenched state [
 <xref rid="B21-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] or after ageing, generally as a result of reduced cooling rates [
 <xref rid="B15-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The reason for this reduction, for instance in the hardness or yield strength, is the coarse precipitates which grow during cooling [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Although these coarse quench induced precipitates have very little hardening effect in themselves [
 <xref rid="B33-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], the atomic fraction of alloying elements that is bound in quench-induced precipitates reduces the amount of solutes available for the formation of strengthening precipitates during ageing. The degree of solute reduction obviously depends on the fraction of quench-induced precipitates that is formed. Another aspect relating to quench sensitivity is the loss of properties across the thickness of a thicker product, which is related to a reduced cooling rate in the core of the material [
 <xref rid="B34-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. However, the definition of quench sensitivity is refined here, and the tendency of an age-hardening alloy to “lose” solute atoms to coarse (some 100 nm to µm sized), undesired quench-induced precipitates is called quench sensitivity. As will be demonstrated below, the quench sensitivity can be characterised by two major attributes: firstly by the minimum cooling rate, which is required to obtain a fully supersaturated solid solution (which after ageing can produce the highest strength), i.e., the so-called upper critical cooling rate (UCCR), and secondly by the slope of property loss as a function of the reducing cooling rate.
</p>
