<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order to obtain a comprehensive understanding of the quench sensitivity of age-hardening alloys, the kinetics and nature of quench-induced precipitation must be analysed. Since there were limited options for in situ analysis prior to the major work reviewed here, most of the earlier experimental work was based on ex situ experiments. In 2010 Shuey and Tiryakioglu published a reviewing chapter on “quenching of aluminium alloys” including experimental results on a broad range of alloys as well as theoretical options for their evaluation [
 <xref rid="B44-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Different quenching paths have therefore been frequently used for samples, for instance by using different quenching media [
 <xref rid="B45-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] or by applying Jominy end-quench tests [
 <xref rid="B50-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Subsequent post-quench analysis of certain properties has led to the assessment of the quench sensitivity. Besides continuous cooling, quenching to various isothermal soaking temperatures has also been frequently applied, again in combination with a subsequent property analysis, which allows isothermal time-temperature property diagrams to be derived, for instance [
 <xref rid="B10-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In order to allow evaluation of continuous cooling basing on isothermal experiments, the quench factor analysis method was developed [
 <xref rid="B20-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and refined [
 <xref rid="B47-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].
</p>
