<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to the martensitic hardening of steels, the relevant quench-induced precipitation only amounts to a small percentage of the total atoms. However, this fraction is only transformed in equilibrium conditions. Under technologically relevant cooling conditions, quench-induced precipitation is already suppressed to a wide extent, and this is the reason why very small amounts of precipitation need to be detected under certain relevant conditions. This means that a very sensitive measurement setup is required for the in situ detection of this unwanted precipitation, which covers the entire relevant dynamic range. There are few physical effects that allow for the in situ detection of changes within the solid-solid phase transformation status. Solid-solid phase transformations can rarely be detected directly, although this might be possible to a certain extent using in situ TEM, requiring very high effort. Hence, the in-situ detection and analysis of quench-induced precipitation typically requires the in situ measurement of changes in certain material properties. For this purpose, properties that change with the phase transition of interest are suitable. This may be the electrical conductivity or resistivity [
 <xref rid="B59-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], the associated changes in volume (measured by dilatometry) [
 <xref rid="B64-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], or the crystallographic features (for instance measured by in situ X-ray scattering experiments [
 <xref rid="B66-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]). Since the relevant solid-solid phase transformations all show a heat effect (e.g., precipitation = exothermic; dissolution = endothermic), one valuable measurement technique for analysing a solid-solid phase transformation in situ is calorimetry, and particularly differential scanning calorimetry (DSC). The reason for the importance of DSC is that it allows us to measure the enthalpy changes associated with precipitation. Moreover, this precipitation enthalpy is often directly proportional to the atomic fraction of the precipitates formed. However, previous DSC analysis of in situ solid-solid phase transformations is mostly restricted to works that concern heating, and which often carry out only a qualitative evaluation. Additionally, these earlier works commonly lack a sufficient dynamic range, and primarily consider heating rates of about 0.1 to 1 K/s (five to a few tens of K/min) (e.g., [
 <xref rid="B72-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]). Until the early 2000s, no DSC analyses involving cooling experiments on quench-induced precipitation in Al alloys were reported; the first works on this topic were published by Kessler et al. [
 <xref rid="B78-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] between 2002 and 2007, and Deschamps et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] in 2009. However, due to the use of only a single DSC device in all cases, these works are still restricted to a relatively limited range of cooling rates. There are a few more recent works that have published cooling DSC curves for AlZnMgCu alloys, using only one cooling rate [
 <xref rid="B34-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>].
</p>
