<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">The transcriptome study here showed that the DNA repair system, in particular, homologous recombination is markedly impaired in AS6-treated MCF7 cells. Moreover, the increased expression of HIF1α and heat shock proteins indicates that cells provoke stress responses under the influence of AS6 at given concentrations (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>H–J). We propose that the weakened homologous recombination is destructive to the cell cycle progression because of genomic instability
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup>. Improper DNA repair is likely to activate the cell cycle checkpoints, halts the cell cycle and to induce apoptosis in the AS6-treated MCF7 cells. In previous studies, AS6-mediated apoptosis was reported in other cell lines, including SW620 and MCF7 cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>
 </sup>. Those studies, which used targeted approaches, proposed an AS6-driven apoptosis through NFκB inhibition and MAPK activation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>
 </sup>. The present study, which used an unbiased screening, suggests that the induction of apoptosis attributes to genomic instability, resulting from the severe reduction in key DNA repair enzymes, including BRCA1, ATM, p52, ATR, and RAD51 in AS6-treated MCF7 cells (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C,D, 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A–C; Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Mutations and deregulation of these enzymes have been reported in cancers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, the mechanism by which AS6 regulates the expression of these enzymes would be an important question to answer for future work.
</p>
