<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">Inflammation is one of the initial responses of the immune system to stimulus. Studies have found that immune dysfunction may be associated with the occurrence of VTE [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Recently, scholars can use immunology to explain some “unprovoked” VTE cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. In order to further clarify the relationship between VTE and the immune system, we selected three immune differential genes S100A12, NR1D2 and CD3G from DEGs, which were significantly overexpressed in VTE. Calcium binding protein S100A12 is an immune molecule present on the mucosal surface, which is mainly secreted by neutrophils [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In addition, an increase in the number of neutrophils can increase the risk of VTE events [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. A cross-sectional study of 550 hemodialysis patients showed that S100A12 protein levels were closely related to the prevalence of cardiovascular disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Therefore, S100A12 can be considered as a biomarker for inflammatory diseases such as VTE. Studies have found that genetic defects of CD3G can lead to impaired expression of CD3 and TCR on the cell surface, so CD3G mutations are related to immune function defects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. CD3G gene polymorphism may affect the occurrence of liver cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. At present, most of the research on CD3G focuses on tumors, and there are few reports on vascular diseases and thrombosis. NR1D2, a nuclear hormone receptor gene, is associated with circadian rhythm, and circadian dysregulation widely affects Ras signaling pathways, T cell receptor signaling pathways, and then triggers various diseases such as tumors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. NR1D2 is also an important regulator of vascular inflammation and is related to the occurrence of cardiovascular events [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. As a common complication of tumor, VTE may be closely related to immune genes CD3G and NR1D2.
</p>
