<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Moreover, the process of cellular response to stress and DNA damage stimulus, as well as oxidative phosphorylation and transcriptional regulation by TP53, were all enriched after DEHP exposure. All these changes seemed to be associated with cellular stress, because TP53 (also termed tumor protein p53) is a DNA sequence-specific transcriptional regulator responsive to various forms of cellular stress and is involved in cell cycle arrest and apoptosis 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>. Moreover, oxidative phosphorylation is the main source of reactive oxygen species (ROS) in mitochondria 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>. Oxidative phosphorylation and mitochondrial activity were also observed in pseudotime analysis, which were largely affected by DEHP. The 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> study demonstrated that the oxidative stress-related gene 
 <italic>Xdh</italic> (xanthine dehydrogenase) may serve as the downstream target of DEHP, whose reduction (through 
 <italic>Xdh</italic> RNAi or melatonin supplement) can inhibit the increasing levels of ROS and mitigate the damage to PF assembly caused by DEHP 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>. Thus, DEHP, as one EDC member, might impair PF assembly through oxidative stress. In terms of molecular mechanisms, previous research suggests that ERs, particularly ER-beta, participate in the DEHP-mediated effect on ovarian tissue 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>. In addition, the alteration of DNA methylation and transgenerational actions by EDCs in germ cells has been well documented 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>-
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>. In fact, H3K4 mono-methylation was likely affected by DEHP in the present study (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>E). A recent study of
 <italic> Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> reports that DEHP exposure alters the expression of the reproduction-related gene 
 <italic>spr-5</italic>, which encodes H3K4me2 demethylase 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>; however, a similar effect of DEHP on H3K4 mono-methylation in the mouse still needs to be studied.
</p>
