<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effect of DEHP on PG cells and its interaction with germ cells during PF formation was also explored. It is known that DEHP impairs the interaction of germ cells and PG cells via decreasing NOTCH2 signaling and impeding the proliferation of PG cells during PF assembly 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, which seemed to be evidenced, at least partially, by the enriched process of the regulation of cyclin-dependent protein kinase activity in the current study, as well as a positive regulation of the cell cycle in BPG. In addition, the death of both EPG and BPG cells was potentially affected by DEHP (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>G-H). Previous research shows that DEHP exposure increases apoptosis of granulosa cells in adults, which leads to an increase in the number of atretic follicles 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>. Similarly, during the perinatal period, TUNEL tests previously suggested that DEHP exposure 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> increases apoptosis in oocytes of neonatal ovaries 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, which is consistent with this study (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>B). Meanwhile, the components of the TGF-beta pathway in germ cells and PG cells were disturbed by DEHP (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, right panel for PG cells). For instance, 
 <italic>Gdf9</italic> on germ cells, and BMP receptors (
 <italic>Bmpr1a</italic> and
 <italic> Bmpr2</italic>) on PG cells, as well as targets (
 <italic>Id2</italic> and
 <italic> Id3</italic> on germ cells) and effectors (
 <italic>Smd2, Smd3</italic> and
 <italic> Smad4</italic> both on germ cells and PG cells), were all influenced by DEHP exposure (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>B-C). Furthermore, GDF9 protein level was more lowly expressed, whilst BMPR1A and SMAD3 were up more highly expressed following DEHP exposure. Growing evidence indicates that TGF-beta signaling is important in the regulation of cyst breakdown and PF assembly 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>. Despite some available connections between DEHP and TGF-beta signaling 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, DEHP toxicity mediated by TGF-beta signaling is still poorly understood, and needs to be further explored.
</p>
