<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Secondly, we investigated whether the ORF6 variants could modulate innate immune responses. The important upregulation of certain genes induced by a SARS-CoV-2 infection observed in the present study were in accordance with typical antiviral restriction responses, such as 
 <italic>BST2</italic>, 
 <italic>IDO,</italic> and 
 <italic>IFTM1</italic> [
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44–46</xref>]. Focusing on the two deletion variants, the expression of interferon-stimulated genes (ISG) was not differentially expressed in comparison with the WT virus, suggesting that the resulted truncated proteins from the two ORF6 deletions did not impact this signalling pathway. This is in contrast to previous findings of interferon pathway dysregulation via STAT1/STAT2 nuclear translocation blocking by the p6 protein [
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] Nevertheless, our transcriptomic analyses revealed an enhanced upregulation of 9 immune-related genes in the NF-kB pathway, including those coding for inflammatory cytokines such as chemokines, IL1A and TNFα, specifically induced by the infection of partial ORF6 deletions. These findings suggest that the p6 protein would interact in an antagonistic manner to suppress their antiviral properties. Recent literature confirms this inhibitory function of the SARS-CoV-2 p6 protein [
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48–50</xref>]. Of interest, the D26 variant, which resulted in a longer protein sequence 
 <italic>in silico</italic> than for the D34 variant, presented an even higher upregulation of these NFKB-driven inflammatory genes. It can be hypothesized that D26 yields a complete loss of function of p6, perhaps due to the additional histidine residues in close proximity to the α-helix, while D34 may lead to a p6 with a somewhat conserved activity. A 27-nt in-frame ORF6 deletion in proximity to D34 and D26 (at position 27264–27290) selected during passaging on Vero6 cells had important three-dimensional structural alterations to the protein [
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].
</p>
