<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chemical diversity has been correlated with biological activity, and the structural diversity of natural products is more like that observed in drugs compared to synthetic libraries [
 <xref rid="B1-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It has also been well documented that the marine environment is a source of unique structural motifs or scaffolds absent in species from the terrestrial environment or in synthetic libraries [
 <xref rid="B2-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These novel scaffolds also contain a higher percentage of nitrogen atoms relative to carbon and oxygen compared to scaffolds derived from terrestrial sources [
 <xref rid="B4-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. This makes the marine environment a preferred source for biodiscovery. The northern coast of New South Wales in eastern Australia is a biogeographic transition zone in the south-west Pacific that is represented by marine species from both tropical and temperate regions [
 <xref rid="B5-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Little is known about the sessile marine invertebrate (apart from corals) biodiversity of this region, and consequently there has been very little natural product chemistry reported for species collected from this location [
 <xref rid="B6-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Due to the paucity of chemical data reported for species from this region, we have initiated a project to investigate the chemical diversity in relation to the sessile marine invertebrate biodiversity of the region. To date, we have collected over 500 sponges, ascidian, and bryozoan specimens from reefs from this region, and a systematic analysis of the chemistry they contain has been initiated [
 <xref rid="B7-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-marinedrugs-19-00095" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Herein, we report on the isolation, structure determination, and biological activity of two new alkaloids, tedaniophorbasins A (
 <bold>1</bold>) and B (
 <bold>2</bold>), possessing a novel skeleton (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="marinedrugs-19-00095-f001">Figure 1</xref>) that we have isolated from 
 <italic>Tedaniophorbas ceratosis</italic> collected from oceanic waters adjacent to Cook Island in far northern New South Wales, Australia. This is the first report on the chemistry of sponges from the genus 
 <italic>Tedaniophorbas</italic>.
</p>
