<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The combination of Pt with another metal is a common route to tune the properties of the ORR catalysts, in particular, to improve its activity, stability, robustness toward poisoning, and to reduce the cost of the catalyst by minimizing the amount of Pt used. In terms of activity, Pt alloys with the first row transition metals (Ni, Co, Cr, Fe, Cu) are reported among the most active catalysts for ORR. In particular, the activity of Pt
 <sub>3</sub>Ni catalysts exceeds that of pure Pt several times.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref482">482</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref483">483</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>In situ</italic> XAS has been widely used to understand the origin of such enhaced performance. Mukerjee et al. investigated Pt–Ni, Pt–Co, Pt–Cr, Pt–Mn, and Pt–Fe alloy NPs with enhanced ORR activity in comparison to that of pure Pt via XAS.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref474">474</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref484">484</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref485">485</xref>
 </sup> The intensity of the Pt-L
 <sub>3</sub> WL within the double-layer region (0.54 V vs RHE) was enhanced in the alloy samples with respect to monometallic Pt, suggesting an increase in d-band vacancies. At the same time, under ORR conditions at a potential of 0.84 V, the intensity of the WL did not increase significantly for alloy catalysts, while for the platinum catalyst it was enhanced noticeably, surpassing that of the alloys. Analysis of the EXAFS spectra showed that a significant Pt–O contribution is present in the data of the Pt catalyst at 0.84 V, but not at 0.54 V and not for the alloy catalysts at any of these potentials. This suggests that the interactions between Pt and oxygen species in the alloy catalysts under ORR are suppressed. This, in turn, indicates that these catalysts are less prone to the poisoning by adsorbed OH, which may explain their enhanced catalytic activity. In fact, a nearly linear relationship between the intensity of the WL and the catalyst activity can be obtained, as observed by Antolini et al. in studies of Pt–Co catalysts with different particle sizes and different Co loadings.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref139">139</xref>
 </sup> Similar decreased Pt oxidation under ORR conditions has been observed also for other Pt-based bimetallic systems that were found to be promising for ORR, such as Pt NPs modified with gold clusters,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref242">242</xref>
 </sup> Pt–Ti intermetallic catalysts,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref486">486</xref>
 </sup> platinum–tungsten carbide catalysts,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref487">487</xref>
 </sup> platinum–vanadium alloys,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref476">476</xref>
 </sup> niobium oxide-supported Pt catalysts,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref488">488</xref>
 </sup> ordered PtFe nanocatalysts,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref489">489</xref>
 </sup> and others.
</p>
