<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interestingly, the secondary metal itself in the aforementioned systems, does not seem to play an important role in the redox processes at the electrode surface, as evidenced by the lack of potential-dependent changes in the K-edge XAS spectra for these transition metals under reaction conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref474">474</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref484">484</xref>
 </sup> The limitation of the alloy systems is that the secondary metal is typically less stable under ORR conditions than Pt and can be leached out, resulting in the loss of catalyst performance. Moreover, the fraction of Pt in these catalysts is still significant; thus, they are not much cheaper than pure Pt catalysts. As a promising alternative, NPs with a non-noble metal alloy core covered with a monolayer of Pt have been proposed. A prominent example is Pd NPs decorated with a monolayer of Pt, which exhibit an ORR activity that surpasses that of pure Pt, and even more importantly, also show superior stability.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref265">265</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref492">492</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref493">493</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, Pt monolayers on Au, Ir, Rh, Ru, and Re cores show decreased activity, while preserving a good stability.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref105">105</xref>
 </sup> An attractive aspect of XAS for studies of these ORR catalysts is its ability to provide quantitative information about the Pt layer thickness, and distinguish between NPs with one and two monolayers of Pt by analyzing the EXAFS CNs. For example, for a single Pt monolayer on Pd(111), the expected Pt–Pt and Pt–Pd coordination numbers are 6 and 3, respectively, while for the system with two Pt monolayers the CNs are 9 and 1.5, respectively. Sasaki et al. demonstrated an excellent agreement of these theoretical values with the CNs extracted from experimental EXAFS data for Pt–Pd NPs where the thickness of the Pt shell was varied by Cu-mediated layer-by-layer Pt deposition.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref105">105</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref265">265</xref>
 </sup> It should be noted here that while the current associated with ORR increases upon addition of the second Pt monolayer, the specific activity decreases.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref105">105</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
