<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The properties of the monolayer Pt catalysts can be tuned in a broad range by choosing more complex core structures. Bimetallic alloy cores formed by metals with different lattice constants allow one to tune the strain induced in the Pt monolayer. For example, it was observed that the ORR activity of Pt monolayers on top of a PdAu alloy core depends significantly on the Pd to Au ratio, with optimal ORR performance achieved at a 9:1 Pd:Au ratio.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref339">339</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref341">341</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, Co–Pd core–shell NPs with Pt monolayer on the surface were also found to exhibit excellent catalytic properties, while containing a significantly lower amount of the noble metals.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref495">495</xref>
 </sup> IrNi bimetallic cores were also described to be promising in terms of the synthesis scalability and cost-efficiency.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref496">496</xref>
 </sup> Particles with even more complex core structure have been proposed, such as Pt monolayer-covered ternary PdNiMo core, where enhanced stability of the catalyst was ensured through the Pd–Mo interaction,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref497">497</xref>
 </sup> and Pt-covered NPs with PdNi core, where the core was stabilized by the incorporation of Au. The latter NPs exhibited a higher activity than Pt/Pd and Pt/PdNi catalysts.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref498">498</xref>
 </sup> On the other hand, an enhancement in ORR activity can also be obtained by replacing some of the Pt in the shell with other metals such as Re, Os, and Ir.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref105">105</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref499">499</xref>
 </sup> Clearly, the more complex the structure of the catalyst gets, the more important is to validate the presence of the desired structural motifs in these systems using experimental measurements. In the aforementioned examples, XAS was very instrumental for this purpose, by providing information ranging from a simple estimate of the constituent metal ratios (either from absorption edge-step analysis or from EXAFS-derived coordination numbers), up to the determination of the particle morphology and alloying/segregation motifs.
</p>
