<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The attractiveness of alloy systems like PdAu for ORR applications relies on the fact that it consists of a combination of oxyphilic and oxyphobic metals. For example, Au (or Ag) binds oxygen species too weakly, while metals like Pd (and also Rh, Pd, and Ir) do it too strongly. Thus, by alloying Pd with Au, the surface binding energy can be tuned and the catalytic properties optimized.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref503">503</xref>
 </sup> While PdAu alloys are relatively well-known, other relevant combinations of metals are less explored. Recently, Li et al. proposed the RhAu system as a promising catalyst for ORR applications.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref503">503</xref>
 </sup> Unlike the Pd–Au system, Rh and Au are considered to be immiscible in their bulk phases. Nevertheless, Rh–Au alloying was demonstrated for NPs prepared via microwave assisted synthesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref504">504</xref>
 </sup> or dendrimer encapsulation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref505">505</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>In situ</italic> XAS measurements from the dendrimer-encapsulated NPs revealed the incomplete reduction of the precursor species (XANES), and the surface segregation of Au (EXAFS).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref505">505</xref>
 </sup> For RhAu NPs synthesized via a microwave-assisted method, significant discrepancy was obtained when comparing the NP sizes extracted from EXAFS and those obtained from TEM. This was explained by the coexistence of particles of different sizes and compositions. By combining the information from EXAFS with NP size distributions from TEM, a structure model was constructed consisting of a mixture of ultrasmall Rh NPs and larger RhAu NPs with Au segregated to surface. Further, by employing Monte Carlo simulations of the NP structure and dynamics, it was demonstrated that the 
 <italic>ab initio</italic> EXAFS spectra, calculated following a model consisting of the NPs of these two types can reproduce reliably the experimental EXAFS data collected at both the Au L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge and the Rh K-edges (
 <xref rid="fig35" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig35" ref-type="fig">35</xref>
 </xref>).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref212">212</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
