<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of heterothermy can also differ between sexes. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.00506" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Noiret et al.</ext-link> report that physiological, metabolic and behavioral responses to food shortage are more flexible in females compared to males of the gray mouse lemur (
 <italic>Microcebus murinus</italic>). This reiterates the notion that heterothermic responses are closely adjusted to both environmental and state-dependent variables (Boyles et al., 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Geiser, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Apart from a direct role in starvation avoidance, heterothermy may also impact survival through a reduction in extrinsic (predation) and intrinsic (somatic wear) mortality risk (Nowack et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.00706" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Constant et al.</ext-link> explore some aspects of the evolution of hibernation behavior by investigating how longevity is affected by phylogenetic signals and activity-time budgets across a range of mammalian hibernators. The authors show that longevity increases with the duration of the hibernation season, particularly in small (&lt;1.5 kg) hibernators. On the other hand, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.00985" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Landes et al.</ext-link> propose that a flexible use of heterothermy may carry ecological and physiological costs, such as changes to the neuroendocrine system and increased free-radical production. While these costs may be marginal at each transition event, they could accumulate over time and therefore emerge with age. Nevertheless, it is assumed that the flexible use of torpor will be beneficial when species need to adapt to climate change.
</p>
