<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Global change and the associated increase in extreme weather events pose an increasing threat to living organisms. This is clearly shown by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.00637" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Weyer et al.</ext-link> in their study of aardvarks (
 <italic>Orycteropus afer</italic>). Aardvarks are nocturnal and tightly control their circadian body temperature rhythm under normal conditions. A summer drought was associated with reduced foraging activity, increased mortality and relaxed body temperature regulation of aardvarks. Individuals that died progressively switched to almost complete diurnal activity. This does not bode well for aardvarks facing climate change, nor for the many animals that depend on aardvark burrows for refuge. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.00153" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Roussel and Voituron</ext-link> express similar concerns for the common toad (
 <italic>Bufo bufo</italic>). Their study found that mitochondria in this species produce ATP less efficiently and at a higher oxidative cost during an acute heat challenge. This might require extra resources to maintain ATP production and oxidative balance, leaving less energy for other tasks during heat stress. In contrast, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2019.01405" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Cooper et al.</ext-link> show that free-ranging zebra finches (
 <italic>Taeniopygia guttata</italic>) can accommodate heatwaves without major impacts on energy or water turnover, provided that drinking water is available. The birds avoid or limit activity during the hottest part of the day and showed pre-emptive feeding and drinking in preparation for inactive periods. It seems that cold weather could be more challenging than heat waves for this desert bird. Stochastic weather events alter not only food and water access, but also availability of other components linked to energy metabolism, such as dissolved oxygen in aquatic systems. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.01106" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Marshall and McQuaid</ext-link> show that snails (
 <italic>Turritella terebra</italic>) balance restricted oxygen availability in hypoxic seawater by downregulating metabolism and energy allocation to various physiological functions. Yet, compensation was incomplete since the snails incurred an oxygen debt in severe hypoxia.
</p>
