<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Climate change and extreme weather events affect not only mature life forms, but can have pronounced effects during development when embryonic/fetal endotherms are actually poikilothermic and ectotherms typically cannot thermoregulate behaviorally. This can shape energy-based trade-offs, such as between thermoregulation and growth and (later) between survival and reproduction (Nord and Nilsson, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Andreasson et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Hence, this Research Topic also explores effects of environmental fluctuations during development. Since genetic adaptation is often slow, there is growing interest in how behavioral and physiological flexibility helps mitigate the challenges of climate change since flexible phenotypes allow organisms to optimize energy allocation when conditions change. In line with this, Nord and Giroud have reviewed recent findings on the effects of developmental temperature in birds and mammals and discuss when the early thermal environment is predisposing or constraining for lifelong thermoregulatory performance in fluctuating environments, and if such effects are heritable. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.00049">Stawski and Geiser</ext-link> manipulated developmental temperature in yellow-footed antechinus (<italic>Antechinus flavipes</italic>) and measured the effects on adult metabolic rates. The study suggests considerable phenotypic plasticity in both sexes, which is likely vital for a short-lived species that only breeds once in a lifetime. While phenotypic plasticity in response to fluctuating environmental conditions during development is often advantageous, so-called counter-gradient variation (Levins, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">1968</xref>) can oppose environmental influences to reduce the extent of phenotypic adaptation. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2020.00547">Pettersen</ext-link> reviews such effects on genetic and phenotypic levels in reptiles, concluding that counter-gradient variation in developmental time may be an important adaptive response to decrease developmental costs for animals in cool climates. These contributions indicate the advantages of phenotypic plasticity in response to environmental conditions and support the notion that the pressure of climate change will likely select for increased phenotypic plasticity rather than for directional adjustment of phenotypes (Canale and Henry, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p>