<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are two forms of MfGL, namely MfGL-I and MfGL-II, in which the latter being the primarily type. In the PG18 strain, MfGL-II enhances the fusion with Molt-3 lymphocytes in a dose-dependent manner. However, the MfGL-I-holding strains, M39 and M52, without MfGL-II, manifest the same fusion efficacy as Molt-3 cells and PG18 [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0260" ref-type="bibr">260</xref>], suggesting that MfGL-I and MfGL-II may serve as fusogens. Nonetheless, the role of MfGL-II in cell membrane fusion remains controversial. For example, Rottem reported that MfGL-II is a bilayer stabilizing lipid and cannot undergo phase transition from a lamellar to an inverted configuration [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0261" ref-type="bibr">261</xref>]. Similarly, using biophysical analysis, Gil et al. discovered that MfGL-II lacks fusogenic properties [
 <xref rid="cit0261" ref-type="bibr">261</xref>]. Therefore, the exact role of MfGL-II needs to be studied further. In addition to the fusion activity, MfGL-II also functions in moonlighting biological activities, including (I) triggering the inflammatory response of human monocytes and rat astrocytes by the activation of protein kinase C, secretion of nitric oxide (NO), prostagalandine E
 <sub>2</sub>, and TNF-ɑ, although much weaker than LPS; (II) yielding a strong immune response; and (III) increasing glucose utilization and lactate formation [
 <xref rid="cit0262" ref-type="bibr">262</xref>]. Nevertheless, the deacylation of MfGL-II or monoclonal anti-phosphocholine antibodies significantly reduces cytokine-stimulating activity, and the MfGL-II antiserum inhibits the attachment of 
 <italic>M. fermentans</italic> to host cells, demonstrating that MfGL-II, especially the phosphocholine residue, plays a pivotal role in 
 <italic>M. fermentans</italic>-host interaction [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0257" ref-type="bibr">257</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0259" ref-type="bibr">259–261</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0263" ref-type="bibr">263</xref>].
</p>
