<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The unique glycolytic and antioxidant system in aerophiles has been a primary focal point in the study of Mtz resistance, including for 
 <italic>Giardia</italic>. Our results indicate that NR-1 (22 677) was downregulated in all MtzR lines, which concurs with previous results [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], including transcriptomics results for the same lines [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Previously, recombinant NR-1 was shown to reduce (i.e., activate) Mtz using NADH as a donor [
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Ansell et al. [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] subsequently hypothesized that NR-1 could use electrons from ferrodoxin to reduce Mtz, which could functionally link NR-1 to pyruvate catabolism and, by extension, to the PFOR-ferredoxin electron transport chain (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>). Taken together, downregulation of NR-1 is the strongest candidate for a universal passive resistance mechanism. Downregulation of PFOR expression was observed only in WB-MtzR in this study, which agrees with transcriptomic data for WB-MtzR and other resistant clones in this genotype [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], although not all clones [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. It is also possible that reduced PFOR enzyme activity, previously observed in 106 and WB Mtz resistant lines [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], might lower the rate of Mtz activation to be functionally analogous as decreased PFOR protein expression. As such, combined investigations of enzyme activity and protein expression may be required to test the interaction of different regulatory mechanisms in Mtz resistance.
</p>
