<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par60">Several proteins were expressed differentially that play a role in inner ear development and morphogenesis. These proteins include cadherin-1 (Cdh1), collagen alpha-1 (XI) chain (Col11a1), inactive tyrosine-protein kinase 7 (Ptk7), SPARC, and unconventional myosin-VI (Myo6). SPARC, which is a calcium binding glycoprotein, was exclusively expressed on P3. Interestingly, through bioinformatics and coIP, we found that SPARC interacts with the BK channel. SPARC’s attributes include acting as a trigger for synapse elimination [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], potentially by decreasing the number of docked vesicles in presynaptic active zones [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] through a protein complex that includes integrin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Moreover, integrins can regulate ion channels [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], so that an Integrin/BK/SPARC complex might contribute to the formation of synapses at active zones, since BK is found at both synaptic and extrasynaptic sites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. In comparison, Ptk7 was upregulated on P3 relative to P14 and exclusively present on P3 relative to P30. Ptk7 plays a role in cell-cell adhesion, cell migration, cell polarity, proliferation, actin cytoskeleton reorganization, apoptosis, and epithelial tissue organization [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Its expression levels on P3, relative to P14 and P30, strongly suggest involvement in development prior to the onset of hearing. In contrast, Cdh1 was present exclusively on P30 relative to P14, and plays a role in cell-cell adhesions, mobility and proliferation of epithelial cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Additional proteins exclusively expressed on P3 relative to P14 include reticulocalbin-1, plexin-B2, and low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 2, which are involved in the development of sensory organs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] and nervous system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>] and thus may contribute to the development of the cochlear sensory epithelium.
</p>
