<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In cancer biology, “single-gene” approaches have been applied to prostate [
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>], gastric [
 <xref rid="B137-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>], liver [
 <xref rid="B125-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>], bladder [
 <xref rid="B139-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>], thyroid [
 <xref rid="B141-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>] and lung [
 <xref rid="B142-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>] tumours and glioblastoma [
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], comparing the connectivity of genes between normal and cancerous tissue. This led to the identification of several gene lists not shared between different cancer types, as also confirmed by a systematic study performed on 12 cancer types [
 <xref rid="B128-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Despite the gene-centred approach, in all studies, the genes with the strongest evidence for differential connectivity were analysed as a whole and often corresponded to previously known and druggable targets [
 <xref rid="B125-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. Despite the lack of a systematic study to compare the functional enrichment of DC genes across cancer types, recurrent Gene Ontology categories comprise cell cycle, apoptosis, and immune system-related genes [
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B141-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>,
 <xref rid="B142-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>,
 <xref rid="B143-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Depending on the researcher’s interest, the search for DC genes can be restricted to selected gene lists [
 <xref rid="B144-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>,
 <xref rid="B145-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. For example, focussing on metabolic genes, a signature of genes suggestive of mitochondrial dysfunction was found to be differentially connected in seven cancer types [
 <xref rid="B145-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. Again, this approach can inform about differences in connectivity, allowing the grouping of samples based on any feature of interest. The comparison of patients responsive and non-responsive to a specific treatment is particularly promising to understand the rearrangement of gene networks leading to drug resistance. Through this means, well-known genes have been confirmed to confer platinum resistance (e.g., CCNE2, AKT1 and MYC), and the additional role of FGFR1 and TSC2 has been proposed [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-21-09461" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
