<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>The marine obligate hydrocarbonoclastic bacterium 
  <italic>Thalassolituus oleivorans</italic> MIL-1 metabolizes a broad range of aliphatic hydrocarbons almost exclusively as carbon and energy sources. We used LC-MS/MS shotgun proteomics to identify proteins involved in aerobic alkane degradation during growth on medium- (
  <italic>n</italic>-C
  <sub>14</sub>) or long-chain (
  <italic>n</italic>-C
  <sub>28</sub>) alkanes. During growth on 
  <italic>n</italic>-C
  <sub>14</sub>, 
  <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> expresses an alkane monooxygenase system involved in terminal oxidation including two alkane 1-monooxygenases, a ferredoxin, a ferredoxin reductase and an aldehyde dehydrogenase. In contrast, during growth on long-chain alkanes (
  <italic>n</italic>-C
  <sub>28</sub>), 
  <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> may switch to a subterminal alkane oxidation pathway evidenced by significant upregulation of Baeyer-Villiger monooxygenase and an esterase, proteins catalyzing ketone and ester metabolism, respectively. The metabolite (primary alcohol) generated from terminal oxidation of an alkane was detected during growth on 
  <italic>n-</italic>C
  <sub>14</sub> but not on 
  <italic>n-</italic>C
  <sub>28</sub> also suggesting alternative metabolic pathways. Expression of both active and passive transport systems involved in uptake of long-chain alkanes was higher when compared to the non-hydrocarbon control, including a TonB-dependent receptor, a FadL homolog and a specialized porin. Also, an inner membrane transport protein involved in the export of an outer membrane protein was expressed. This study has demonstrated the substrate range of 
  <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> is larger than previously reported with growth from 
  <italic>n</italic>-C
  <sub>10</sub> up to 
  <italic>n</italic>-C
  <sub>32</sub>. It has also greatly enhanced our understanding of the fundamental physiology of 
  <italic>T. oleivorans</italic>, a key bacterium that plays a significant role in natural attenuation of marine oil pollution, by identifying key enzymes expressed during the catabolism of 
  <italic>n</italic>-alkanes.
 </p>
</abstract>
