<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phospholipid-transporting ATPases (gPLTATPase) and gPSS have been suggested to form crucial links in the import and metabolism of phospholipids [
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and were upregulated in WB-MtzR along with multiple genes involved in fatty acid intake, synthesis, modification, and metabolism. This suggests lipid metabolism may be increased in some MtzR isolates, possibly to ensure membrane integrity for signaling pathways. In addition, phosphatidylinositol pathways, which are associated with regulating cell growth in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], were upregulated in WB-MtzR, which has impaired growth rates compared to its MtzS parent [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In WB-MtzR, the highest upregulated kinase was a putative choline/ethanolamine kinase responsible for initiating synthesis of phosphatidylcholine and phosphatidylethanolamine via phosphorylation. In 
 <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>, inhibition of choline/ethanolamine kinases leads to a significant decrease of phospholipids and arrest of parasite growth [
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] and suggests links between lipid composition, oxidative damage, and growth in WB-MtzR. In contrast, 106-MtzR downregulated phospholipid import and metabolism genes, as well as phosphatidylinositol pathways. Additionally, membrane-associated dipeptidyl peptidases, which are known to regulate crucial proteolytic events during encystation [
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], were differentially expressed across all lines, suggesting the importance of membrane signal-transduction events in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> MtzR phenotypes. Further, differentially expressed alpha-giardin proteins, which are known to interact with phospholipids in the membrane, were exclusively downregulated in MtzR lines. Membrane lipid composition, such as un/saturation of phospholipid fatty acyl components, is known to change the sensitivity of the membrane to oxidative stress and damage [
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], and increased fatty acid unsaturation is dynamically regulated during encystation in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Although not detected in the proteomic dataset, at the transcript level [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], fatty acid elongase 1 (gFAELO) (92 729) was upregulated in WB-MtzR and 713-MtzR, along with 3 gLCFACL long chain fatty acid CoA ligases, providing further evidence of fatty acid composition changes in the membranes of MtzR isolates.
</p>
