<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>VSP variants in MtzR lines displayed similar trends in the proportion and magnitude of differentially expressed VSPs, although specific VSP variants and the direction of differential expression diverged, and MtzR lines were substantially different from MtzS parents and each other (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>, panels B and C). This divergence may be a product of spontaneous VSP-variant switching [
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] and differences in both time in culture and generation time for the 6 lines. However, large changes in VSP expression and turnover have been observed in other oxidative stress experiments [
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], and it remains unclear if a specific variant may have functional contributions to limit oxidative damage. Both VSP and HCMP gene families are rich in cysteine, which is the major low-molecular-weight thiol in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], and their multiple CXC/CXXC motifs potentially contribute to thiol and redox chemistries [
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Proteomic methods are available that allow selective modification to identify and discriminate reversible and irreversible oxidation states in cysteine [
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], which would provide evidence of the states of the multiple cysteines in VSPs, including those known to be lipid modified [
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. While further evidence is required to determine whether specific 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> VSPs contribute to alleviating oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], including Mtz-induced oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], collective VSP protein expression as a measure of antigenic switching rates may sensitively indicate significant restructuring of populations following xenobiotic or physiological stress. Large and statistically significant changes in VSP expression have been previously detected during proteomic analyses of encystation [
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> host–parasite models [
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] in shorter timeframes than reported for spontaneous antigenic switching [
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. This indicated that VSPs may be one of the most dynamic and sensitive protein families within 
 <italic>Giardia</italic>.
</p>
