<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 thus certainly contributes to regulating resting membrane potential in microglia (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>), we believe, its more important role, and the reason for why Kv1.3 expression increases in activated microglia, is the channel’s ability to offset extreme and prolonged membrane depolarization that potentially can negatively impact microglial health and physiology as revealed by current injection experiments. While current injections of 25 pA are not able to depolarize K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 expressing microglia beyond −30 mV in the absence of blockers, microglia pretreated with K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 blockers depolarize to potentials of +50 mV in response to the same 25 pA current injections [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], suggesting that K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 is able to “clamp” membrane potential close to the channel’s activation threshold potential to prevent excessive membrane depolarizations (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>). The situation in microglial physiology where this capacity is important is when microglia are exposed to extracellular ATP, a danger signal that can reach concentrations in the high micromolar range due to release of cytosolic ATP from damaged neurons or ATP-containing synaptic vesicles [
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], which activate P2X receptor channels leading to intense depolarizations [
 <xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In our own hands, current clamp experiments performed on undifferentiated and LPS stimulated microglia showed that acute exposure to 100 μM ATP, which out of the P2X receptors expressed in microglia primarily activates P2X4, lead to more pronounced depolarizations in undifferentiated microglia, despite their more hyperpolarized resting membrane potential than in K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3
 <sup>high</sup> LPS-stimulated microglia, which did not depolarize above −40 mV. K
 <sub>V</sub>1.3 blockers impaired this ability to resist ATP-induced depolarizations and microglia depolarized in their presence [
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. 
</p>
