<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RSV is a major human pathogen that represents the most common cause of pediatric hospitalization in young children. Because RSV replicates to high levels in airway epithelial cells, where the timing and character of the IIR epithelial cells plays an important role in the pathogenesis of disease and resolution, understanding the IIR to RSV in models relevant to disease is important. Previous work has shown that small-airway epithelial cells rapidly secrete cytokines [
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], IFNs [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], exosomes [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and damage-associated patterns [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-13-00218" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] in response to RSV replication. In this study, we applied single-molecule real-time (SMRT) RNA sequencing to explore regulated AS in a human small-airway epithelial cell (hSAEC) model in response to RSV replication. Using an established informatics pipeline, we identified substantial numbers of mRNA-processing events in our curated transcriptome of 113,082 unique transcripts encoded by 13,038 genes. These events include alternative polyadenylation utilization, cryptic exonic inclusion, alternative splice site utilization, exon occlusion/skipping, and intronic inclusion. To understand the role of mRNA processing in the IIR, we focused on the detailed AS events of differentially expressed mRNAs exhibiting differential inclusion utilization (DIU), a designation indicating the abundance of major splice forms are changed by RSV infection. Viewed through this lens, we identified 355 mRNA transcripts that were induced by 1.5 log2 fold change with a false discovery rate (FDR) of 0.05 by RSV replication and exhibited DIU. RSV-regulated DIU transcripts included AS events with inclusion of exons that encode different miRNA-binding sites and alternative post-translational modifications. Functional genome ontology (GO) enrichment and network analysis shows the DIU genes are highly represented in cell cycle regulation and major transcriptional regulators of the IIR.
</p>
