<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here, we analyze scRNA-seq data from a myxoid liposarcoma (MLS) cell line. The MLS data, including ERCC spike-ins and 94 single MLS cells with 59838 genes, are available in the ArrayExpress database at EMBL-EBI with accession number E-MTAB-6142 [
 <xref rid="B93-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. The MLS notebook is available at 
 <uri xlink:href="https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ocbe-uio/DIscBIO/blob/dev/notebook/DIscBIO-MLS-Binder.ipynb" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/ocbe-uio/DIscBIO/blob/dev/notebook/DIscBIO-MLS-Binder.ipynb</uri>. Myxoid liposarcoma is a rare type of tumor driven by specific fusion oncogenes, normally FUS-DDIT3 [
 <xref rid="B94-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>], with few other genetic changes [
 <xref rid="B96-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. The 94 single cells were collected based on their cell cycle phase (G1, S or G2/M), and assessed in the collection step by analyzing their DNA content using Fluorescence Activated Cell Sorter [
 <xref rid="B93-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. The original study aimed at investigating the gene expression dynamics during the course of the cell cycle in MLS cells. Moreover, it aimed at resolving the dynamics within phases using pseudo-time ordering as well as gene clustering of the DEGs between phases [
 <xref rid="B93-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Here, we take another direction aiming at defining the molecular signature of sub-populations of MLS cells in association with their cell cycle phases. After downloading, unzipping the “E-MTAB-6142.processed.1.zip” and saving it in the working directory, the read counts matrix can be loaded to DIscBIO using the “read.table” or “read.csv” functions. During the preprocessing, genes were selected by accounting for technical noise based on the variation and expression of the ERCC spike-ins, which were added to each sample before library preparation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01399-f006">Figure 6</xref>a). A total of 5684 genes (black dots) have a variation above the noise level (red curve). The resulted genes from the technical noise filtering were used for the downstream analysis. After filtering the dataset, three stable MLS clusters (Jaccard similarity &gt; 0.6) were obtained based on model-based clustering and visualized in a PCA plot (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01399-f006">Figure 6</xref>b). Clusters can be visualized by 
 <italic>t</italic>SNE maps as well. However, considering the distinctive separation, PCA plots showed intact projection of the contents of the clusters generated by model-based clustering. One possible explanation could be that the linear probabilistic processing of the PCA matches with the probability model-based clustering, which generates a model for every cluster and computes the best fit of the data to the generated model [
 <xref rid="B98-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. The MLS clusters match with the cell cycle phases in the initial study [
 <xref rid="B93-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Cluster 1 is characterized by low consistency (Silhouette width = −0.1), whereas Clusters 2 and 3 have reasonable consistency (Silhouette width &gt; 0). Pseudo-temporal ordering showed a gradual transition between the cells’ transcription profiles across the clusters (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01399-f006">Figure 6</xref>c). Both the clustering and pseudo-time overlap with the cell cycle phases (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01399-f006">Figure 6</xref>d). Cells in Cluster 2 are mainly in the G2 phase, whereas the majority of the cells in Cluster 3 are in the S phase. Cluster 1 shows heterogeneous cells with different cell cycle phases. No outlier cells were detected in any of the clusters (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01399-f006">Figure 6</xref>e). To investigate the similarities between the single cells, Euclidean distances of Pearson transcriptome correlation matrix were computed. Based on these similarities, a heatmap portrayal of the cell-to-cell distances was plotted using Euclidean as the distance measure and single linkage as the clustering method.
</p>
