<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another parameter, extracted from EXAFS data analysis, that can be used to track the changes in the sample oxidation state is the interatomic distance. A contracted bond length is commonly associated with an increased oxidation state.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref245">245</xref>
 </sup> This argument was used to confirm the changes in the Ni oxidation state in Ni–Fe catalysts during the electrochemical water splitting.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref245">245</xref>
 </sup> Gorlin et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref251">251</xref>
 </sup> also used Ni–O and Fe–O interatomic distances to determine Fe and Ni oxidation states in similar materials. Different Cu–O distances can also be used to distinguish between Cu
 <sub>2</sub>O and CuO species.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref252">252</xref>
 </sup> In many cases, DFT calculations can be very helpful in establishing the relations between oxidation state and interatomic distances.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref245">245</xref>
 </sup> The use of EXAFS for the determination of the oxidation state can be especially helpful in the case of XAS data collected at high energies, where the XANES spectral features are broad and their interpretation is ambiguous. For example, XANES data analysis at the Sn K-edge may give ambiguous results due to the similarity of the spectra for Sn
 <sup>0</sup> and Sn
 <sup>2+</sup> species, and therefore, the detection of Sn
 <sup>2+</sup> species can be problematic. The Sn–O distance for SnO, however, is significantly longer than that in SnO
 <sub>2</sub> (2.22 vs 2.05 Å), thus allowing one to distinguish between 2+ and 4+ species based on EXAFS data analysis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref253">253</xref>
 </sup> It is, of course, also always advantageous to contrast XAS findings with results from other techniques, as for example Raman spectroscopy, as illustrated in ref (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref254">254</xref>).
</p>
