<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We found that humans with pulmonary Aspergillosis manifested elevated levels of sTREM1 in BALs. Accordingly, mice infected with 
 <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> showed increased lung sTREM1 levels (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3a</xref>). In vivo, the role of TREM1 has been characterized in experimental murine models of microbial sepsis, infection with influenza virus, 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> major and other bacterial infections, in which suppression of TREM1 signaling conferred significant protection [
 <xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43–45</xref>]. In these models, protection was associated with reduced severe inflammation and diminished expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines [
 <xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In the case of 
 <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> infections, although reduced cytokine-driven inflammation can contribute to less damage in the lungs, impaired innate immune response and a lower capacity to mount early cytokine responses represent a primary risk factor for susceptibility, particularly in an immunosuppressed host [
 <xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In this sense, our study showed that, compared to WT mice, immunosuppressed 
 <italic>Trem</italic>1
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice were more susceptible to aspergillosis. We found that both granulocytes and monocytes were recruited after infection in the murine lungs although cell recruitment was affected in the TREM1–deficiency setting. Granulocytes and monocytes were diminished in 
 <italic>Trem</italic>1
 <sup>−/-</sup> infected mice compared to infected WT mice at 2 dpi. Fungal burden was checked in both groups (data not shown) to discard that the observed differences were not a consequence of differential fungal growth in the lungs. Furthermore, we showed that the difference in the amount of granulocytes and monocytes was still maintained after 5 dpi and they were below the initial values in the 
 <italic>Trem</italic>1
 <sup>−/-</sup> background. Since recruitment and activation of polymorphonuclear neutrophils and mononuclear cells into the lungs is a crucial event in the early phases of IPA [
 <xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], we could attribute an increased susceptibility of 
 <italic>Trem</italic>1
 <sup>−/-</sup> mice to an impaired pulmonary inflammation in response to 
 <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> that impacted survival in the immunosuppressed host.
</p>
