<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With the excessive consumption of nonrenewable resources, the energy crisis spreads around the world. Therefore, it is urgent to explore new ways for storing energy [
 <xref rid="B1-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. As one of effective energy-storage devices, lithium ion batteries (LIBs) have attracted broad attention due to its high energy density, long cycling life, and light weight [
 <xref rid="B3-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The property of an anode material has a significant effect on the final performances of a total LIB. At present, anode materials mainly include conversion reaction type, alloy-type, and carbonaceous materials [
 <xref rid="B6-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, the applications of both conversion-reaction-type and alloy-type anodes are restricted by their low conductivity and serious volume expansion during cycling [
 <xref rid="B10-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Compared with these kinds of anodes, carbon-related materials (such as graphite, graphene, activated carbon, carbon nanotubes, carbon fibers, etc.) present good characteristics including high safety, high conductivity, low cost, excellent electrochemical stability, and high mechanical firmness [
 <xref rid="B14-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Therefore, carbon materials have become mainstream materials for commercial LIB anodes for many years. In particular, porous carbon materials with plenty of network structure can provide short diffusion pathways for ion and electron transport and large active regions for electrochemical reactions [
 <xref rid="B20-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In this situation, the preparation methods of porous carbon materials were studied by scientists from all over the world with great enthusiasm. Among various ways, it is a green and environmentally friendly route to fabricate porous carbon from biomass wastes [
 <xref rid="B24-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In recent years, the synthesis methods towards porous carbon derived from different biomass materials have been developed successfully. Many biomasses such as walnut shell, duckweed, coir pith, and bean-dreg [
 <xref rid="B26-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-nanomaterials-10-00346" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] are developed into porous carbon materials. These materials show good electrochemical performance as anodes for LIBs. However, it is difficult to collect some biomass materials in a relatively concentrated region, which limits the mass production of biomass carbon materials.
</p>
