<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A topical 4-MU formulation, based on standard pharmacology of topical applications was developed using propylene glycol (PG), ethanol (EtOH) and water with 4-MU as our active element. Based on the literature review, we first defined the minimal and maximal concentrations of each of the components in the topical formulation. In order to optimize the percentage of each of these components in the formulation to obtain maximal HA reduction in skin, an initial design of experiments (DOE) was performed formulated with the above 3 parameters with minimum and maximum concentrations (boundary conditions) for each parameter as follows: PG (0 and 60%), EtOH (0 and 60%), and 4-MU (0 mM and 2 mM) (
 <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), and remaining volume made up with water. Central Composite Design predicted 15 different formulations with varying does of each of the individual components (
 <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), each of which were applied to the backs of the initial test cohort of mice to study the effect of each combination on skin HA levels at the completion of the time course of topical application. RSM was used for modeling the process and studying the interaction between parameters for the reduction of HA. The regression equation was then used as objective function for process optimization in GA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>). The predicted optimal formulation was then validated in a second cohort of mice. DOE and RSM are commonly used to develop optimal concentrations of products used in the biotechnology field, particularly with agricultural and food engineering. The utility of these methods lies in the ability of these powerful computational tools to extrapolate a wide range of responses from a limited number of biologic experiments, once maxima and minima concentrations of each of the components that go into the formulation are defined based upon industry standards or literature.
</p>
