<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Above discussion indicates that the interfacial issues between SCEs and Li anode or cathode such as large resistance and unstable interface can be effectively solved by special design of SCEs and its battery structure. In addition, construction of effective Li‐ion pathway and tight contact interface with both cathode and anode is strongly required for preparing the all‐solid‐state battery.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">92</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0107" ref-type="ref">107</xref> There are some works to simultaneously solve the interfacial issues between SCEs and Li anode and cathode by designing the SCEs with unique structure and components. Goodenough and co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0108" ref-type="ref">108</xref> first proposed the concept of polymer/ceramic/polymer sandwich electrolyte (PCPSE) (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0010" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>10</bold>
 </xref>a). On one hand, the introduction of ceramic layer blocks the anions of the polymer salt and thus reduces the double‐layer electric field at the Li/polymer interface, which reduces the chemical/electrochemical decomposition of the polymer electrolyte and improves the coulombic efficiency of the battery. On the other hand, the polymer layers provide wet contact with both LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> cathode and Li metal anode, which leads to lower Li ion transfer resistance and a uniform Li ion flux across the interface and thus suppress the Li dendrite formation, and the Li/LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> cell delivering a stable capacity of 130 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> after 100 cycles with an efficiency of 99.7–100%. Huo et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">109</xref> also reported a sandwich‐type SCE consisting of a “polymer‐in‐ceramic” interlayer of 80 vol% 5 µm LLZTO (PIC‐5 µm) sandwiched between two “ceramic‐in‐polymer” thin‐film outer layers of 20 vol% 200 nm LLZTO particles (CIP‐200 nm) (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0010" ref-type="fig">10</xref>b). The PIC‐5 µm interlayer presents high mechanical strength, which can effectively suppress the Li dendrite growth. The CIP‐200 nm layer on both anode and cathode sides possesses a smooth and flexibility surface with a high t
 <sub>Li</sub>
 <sup>+</sup> of 0.47, which can achieve an excellent compatible contact with both Li anode and LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> cathode to reduce the interfacial resistance. As a result, the LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/SCE/Li cells present excellent cycle performance at room temperature. Some other researches also adopt similar strategy to simultaneously modify the interface of SCE with both cathode and anode.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0110" ref-type="ref">110</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0111" ref-type="ref">111</xref> The polymer layers provide soft contact with both electrodes and rigid layer guarantees mechanical properties.
</p>
