<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to the different characteristics of cathode and anode, SCEs with Janus structure were constructed to provide more adaptable solutions for building both excellent interfaces with cathode and anode.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0112" ref-type="ref">112</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0113" ref-type="ref">113</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0114" ref-type="ref">114</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0115" ref-type="ref">115</xref> Guo and co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0113" ref-type="ref">113</xref> proposed a thin asymmetric SCE with high modulus to suppress Li dendrite growth and flexibility to enable low interface resistance with both cathode and anode. In this asymmetric SCE, a rigid LLZO layer (5.7 µm) modified with an ultrathin 7.5 nm polymer is coated on one side surface of separator, which not only can effectively suppress the Li dendrite growth, but also form a stable and lower resistance interface with the Li metal anode. In addition, a soft polymer layer (5.4 µm) is used to modify the other side surface of separator, which spreads exterior and interior of cathode and separator to form connected interfaces with cathode and an integrated battery structure (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0010" ref-type="fig">10</xref>c). A continuous ion pathway is formed from anode to cathode. With this asymmetrical design, the Li/Li symmetrical cell delivers an extremely flat and stable voltage plateau for 3200 h, indicating stable lithium plating/stripping reversibility and the significant restrained Li dendrite growth. Guo and co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0114" ref-type="ref">114</xref> also developed a type of heterogeneous multilayered solid electrolyte (HMSE), in which the oxidation‐resistant PAN contacts with high‐voltage cathode, in‐situ photopolymerizable reduction‐tolerant polyethylene glycol diacrylate (PEGDA) faces the Li metal anode, and a Janus and flexible PAN@LAGP (80 wt%) composite electrolyte is designed as intermediate layer (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0010" ref-type="fig">10</xref>d). The HMSE presents effective inhibition to Li dendrite growth and excellent compatibility with both cathode and anode. The Li/Li symmetric batteries using the HMSE can cycle steadily for more than 1000 h under 2 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup> with a stable polarization less than 40 mV. When paired with LiNi
 <sub>0.6</sub>Co
 <sub>0.2</sub>Mn
 <sub>0.2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and LiNi
 <sub>0.8</sub>Co
 <sub>0.1</sub>Mn
 <sub>0.1</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> cathodes, the solid‐state Li metal batteries using HMSE exhibit excellent electrochemical performance. Furthermore, Guo and co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0115" ref-type="ref">115</xref> designed a compatible SCE by coating the PAN and PEO layers to both sides of LATP ceramic electrolyte (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0010" ref-type="fig">10</xref>e). The PAN‐based layer constructs soft‐contact and high‐voltage tolerance with LiNi
 <sub>0.6</sub>Mn
 <sub>0.2</sub>Co
 <sub>0.2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> cathode, meanwhile the PEO layer at anode side can effectively protect the Li metal from reacting with LATP and release the electric double‐layer accumulation between LATP and Li anode to suppress Li dendrite growth. These works demonstrate the extreme significance to construct the Janus structure of SCE for high performance of all‐solid‐state lithium metal batteries. The Janus structure design for SCE can greatly enhance the mechanical strength and reduce the thickness of SCE, which is also quite significant for preparing the all‐solid‐state Li metal battery with high volumetric energy density.
</p>
