<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par54">It is known through loss-of-function mutations in the key GA biosynthesis regulatory enzymes display dwarf phenotypes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Apart from biosynthesis-related genes, DELLAs are the key genes in the GA signal transduction pathway and DELLA deletion mutations in maize and brassica have been associated with dwarfism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The differential expression of DELLAs was not recorded in the comparative transcriptome analysis between WT and MT banana pseudostems. Similar observations have been previously recorded in autotetraploid apple where authors did not find differential regulation of DELLAs. However, the authors concluded that the stem height was being regulated by GA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. We also propose similar GA regulated pseudostem height regulation in MT. This proposition is based on many observations. First, the 36.66 fold up-regulation of one gibberellin regulated protein (
 <italic>Ma06_g04390</italic>) is an important observation, as in cucumber hypocotyl, this gene has been reported to encode a classical arabinogalactan protein and is involved in stem elongation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Second, we also observed an increased expression of two other genes that are induced by GA i.e. interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinases with very high fold change values. This observation is in agreement with the fact that in rice, a receptor-like kinase named PSRK2 was induced by GA and was only found in the stem [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Third, the observation that a probable 2-oxoglutarate-dependent dioxygenase (
 <italic>Ma07_g15430</italic>) showed increased expression, further supports our proposition of possible involvement of GA in pseudostem height. This gene belongs to 2OG-Fe (II) oxygenase superfamily and its homologs are known for their role in catalyzation of latter reactions in the GA biosynthesis pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Fourth, it is known that brassinosteroids (BRs) and GA are two predominant hormones regulating plant cell elongation. A defect in either of these leads to reduced plant growth and dwarfism. BRI is the major receptor of BR and overexpression of BRI1 in Arabidopsis has shown increased cell elongation and increased number of brassinolide binding sites in membrane fractions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. The significant increase in the expression of two BRI1 genes in MT suggests that BR is increasing pseudostem height by cell elongation. This observation is consistent with the results that decreased BR content in the autotetraploid apple caused dwarf phenotype [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Furthermore, BR catabolism is activated by LOB domain-containing proteins which are particularly important in the control of stem elongation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. We observed that one LOB domain-containing gene had higher expression in WT. LOB domain-containing genes are targeted by DELLA proteins. LOB genes are categorized as organ boundary genes. Thus the organ boundary genes could regulate stem growth by restricting signals that control stem elongation, such as BR, which further regulates GA synthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. It has been already established in rice that BR modulates GA biosynthesis and hence regulates cell elongation. Fifth, the regulation of JAZ and TCP further supports the possible involvement of GA in pseudostem height regulation. Finally, the mevalonate pathway has also contribution to the GA biosynthesis pathway because geranylgeranyl diphosphate is synthesized by either a mevalonate-dependent or a non-mevalonate pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The increased expression of a gene associated with mevalonate kinase activity suggests that GA metabolism is influencing the phenotype and the GA biosynthesis is possibly due to changes in the mevalonate-dependent pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].
</p>
