<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55">GAs also work in coordination with BR, ABA, auxin, and other hormones for stem growth regulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Auxin biosynthesis, transport, and sensitivity are associated with cell elongation in plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Auxin has a specific role in epidermis during hypocotyl elongation is and controls BR synthesis and signaling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Epidermis coordinates auxin-induced stem growth hence changes in auxin flux in cells could be linked with cell elongation via auxin efflux carrier proteins (also known as PINs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The up-regulation of two PINs in MT suggests that a similar mechanism might be present in banana stem. This observation is supported with the fact that we noticed up-regulation of one HD-zip protein in MT. Previously; links have also been established between auxin and the members of HD-zip proteins. The HD-zip gene (
 <italic>AtHB2</italic>) controls the elongation of hypocotyl depending on the auxin transport system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Furthermore, ABC transporters also play roles in auxin transport. The dwarf phenotype in Arabidopsis has also been implicated to ABC transporters owing to their involvement in auxin transport [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Therefore, any up-regulation of ABC transporter in MT will further verify that auxin influx in elongated pseudostem could be a possible regulatory mechanism. In this study two the ABC transporter had higher expression. In addition, ABC transporter was one of the significantly enriched pathways in transcriptome as well as metabolome (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Additionally, the relatively higher expression of phospholipases and a patatin-like protein 2 is quite relevant to these results because it has been established that phospholipases (including patatin-related phospholipases) have functions in auxin signal transduction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Together, these findings suggest that auxin flux in the pseudostem was significantly affected and could lead to elongation of the stem.
</p>
