<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par56">Phospholipase-As have not been well characterized regarding cell elongation in Arabidopsis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Therefore, the higher expression of phospholipases also suggests possible role in cell elongation in MT. Stem elongation or plant height is accomplished by cell expansion/elongation, which is a tightly regulated process. In Arabidopsis, cell elongation is further responsible for hypocotyl growth, while in cotton it is attributed to fiber elongation. The exclusive accumulation of scutellarin (
 <italic>pmp000012</italic>) in MT suggested that MT pseudostems are experiencing elongation. Scutellarin is a parahormone that promotes root elongation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] (Additional Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Overall, all plant organs owe their final size to a period of significant cell elongation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Regarding cell elongation, our results showed that a probable GABA transporter had a lower expression, while a white-brown complex homolog protein 15 showed increased expression. These observations indicate that like Arabidopsis and cotton, banana cell elongation is also regulated in a complex manner [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. As the size of a plant cell is determined by the extent of the surface of its wall, cell elongation may be defined also as any permanent increase in the surface of the cell wall [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Therefore, cell wall modification is an important consideration when comparing WT and MT banana pseudostems. We further checked whether cell-wall elasticity or porosity is affected during pseudostem elongation in banana. Previous investigations in Arabidopsis showed that cellulose composition and cell-wall thickness were affected very little during stem elongation. The role of pectin and cellulose is quite established in control of internode elongation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Our observations in MT pseudostem suggest that banana might adopt a strategy to control the cell-wall rigidity and possibly reduce its visco-elasticity by down-regulating PMEI. The increased expression of probable mannan synthases and reduced expression of cellulose-synthase-like protein might be associated with protein-mediated changes in cell-wall extensibility driven by the circadian clock which should be further validated by future studies (Additional Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">3</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. Furthermore, the increased expression of four COMTs is consistent with the previous reports on high lignin content, mechanical strength, and stem strength in lodging resistant wheat [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. In this regard, the 81.968 fold higher accumulation of D-xylonic acid was an important observation with no accumulation in WT (Additional Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">5</xref>). D-xylonic acid has been found as a predominant constituent of the hemicellulose in pomegranate thus suggesting that large-scale cell wall modification is underway in MT [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. This is further evident from the 57 and 53 fold up-accumulation of major lignans i.e. pinoresinol-hex and pinoresinol-aceGlu, respectively, in MT (Additional Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">5</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>].
</p>
