<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Our long-term study over &#8764;3.5 years assessed intra-and inter-annual variability in aardvark body temperature and activity responses to fluctuations in environmental conditions in the semi-arid Kalahari and allowed us to elucidate differences between drought and non-drought years. During a drought year, vegetation was scarce. Aardvarks were partly diurnal during the drought summer as well as during much of the subsequent winter, and displayed minimum 24-h body temperatures as low as 24&#176;C, resulting in exaggerated heterothermy. Several aardvarks died during the drought summer and the following winter after exhibiting large amplitudes of the 24-h body temperature rhythm and diurnal foraging activity. In comparison, during non-drought years, when above-average rainfall generated high vegetation productivity and thus likely high availability of aardvark prey (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Weyer, 2018</xref>), aardvarks remained nocturnal throughout the summer and most of the winter. Rather than extending their foraging duration in an attempt to obtain more food, aardvarks shortened their foraging duration during the drought and winter, most notably during a winter following drought. Our data showed that, of the variables that we measured, the key driver of changes in body temperature and activity in our Kalahari aardvarks was EVI. In our GLMMs, EVI (a measure of vegetation greenness) was associated positively with minimum 24-h body temperature, and very strongly and inversely with amplitude of the 24-h body temperature rhythm, an index that we have proposed for the well-being of mammals (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Hetem et al., 2016</xref>). EVI also was associated positively with the duration of the aardvarks&#8217; foraging activity and with the time of emergence and return to the burrows, which resulted in an increase in the proportion of diurnal activity that took place when vegetation was brown. Moreover, minimum 24-h body temperature was a relevant driver of aardvark activity, such that the lower their minimum 24-h body temperature was, the more likely aardvarks were to become diurnal, and to emerge from and return to their burrows earlier. We conclude that the aberrations that we observed in body temperature and activity patterns during droughts were mainly related to energy deficits, and the aardvarks behaved in a way that reduced the thermoregulatory cost of those energy deficits (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). Similar declines in minimum 24-h body temperature have been observed in other large mammals that experienced an energy deficit (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Hetem et al., 2016</xref>). For example, Arabian oryx (<italic>Oryx leucoryx</italic>) showed low minimum 24-h body temperatures throughout the dry, resource-scarce period, irrespective of ambient temperatures (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Hetem et al., 2010</xref>).</p>