<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Aardvarks were affected adversely by reduced prey availability not only during the 2013 summer drought itself, but afterwards, because surviving aardvarks took a long time to improve their body condition (indicated by return of homeothermic body temperature patterns) after the drought winter. The single individual (
 <italic>A06</italic>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) for which data are available for the autumn after the 2013 drought summer did not show diurnal activity and had only short bouts of heterothermy during the summer drought compared to other aardvarks, and showed a rapid return to stable thermoregulation following the onset of summer rains, but a second decline in minimum body temperature and longer-lasting heterothermy during the subsequent cold and dry winter. During this winter (2013), additional aardvarks died (including one of our study aardvarks) and no study aardvark maintained stable body temperature at night (mean amplitude of the 24-h body temperature rhythm during August 2013 was 4.7 ± 1.3°C; absolute range 24.7 to 38.8°C). The 11.7°C amplitude of the 24-h body temperature rhythm in a surviving individual during that winter is the largest recorded in any large, free-living mammal to date, larger than that previously reported for aardvarks during the summer drought (8.6°C; 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Rey et al., 2017</xref>) or for Arabian oryx in the harsh Arabian Desert (7.7°C; 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Hetem et al., 2010</xref>). The variable minimum 24-h body temperatures of our aardvarks are incongruent with the controlled downregulation of body temperature as a result of a reduction of the hypothalamic set-point, as in torpor (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Heldmaier and Ruf, 1992</xref>). Rather than a regulated response, the loss of body condition and high mortality rate associated with lowered 24-h minimum body temperatures of our aardvarks imply that the animals were experiencing an energy deficit. Like our aardvarks during non-drought conditions, free-living aardvarks during winter and summer in the Karoo, South Africa displayed a bimodal 24-h rhythm of body temperature with lower body temperature during the day when the aardvarks were inactive inside their burrows, and higher body temperatures at night when they were foraging actively (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Skinner, 2004</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Skinner (2004)</xref> suggested that the endogenous heat produced by intense digging might restrict aardvark foraging to the cooler night-time during hot periods whereas sensitivity to cold might force aardvarks to shift their foraging activity earlier; they claimed that aardvarks avoided air temperatures below 2°C. Our data do not support those suggestions. On occasion, our aardvarks still were active at air temperatures below freezing (compare panels 
 <bold>A</bold> and 
 <bold>B</bold> of 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>), and we observed them engaged in digging activity during the heat of the day in summer.
</p>
