<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In terms of aardvarks timing their activity according to their prey availability, optimal foraging theory predicts that a species would coordinate the timing of its foraging activities with the times of the day at which their prey is most accessible, to maximise energy intake. Harvester termites, a key prey item of Kalahari aardvarks (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Weyer, 2018</xref>), occur in deep (up to 7 m) underground hives (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Hartwig, 1965</xref>). To harvest grass (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Nel and Hewitt, 1969</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Symes and Woodborne, 2011</xref>), these termites must undergo daily vertical migrations from the deep hive area and move to the upper, warmer soil levels during the day, to warm up in anticipation of their daily foraging. Thus, in winter, termites might aggregate near the surface several hours before emerging to forage during the daytime, which might explain a shift in aardvark foraging to earlier times in winter. In summer, the termites would be expected to migrate toward the upper levels of the soil in the evening, in anticipation of their night-time foraging, which would match the nocturnal activity of the aardvarks in summer. However, aardvarks at Tswalu became mostly diurnal during drought winters but less so during non-drought winters, thus an adaptation of their active phase to the timing of termite activity was unlikely to have been the explanation for the seasonal shift in aardvark activity. Similarly, in the Karoo, aardvark activity was independent of prey activity as the aardvarks were nocturnal but their predominant prey ants 
 <italic>Anoplolepis custodiens</italic> (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Taylor et al., 2002</xref>) were predominantly diurnal (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Lindsey and Skinner, 2001</xref>). Moreover, harvester termites also have been reported to forage diurnally even at high temperatures (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Nel, 1970</xref>), substantiating the argument that aardvark activity is independent of that of prey activity. That our aardvarks could forage at night or in the day implies that termites were available to them at all times.
</p>
