<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A more common approach for the identification of alloying and ordering motifs in heterometallic compounds relies on the interpretation of coordination numbers. For example, for a homogeneous alloy formed by atoms of types A and B, the ratio of CNs for A–B bonds and A–A bonds should be equal to the ratio of the molar fractions of B and A atoms, 
 <inline-formula id="d33e3922">
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m024.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>. Deviations from this relationship indicate segregation of the metals: the ratio 
 <inline-formula id="d33e3925">
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m025.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> being lower than 
 <inline-formula id="d33e3928">
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m026.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> means that the environment around the A atoms is, on average, enriched by atoms of type A, and suggests a tendency of the A-type atoms to cluster.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref184">184</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref313">313</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>AB</italic>
 </sub> equal to 0 indicates complete segregation of the metals. To further discriminate between a random alloy structure and an ordered material, one can calculate Cowley’s short-range order parameter:
 <disp-formula id="eq17">
  <graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m027" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>17</label>
 </disp-formula>Here 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>A</italic>
 </sub> = 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>AB</italic>
 </sub> + 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>AA</italic>
 </sub> is the total coordination number of atoms A. For random alloys, α is expected to be 0. Positive α values indicate segregation (clustering), while negative α values indicate ordering. For 3D fcc-type alloys, α can assume values between −1/3, for a perfectly ordered Cu
 <sub>3</sub>Au-type alloy, and +1 for a completely segregated system.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref184">184</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref313">313</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref314">314</xref>
 </sup> The linear relationship between all coordination numbers extracted for PdAu NPs of different sizes and compositions, and the fraction of Pd atoms 
 <italic>x</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>Pd</italic>
 </sub>, observed in ref (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref241">241</xref>) and shown in 
 <xref rid="fig18" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig18" ref-type="fig">18</xref>
 </xref>a, indicates α = 0 and a random alloy structure.
</p>
