<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fowl adenoviruses (FAdVs) are non-enveloped double-stranded DNA viruses, which belong to the family 
 <italic>Adenoviridae, aviadenovirus</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. FAdVs are grouped into five species (FAdV-A to FAdV-E) with 12 serotypes (FAdV-1 to 8a and 8b to 11) based on restriction enzyme digest pattern and serum cross-neutralization test [
 <xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Different from other serotype fowl adenoviruses, FAdV-4 mainly causes hepatitis-hydropericardium syndrome (HHS) in 3–6 week-old broiler chickens with high morbidity and mortality [
 <xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3–5</xref>]. HHS caused by FAdV-4 was first reported in Pakistan in 1987 [
 <xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and then spread into other countries and regions, including Iraq, India, Japan, Mexico, Chile, Ecuador, Poland, Russia, Slovakia, Hungary, Korea, and China [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and resulted in enormous economic loss to the poultry industry worldwide. However, the molecular pathogenesis of FAdV-4 is barely known. Fibers are thought to be critical for viral infection and pathogenesis of FAdV [
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. It should be noted that serotypes FAdV-1, FAdV-4, and FAdV-10 have two Fibers (Fiber-1 and Fiber-2). Zhang et al recently reported that Fiber-2 and Hexon, but not Fiber-1, were the virulent determiners for the highly pathogenic FAdV-4 isolates in comparison with the nonpathogenic strain [
 <xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Our group and other group’s recent studies found that the Fiber-1, not Fiber-2, directly triggered the viral infection of FAdV-4 via its shaft and knob domains [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, the molecular basis of the Fiber-2 in the pathogenesis of the highly pathogenic FAdV-4 need to be further elucidated. Here, Fiber-2 was identified to be interacted with the karyopherin alpha 3/4 (KPNA3/4) via its N-terminus of 1–40aa, and KPNA3/4 could facilitate the replication of FAdV-4. Moreover, a rescued FAV-4-Del virus with a deletion of 7–40aa in Fiber-2 was highly attenuated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, and could provide efficient protection against the lethal challenge.
</p>
