<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">The second aim of this study was to compare DDA and DIA in order to decide which method to use in future studies. First of all, DIA yielded more precise estimates than DDA. As a consequence, many proteins in the DIA analysis were also statistically significant after FDR control, while only a few in the DDA analysis. In addition to this, DIA had no missing values. Out of the 103 proteins that remained after peak selection in Skyline and selected for statistical analysis, we removed 13 from the analysis due to missing values in the DDA analysis. This is due to the fact that DDA randomly measures only the most abundant peptides if too many peptides elute at the same time in one MS1 scan, then the low abundant peptides are therefore missed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. This makes DDA data less reproducible than DIA data, and there is also a risk that the low-abundant proteins are excluded [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. This problem is circumvented in DIA, since all precursor ions within a certain m/z range are measured [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Another advantage with DIA is that it is possible to base the quantitation on MS2, which is not possible with DDA. MS2 is also often used for identification and validation with DIA, which is only possible with DDA if MS2 is available. One factor that might be regarded as a disadvantage with DIA is that it is more time-consuming than DDA, as the manual peak selection that needs to be performed before the data can be analysed is tedious [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Another feature is that the DIA data contains more complex MS2 spectra that require a spectral library for extracting the data. Improved software solutions could have a great impact on these drawbacks. The high complexity of the data also results in the need of larger data storage space, which might be a challenge. Even though DIA might be superior to DDA in several ways, on average, both methods, as expected, give similar point estimates of the differences between the two analysed tissues. The higher precision of DIA can probably be explained by the fact that the peptides are manually selected in DIA, resulting in the removal of peptides with worse chromatographic performance. Taken together, the advantages of DIA make it the preferred method of choice.
</p>
