<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To sum up, impressive lithium ion storage properties with exceptional power/energy ratings and cyclic durability have been realised without sophisticated nanostructuring/nanoscaling, but rather only through architecting the binary metal oxide-intercalated carbon bulk configuration. To be precise, using an eco-benign, expeditious, and economical gel pyrolysis recipe, a high density of homogeneous SnO
 <sub>2</sub> and Fe
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles were successfully inlayed into the carbon lamellas in a conductive protecting carbon sheath. A facile low-temperature annealing imparts the highly dispersed-SnO
 <sub>2</sub> and Fe
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles with an average size of about 5 nm, as well as the exceptional anti-coarsening and surface-to-volume atom ratio. It is this novel anode material that potently adopts this distinctive microscopic sandwich superstructure motif to endow the topologically frustrated host structure for the tenable conversion reaction with easy and defect-resistant Li motion and multielectron events. The “carbon sheath” intrinsic matrix of the nanohybrid combining with the “Li
 <sub>2</sub>O” formed from the conversion reaction can function as a mixture buffering matrix that conduces to keep the electro-chemically formed nanoscaled metal particles apart and thwart their agglomeration during the Li-Sn alloy formation/decomposition, thus curbing the volume/stress side-effect and capacity fading by maintaining the electrode integrity. Factoring in the low cost of raw materials, B-SFO@C can be revered as an eminent anode substance for stationary LIBs. The employed methodology here can recapitulate a very appealing arena towards maturing the metal-carbon nanohybrid wherein both distinguished virtues of the large theoretical capacity of metals and exceptional conducting/buffering functions of carbon are able to be sufficiently leveraged, complemented and finally rolled into one. A distinctive engineering tenet or direction for anode substances within lithium-ion cells can be inferred from the insights into this superior electrochemical reaction performance, coupled with the rich chemistry of synthetic strategies. That is, maintaining the high dispersion state of the ultrafine multi-component metal oxide nanoparticles within the micro-sized, compactly packed, and elastic carbon nanostructure is vital to improve the reversibility, cyclability, capacity, and rating of the conversion reaction-based metal oxide electrodes. In the case of the fruitful anode material engineering, we can envisage that an extensive portfolio of the multi-nary metal oxides (using the IVA, VA, and VlllB metals such Sb, Bi, Se, Ge with the greater capacities) and micron dimensional compact carbon matrix turns feasible, and the miscellaneous conversion reaction nanocomposite anode materials can be innovated with a fine-modulating of their Li storage behaviours. As long as the metal oxides encompass an available redox-active ingredient, the carbon substrates may get enlisted in both electronic conductivity and textural stability without respect to crystalline structures and combinations. In addition, because conversion reactions of different metal oxides can readily occur in varied voltage windows, a built-in electronic field between different and adjacent metal nanocrystals comes into being, and so the electrochemical process can smoothly take place to further circumvent a drastically aggressive volume perturbation, dendritic plating behaviour, and stress intensification, in sharp contrast with a unitary metal oxide electrode. Therefore, the selection of the sequential (de)lithiation potentials of the combined metal components can also serve as an additional paramount rudder for manipulating the electrochemical properties of the hybrid material electrodes. All taken together, the multi-nary metal oxide–carbon composite with the metal nanoparticles uniformly sequestrated into the lamellar carbon matrix could inaugurate an alternative roadmap for both academic research and the realistically-related deployment of greatly durable, high-rate, conversion-type anode substances in all batteries technologies.
</p>
