<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="proteomes-01-00219-f005" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Identity and interaction of proteins within functional network that are altered by 24 h carbon nanotube exposure. STRING database was used to illustrate the interactions of the proteins that were altered by exposure to a low dose of both SWCNT and MWCNT. The strength of the interactions is indicated by the thickness of the connecting lines. Proteins that have no connecting lines have been identified as altered by both SWCNT and MWCNT exposure but are not part of a network that connects them to any of the other altered proteins. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Proteins within functional network of “Cell Death”. Proteins in the left circle are component of adherens junctions, and proteins in the right circle are component of ribonucleoprotein complex. Hub proteins in the network: RPLP0, ribosomal protein large P0; RPS3A, ribosomal protein S3A; EEF1A1, eukaryotic translation elongation factor 1 alpha-like 7; TPT1, tumor protein translationally-controlled 1; HSP90AA1, heat shock protein 90 kDa alpha (cytosolic) class A member 1; STAT1, signal transducer and activator of transcription 1, 91 kDa; STIP1, stress-induced-phosphoprotein 1; CDH1, cadherin 1 type 1 E-cadherin (epithelial); JUP, junction plakoglobin; (
   <bold>B</bold>) Proteins within functional network of “Cell Survival”. Proteins in the upper circle are involved in the regulation of cell death, and proteins in the lower circle are located on the nucleoplasm. Hub proteins in the network: CDH1; STAT1; (
   <bold>C</bold>) Proteins within functional network of “Organization of Cytoplasm”. Proteins in the upper circle are component of actin cytoskeleton, and proteins in the lower circle are located on plasma membrane. Hub proteins in the network: CDH1; (
   <bold>D</bold>) Proteins within functional network of “Proliferation of Cells”. Proteins in the left circle are component of anchoring junctions, and proteins in the right circle are involved in the ATP catabolic process. Hub proteins in the network: JUP; EZR, ezrin; CDH1; LMNA, lamin A/C; HNRNPR, heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein R; GNB2L1, guanine nucleotide binding protein (G protein), beta polypeptide 2-like 1; TPT1; STAT1; (
   <bold>E</bold>) Proteins within functional network of “Cell Movement”. Proteins in the upper circle are component of actin cytoskeleton, and proteins in the lower circle are involved in the regulation of cell death. Hub proteins in the network: HSP90AA1; CDH1; GNB2L1; (
   <bold>F</bold>) Proteins within functional network of “Viral Infection”. Proteins in the circle are located on the nucleoplasm. Hub proteins in the network: STAT1; HNRNPU, heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein U (scaffold attachment factor A); TPT1. 
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="proteomes-01-00219-g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
