<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Endogenous electric fields (EFs) and wound currents are generated spontaneously in many tissues following injury and are present at the wound site during the process of wound healing [
 <xref rid="B1-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Dynamic changes in wound-generated electric currents demonstrate that electrical signaling is an active response to injury [
 <xref rid="B2-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Many types of cells respond to weak direct current (DC) EFs with a galvanotropic response (polarized shifting of cellular orientation in an EF), which is followed by a galvanotaxic response (migration of a cell in an EF) [
 <xref rid="B3-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Different cell types from the same tissue can respond differently to the same electrical signal. Peculiar differences in Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>, Na
 <sup>+</sup>, and K
 <sup>+</sup> channels, surface charges, and specific membrane resistance may contribute to the inherent directional movement of cells during applied EFs [
 <xref rid="B4-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In the cornea, injury-induced corneal wound currents directly correlate with the wound healing rate. In physiological conditions, the human cornea shows small outward currents (0.07 μA/cm²), which simultaneously increase up to 5-fold upon wounding (0.41 μA/cm²) for approximately 6 h [
 <xref rid="B5-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The human corneal epithelium contains an active Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup>-ATPase transport system, with an inward flow of sodium ions and active outward transport of Cl
 <sup>−</sup> ions across the stroma and epithelium, establishing a trans-epithelial potential difference. Wounding disrupts this potential difference and consequently leads to the flow of Na
 <sup>+</sup> and K
 <sup>+</sup> into the wound from the surrounding tissue, generating a laterally orientated physiological EF that can direct orientation and migration of corneal epithelial cells and enhance the epithelial wound healing rate by controlling the division axis in epithelial cells [
 <xref rid="B6-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
