<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The behavior of corneal epithelial cells and keratocytes varies in applied DC EFs, where epithelial cells, at field strength of 400 V/m, migrate in the cathodal direction and stromal fibroblasts (600 V/m) migrate in the anodal direction [
 <xref rid="B8-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Applied external EF stimulations also influence the axis of corneal epithelial cell division, and in the presence of small EFs (e.g., 100 V/m), cultured corneal epithelial cell migration, orientation display serum, growth factor and substrate dependence in vitro [
 <xref rid="B9-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Application of high EFs, for example 250 V/m, is necessary to observe cathodal migration of corneal epithelial cells in serum-free culture conditions. Further, human and bovine corneal epithelial cells show similar migration patterns in the applied small EFs [
 <xref rid="B11-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The strength of the EFs in the vicinity of the lesion also influences the rate of re-epithelialization [
 <xref rid="B13-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], while increased wound field strengths enhance corneal wound epithelialization. Studies on the role of wound-induced electrical currents show that Cl
 <sup>−</sup> and Na
 <sup>+</sup> are the major components of electric currents in rat corneal wounds. In the resting, non-wounded cornea, Na
 <sup>+</sup> is the main component of ionic transport, whereas Cl
 <sup>−</sup> is an important component of the endogenous EF at the wound edges. These findings allowed researchers to test clinically approved pharmacological agents such as aminophylline, ascorbic acid, and furosemide to control the Cl
 <sup>−</sup> flow, thereby modulating electric currents in wounds [
 <xref rid="B14-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The same approach in the form of chloride-free or aminophylline eye drops has been shown to enhance healing of damaged human corneas by offering bioelectric stimulation without electrodes [
 <xref rid="B5-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. At the cellular level, corneal injury causes significant changes in distribution and expression pattern of the calcium-activated chloride channel CLC2 in the human corneal epithelium. The time course of CLC2 mRNA upregulation correlates with increased Cl
 <sup>−</sup> flux, which sequentially reaches its maximum within 1 h after wounding [
 <xref rid="B2-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Furthermore, applied EFs also influence the regeneration of nerves after injury [
 <xref rid="B15-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and wound-generated endogenous EFs also control the rate of nerve sprouting, nerve growth, and regeneration, along with epithelial wound healing [
 <xref rid="B16-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
