<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All of the literature reports so far regarding the application of external EFs in corneal wound healing have reported on the application of DC EFs. However, in certain cell types, the application of DC EFs has been shown to negatively affect cell viability and proliferation when compared to alternating current (AC) EFs [
 <xref rid="B18-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], suggesting cell survival benefits of AC EFs [
 <xref rid="B20-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Furthermore, it is known that the exposure of cells to AC EFs significantly enhances intracellular calcium signaling and also alters various cellular functions [
 <xref rid="B7-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. DC is the continuous unidirectional flow of charged particles, which results in electrode polarity. However, on the other hand, AC is the continuous bidirectional flow of charged particles without electrode polarity, resulting in the repetitive stimulation of the target cells [
 <xref rid="B23-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and also minimizing electrode corrosion [
 <xref rid="B24-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Further, electric stimulation is known to enhance regeneration-associated gene (RAG) expression and regulate cell behavior by activating many intracellular signaling pathways and shows great promise in disease treatment and wound healing [
 <xref rid="B25-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Since electrical signaling is an active response to injury and it is known that the application of external electrical stimulation modulates the rate of corneal epithelial function, especially at the beginning of the wound healing process, the present work aims to analyze the gene and protein expression profiles following AC EF stimulation. As it is also known that commonly used DC EFs are the cause of most faults [
 <xref rid="B29-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], resulting in the buildup of ions near electrodes that can eventually nullify the applied EF [
 <xref rid="B21-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], a novel in vitro system for electric stimulation with AC voltage [
 <xref rid="B26-genes-12-00299" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] was used in the present study to investigate the differential expression of genes and proteins in corneal epithelial cells. 
</p>
