<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Results of the comparative annotation analysis of Se-enriched and non-Se-enriched rice demonstrated significant differences at the proteome expression level. A series of bioinformatic analysis pointed out the presence of 401 differential proteins. Of these, 77 targeted differential proteins were divided into 10 groups: oxidoreductase, transferase, isomerase, heat shock protein, lyase, hydrolase, ligase, synthetase, tubulin, and actin, based on their functions. The functional distribution is further discussed in 
 <xref rid="biomolecules-09-00130-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. Oxidoreductase proteins mainly participate in the anti-stress and bioregulation synthesis process. Among the 27 identified oxidoreductases, there were 12 up-regulated and 15 down-regulated proteins in non-Se-enriched rice relative to the natural Se-enriched rice. OsAPx02, CatC and riPHGPX proteins were identified to have high expression. The first two were up-regulated proteins, and the latter was down-regulated protein. The OsAPx02 belongs to the APX (ascorbate peroxidase) gene family, and it is one of the important members of the ROS scavenging system. It participates in many reactive oxygen metabolism processes in cells and plays an active role in maintaining normal cell metabolism. The studies showed that the OsAPx02 gene can enhance the growth and development of rice in drought, salt, and low-temperature resistant environments [
 <xref rid="B18-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. CatC is an important antioxidant and key enzyme in the defence system established by plants during growth. CatC can inhibit the excessive growth of H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, and is thus an important enzyme in the plant that controls H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> levels and the redox balance of plant cells [
 <xref rid="B27-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. CatC plays an important role in stress resistance, and it can improve the defence ability of rice [
 <xref rid="B28-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The riPHGPX belongs to the GSH-Px (glutathione peroxidase) gene family, and it plays an important role by regulating and catalyzing the redox state in cells [
 <xref rid="B29-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The number of down-regulated proteins was higher than that of the up-regulated proteins in the oxidoreductase group. Thus, the oxidoreductase’s anti-stress, anti-oxidation and reactive oxygen catabolism in natural Se-enriched rice were better than that in non-Se enriched rice.
</p>
