<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There were seven targeted differential proteins in the isomerase class, including three up-regulated and four down-regulated proteins. Isomerases proteins are known for their functions viz., stress resistance, plant carbohydrate and nitrogen-containing compound metabolism. OsI_05445 belonged to the protein disulfide isomerase (PDI) gene family and found high expression in Se-enriched rice. It mainly participated in the repair of damaged proteins under adverse stress to promote the synthesis of nascent peptides [
 <xref rid="B32-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], which indicated that the resistance ability of natural Se-enriched rice was better under stress conditions than that of the non-Se-enriched rice. Among the five targeted differential heat shock proteins (HSP), one was up-regulated, and four differential proteins were down-regulated. Biological processes of anti-stress and protein folding are mainly controlled by HSP. Os01g0180800 and OJ1540_H01.1 were found to have the highest expression. Os01g0180800 protein belongs to the Hsp70 gene, which is the most important and conserved HSP family. Hsp70 represents constitutive expression in-vivo. Under heat shock conditions, this protein found significant expression and control sorting of the nascent peptide chain, maturation as well as the transport of secreted proteins to the extracellular organelles [
 <xref rid="B34-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. OJ1540_H01.1 protein belongs to Hsp90, which is also a highly conserved heat shock protein. It functions in the correct regulation of various proteins in plant cells, while also ensuring cell stability under adverse stress conditions [
 <xref rid="B36-biomolecules-09-00130" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Both the studied HSPs found with maximum expression were down-regulated proteins. Hence, the anti-stress participation ability of natural Se-enriched rice was better than that of non-Se-enriched rice.
</p>
