<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In solution, ions can interact, with a varying degree of strength, with the surrounding water molecules. A key question concerning the effect of salts on any given solution property pertains to the number of water molecules affected. The hydration number (
 <italic>h</italic>) of an aqueous electrolyte has been loosely understood as the number of water molecules participating in the solvation of the ions and influenced by the presence of the ions.[
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref>] Knowing the hydration number of aqueous electrolytes is important in several fields. In aqueous electrolyte thermodynamics, various hydration‐based theoretical models have been developed to predict the equilibrium behavior and chemical speciation of natural aqueous solutions (oceans, brines, ground waters and atmospheric aerosols) and industrial systems (ionic liquids, underground contaminants, fluids used for oil and gas processing).[
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>] These hydration models have mathematical expressions that depend parametrically on the hydration number, here defined as the average number of molecules bound to the compound more strongly than they are bound to other water molecules.
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>[6]</sup>
 </xref> Similarly, in the determination of thermodynamic colligative properties (freezing point depression, boiling point elevation, vapor pressure lowering and osmotic pressure), the hydration number refers to the average number of water molecules that are bound sufficiently strongly to the ions so as to be removed from the solvent and become part of the solute.
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>[7]</sup>
 </xref> The hydration number is also relevant in the transport of biologically important metal ions at interfaces such as cell membranes,
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>[8]</sup>
 </xref> channels,
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>[9]</sup>
 </xref> and nanofluidic systems,
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>[10]</sup>
 </xref> as tightly bound water increases the apparent ionic size.[
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="cphc202000498-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>]
</p>
