<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent efforts combining genetic disruption tools and phenotypic analysis in human and rodent malaria parasites have revealed that ∼78% of 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic>-encoded membrane transport proteins (MTPs) are either essential or necessary for normal grow and development [
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref>], thus confirming their therapeutic potential [
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Among the annotated 144 MTPs, 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> encodes 13 P-type ATPases [
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], most of them refractory to gene deletion [
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. P-type ATPases are a large family of primary transporters that utilize the energy from ATP hydrolysis to pump cations (subfamilies P1, P2 and P3)[
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], lipids (subfamily P4)[
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], polyamines (subfamily P5B)[
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], or even to discolase single transmembrane domains (P5A subfamily)[
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic>, P-type ATPases maintain ion homeostasis during its intracellular life-cycle [
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> Na
 <sup>+</sup>/H
 <sup>+</sup> P-type ATPase (PfATP4) has been identified as the target of the antimalarial family of drugs spiroindolones [
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> homologue of the sarco/endoplasmic reticulum Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> ATPase (SERCA) pump (PfATP6) was initially proposed as an artemisinin target [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], although studies using recombinant PfATP6 did not support this [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Recently, gene-targeting approaches have also uncovered the important role for parasite’s progression of the P4 subfamily, also known as lipid flippases [
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4–6</xref>]. In eukaryotes, P4-ATPases maintain the asymmetric distribution of phospholipids in membranes by translocating phospholipids from the extracellular (or luminal) leaflet to the cytoplasmic leaflet [
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], key in important physiological functions as vesicle budding and protein trafficking [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Moreover, new roles of these transporters have emerged in recent years as membrane lipids are also implicated in cell-signalling events. In plants, the transport of lysophospholipids mediated by a P4-ATPase is involved in root development and size of stomatal apertures [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Also, the virulence of some pathogens and drug disponibility have been correlated with the expression and activity of P4-ATPases [
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The genome of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> contains four putative P4-ATPases: PfATP2, PfATP7, PfATP8 and PfATP11 [
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], well conserved in 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> species with the exception of PfATP11 [
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> encodes two P4-ATPase-like proteins only present in the Apicomplexa phylum: GCα and GCβ, consisting of a N-terminal P4-ATPase-like domain connected to a C-terminal guanylate cyclase domain. While there is some discrepancy with regard the vital role of ATP7 and ATP8 [
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], all the studies agree that the activites of PfATP2 and its ortholog in the mouse malaria parasite 
 <italic>P. berguei</italic> are completely irreplaceable during the blood stages. Moreover, in a recent study [
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], gene duplication of the gene encoding PfATP2 was associated with drug-resistant phenotypes against two drugs antimalarial compounds. This eventually situates PfATP2 either, as the target of these two antimalarial compounds or responsible of reducing the local concentration of these drugs at the target site.
</p>
