<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cobalt, nickel, and manganese formates are soluble in water [
 <xref rid="B192-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>]. However, during leaching, these compounds form an amorphous precipitate over time as reported by Gao et al. [
 <xref rid="B193-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>]; a phenomenon that we associate with common ion-effect because of the presence of highly soluble lithium formate (346.6 g/100 g water at 100 °C) [
 <xref rid="B194-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. This precipitation behavior is confirmed by the rapid decrease in dissolution efficiencies for Co, Ni, and Mn salt after 10 min of leaching. Lithium formate did not seem to follow this precipitation process keeping a positive reaction rate all along the process. Offering a high solubility regarding Li ions (186 g/100 g water at 100 °C) [
 <xref rid="B192-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>], acetic acid is another potential leaching agent for NMC dissolution. Its low leaching efficiency for aluminum is an advantage over inorganic acids, allowing to selectively leach active material from cathode scrap [
 <xref rid="B195-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>]. Similarly, Yang et al. added acetic acid and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> to an open reactor to selectively recover lithium from LFP batteries [
 <xref rid="B77-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The lithium recovery reached more than 90% while phosphate and Fe dissolutions remained below 1%. The process flowchart is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-00801-f015">Figure 15</xref>. Apart from processes discussed herein, other ones are summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-13-00801">Table S9 and Table S10 in supplementary Information</xref> [
 <xref rid="B196-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>,
 <xref rid="B197-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>,
 <xref rid="B198-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>,
 <xref rid="B199-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>,
 <xref rid="B200-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">200</xref>,
 <xref rid="B201-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>,
 <xref rid="B202-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">202</xref>,
 <xref rid="B203-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>,
 <xref rid="B204-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>,
 <xref rid="B205-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">205</xref>].
</p>
