<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <p id="Par1">Control of stage specific spike in ethylene production at anthesis has been a vauable route to potentially enhance genetic ceiling for grain filling of rice spikelet. A number of genes controlling ethylene homeostasis and starch synthesis have been identified so long, but lack of credible information on master modulation of gene expression by miRNAs and their target genes associated with hormonal dynamics obfuscate mechanisms controlling genotype difference in quantum of grain filling. The confusion accounts for consequent shrinkage of options for yield manipulation. In a two by two factorial design, miRNA regulation of spikelet specific grain development in low against high sterile recombinant inbred lines of rice 
  <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. namely CR 3856-62-11-3-1-1-1-1-1-1 (SR 157) and CR 3856-63-1-1-1-1-1-1-1 (SR 159) respectively, and inferior verses superior spikelets were compared during first 10 days after anthesis. Grain filling was poorer in SR159 than SR157 and inferior spikelets in the former were most vulnerable. Between the cultivars, overall expression of unique miRNAs with targets on ethylene pathway genes was higher in SR159 than SR157 and the situation was opposite for auxin pathway genes. Precision analysis in psTarget server database identified up-regulation of MIR2877 and MIR530-5p having Os11t0141000-02 and Os07t0239400-01 (PP2A regulatory subunit-like protein and ethylene-responsive small GTP-binding proteins) and MIR396h having Os01t0643300-02 (an auxin efflux carrier protein) and Os01t0643300-01 (a PIN1-like auxin transport protein), as targets with highest probability at anthesis and 5 days after anthesis respectively, in the inferior spikelet and the fold change values of DGE matched with pattern of gene expression (relative transcript level) in the qRT-PCR studies conducted for relevant miRNAs and protein factors for ethylene and auxin signalling. In conclusion, epigenetic regulation of both auxin and ethylene homeostasis control grain filling of rice spikelet was established, but evidences were more robust for the latter.
 </p>
</abstract>
