<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">In plants, the stem is initiated at shoot apical meristem (SAM) and in the case of seed plants, it is originated from the sub-apical region (called rib zone, RZ) of SAM [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Additionally, the monocot stem elongation is promoted by intercalary meristems (IM). Both RZ and IMs are the main sites where stem growth starts under GA stimuli [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. GA degrades DELLA proteins and stimulates the cell division in RZ zone. DELLAs, the proteins controlling cell division in the stem, are functionally associated with transcription factors (TFs) e.g. DELLAs bind and inhibit the activity of class 1 teosinte branched 1 (TCP), cycloidea, and proliferating cell factor TFs, which further activates other genes associated with cell cycle progression in stem [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Recent studies have highlighted the direct link of DELLAs and cell prolification in RZ, which not only influences stem elongation but also the SAM size. Other than DELLAs, organ boundary genes such as lateral organ boundaries (LOB) domain-containing genes, have also been implicated in stem elongation by restricting signals that control stem elongation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The establishment of vascular pattern in the early stages of stem development is a key stage and is under the influence of auxin flow. In this regard, the role of auxin efflux carrier proteins has been associated with the cell elongation in root epidermal cells but such a role in stem elongation has not been explored yet [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. After the initial growth based on cell prolification, cell expansion comes into action for internode growth. Stem growth is adjusted to changeable conditions by the rapid differential growth. For cell prolification as well as expansion, the prominent role of cell-wall related genes is also an important consideration. Finally, the coordination between tissue layers through signaling also plays an important role during stem elongation. The role of auxin in BR production and synthesis as well as the signaling between BR and very long-chain fatty acids in the epidermis are good examples [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].
</p>
