<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Enrichment evaluations are needed for all individuals due to differences between species, but also individual histories and preferences. A specific challenge of evaluating enrichment for nocturnal mammals is that the animals are typically beginning to wake as care staff are finishing their workday, so in-person enrichment evaluations are not always possible. Although informal evaluations are frequently completed, these evaluations can overlook individual behavioral changes that would indicate if the enrichment is meeting the intended goal or has positively affected animal welfare. For example, evaluations might be based on indirect evidence of use (such as food depletion or object location), but it may not be possible to link these changes to individuals if animals are housed socially. In some cases, the animal&#8217;s light cycles are shifted so that their active period corresponds with zoo operating hours, which allows for direct evaluation. Enrichment evaluations have been performed under these conditions for some nocturnal species, including kinkajous (<italic>Potos flavus</italic>; [<xref rid="B15-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]), armadillos (<italic>Dasypus novemcinctus</italic>), Senegal bushbabies (<italic>Galago senegalensis</italic>) and two-toed sloths (<italic>Choloepus didactylus</italic>; [<xref rid="B16-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]), and ghost bats (<italic>Macroderma gigas</italic>) and yellow-bellied gliders (<italic>Petaurus australis</italic>; [<xref rid="B17-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]). However, the welfare implications of modifying light cycles and illuminating the habitat during the dark phase for ease of visitor viewing are complex and not fully understood [<xref rid="B18-animals-10-01433" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Another option is to use technology to perform observations. Low-light or infrared camera systems are an option that permit observers to watch an animal&#8217;s nocturnal activity while having minimal impact on the animal. </p>