<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recycling of LIBs has been studied as early as after the commercialization of LCO batteries by Sony in 1991 [
 <xref rid="B21-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The first work on LIBs recycling at pilot level started in 1995 by Recupyl with support from French Environmental Agency. The installation obtained an agreement on behalf of French Authorities in 1998. Recupyl’s work continued with European Union support under the Valibat project in collaboration with Taridan, the French Alternative Energies and Atomic Energy Commission, Rhodia, and Sedena. In the meantime, the first academic paper on recycling had been published by Zhang et al. in 1998 [
 <xref rid="B42-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and the number of such publications continuously increased since. More than 20 years later, LIB recycling still attracts the attention of scholars [
 <xref rid="B6-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, the interest for spent LIBs is mainly limited to the extraction of Co, Ni, and Mn [
 <xref rid="B4-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Other materials, such as Li and FePO
 <sub>4</sub>, cannot be recovered using the current standard pyrometallurgical methods [
 <xref rid="B10-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Nevertheless, processing of LFP has been studied by some authors as either a distinct process or a general one that encompasses all LIB chemistries. For example, the selective leaching process developed by Zou and Gratz could be used to treat mixtures of NMC, LCO, LMO, and LFP [
 <xref rid="B43-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The patent published by Recupyl in 2005 focused on the treatment of Mn-, Ni-, and Co-rich batteries; however, it could be adapted to manage spent LFP as well [
 <xref rid="B44-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. 
</p>
