<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Particularly, the “recycling” branch covers an entire range of methods including “recondition” 
 <inline-graphic xlink:href="materials-13-00801-i001.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>, “recycle” 
 <inline-graphic xlink:href="materials-13-00801-i002.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>, and “down-cycle” 
 <inline-graphic xlink:href="materials-13-00801-i003.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>. Although the general objectives of recycling are to maximize the material recovery and economic value while minimizing the environmental impact, it also includes processes that focus on recovering only one target component from the whole battery system or degrade LIB components to different degrees of lower value products [
 <xref rid="B48-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The term “downcycling” can be used to refer to this degradation process, whether deliberate or unintended, and is also designated as “open-loop” recycling in the literature [
 <xref rid="B49-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The quality and inherent properties of a product that enters an open-loop recycling chain are undoubtedly altered. This arises from the cross-contamination with other type of materials, mixing various additive elements contained in similar materials, or the degradation of the physical and chemical properties of the recycled material. More specifically, downcycling is unintended when the qualities of a material have been degraded owing to its manipulation and processing. Conversely, downcycling is deliberate when the purpose of the process is to return the material to its more simple or elementary form. Thus, to reverse such decrease in quality, recycling should include additional costly purification steps. For example, Ni and Co alloys are recovered when Co- and Ni-based LIBs are processed together with ore concentrate in a smelter like Glencore’s Sudbury (Canada) facilities. The Co and Ni alloy requires additional hydrometallurgical treatment before it can be used for synthesis of fresh cathode compounds suitable for manufacturing new LIBs.
</p>
