<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The interactions between the constituent metals in bimetallic systems provide many exciting possibilities to tune the catalyst properties. In general, the coexistence of atoms of different types, where each of them may have its own catalytic activity for the particular reaction, results in a plethora of possible effects such as the presence of unique heterometallic sites on the catalyst surface, changes in the lattice constant, increased disorder and heterogeneity, induced stress due to lattice mismatch, charge transfer, and change in the electronic properties.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref292">292</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref297">297</xref>
 </sup> For example, for CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR applications, where CO
 <sub>2</sub> can be converted into a number of different reaction products, alloying Cu with secondary metals such as Zn, Co, Ag, or Au is a common route to control the selectivity of the catalyst.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref111">111</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref252">252</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref298">298</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref307">307</xref>
 </sup> For the same reaction, segregated Au-core Pd-shell NPs were proposed, where the selectivity for CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR to different hydrocarbons can be tuned by controlling the Pd shell thickness.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref308">308</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref309">309</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, Au–Pd alloy NPs were found to be active for the production of CO.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref310">310</xref>
 </sup> For PdPt NPs, depending on the order of the deposition of the different metals on the carbon support (i.e., Pt/Pd/C or Pd/Pt/C), enhanced selectivity toward hydrogen or formate production was obtained, respectively.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref311">311</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, the composition, structure, and architecture (e.g., random alloy vs segregated structure) of catalyst often change under working conditions. 
 <italic>Operando</italic> studies are thus indispensable for understanding the catalytic processes in these materials. The XAS method gives unique capabilities in this case, being an element-specific method, and thus providing the possibility to probe independently the local structure around each of the constituent metals.
</p>
