<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The pronounced effect of alloying on XANES spectra can be well seen in 
 <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">17</xref>
 </xref>a and b, where Cu K-edge XANES spectra collected for CuZn and CuNi bulk alloys
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref312">312</xref>
 </sup> and Au L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge spectra for AuPd NPs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref200">200</xref>
 </sup> are compared. The observed differences between spectra for alloys with different compositions signify, in part, modifications in the electronic structure.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref137">137</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref138">138</xref>
 </sup> In particular, the intensity of pre-edge features at ∼0–5 eV in 
 <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">17</xref>
 </xref>a was associated with the number of empty states in the vicinity of Cu, resulting in sharper features in the case of Ni-rich alloys, where Ni has no 4s electrons, and a less pronounced feature in the case of Zn-rich alloys (one extra 4s electron in comparison to metallic Cu).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref312">312</xref>
 </sup> Similar trends in 
 <italic>operando</italic> Cu K-edge XANES spectra were recently observed for nanosized CuZn catalysts during CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>
 </sup> Note here that because Ni, Cu, and Zn are neighbors in the Periodic Table, and have similar photoelectron scattering properties, it is difficult to distinguish between them using EXAFS-based analysis approaches. Insights from XANES can thus be very helpful to distinguish between Cu-rich and Zn-rich environments. One limitation of the XANES method here, however, is that modeling of alloying effects on the near-edge XAS features is currently challenging, as demonstrated in 
 <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">17</xref>
 </xref>b by comparing the trends in the experimental and simulated Au L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge data in PdAu alloys, hindering applications of XANES for quantitative data analysis.
</p>
