<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The causative agent of AHPND is a unique strain of 
 <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> that contains a plasmid encoding the binary Photorhabdus insect-related (Pir) toxin genes PirA/PirB [
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The AHPND-causing strain of 
 <italic>V. parahaemolyticus</italic> (designated here as VP
 <sub>AHPND</sub>) contains a 70 kbp plasmid (designated pVA1) with sequence encoding for the PirA and PirB genes, which is absent in non AHPND-causing 
 <italic>V. parahaemolyticus</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9–13</xref>]. Removal of the pVA1 plasmid from VP
 <sub>AHPND</sub> causes the bacteria to lose its ability to cause AHPND [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similarly, selective knockdown of the Pir genes or removing the Pir toxins from VP
 <sub>AHPND</sub> render the bacteria unable to cause AHPND in shrimp [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Even though PirA and PirB make up the binary toxin, PirB seems to be the main toxin protein that causes AHPND. For instance, shrimp did not display AHPHD symptoms when challenged with only PirA by reverse gavage, while the same treatment with only PirB resulted in typical symptoms of AHPND [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similarly, when shrimp were cultured for 6 h in seawater containing a VP
 <sub>AHPND</sub> isolate (designated 5HP), only PirB toxin was detected in the hepatopancreas of shrimp displaying the characteristic histopathological signs of AHPND, i.e. sloughing of the epithelial cells of hepatopancreatic tubules [
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Recombinant PirB is more toxic to brine shrimp larvae compared with PirA [
 <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The B subunit of PirAB
 <sup>vp</sup> also recognizes glycosaminoglycan molecules (amino sugars) and participates in bacterial pathogenicity [
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The PirA protein seems to play an auxiliary role in the pathogenesis of AHPND, while PirB alone could cause cellular damage, such as necrosis, apoptosis and other pathophysiological damage associated with AHPND [
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
