<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Characteristically, coronavirus (CoV) infection begins with viral entry that is mediated by the transmembrane spike (S) glycoprotein. This process entails (i) host cell receptor binding by the S1 subunit, and (ii) proteolytic cleavage to yield the activated S2 subunit, which mediates virus-cell fusion and entry at the endosomes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Similar to the closely related SARS-CoV, SARS-CoV-2, the novel coronavirus responsible for COVID-19, uses the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) type I membrane protein as its primary receptor in cross-species and human-to-human transmission, which occurs primarily via respiratory droplets and contact
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. In addition to the respiratory tract and lungs, human ACE2 is broadly expressed in many organs including the heart, kidney and intestine. This is consistent with non-respiratory symptoms in COVID-19 patients such as acute cardiac injury, renal failure, and diarrhea
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. A risk map based on ACE2 expression has identified the respiratory tract, esophagus, lung, heart, kidney, ileum and bladder as highly vulnerable organs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. Specifically, there is enriched ACE2 expression in type II alveolar cells (AT2), myocardial cells, proximal tubules of the kidney, ileum and esophageal epithelial, and bladder urothelial cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. In addition to ACE2, host cell serine protease transmembrane protease serine 2 (TMPRSS2) is also important for the S glycoprotein activation for fusion
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Unlike SARS-CoV, the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein contains a polybasic cleavage site at the S1/S2 junction, which can be cleaved by furin, leading to efficient cell-to-cell transmission, possibly increasing COVID-19 disease severity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Other important host cell factors that contribute to SARS-CoV-2 entry include phosphatidylinositol 3-phosphate 5-kinase (PIKfyve), lysosomal two pore channel subtype 2 (TPC2), and endosomal cysteine protease cathepsin L (CTSL)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. Overall, a number of factors facilitate entry of SARS-CoV-2 during COVID-19; amongst these, ACE2, TMPRSS2, and CTSL have been repeatedly identified as central viral entry factors, as summarized in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.
</p>
