<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <italic>Background</italic>: Many microRNAs have been identified as critical mediators in the progression of melanoma through its regulation of genes involved in different cellular processes such as melanogenesis, cell cycle control, and senescence. However, microRNAs’ concurrent participation in syngeneic mouse B16F1 melanoma cells simultaneously induced decreased proliferation and differential pigmentation by exposure to 5-Brd-2′-dU (5’Bromo-2-deoxyuridine) and L-Tyr (L-Tyrosine) respectively, is poorly understood. 
  <italic>Aim</italic>: To evaluate changes in the expression of microRNAs and identify which miRNAs in-network may contribute to the functional bases of phenotypes of differential pigmentation and reduction of proliferation in B16F1 melanoma cells exposed to 5-Brd-2′-dU and L-Tyr. 
  <italic>Methods</italic>: Small RNAseq evaluation of the expression profiles of miRNAs in B16F1 melanoma cells exposed to 5-Brd-2′-dU (2.5 μg/mL) and L-Tyr (5 mM), as well as the expression by qRT-PCR of some molecular targets related to melanogenesis, cell cycle, and senescence. By bioinformatic analysis, we constructed network models of regulation and co-expression of microRNAs. 
  <italic>Results</italic>: We confirmed that stimulation or repression of melanogenesis with L-Tyr or 5-Brd-2′-dU, respectively, generated changes in melanin concentration, reduction in proliferation, and changes in expression of microRNAs 470-3p, 470-5p, 30d-5p, 129-5p, 148b-3p, 27b-3p, and 211-5p, which presented patterns of coordinated and reciprocal co-expression, related to changes in melanogenesis through their putative targets 
  <italic>Mitf</italic>, 
  <italic>Tyr</italic> and 
  <italic>Tyrp1</italic>, and control of cell cycle and senescence: 
  <italic>Cyclin D1</italic>, 
  <italic>Cdk2</italic>, 
  <italic>Cdk4</italic>, 
  <italic>p21</italic>, and 
  <italic>p27</italic>. 
  <italic>Conclusions</italic>: These findings provide insights into the molecular biology of melanoma of the way miRNAs are coordinated and reciprocal expression that may operate in a network as molecular bases for understanding changes in pigmentation and decreased proliferation induced in B16F1 melanoma cells exposed to L-Tyr and 5-Brd-2′-dU.
 </p>
</abstract>
