<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">DEGs in the HYPO were enriched for several aggression-related processes, including terms associated with behavior, steroids, glutamate, and somatostatin. One of the most frequently proposed mechanisms of action for the long-term behavioral effects of prenatal T are enhanced sex steroid production and/or sensitivity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. We found that plasma T levels did not differ between prenatal treatments, and while our power to detect statistical significance was low, this does agree with past work showing variable support for an effect of prenatal T on sex steroid production [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Furthermore, we did not find that sex steroid receptors (e.g., androgen and estrogen receptors) were differentially expressed. However, the GO term cellular responses to steroid hormone stimulus was enriched with DEGs and this included nuclear transcription factors that interact with steroid receptors (e.g., NR2F1 and NR4A1), suggesting more subtle, nuanced changes may have occurred in the androgenic signaling system. Corticotropin releasing hormone (CRH) was also among the DEGs in this biological process, which could hint at differential regulation of corticosteroid secretion. Other up-regulated enriched processes included glutamate receptor and somatostatin signaling. Glutamate receptors excite neural circuits critical to aggressive behaviors and heightened expression may increase behavioral sensitivity, leading to more exaggerated responses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Finally, we found that three somatostatin receptors (SSTR1, 3, 5) were up-regulated in males from T-injected eggs. This finding mirrors those in socially dominant fish in which somatostatin receptors are also expressed more highly [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], suggesting up-regulation of somatostatin signaling may be a conserved component of aggressive and socially dominant individuals. Collectively, these findings offer several candidate genes and pathways with well-established links to aggression that may be sensitive to prenatal T.
</p>
