<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42">Epigenetic mechanisms are a promising candidate for explaining how long-term changes in gene expression are programmed. We found hundreds of gene-specific DMRs, both CpG and non-CpG, between treatment groups. A handful of genes with DMRs in the HYPO were also differentially expressed, suggestive of a regulatory relationship, although more extensive testing would be needed to validate this. Several of these genes were identified as being in a highly connected PPI subnetwork, including ADCY2 and PCSK2 (both up-regulated with decreased methylation in males from T-injected eggs). ADCY2 is a key enzyme in cAMP signaling that exerts a strong effect on gene transcription patterns [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. PCSK2 is involved in processing numerous prohormones, including proopiomelanocortin, prosomatostatin, and proglucagon [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Our PPI analysis indicated that these genes may interact with somatostatin, corticotropin, glutamate, and melanocortin receptors involved in signaling and hormone regulation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Thus, prenatal T may cause altered DNA methylation of a few highly connected genes that have the potential to initiate a cascade of effects in numerous behavioral pathways. It is also possible that non-DEGs with DMRs are primed for future differential transcriptional responses (e.g., [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]). Genes with mCG in the HYPO were enriched for processes that could broadly influence neural activity, like cell morphogenesis. The mechanisms linking prenatal T and gene-specific methylation are currently unknown, but neurotransmitters and steroid receptors have shown the potential to direct methylation patterns via non-coding RNAs and DNA methyltransferase enzyme activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], altogether making this an exciting avenue for future research.
</p>
