<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">While both treatment groups were presented with the same social stimulus, T-treated males behaved more aggressively than controls and the subset we sampled for molecular analyses only included T males that showed consistently high aggression, making it possible that some of the genomic patterns we found are a result of acting aggressively. However, our data indicate we captured stable phenotypic differences resulting from the treatment rather than socially induced patterns. Transcriptome-wide patterns of gene expression in the HYPO were better explained by prenatal treatment than individual aggression scores. We also found expression profiles indicative of dominant behavioral phenotypes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] rather than enrichment of the more labile neurogenomic processes associated with aggressive actions (e.g., energy metabolism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]). Furthermore, evidence thus far indicates that socially induced changes in DNA methylation occur on longer time scales (hours compared to minutes) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], suggesting the DMRs we identified are likely due to the prenatal treatment. Nevertheless, we are limited in our ability to form conclusions about within-group variation. While over two-thirds of males from T-treated eggs were more aggressive than the average control male, there were a handful that showed lower levels of aggression (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), which highlights the need for future work to explore individual variation in sensitivity to prenatal hormones. Additionally, by having only sampled adults, we are also unable to separate whether the effects we observed were a direct effect of T on genes during embryonic development or if these changes in adulthood were due to more indirect effects (e.g., a consequence of altered juvenile development or changes in a subset of genes that then elicit downstream effects). Regardless, these data are an important first step that highlight molecular processes potentially affected by the cumulative phenotypic effects of prenatal T.
</p>
