<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 4.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Whole lung cell suspensions from 
   <italic>Trem</italic>1
   <sup>+/+</sup> and 
   <italic>Trem1</italic>
   <sup>−/−</sup> infected mice at different times (D2, 2 days; D3, 3 days; D5, 5 days) and control mice were prepared, counted and stained with the mAbs indicated below for flow cytometry analyses (see Materials and Methods) using anti-CD11b-PECy7 and anti-Gr-1-PE (myeloid cells), anti-CD3-FITC, anti-CD4-APCCy7 and anti-CD8-PE (T cells), anti-CD19-Violet 421 (B cells). Viable cells were calculated on the basis of LIVE/DEAD violet-510 exclusion. Fluorescence scales are logarithmic. a) Representative dot plots of the myeloid cell populations at d2 pi in the myeloid gate to discriminate granulocytes (Gr-1+ CD11b+) from monocytes (Gr-1-CD11b+). b) Bar graphs represent total number of lung myeloid cells recovered from 
   <italic>Trem</italic>1
   <sup>+/+</sup> (black bars) and 
   <italic>Trem</italic>1
   <sup>−/−</sup> (white bars) from uninfected mice and after infection with 
   <italic>A. fumigatus</italic> at different days post-infection. Calculations of the total number were performed from the frequencies obtained of each population and referred to the lung weight/total animal weight. c) Representative dot plots of the lymphoid cell populations at d2 pi from lymphoid gating. Arrows indicate gating on CD3+ cells in order to study CD4+ and CD8+ cells. d) Bar graphs represent total number of lung lymphoid cells from both strain mice at indicated days after infection and uninfected mice calculated as described before. Data are mean ± SEM (n = 6). Comparisons were performed by using a two-tailed Student t-test. **, p &lt; 0.01; *, p &lt; 0.05
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1879471_F0004_OC" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1879471_F0004_PB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </alternatives>
</fig>
