<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">The dynamic expression characteristics of miRNAs between the two extreme types of spikelets, the superior one producing high density grains verses the inferior spikelet failing in grain filling and spikelets of high sterile cultivar against low sterile cultivar have remained elusive so long in the literature. In our previous work, under-expression of genes encoding enzymes/protein factors for starch biosynthesis pathway and endosperm cell division and over-expression of genes controlling synthesis of enzymes, receptors and transducers for up-regulated ethylene synthesis, signal transduction to the detriment of grain filling of inferior spikelet have been identified and explained
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, it has been shown that high ethylene production slackens grain filling in several rice cultivars
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. Obviously, it is evident that expression of genes, which controls hormone homeostasis, endosperm cell division and carbohydrate metabolic pathways are crucial determinants for spikelet specific grain filling in rice panicle at the early stage of grain filling. Precisely, the mechanism of under- and over-expression of the genes, that might have undergone post translational epigenetic modification in the inferior verses superior spikelet and high sterile verses fertile cultivars are not known. In this context, miRNA mediated regulation of grain filling of rice spikelets have been characterized by
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. These investigations had specifically targeted the two extreme type of spikelets contrasting for grain filling attributes in a single cultivar 
 <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. sub-species japonica, cv. Xinfeng and reached to conclusion that slow filling amounting to poor grain weight of inferior verses superior spikelet could be the final outcome of differences in expressions and functions of miRNAs. In the absence of comparisons between genotypes differing in grain filling phenotype, the conclusion reached above could be unique to the cultivar used.
</p>
