<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">High throughput miRNA sequencing analysis in the two RILs with contrasting grain filling attributes revealed differential regulation of several miRNAs on a temporal scale during the first 10 days post-anthesis, where dramatic changes in hormone homeostasis is generally noticed in the developing grains. We reported earlier that intrinsic concentration of ethylene is high at anthesis and declines rapidly with passage of time within the first 5 days and comes to ground level thereafter in the residual part of grain development period
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Conversely, intrinsic IAA concentration comes to peak level at 10 days post anthesis and remains stable thereafter till maturity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Jones et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup> opined that endosperm storage capacity (sink capacity) is pre-fixed by cell division, cell expansion and organ proliferation taking place during the early period of grain filling. In rice, we have noted that cell division and starch synthesis of endosperm in rice kernel seldom increase beyond day 12 after anthesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup> and hence, genetic or epigenetic factors controlling transcriptome dynamics of the processes are of high value for manipulation of final grain size in this period. Typical to characteristic, miRNAs belong to the class of small RNA possessing base pair length of 20–24
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. In our study, maximum read length distribution of small RNAs ranged between 23 and 25 bp, with maximum number of sequence at 24 bp (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), suggesting their participation in grain development. The base pair length of miRNAs involved in grain filling between days 10 and 35 post anthesis of 
 <italic>japonica</italic> rice cv. Jinfeng2 ranges between 20 and 23 bp
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. While confirming the base pair length of the participatory miRNAs, our study further appends the first 10 days after anthesis into this period for miRNAs epigenetic regulation. An average of 201 and 196 known miRNAs of SR-159 and SR-157 respectively, were detected in cluster analyses during the three stages of grain development in the first 10 days after anthesis (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Similarly, the number of unique miRNAs was at least 10 more in SR-159 than SR-157 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). However, the number of common miRNAs expressing during the 10 days period after anthesis in SR-159 and SR-157 were 86 and 94 respectively, implying that more epigenetic regulators participated in grain filling of the latter compared to former (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In comparison, Peng et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> identified 457 known miRNAs in the 
 <italic>japonica</italic> rice cultivar Xinfeng during the grain filling period ranging from day 10 to 35 after anthesis. The sequencing analysis on day 18 in this cultivar revealed presence of 351 and 312 known miRNAs, respectively in the superior and inferior spikelets
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> and cluster analysis identified 189 miRNAs expressing differentially between the two contrasting spikelets. Taking into consideration, data generated in the aforesaid reports as well as our own, natural expression of these miRNAs in developing rice grain could be specific to the cultivar and sampling stages. In the RIL cultivars used in our study, a total of 66 miRNA families were identified in the developing spikelets during the first 10 days after anthesis. MIR166 and MIR812 families were most abundant in expression followed by MIR444 and MIR1846 (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). This observation pointed to active participation of MIR166 and MIR812 in targeting gene expression during grain development of the RIL cultivars used, i.e. similar to the observation of Peng et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>, where various members of these two families express significantly during grain filling. In our work, cultivar difference in expression of unique miRNAs was significant, but the number fluctuated with passage of time. Higher number of unique reads of miRNAs aligned to genome expressed on day 5 than on days 0 or 10 post-anthesis and they accounted for at least 80% of the total number of unique reads (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). This percentage of distinct reads coinciding to rice genome is much better than the level of 77.18% match observed by Peng et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. Yi et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup> studied expression profile of miRNAs of developing grains in 
 <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L. cv. Nipponbare from 5 to 17 days after fertilization and identified 161 known miRNAs expressing differentially during the developmental period and a high proportion of them were up-regulated between days 5 and 7. The known miRNA statistics in our study, almost matched with this observation, in which the expressed miRNA number was often higher on day 5 than on days 0 or 10 after anthesis (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>).Thus epigenetic regulation of genome for grain filling was most critical at day 5 post anthesis for the cultivars studied.
</p>
