<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Virulence</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Virulence</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Virulence</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2150-5594</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2150-5608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7946022</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33682623</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21505594.2021.1894834</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1894834</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" vocab-term="Version of Record" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Therapeutic implications of <italic>C. albicans-S. aureus</italic> mixed biofilm in a murine subcutaneous catheter model of polymicrobial infection</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">T. VILA ET AL.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">VIRULENCE</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vila</surname><given-names>Taissa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Eric F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Montelongo-Jauregui</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Van Dijck</surname><given-names>Patrick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>Amol C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCracken</surname><given-names>Carrie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>Vincent M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004"><sup>d</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005"><sup>e</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jabra-Rizk</surname><given-names>Mary Ann</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005"><sup>e</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Department of Oncology and Diagnostic Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution>School of Dentistry, University of Maryland</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Baltimore</city>, <state>MD</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label><institution-wrap><institution>Laboratory of Molecular Cell Biology, Institute of Botany and Microbiology, KU Leuven</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Leuven-Heverlee</city>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label><institution-wrap><institution>VIB-KU Leuven Center for Microbiology</institution></institution-wrap>, <state>Flanders</state>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>d</label><institution-wrap><institution>Institute for Genome Sciences, University of Maryland School of Medicine</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Baltimore</city>, <state>MD</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>e</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, <institution-wrap><institution>University of Maryland School of Medicine</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Baltimore</city>, <state>MD</state>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">CONTACT Mary Ann Jabra-Rizk <email xlink:href="mailto:mrizk@umaryland.edu">mrizk@umaryland.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage seq="57">835</fpage><lpage>851</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" start_date="2021-03-06">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="KVIR_12_1894834.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Biofilm-associated polymicrobial infections tend to be challenging to treat. <italic>Candida albicans</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> are leading pathogens due to their ability to form biofilms on medical devices. However, the therapeutic implications of their interactions in a host is largely unexplored. In this study, we used a mouse subcutaneous catheter model for <italic>in vivo</italic>-grown polymicrobial biofilms to validate our in vitro findings on <italic>C. albicans</italic>-mediated enhanced S. aureus tolerance to vancomycin <italic>in vivo</italic>. Comparative assessment of <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from catheters with single- or mixed-species infection demonstrated failure of vancomycin against <italic>S. aureus</italic> in mice with co-infected catheters. To provide some mechanistic insights, RNA-seq analysis was performed on catheter biofilms to delineate transcriptional modulations during polymicrobial infections. <italic>C. albicans</italic> induced the activation of the <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm formation network <italic>via</italic> down-regulation of the lrg operon, repressor of autolysis, and up-regulation of the ica operon and production of polysaccharide intercellular adhesin (PIA), indicating an increase in eDNA production, and extracellular polysaccharide matrix, respectively. Interestingly, virulence factors important for disseminated infections, and superantigen-like proteins were down-regulated during mixed-species infection, whereas capsular polysaccharide genes were up-regulated, signifying a strategy favoring survival, persistence and host immune evasion. <italic>In vitro</italic> follow-up experiments using DNA enzymatic digestion, lrg operon mutant strains, and confocal scanning microscopy confirmed the role of <italic>C. albicans</italic>-mediated enhanced eDNA production in mixed-biofilms on <italic>S. aureus</italic> tolerance to vancomycin. Combined, these findings provide mechanistic insights into the therapeutic implications of interspecies interactions, underscoring the need for novel strategies to overcome limitations of current therapies.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>Candida</kwd><kwd>Staphylococcus</kwd><kwd>mixed-biofilms</kwd><kwd>polymicrobial infections</kwd><kwd>transcriptome</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="71"/><page-count count="17"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Polymicrobial infections caused by a combination of microorganisms are responsible for significant mortality and morbidity [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1&#x02013;3</xref>]. Biofilm-associated mixed infections, such as those on indwelling medical devices, are particularly challenging to treat due to their inherent heterogeneity, which can be further amplified by synergistic inter-species interactions [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4&#x02013;6</xref>]. Therefore, understanding the molecular inter-species interactions will greatly aid in designing novel therapeutic strategies targeting mixed biofilm infections, specifically those involving fungi and bacteria.</p><p><italic>Candida albicans</italic> is the most common human fungal pathogen causing diseases ranging from superficial mucosal to life-threatening systemic infections [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7&#x02013;9</xref>]. The majority of <italic>C. albicans</italic> infections are associated with its ability to form biofilms where adhesion of yeast cells to the substrate is followed by proliferation and formation of hyphae, resulting in a network of cells embedded in an extracellular matrix [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10&#x02013;13</xref>]. <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm matrix is complex, with major polysaccharide constituents being &#x003b1;-mannan, &#x003b2;-1,6-glucan, and &#x003b2;-1,3-glucan which has been linked to resistance of biofilm to antifungals [<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14&#x02013;17</xref>]. However, in various niches in the host, <italic>C. albicans</italic> coexists with numerous bacterial species, most notably <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> a major human bacterial pathogen that causes a wide variety of diseases [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18&#x02013;24</xref>]. <italic>S. aureus</italic> alone is a poor former of biofilms, however, together with <italic>C. albicans</italic>, this species forms a substantial biofilm where the fungus creates a scaffold for the bacteria [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The growing use of implanted medical devices is another reason why the incidence of <italic>Candida</italic> and staphylococcal infections has steadily increased, since the majority of these infections are emerging from biofilms formed on medical implants [<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>Our previous characterization of mixed <italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> demonstrated that <italic>S. aureus</italic> exhibits high affinity to the <italic>C. albicans</italic> hyphal form as these species co-adhere and interact synergistically, forming a dense and architecturally complex biofilm [<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Furthermore, using a mouse model of oral co-infection, we demonstrated that onset of oral candidiasis may lead to systemic staphylococcal infection, stemming from a thick matrix of mixed biofilm formed on tongue tissue [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Our subsequent <italic>in vitro</italic> studies into the therapeutic implication of <italic>C. albicans-S. aureus</italic> interactions in biofilm demonstrated that <italic>C. albicans</italic> secreted matrix polysaccharides, primarily &#x003b2;-1,3-glucan, confers <italic>S. aureus</italic> with enhanced tolerance to antimicrobials by impeding drug penetration through the biofilm [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. However, findings from the study also indicated that other factors may also contribute to the enhanced <italic>S. aureus</italic> tolerance to antimicrobials, which we subsequently identified to be farnesol, a quorum-sensing molecule secreted by <italic>C. albicans</italic> [<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Specifically, we demonstrated that farnesol indirectly confers <italic>S. aureus</italic> tolerance to vancomycin by elicitng a stress response <italic>via</italic> activation of the thiol-based redox system.</p><p>In addition to secreted proteins and carbohydrates one major distinguishing feature of biofilms is the presence of secreted extracellular DNA (eDNA), particularly in staphylococcal biofilms where it is crucial for biofilm structural integrity and maintenance [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33&#x02013;35</xref>]. In fact, the extracellular matrix of <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm is primarily composed of eDNA and the polysaccharide intercellular adhesin (PIA) [<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The formation of the eDNA matrix appears to be necessary for early staphylococcal biofilm development, as early DNase treatment profoundly impairs biofilm formation [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In <italic>S. aureus</italic>, the generation of the eDNA matrix is facilitated by autolysis of a subset of initial biofilm cells, regulated by the <italic>cidABC</italic> and <italic>lrgAB</italic> operons [<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38&#x02013;40</xref>]. Gene regulation in <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms is complex and involves the activity of several major global regulators [<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]; however, the environment in a biofilm can be altered by the presence of co-infecting microorganisms where polymicrobial interactions can result in augmented pathogenesis. To that end, the overall goal of this study was to elucidate the impact of inter-species interactions during a biofilm-associated infection in a host. Specifically, we used an established mouse model for <italic>in vivo</italic> grown biofilms to demonstrate the therapeutic implications of device-associated polymicrobial infections. Further, we aimed to provide lacking insights into the transcriptional changes governing the interactions between these diverse pathogens, particularly within the context of antimicrobial resistance.</p></sec><sec id="s0002" disp-level="1"><title>Materials and methods</title><p><bold>Reagents</bold>. MTS tetrazolium-based proliferation assay and the QuantiFluor&#x000ae; dsDNA System kit were purchased from Promega (Madison, WI); vancomycin hydrochloride from Hospira Inc. (Lake Forest, IL); Deoxyribonuclease I from bovine pancreas (DNAse I), Lysostaphin from <italic>Staphylococcus staphylolyticus</italic>, Lyticase from <italic>Arthrobacter luteus</italic>, Calcofluor-White and tribromoethanol (TBE) were purchased from MilliporeSigma Co. (St. Louis, MO); Concanavalin-A and vancomycin conjugated to BODYPI FL from Invitrogen (Carlsbad, CA).</p><p><bold>Strains and growth conditions</bold>. The <italic>Candida albicans</italic> wild-type strain SC5314 [<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] and the methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strain (USA300 LAC) were used in this study. <italic>S. aureus</italic> mutant derivatives of the reference WT strain defective in cell autolysis regulation (&#x02206;lrgA and &#x02206;lrgB) were obtained from the Nebraska Transposon Mutant Library (University of Nebraska, NE). <italic>C. albicans</italic> was grown on yeast peptone dextrose broth (YPD) (Difco Laboratories) overnight at 30&#x000b0;C and <italic>S. aureus</italic> cultures were grown overnight in trypticase soy broth (TSB) (Difco) at 37&#x000b0;C. Cells were washed in Phosphate Buffered Saline (PBS) and resuspended in RPMI 1640-HEPES (Invitrogen) media to final cell density needed.</p><p><bold><italic>In vitro S. aureus</italic> vancomycin susceptibility testing in single and mixed biofilms</bold>. Single- and mixed-species biofilms were grown in the wells of 96-well polystyrene flat-bottom plates as we previously performed [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. <italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> cell suspensions were adjusted to a final concentration of 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup> cells/ml in RPMI 1640-HEPES medium and 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of cell suspensions were seeded in the wells individually or in combination. Plates were incubated for 90&#x000a0;mins at 37&#x000b0;C, then washed with PBS to remove non-adherent cells. Fresh medium (100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l) was added to each well, and biofilms were allowed to form for 24&#x000a0;hrs at 37&#x000b0;C. Following incubation, wells were gently washed with PBS to remove non-sessile cells. Vancomycin (800&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) was added to wells, and plates were incubated for 24&#x000a0;hrs at 37&#x000b0;C. Following incubation, wells were sonicated to disrupt biofilms, and cell suspensions were diluted and plated on <italic>S. aureus</italic>-specific and <italic>Candida</italic>-specific chromogenic medium (CHROMagar; DRG International, Inc.) for CFU (colony forming units) enumeration. Control wells with no vancomycin were included; vancomycin concentration used was determined based on our previously published work on mixed biofilm assays [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p><bold>Animal studies</bold>. All animal experiments were conducted at the AAALAAC accredited Animal Facility of the University of Maryland, Baltimore and were approved by Animal Care and Use Committee. Three-month-old female Balb/c mice were purchased from Envigo; animals received food and water <italic>ad libitum</italic> and were housed at a maximum of 5 mice per cage, weighed and closely monitored for any signs of distress throughout experimental periods.</p><p><bold>Polymicrobial catheter infection mouse model</bold>. The previously described rodent model [<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] was adopted, with modifications. Mice were immunosuppressed by the addition of dexamethasome (Sparhawk Laboratories; Lenexa, KS) in drinking water at final concentration of 0.4 mg/L one day prior to infection, which was maintained throughout the study. 5&#x02013;8 fragments of polyurethane triple-lumen central venous catheters (1 or 0.5 cm in length) (Jorgensen Laboratories; Loveland, CO) were pre-coated overnight with fetal bovine serum (Gibco&#x02122;; Waltham, MA) at 37&#x000b0;C. Catheters were then inoculated with single or mixed-species cell suspensions of <italic>S. aureus</italic> and/or <italic>C. albicans</italic> in RPMI 1640-HEPES at final concentrations of 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup> cells/ml for 90&#x000a0;mins at 37&#x000b0;C to allow for microbial adhesion to catheters. For each experimental set, <italic>in vitro</italic>-infected catheters were processed for assessment of microbial recovery to confirm standardized microbial adherence to catheters prior to implantation. For implantation in animals, following <italic>in vitro</italic> infection, fragments were rinsed with PBS and kept on ice until implanted. Mice were anesthesized by intraperitoneal injections (0.5&#x000a0;ml) of TBE solution (250 mg/kg body weight) and the dorsum was shaved; small incisions were aseptically made (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2a-i</xref>), and a subcutaneous tunnel created allowing for insertion of 5&#x02013;8 pieces of catheters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2a</xref>-ii). Incisions were sealed using 3M Vetbond&#x02122; tissue glue and lidocaine analgesic gel was applied to the incision area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2a</xref>-iii). Animals were placed in a supine position under a heating lamp and monitored until they recovered from anesthesia, and then daily for any developing clinical signs of distress. Animals were euthanized by CO<sub>2</sub> inhalation followed by cervical dislocation and catheters were harvested individually.</p><p><bold>Scanning electron microscopy (SEM) analysis of explanted catheters for evaluation of <italic>in vivo</italic>-grown biofilms</bold>. In order to visualize the biofilms formed within the lumen of the catheters, representative fragments from each group were processed for SEM analysis. Explanted catheters were rinsed with PBS then fixed in 2% paraformaldehyde, 2.5% glutaraldehyde in phosphate buffer (pH 7.4). Catheters were post-fixed with 1% osmium tetroxide in PBS for 1&#x000a0;hr, washed with buffer, dehydrated in a series of graded ethyl alcohol, 30%, 50%, 70%, 90%, and 3 times in 100% for 10&#x000a0;mins each. Specimens were critical-point dried in CO<sub>2</sub>, mounted on SEM pin mounts, and sputter coated with platinum-palladium (EMS 150&#x000a0;T ES). SEM images were acquired using a Quanta 200 scanning electron microscope (FEI Co., Hillsboro, OR), and images were processed using Adobe Photoshop software.</p><p><bold>Vancomycin treatment of mice with single and mixed species catheter infection</bold>. To comparatively evaluate the therapeutic efficacy of vancomycin against <italic>S. aureus</italic> in animals with single or mixed catheter infections, animals were divided into a control (no therapy) group and experimental (therapy) group; within each group, 3 subgroups were included: implanted with catheters infected with <italic>S. aureus, C. albicans</italic> or in combination for a total of 6 groups with 5 animals in each group. Animals in the treated group were administered vancomycin twice daily by intraperitoneal injections (0.25&#x000a0;ml) at 55 mg/kg, and treatment was initiated on the 3<sup>rd</sup> day post-catheter implantation and continued for 5&#x000a0;days, then animals were euthanized. Untreated control groups received sterile PBS injections, and mice with <italic>C. albicans</italic> mono-infected catheters were also treated with vancomycin as control. Harvested catheters were aseptically fragmented, sonicated in sterile PBS to detach biofilms and cell suspensions were diluted and plated on species-specific chromogenic media for CFU enumeration; each harvested catheter was processed individually. As pilot experiments indicated blockage of the catheters by host tissue and immune cells compromising vancomycin delivery into catheter lumen, therapy experiments were performed using longitudinally cut catheters implanted with lumen facing downwards, in direct contact with the tissue. Experiments were performed on 5 separate occasions and data combined.</p><p><bold>Global transcriptional analysis of single and mixed-species catheter biofilms using RNA-sequencing</bold>. To ensure sufficient RNA yield, initial experiments were performed to determine optimum cell densities for catheter inoculation prior to implantation. Based on measurement of RNA from extracted catheters, cell densities of 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>8</sup> and 5&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>8</sup> cells/ml for <italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic>, respectively, were selected for the initial <italic>in vitro</italic> catheter inoculation. Implantation of catheters was performed as described above and animals were euthanized on the 3rd-day post-catheter implantation; catheters were collected in RNAlater buffer, aseptically fragmented, sonicated in RNAse free water to detach biofilms, and cells from all catheters recovered from each mouse were pooled by centrifugation. In parallel, prior to extraction, suspensions were diluted and plated for CFU enumeration to assess microbial recovery. Pooled cells were snap-frozen on dry ice and ethanol, allowed to thaw at room temperature (RT), then incubated for 30&#x000a0;mins at 37&#x000b0;C in &#x0201c;<italic>digestion buffer</italic>&#x0201d; containing 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml of lysostaphin (for <italic>S. aureus</italic> cell wall digestion) and/or 100&#x000a0;U/ml of lyticase (for <italic>C. albicans</italic> cell wall digestion) and RNAse inhibitor in TRIS-EDTA 1x buffer. RNA was extracted in 1&#x000a0;ml of TRI Reagent&#x02122; Solution (Ambion, Invitrogen; Carlsbad, CA) using bead-beating for 30&#x000a0;mins at RT followed by purification using Direct-zol RNA Miniprep kit (Zymo Research; Tustin, CA). Eluted RNA was analyzed in a Nanodrop Lite (Thermo Scientific). Total RNA was subjected to rRNA depletion with the Illumina Ribominus Depletion kit (bacteria module) and/or the Ribominus Eukaryote Kit. All RNA-seq libraries (strand-specific, paired end) were prepared with the TruSeq RNA sample prep kit (Illumina). Seventy-five nucleotides of the sequence were determined from both ends of each cDNA fragment using the HiSeq platform (Illumina). Sequencing reads were aligned to the reference genomes (<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> USA300 TCH1516 uid58925; <italic>C. albicans</italic> strain SC5314) using HISAT [<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and alignment files were used to generate read counts for each gene; statistical analysis of differential gene expression was performed using the DEseq package from Bioconductor [<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. A gene was considered differentially expressed the p-value for differential expression was less than 0.05. Two biological samples from each experimental group were analyzed. Sequencing reads were aligned to the reference genomes (<italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> USA300 TCH1516 uid58925, <italic>C. albicans</italic> strain SC5314)</p><p><bold><italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of biofilm formation of the <italic>S. aureus</italic> lrgA and lrgB mutant strains</bold>. Biofilm formation of <italic>S. aureus</italic> knock-out mutants defective in cell autolysis regulation (&#x02206;lrgA and &#x02206;lrgB) was comparatively evaluated to the WT strain. 24&#x000a0;hrs biofilms were evaluated based on metabolic activity measurement using the MTS-assay as per manufacture directions (Promega; Madison, WI). Total biofilm biomass was evaluated by the crystal violet staining assay where 24&#x000a0;hr-grown biofilms were fixed in methanol for 20&#x000a0;mins, air dried and stained with crystal violet solution (0.2%) for 20&#x000a0;mins. The excess crystal violet was removed, plates were washed twice with PBS and cell-bound crystal violet was dissolved in 33% acetic acid. 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of the extraction solution was transferred to 96-well plates and absorbance was measured at 595&#x000a0;nm.</p><p><bold><italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of eDNA accumulation in single- and mixed-species biofilms</bold>. 24&#x000a0;hr-preformed single and mixed-species biofilms were grown as described above using 6-well microtiter plates and eDNA was quantified as previously described with modifications [<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Briefly, biofilm supernatant was aspirated and formed biofilms were harvested by scraping and resuspended in 1&#x000a0;ml PBS. Suspensions were centrifuged for 10&#x000a0;mins at 5000&#x000a0;g to separate cells and the soluble biofilm matrix and the recovered supernatant was filtered using 0.22&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m Millex syringe filters. The amount of eDNA was quantified using the QuantiFluor&#x000ae; dsDNA System kit (Promega, Madison, WI) as per manufacturers instructions. Fluorescence was measured at 504&#x000a0;nm/531&#x000a0;nm (Ex/Em) in triplicates per sample in flat-bottom black-sides 96-well plates (Greiner, Kremsm&#x000fc;nster, Austria) using Biotek Cytation 5 plate reader.</p><p><bold>Effect of biofilm DNAse treatment on vancomycin susceptibility of lrgA and lrgB <italic>S. aureus</italic> mutants</bold>. Effect of biofilm DNAse I treatment on vancomycin susceptibility was evaluated as previously described [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], with modifications. 24&#x000a0;hr-preformed biofilms of the WT, &#x02206;lrgA and &#x02206;lrgB strains were grown as described above; following removal of non-biofilm cells, DNAse I (0.625 mg/ml), vancomycin (200, 100, 50 and 25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) or a combination of both were added to appropriate wells. Following 24&#x000a0;hrs incubation at 37&#x000b0;C, metabolic activity of biofilm cells was measured using MTS-assay. Control wells with no treatment were included; DNAse I optimal activity concentration was pre-determined in a dose&#x02013;response assay (data not shown).</p><p><bold>Effect of biofilm DNAse treatment on <italic>S. aureus</italic> vancomycin susceptibility in single and mixed biofilms with <italic>C. albicans</italic></bold>. 24&#x000a0;hr-preformed single and mixed-species biofilms were grown as described above and, after removal of non-sessile cells, DNAse I (0.625 mg/ml), vancomycin (800&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) or a combination of both were added to appropriate wells with biofilms. Following 24&#x000a0;hrs of incubation at 37&#x000b0;C, wells were sonicated, and cell suspensions were diluted and plated on species-specific chromogenic media for CFU enumeration. Control wells with no treatment were included; DNAse I optimal activity concentration was pre-determined in a dose&#x02013;response assay (data not shown) and the vancomycin concentration used was based on our previously published work on mixed biofilm assays [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p><bold>Confocal scanning laser microscopy (CSLM) analysis of vancomycin diffusion through single and mixed-species biofilms with and without DNAse treatment</bold>. To visualize the effect of eDNA enzymatic digestion on vancomycin diffusion through single and mixed biofilms, confocal scanning laser microscopy was performed as we previously described [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], with modifications. Single-species <italic>S. aureus</italic> or mixed-species <italic>C. albicans-S. aureus</italic> biofilms were grown on glass coverslip-bottom dishes (MatTek Co., Ashland, MA), as described above, for 24 hrs. Following incubation, biofilms were treated with DNAse I (0.625 mg/ml) or fresh RPMI (control) and fluorescent vancomycin conjugated to BODYPI FL (1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml; 488/650) was added to both control and treated biofilms, and the system was incubated for 1&#x000a0;hr at 37&#x000b0;C. <italic>S. aureus</italic> cells were stained with concanavalin A (ConA) conjugated to Alexa 657 (50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml; 650/668&#x000a0;nm) and <italic>C. albicans</italic> with calcofluor-white (0.05%; 433/355). Biofilms were gently washed and immediately observed in an inverted confocal laser scanning microscope (Nikon T2i). At least three random fields were visualized for each sample, and representative images of the reconstructed Z-stacks are presented.</p><p><bold>Data analysis</bold>. All statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism 8.0 software. All <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments were performed on at least 3 separate occasions and in triplicate where applicable, and averages were used to present data. Multiple groups were compared by 2-way ANOVA with Tukey&#x02019;s multiple-comparison correction. The set of data obtained from WT and lrg mutants biofilm susceptibility to vancomycin alone or combined with DNAse was analyzed by 2-WAY ANOVA using the Multiple Effect analysis (Mixed Model). Student&#x02019;s unpaired t-test was used to compare differences between two samples; p values of &#x0003c;0.05 were considered to be significant. For <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments, the database for statistical analysis was built up by incremental addition of experimental data. Based on our analysis, a sample size of 5 mice per experimental group will have at least 80% power to detect difference of 80%. All experiments were performed on at least three separate occasions, analyzed separately and averages used to present data. The Kruskal-Wallis one-way analysis of variance test and Dunnet&#x02019;s Multiple Comparison Test were used to compare differences between multiple groups and statistical significance, respectively. P values &#x0003c;0.05 were considered to be significant.</p></sec><sec id="s0003" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><p><bold>Mixed biofilm growth confers <italic>S. aureus</italic> with enhanced tolerance to vancomycin <italic>in vitro</italic></bold>. C Single- and mixed-species biofilms were grown in 96-well plates using <italic>S. aureus</italic> USA300 and <italic>C. albicans</italic> SC5314 reference strains for 24 hrs and then treated with vancomycin (800&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) for 24 hrs at 37&#x000b0;C. Following incubation, wells were sonicated to disrupt biofilms, and cell suspensions were diluted and plated on <italic>S. aureus</italic>-specific and <italic>Candida</italic>-specific chromogenic medium (CHROMagar; DRG International, Inc.) for CFU (colony forming units) enumeration. Consistent with previous observations, significant <italic>S. aureus</italic> killing was seen in the vancomycin-treated single-species biofilms (****, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001), which was significantly lower in mixed biofilms with <italic>C. albicans</italic> (**; p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>).<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Vancomycin susceptibility testing of single <italic>S. aureus</italic> and mixed <italic>S. aureus-C. albicans</italic> biofilms</bold>. Single- and mixed-species biofilms were grown for 24 hrs in the wells of 96-well plates then treated with vancomycin (800&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) for 24 hrs. Following incubation, biofilms cells were harvested and plated on species-specific chromogenic medium. Based on CFU values, results demonstrated significant efficacy for vancomycin against <italic>S. aureus</italic> in single-species biofilms with significantly reduced efficacy against <italic>S. aureus</italic> in mixed-species biofilm. *, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; ***, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0,001</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0001_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0001_PB"/></alternatives></fig><fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>(a) <bold>Subcutaneous catheter model for <italic>in vivo</italic>-grown polymicrobial biofilms</bold>. (i) A small incision is made in a shaved area in the dorsum of the back; <bold>(ii)</bold> catheter fragments are inserted within a subcutaneous tunnel; <bold>(iii)</bold> incision is sealed with vet glue; <bold>(iv)</bold> catheters with formed polymicrobial biofilms are harvested from euthanized animals 2&#x02013;6&#x000a0;days post-implantation. (b) <bold>Scanning electron micrographs of explanted catheters with Sa-Ca mixed biofilms. (i)</bold> Yellow arrows pointing to biofilm consisting of fungal and bacterial cells embedded in a polysaccharide matrix formed within the lumens of catheters after 8&#x000a0;days; <bold>(ii)</bold> longitudinally cut catheter fragment with biofilm. Bars&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;400&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m (i) and 500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m (ii). (c) <bold>Time-course experiments for evaluation of microbial recovery from catheter biofilms</bold>. Based on comparative assessment of CFUs from processed harvested catheters, 3&#x000a0;days post-implantation was selected as the optimal time-point for biofilm formation</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0002_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0002_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p><p><bold>Scanning electron microscopy and microbial recovery reveals formation of robust mixed biofilms within implanted catheters</bold>. In order to determine optimal <italic>in vivo</italic> biofilm growth period, initially, small groups of animals with implanted catheters were euthanized two, three, four, and six days post-implantation and catheters were evaluated for microbial recovery. Based on CFU counts, significantly less <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>C. albicans</italic> were recovered from mixed-species catheters after 2&#x000a0;days (***, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001 and **, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01; respectively), compared to from single-species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2c</xref>) and for both species CFU were equivalent in single and mixed biofilms by day 3. Based on the kinetics study, CFU recovery 3&#x000a0;days post-implantation was determined to be optimal time-point, after which growth of both species reached a plateau. SEM representative images of lumens of explanted catheters revealed the presence of mature mixed biofilms after 8&#x000a0;days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2b</xref>). Comparatively, single-species <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms had less biomass than <italic>C. albicans-S. aureus</italic> mixed biofilms, whereas the <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilms consisting primarily of hyphae were comparable between <italic>C. albicans</italic> single and mixed biofilms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>).<fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Representative SEM images of biofilms within explanted catheters after 8&#x000a0;days</bold>. Catheters infected with (a-b) <italic>S. aureus</italic> only; (c-d) <italic>C. albicans</italic> only; and (e-f) <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>C. albicans</italic> (mixed biofilms). Bars: A =&#x000a0;400&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m; B =&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m; C =&#x000a0;1 mm; D, E =&#x000a0;200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m and F =&#x000a0;10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0003_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0003_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p><p><bold><italic>In vivo</italic> vancomycin therapy reduces <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from single species but not from mixed-species infected catheters</bold>. After confirming the suitability of the model for <italic>in vivo</italic> biofilm development, vancomycin therapy was administered twice daily for 5&#x000a0;days starting 3-days post-catheter implantation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4a</xref>). Based on microbial recovery from explanted catheters, vancomycin treatment resulted in significantly less <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from catheters from animals with single-species infection (****, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001), but had no impact on <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from animals with mixed-species catheter infections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4b</xref>). Vancomycin had no effect on <italic>C. albicans</italic> recovery under all conditions tested (suppl. Fig S1).<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><bold>Efficacy of vancomycin therapy in mice with catheters with single or mixed-species infection</bold>. (a) <bold>Timeline of infection and treatment</bold>. Vancomycin was administered (55 mg/kg) 3&#x000a0;days post-catheter implantation twice daily for five days and microbial recovery from explanted catheters was evaluated. (b) Following explantation, catheters were sonicated to disrupt biofilms, and cell suspensions were diluted and plated on species-specific chromogenic media for assessment of microbial recovery. Based on CFU counts, vancomycin treatment resulted in significant decrease in <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from catheters infected only with <italic>S. aureus</italic>, whereas vancomycin had no effect on <italic>S. aureus</italic> from catheters co-infected with <italic>C. albicans</italic>. ****, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001; ns, not significant</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0004_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0004_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p><p><bold><italic>C. albicans</italic> modulates expression of <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm regulators in mixed-species biofilms</bold>. Transcriptomic analysis of <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovered from explanted catheters revealed that 134 genes were differentially expressed between the multi-species biofilms and the <italic>S. aureus</italic> alone biofilms. These included 43 genes with higher expression in the multi-species biofilm and 91 genes with lower expression in the multi-species biofilm (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and S1). The most notable modulations were in <italic>S. aureus</italic> key-regulatory genes involved in biofilm formation, including sarU, icaB, icaC, lrgA, lrgB and nuc (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). While the ica genes involved in the production of PIA (polysaccharide intercellular adhesin) were upregulated, the anti-holin like repressors of cell autolysis (lrgA and B) and the DNA nuclease (nuc) were downregulated. An overall downregulation of toxins and hemolysins was seen in <italic>S. aureus</italic> from mixed-biofilms including genes for gamma-hemolysins, alpha-hemolysin, leucocidin and staphylokinase; similarly, immunomodulatory and adhesion genes were also found to be down-regulated in <italic>S. aureus</italic> in mixed biofilms. In contrast, capsular polysaccharide biosynthesis was significantly induced by the presence of <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Although 114&#x000a0;<italic>C. albicans</italic> genes were found to be differentially-expressed between <italic>C. albicans</italic> alone and mixed-species biofilms (Table S2), Gene Ontology Analysis (GO) did not detect significant enrichment among the differentially-expressed genes. Therefore, we focused our downstream analyses on <italic>S. aureus</italic> genes that were significantly regulated in the mixed-species biofilms.<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Select <italic>S. aureus</italic> genes with differential expression during mixed catheter infection with <italic>C. albicans.</italic></p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Gene</th><th align="center" char=".">LFC <sup>a</sup></th><th align="center" char=".">p-value</th><th align="center">ORF description</th><th align="center">Function</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5" align="left"><bold>Biofilm formation</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">sarU</td><td align="char" char=".">2.06</td><td align="char" char=".">0.015</td><td align="left">accessory regulator U</td><td align="left">positive activator of agr</td></tr><tr><td align="left">icaB</td><td align="char" char=".">1.84</td><td align="char" char=".">0.011</td><td align="left">intercellular adhesion protein B</td><td align="left">PIA synthesis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">icaC</td><td align="char" char=".">1.3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.06</td><td align="left">intercellular adhesion</td><td align="left">PIA synthesis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lrgA</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;0.98</td><td align="char" char=".">0.03</td><td align="left">anti-holin like protein</td><td align="left">repressor of autolysis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lrgB</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.2</td><td align="char" char=".">0.038</td><td align="left">anti-holin like protein</td><td align="left">repressor of autolysis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">nuc</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.32</td><td align="char" char=".">0.002</td><td align="left">secreted thermostable nuclease</td><td align="left">degradation of eDNA; biofilm dispersal</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left"><bold>Secreted exotoxins</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">hlgC</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.2</td><td align="char" char=".">0.034</td><td align="left">gamma hemolysin component C</td><td align="left">pore forming toxin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">hlgB</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.31</td><td align="char" char=".">0.0216</td><td align="left">gamma hemolysin component B</td><td align="left">pore forming toxin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">hyl</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.78</td><td align="char" char=".">0.007</td><td align="left">alpha-toxin (alpha-hemolysin)</td><td align="left">pore forming toxin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lukF-PV</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1</td><td align="char" char=".">0.045</td><td align="left">panton-Valentine leucocidin (F)</td><td align="left">pore forming toxin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">lukS-PV</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.6</td><td align="char" char=".">0.0021</td><td align="left">panton-Valentine leucocidin (S)</td><td align="left">pore forming toxin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">USA300HOU-2013</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.81</td><td align="char" char=".">0.0023</td><td align="left">leucocidin subunit</td><td align="left">pore forming toxin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">USA300HOU-2011</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;2.01</td><td align="char" char=".">0.00092</td><td align="left">leucocidin subunit</td><td align="left">pore forming toxin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">sak</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;2</td><td align="char" char=".">0.0027</td><td align="left">staphylokinase</td><td align="left">promotes bacterial dissemination</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5" align="left"><bold>Superantigens and host immune response</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">isaB</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.152</td><td align="char" char=".">0.026</td><td align="left">immunodominant antigen</td><td align="left">elicits immune response &#x02013; during septicemia</td></tr><tr><td align="left">set19</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.2</td><td align="char" char=".">0.024</td><td align="left">superantigen like protein-toxin</td><td align="left">activates immune response</td></tr><tr><td align="left">chp</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.51</td><td align="char" char=".">0.002</td><td align="left">chemotaxis inhibiting protein CHIPS</td><td align="left">inhibits neutrophil chemotaxis</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Emp</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.021</td><td align="left">extracellular matrix protein</td><td align="left">adhesion to host tissue</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ear</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.5</td><td align="char" char=".">0.012</td><td align="left">Ear protein</td><td align="left">superantigen</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AlsS</td><td align="char" char=".">1.28</td><td align="char" char=".">0.025</td><td align="left">immunodominant antigen B</td><td align="left">immune evasion</td></tr><tr><td align="left">cap5E</td><td align="char" char=".">1.92</td><td align="char" char=".">0.04</td><td align="left">capsular polysaccharide biosynthesis</td><td align="left">immune evasion</td></tr><tr><td align="left">capC</td><td align="char" char=".">1.3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.038</td><td align="left">capsular polysaccharide biosynthesis</td><td align="left">immune evasion</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p><bold><italic>S. aureus</italic> lrgB mutant biofilms exhibit accumulation of eDNA in the ECM and enhanced susceptibility to vancomycin upon DNAse treatment of biofilm</bold>. Compared to the WT strain, analysis of 24 hr-biofilms demonstrated reduced metabolic activity (**, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5a</xref>) for the lrgB mutant but comparable biomass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5b</xref>), and slightly reduced susceptibility to higher vancomycin concentrations (WT x &#x02206;lrgB: p =&#x000a0;0.0147 using Multiple Effect analysis; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5c</xref>). In contrast, the lrgA mutant exhibited similar biofilm-forming ability as the WT strain and increased susceptibility was observed for reduced vancomycin concentrations (WT x &#x02206;lrgA: p =&#x000a0;0.0008 using Multiple Effect analysis; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5c</xref>). DNAse treatment of biofilms had no significant impact on the susceptibility of the WT or the &#x02206;lrgA strains to vancomycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5c</xref>); in contrast, DNAse biofilm treatment significantly increased the susceptibility of the &#x02206;lrgB strain to vancomycin (*, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; **, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5c</xref>).<fig id="f0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><bold>Evaluation of biofilm formation of <italic>S. aureus</italic> lrg mutants defective in cell autolysis regulation (&#x02206;lrgA and &#x02206;lrgB)</bold>. <italic>S. aureus</italic> WT and derived mutants &#x02206;lrgA and &#x02206;lrgB biofilms were grown for 24 hrs in the wells of 96-well plates at 37&#x000b0;C. (a) <bold>Biofilm metabolic activity</bold>. Based on MTS assay on 24 hr-biofilms, &#x02206;lrgB exhibited reduced metabolic activity (**, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) compared to the WT strain, whereas &#x02206;lrgA activity was comparable to that of the WT. (b) <bold>Biofilm biomass</bold>. Crystal violet staining indicated comparable biofilm biomass for the mutant strains and WT. (c) <bold>Evaluation of biofilm vancomycin susceptibility with and without DNAse treatment</bold>. 24 hr-biofilms were treated with vancomycin alone or in combination with DNAse (0.625 mg/ml) for 24 hrs and metabolic activity was quantified using the MTS-assay. Based on comparative assessment of metabolic activity of treated and untreated biofilms, &#x02206;lrgB exhibited slightly reduced susceptibility to vancomycin compared to WT (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0147 at 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), which was completely reversed upon DNAse treatment. &#x02206;lrgA was more susceptible to vancomycin than the WT at lower vancomycin concentrations concentrations (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0008 at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml), however no significant effect was seen upon DNAse treatment. Data set obtained in this experiment (C) was analyzed as analyzed by 2-WAY ANOVA using the Multiple Effect analysis (Mixed Model). For all experiments in this figure: *, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; **, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; ns, not significant</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0005_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0005_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p><p><bold><italic>C. albicans-S. aureus</italic> mixed-species biofilm exhibit increased eDNA content compared to single-species biofilms</bold>. eDNA from single species and mixed biofilm was recovered and quantitatively compared using a fluorescence-based kit. As expected, eDNA content recovered from mixed biofilms was significantly higher than that recovered from biofilms formed by <italic>S. aureus</italic> or <italic>C. albicans</italic> alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6a</xref>).<fig id="f0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>(a) <bold>Comparartive evaluation of eDNA content in single- and mixed-species biofilms</bold>. No significant differences in amounts of eDNA was noted in <italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> single species biofilms. Significantly more eDNA was present in mixed biofilms compared to single species biofilms, individually and combined. (b-d) <bold>Effect of DNAse treatment on biofilm structure and <italic>S. aureus</italic> susceptibility to vancomycin</bold>. 24 hr-preformed single- and mixed-species biofilms were treated with vancomycin alone or in combination with DNAse (0.625 mg/m;) for 24 hrs at 37&#x000b0;C. (b) <bold>Vancomycin susceptibility of DNAse-treated and untreated biofilms</bold>. After sonication to disrupt biofilms, cell suspensions were diluted and plated on species-specific media for CFU enumeration. Results show DNAse treatment did not impact <italic>S. aureus</italic> susceptibility to vancomycin in single species biofilm; however, DNAse treatment significantly sensitized <italic>S. aureus</italic> to vancomycin in mixed-species biofilms. DNAse alone was used as negative control and showed no significant effect on biofilm viability compared to untreated controls. (c, d) <bold>CLSM analysis of vancomycin diffusion through DNAse-treated and untreated <italic>S. aureus</italic> single and mixed biofilms</bold>. Fluorescently-labeled vancomycin (green/white) was added to 24 hr pre-formed single- and mixed-species biofilms, with or without DNAse (0.625 mg/ml). <italic>S. aureus</italic> was stained with concanavalin A (ConA; magenta) and <italic>C. albicans</italic> with calcofluor-white (blue). Representative reconstructed Z-stacks are shown. (c) <bold><italic>S. aureus</italic> single-species biofilm</bold>. DNAse treatment resulted in a more dispersed distribution of vancomycin (green/white) throughout the layers of the biofilm. (d) <bold>Mixed-species biofilms of <italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic></bold>. Unlike the effect on <italic>S. aureus</italic> single-species biofilm, DNAse treatment resulted in significant disruption of mixed biofilm structure, which was comcomittant with increase in vancomycin signal (green/white). Bars&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;40&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. For all experiments in this figure: ns, not significant; *, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; **, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; ****, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001. Graph error bars show the standard error of the mean (SEM)</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0006_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0006_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p><p><bold>DNAse treatment of mixed <italic>S. aureus-C. albicans</italic> biofilm enhances vancomycin efficacy against <italic>S. aureus</italic></bold>. To determine whether increase in eDNA contributes to the enhanced <italic>S. aureus</italic> tolerance to vancomycin in mixed biofilm, vancomycin susceptibility testing was performed in the presence of DNAse. Based on CFU counts, DNAse treatment of mixed biofilms significantly sensitized <italic>S. aureus</italic> to vancomycin (*, p &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6b</xref>). In contrast, DNAse did not impact <italic>S. aureus</italic> susceptibility to vancomycin in single-species biofilm. DNAse alone had no significant effect on <italic>S. aureus</italic> viability compared to untreated controls.</p><p><bold>DNAse treatment significantly disrupts mixed-species biofilm impacting vancomycin distribution</bold>. Confocal laser scanning microscopy (CLSM) was performed using fluorescent vancomycin to visualize the effect of DNAse treatment on vancomycin diffusion through single and mixed biofilms. <italic>S. aureus</italic> cells were stained with concanavalin A (ConA; magenta) and <italic>C. albicans</italic> with calcofluor-white (blue). Vancomycin penetration through the biofilms is seen in white and green (overlapping of green in high intensity generates the white color). Compared to untreated <italic>S. aureus</italic> single-species biofilm, biofilm z-stack reconstructions demonstrated that DNAse treatment resulted in a more dispersed distribution of vancomycin (green/white) throughout the layers of <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6c</xref>). In contrast, DNAse treatment of mixed <italic>C. albicans-S. aureus</italic> biofilms resulted in significant disruption in the biofilm structure, and increase in vancomycin presence (green/white) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6d</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0004" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>Mixed fungal-bacterial infections tend to be the most complex and challenging to treat; however, the impact of these interactions on therapy remains largely understudied. <italic>Candida</italic> and <italic>s</italic>taphylococci species are the most common etiological agents isolated from device-associated nosocomial infections, and co-infection with these species poses a significant therapeutic challenge [<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Therefore, it has become crucial to understand the mechanisms of inter-species interactions within the context of polymicrobial infections. However, a major challenge in investigating polymicrobial biofilm-associated infections is the development of suitable animal models that account for host factors, and allow for evaluation of efficacy of treatment strategies under <italic>in vivo</italic> conditions. Therefore, to substantiate our <italic>in vitro</italic> findings on enhanced <italic>S. aureus</italic> antimicrobial tolerance in mixed biofilms with <italic>C. albicans</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>), we modified the established mouse subcutaneous catheter model, which proved to be suitable for sustaining polymicrobial biofilm formation, as demonstrated by SEM analysis of explanted catheters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Fig. 2</xref>, 3) [<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Vancomycin therapy was implemented at clinically relevant therapeutic doses over a period of five days in mice with single-species or mixed-species infected catheters. Comparative assessment of <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from explanted catheters demonstrated inefficacy for vancomycin against <italic>S. aureus</italic> in mice with co-infected catheters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4</xref>). Vancomycin is one of the few antibiotics that have remained effective against methicillin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic>, and development of resistance to vancomycin is relatively rare [<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Therefore, the demonstration of failure of vancomycin against mixed <italic>C. albicans-S. aureus</italic> device infection carries significant clinical implications. Notably, although single-species <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms were statistically susceptible to vancomycin treatment, the level of response was variable among the experimental sets. It is important to note however, that although the subcutaneous catheter infection model is an appropriate and reproducible model to evaluate foreign device biofilm infections and anti-biofilm strategies [<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], one disadvantage is lack of blood flow, which can result in inefficient drug delivery to the biofilm within the catheter. In fact, an initial pilot study indicated no effect for vancomycin on <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovery from single-species biofilms, supporting this concern (data not shown), and therefore, to circumvent this problem, for the therapy experiments, the catheters were cut longitudinally prior to inoculation and implantation in the animals. Neverthelss, despite this limitation, the findings from using the model for <italic>in vivo</italic>-grown polymicrobial biofilms serve as a proof-of-principle underscoring the challenges associated with treatment of device-associated fungal-bacterial infections.</p><p>To provide insights into the mechanisms contributing to the observed therapeutic implications of mixed biofilm infections, we performed RNA-seq analysis to delineate changes in gene expression during polymicrobial infections. The most significant finding from the comparative transcriptome analysis of <italic>S. aureus</italic> was the down-regulation of the repressors of autolysis, lrgA and lrgB (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and Table S1), during mixed catheter infection. eDNA is essential for bacterial biofilm formation and stability, and the majority of eDNA in the biofilm matrix is a result of cell lysis, which are critical for biofilm attachment during the initial stages of development [<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Regulatory mechanisms in <italic>S. aureus</italic> controlling cell death and lysis during biofilm development are mediated by the opposing functions of the cid and lrg operons encoding holin- and antiholin-like proteins, respectively, [<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The lrg operon encoding LrgA and LrgB proteins are the inhibitory counterparts to cid, and a repressor of murein hydrolase activity that hydrolyzes components of the cell wall involved in autolysis. Therefore, down-regulation of lrgAB promotes the activity of the cidA-encoded holin allowing increased activity of murein hydrolases, cell lysis and eDNA production. In fact, the lrgAB mutant was shown to exhibit increased biofilm matrix-associated eDNA, consistent with its role as an inhibitor of cidA-mediated lysis [<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Similarly, staphylococcal thermonuclease (nuc), which was down-regulated during mixed catheter infection, was also shown to be involved in biofilm development, and a nuc mutant was reported to form thicker biofilms containing increased levels of eDNA [<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Therefore, cell lysis and genomic DNA release during biofilm development is regulated <italic>via</italic> opposing activities of the cid and lrg gene products, while staphylococcal thermonuclease functions to degrade the eDNA, possibly as a mean to promote biofilm dispersal.</p><p><italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm formation is a two-step process that requires the adhesion of bacteria to a surface followed by cell-cell adhesion or intercellular aggregation. In staphylococci, the main molecule responsible for intercellular adhesion is the polysaccharide intercellular adhesin (PIA), also called poly-N-acetylglucosamine (PNAG), which together with other polymers such as teichoic acids forms the major part of the extracellular biofilm matrix [<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. PIA biosynthesis is mediated by the intercellular adhesin (ica) locus, <italic>icaADB</italic> and <italic>C</italic>, with the icaB and icaC genes encoding for extracellular membrane proteins, and icaC proposed to be a putative PIA exporter [<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Transcriptome analysis of <italic>S. aureus</italic> recovered from mice with mixed catheter infection demonstrated both icaB and icaC to be upregulated. Regulation of icaADBC is complex and numerous regulatory factors have been implicated, many of which are well-known global transcriptional regulatory factors like SarA and sigmaB [<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. SarA also appears to enhance biofilm formation more directly, by increasing ica expression [<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Interestingly, SarU, a member of the SarA family proteins was found to be up-regulated during mixed catheter infection. Combined, the down-regulation of the lrg operon and nuc, concomitant with the upregulation of the icaADBC-encoded PIA indicate transcriptional activation of the <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm formation regulatory network, induced by the presence of <italic>C. albicans</italic> during mixed biofilm growth.</p><p>It is well established that biofilms are physiologically different from planktonic cells and cells in a biofilm have altered metabolic activity. In a comparative transcriptome analysis to determine which genes are up-regulated in <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm, a study by Resch <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] found that, although the cell envelope appeared to be a very active compartment in biofilm cells as indicated by up-regulation of PIA, virulence factors such as toxins and proteases were up-regulated under planktonic growth conditions but not during biofilm growth. These findings are in line with ours, where a set of host cell-damaging proteins were found to be down-regulated during mixed species infection including gamma-hemolysins (&#x003b3;-hemolysin) HlgAB and HlgCB. Interestingly, staphylococcal alpha-hemolysin (&#x003b1;-hemolysin) encoded by the gene <italic>hla</italic>, also plays a major role in the biofilm formation and appears to be primarily required for cell-to-cell interactions. In fact, a mutant allele of <italic>hla</italic> was shown to initially aid in colonizing a substratum. In addition to hemolysins, <italic>S. aureus</italic> secretes bi-component cytotoxins, Panton-Valentine leukocidins, encoded by the genes <italic>lukSF-PV</italic> composed of two co-transcribed open reading frames (<italic>lukS-PV</italic> and <italic>lukF-PV</italic>), which were also found to be down-regulated during mixed catheter infection [<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Expression and secretion of these factors play specific roles in certain <italic>S. aureus</italic> life stages and diseases, and are tightly controlled by a number of regulatory systems. Most notable is the accessory gene regulator (agr), a well-characterized two-component regulatory system that plays a critical role in the up-regulation and down-regulation of protease and exotoxins, respectively, [<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60&#x02013;62</xref>]. Interestingly, SarU, a positive activator of agr expression, is a member of the SarA family proteins; sarA is a transcriptional regulator that represses extracellular proteases and therefore, the observed elevated sarU expression during mixed catheter infection may result in additional amplification of agr signal, and explain the observed down-regulation of exotoxins in our infection model [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>].</p><p>Interestingly, in contrast to our findings, recent studies by Todd <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] aiming to elucidate observed enhanced mortality during polymicrobial <italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic> intra-abdominal infection, identified <italic>C. albicans</italic>-mediated increase in <italic>S. aureus</italic> secreted alpha- and delta-toxins during polymicrobial infection. Although these factors are important virulence factors in <italic>S. aureus</italic> crucial to its ability to cause systemic and disseminated infections, down-regulation of these factors might contribute to survival, persistence, and growth in a biofilm environment, as was seen in our biofilm infection model. Nevertheless, the contrasting regulation of <italic>S. aureus</italic> exotoxins mediated by <italic>C. albicans</italic> between the two animal models highlights the complex interactions between these two pathogens, and support the notion of niche-specific augmented pathogenesis in a co-infected host.</p><p>It is important to note that previous studies by Peters <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] exploring the mechanism by which <italic>C. albicans</italic> augments <italic>S. aureus</italic> infection during polymicrobial intrabdominal infection, correlated lethal outcomes with exacerbation of host inflammatory responses. These findings are interesting as our transcriptome analysis of mixed-species catheter infection seemed to indicate potential dampening of host immune responses <italic>via</italic> down-regulation of super-antigen like proteins in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, such as the immunodominant surface antigen B (IsaB) which was shown to elicit immune response during septicemia [<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. These findings are in line with the overall perception that biofilms tend to be resistant to host immune defense system [<xref rid="cit0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Interestingly, in addition to contributing to biofilm matrix, PIA molecules, which we found to be up-regulated during mixed catheter infection, also serve to shield cells from neutrophil phagocytosis, thus significantly contributing to biofilm resistance from elimination by innate host defense [<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Most significantly however, was the noted up-regulation of <italic>S. aureus</italic> capsular polysaccharide biosynthesis during mixed catheter infection. The production of capsular polysaccharide by <italic>S. aureus</italic> has been proposed as an anti-phagocytic evasion strategy by inhibiting neutrophil phagocytosis [<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Serotype 5 and 8 capsular polysaccharides predominate among clinical <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates and animal studies have revealed that staphylococcal capsules enhance virulence by impeding phagocytosis. Furthermore, the capsule was also shown to modulate <italic>S. aureus</italic> adherence to surfaces <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>, suggesting that it also promotes bacterial colonization, and persistence in the infected host [<xref rid="cit0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]</p><p>In light of the findings from the transcriptional analysis indicating enhanced <italic>S. aureus</italic> autolysis in mixed biofilms, and given the implication of biofilm eDNA on staphylococcal resistance to antimicrobials, as follow-up studies, we comparatively evaluated the accumulation of eDNA in single- and mixed-species biofilms. Additionally, the effect of eDNA on <italic>S. aureus</italic> response to vancomycin was also evaluated using DNA enzymatic digestion, and mutant strains lacking lrg operon genes. Quantification of eDNA in biofilms indicated a comparable level of eDNA produced by each species in their respective biofilms. In comparison, the total amount of eDNA in the mixed-species biofilms was significantly higher (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6a</xref>). Given that both species produced eDNA and the assay is not specific, it remains speculative at this time to confirm increase in <italic>S. aureus</italic> eDNA specifically in mixed biofilm. It is noteworthy however that eDNA level in mixed biofilms was greater than the combined eDNA concentrations from single-species biofilms (0.2350&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0046 versus 0.216&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00989; p =&#x000a0;0.2592; data not shown). Nevertheless, DNAse treatment of mixed biofilms significantly sensitized <italic>S. aureus</italic> to vancomycin, but had little impact on <italic>S. aureus</italic> susceptibility in single-species biofilm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6b</xref>). The impact of DNAse on mixed biofilms was further demonstrated using confocal laser scanning microscopy where fluorescently-labeled vancomycin diffusion through DNAse treated biofilms caused significant disruption to the mixed biofilm structure, resulting in a more dispersed and accessible distribution of vancomycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6c,D</xref>). Comparative evaluation of biofilm formation using the lrg mutant strains paradoxically demonstrated reduced metabolic activity in lrgB mutant biofilm, but no reduction in biofilm biomass, indicating decrease in cell viability due to increase in cell lysis, without impacting biofilm due to increase in eDNA content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5a-C</xref>). Theses findings were substantiated by the reduced susceptibility of the lrgB mutant to vancomycin, which was reversed upon DNAse treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5c</xref>). It is important to mention that the down-regulation of the lrg operon during <italic>in vivo</italic> grown mixed staphylococcal-<italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm and inc12qqrease in biofilm eDNA content was previously reported by Pammi <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], using a similar model. However, in that study, microarrays were used to delineate changes in <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> gene expression induced by <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Although the authors posited that the enhanced release of eDNA due to increased autolysis would affect antibiotic tolerance, antimicrobial susceptibility assays were not performed <italic>in vitro</italic> or <italic>in vivo</italic>. However, the key role for eDNA in mediating staphylococcal tolerance to antimicrobials in single-species biofilm was clearly demonstrated by subsequent studies by Doroshenko <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="cit0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] and Brackman <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In terms of therapeutic implications of the findings from our study, it is important to note an interesting study by Siala <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] demonstrating that the antifungal caspofungin improves the activity of fluoroquinolones against <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms <italic>in vitro</italic> as well as in a similar subcutaneous biofilm model system as used in our study. Subsequent sequence analysis revealed a shared homology for IcaA with &#x003b2;-1-3-glucan synthase, the enzyme responsible for synthesis of &#x003b2;-1-3-glucan in <italic>C. albicans</italic>, and the target for caspofungin. The findings from the study did in fact show that caspofungin treatment destructured the <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm, and reduced polymerization of matrix polysaccharides increasing drug penetration into biofilms. Hence, the authors proposed that IcaA inhibitors could be useful in the treatment of <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm infections, substantiating the significance of our findings demonstrating up-regulation of the ica operon in mixed biofilms. However, as caspofungin is the drug of choice for treatment of <italic>C. albicans</italic>-biofilm infections, the findings from the study are of even more significance in light of ours identifying an important role for eDNA in the <italic>C. albicans</italic>-mediated enhanced <italic>S. aureus</italic> tolerance to antimicrobials. In fact, eDNA has been described as a promising new target for staphylococcal anti-biofilm treatments [<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and therefore, it is conceivable to speculate that the application of combination DNase-caspofungin treatment may prove effective against mixed <italic>C. albicans</italic>-staphylococci biofilm infections.</p><p>Combined with the findings from our previous studies [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], we propose that in a mixed biofilm, the <italic>C. albicans</italic> polysaccharide matrix, the increase in <italic>S. aureus</italic> matrix components, and interactions <italic>via</italic> secreted chemical moleucles, create a protective environment advantageous to <italic>S. aureus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7</xref>). Therefore, the work presented provides novel mechanistic insights into interspecies interactions in biofilms, with important clinical relevance. We expect the novel findings from this study to further our understanding of the enhanced pathogenesis and resistance of biofilm-associated polymicrobial infections, which may contribute to the development of novel therapeutic strategies targeting these complex infections.<fig id="f0007" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic representation of the proposed mechanisms for the <italic>C. albicans</italic>-mediated enhanced <italic>S. aureus</italic> tolerance to vancomycin</bold>. Previously [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], we proposed a &#x0201c;<italic>Barrier Model</italic>&#x0201d; whereby the <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm matrix, consisting of hyphae and secreted cell wall polysaccharides (&#x003b1;-mannan, &#x003b2;-1,3-glucan and &#x003b2;-1,6 glucan), impedes vancomycin diffusion through the mixed-species biofilm, providing embedded <italic>S. aureus</italic> cells with protection against antimicrobials. However, a subsequent study [<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], indicated a key role for the <italic>C. albicans</italic> secreted quorum sensing molecule farnesol in the enhanced <italic>S. aureus</italic> tolerance to vancomycin, <italic>via</italic> activation of a bacterial stress response. In this current study, we demonstrate that <italic>C. albicans</italic> induces transcriptional modulations in key <italic>S. aureus</italic> regulatory genes involved in biofilm formation, <italic>via</italic> down-regulation of the lrg operon, repressor of autolysis, and up-regulation of the ica operon, resulting in increase in eDNA and extracellular polysaccharide (PIA/PNAG) production, respectively. Therefore, in a mixed biofilm, the <italic>C. albicans</italic> polysaccharide matrix, combined with increase in <italic>S. aureus</italic> matrix components, and interactions <italic>via</italic> secreted chemical molecules, create a protective environment advantageous to <italic>S. aureus.</italic></p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0007_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0007_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4062"><caption><title>Supplemental Material</title></caption><media xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_SM4062.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="s0005" disp-level="1" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></sec><sec id="s0006" disp-level="1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental material</title><p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/21505594.2021.1894834">here</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jabra-Rizk</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Pathogenesis of polymicrobial biofilms</article-title>. <source>Open Mycol J</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jabra-Rizk</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x02019;May</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Polymicrobial Interactions: impact on Pathogenesis and Human Disease</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>213</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sancho</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Artero</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaragoza</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of nosocomial polymicrobial bloodstream infections on the outcome in critically ill patients</article-title>. <source>Europ J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1796</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22167257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Harriott</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noverr</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Importance of Candida-bacterial polymicrobial biofilms in disease</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>563</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21855346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Harriott</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noverr</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Ability of Candida albicans mutants to induce Staphylococcus aureus vancomycin resistance during polymicrobial biofilm formation</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3746</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3755</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20566760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Harriott</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noverr</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title><italic>Candida albicans</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> form polymicrobial biofilms: effects on antimicrobial resistance</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3914</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3922</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jabra-Rizk</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsui</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Candida albicans pathogenesis: fitting within the host-microbe damage response framework</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2724</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2739</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27430274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pfaller</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diekema</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of invasive candidiasis: a persistent public health problem</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>163</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17223626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vila</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sultan</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montelongo-Jauregui</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Oral candidiasis: a disease of opportunity</article-title>. <source>J Fungi (Basel)</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>E15</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31963180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tsui</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jabra-Rizk</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Pathogenesis of Candida albicans biofilm</article-title>. <source>Pathog Dis</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>tw018</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tournu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dijck</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Candida biofilms and the host: models and new concepts for eradication</article-title>. <source>Int J Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2012</volume>:<page-range>1&#x02013;16</page-range>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nett</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andes</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Candida albicans biofilm development, modeling a host-pathogen interaction</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>340</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16815078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wall</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montelongo-Jauregui</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vidal Bonifacio</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Candida albicans biofilm growth and dispersal: contributions to pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zarnowskia</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sancheza</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Community participation in biofilm matrix assembly and function</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>112</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>112</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25535392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nett</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanchez</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cain</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Genetic basis of candida biofilm resistance due to drug-sequestering Matrix Glucan</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>202</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20497051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nett</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanchez</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andes</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Interface of Candida albicans biofilm matrix-associated drug resistance and cell wall integrity regulation</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1660</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1669</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21666076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pierce</surname>
<given-names>CG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vila</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romo</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The Candida albicans biofilm matrix: composition, structure and function</article-title>. <source>J Fungi (Basel)</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof3010014</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harper</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shopsin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Staphylococcus aureus pathogenesis in diverse host environments</article-title>. <source>Path Dis</source>. <year>2017</year>;<fpage>ftx005</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femspd/ftx005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jabra-Rizk</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Community-associated methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus: an enemy amidst us</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e1005837</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27711163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Monaco</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pimentel De Araujo</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cruciani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Worldwide epidemiology and antibiotic resistance of Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>Curr Top Microbiol</source>
<year>2016</year>. <comment>Immunol Epub ahead of print</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Powers</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wardenburg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Igniting the fire: staphylococcus aureus virulence factors in the pathogenesis of sepsis</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1003871</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24550724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wargo</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hogan</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fungal-bacterial interactions: a mixed bag of mingling microbes</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16777473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Morales</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hogan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title><italic>Candida albicans</italic> interactions with bacteria in the context of human health and disease</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1000886</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20442787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Carolus</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dyck</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dijck</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Candida albicans and Staphylococcus species: a threatening twosome</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2162</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31620113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ovchinnikova</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoyer</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Staphylococcus aureus adherence to Candida albicans hyphae is mediated by the hyphal adhesin Als3p</article-title>. <source>Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>158</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2975</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2986</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Otto</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Staphylococcal Biofilms</article-title>. <source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>322</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18453278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pfaller</surname>
<given-names>MND</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diekema</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Azie</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology and outcomes of candidemia in 3648 patients: data from the Prospective Antifungal Therapy (PATH Alliance(R)) registry, 2004-2008</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>74</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23102556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jabra-Rizk</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheper</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Microbial interactions and differential protein expression in Staphylococcus aureus&#x02013;Candida albicans dual-species biofilms</article-title>. <source>FEMS Imm Med Microbiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsui</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuchar&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Commensal Protection of Staphylococcus aureus against Antimicrobials by Candida albicans Biofilm Matrix</article-title>. <source>MBio</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e01365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27729510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuchar&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Dijck</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical implications of oral candidiasis: host tissue damage and disseminated bacterial disease</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>613</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25422264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schlecht</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krom</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Systemic Staphylococcus aureus infection mediated by Candida albicans hyphal invasion of mucosal tissue.</article-title>. <source>Microbiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsui</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuchar&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of Staphylococcus aureus response to antimicrobials by the Candida albicans quorum sensing molecule farnesol</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>e01573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28893777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pammi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hicks</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Biofilm extracellular DNA enhances mixed species biofilms of Staphylococcus epidermidis and Candida albicans</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24228850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Martins</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uppuluri</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Presence of extracellular DNA in the Candida albicans biofilm matrix and its contribution to biofilms</article-title>. <source>Mycopathologia</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20012895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rice</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boles</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <source>Modulation of eDNA release and degradation affects Staphylococcus aureus biofilmm aturation</source>. <publisher-name>PLoS ONE</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ranjit</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Endres</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bayles</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Staphylococcus aureus CidA and LrgA proteins exhibit holin-like properties</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>193</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21421752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rice</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Firek</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nelson</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The Staphylococcus aureus cidAB operon: evaluation of its role in the regulation of murein hydrolase activity and penicillin tolerance</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>185</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2643</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12670989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bayles</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The biological role of death and lysis in biofilm development</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>726</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17694072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Van Den Esker</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kov&#x000e1;cs</surname>
<given-names>&#x000c1;T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuipers</surname>
<given-names>OP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>From cell death to metabolism: holin-antiholin homologues with new functions</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e01963</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29208748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rice</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boles</surname>
<given-names>BR</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of eDNA release and degradation affects Staphylococcus aureus biofilm maturation</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e5822</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19513119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beenken</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dunman</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McAleese</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Global gene expression in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilms</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>186</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>4665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4684</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muir</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of virulence in staphylococcus aureus : molecular mechanisms and remaining puzzles</article-title>. <source>Cell Chem Biol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26971873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>[43]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gillum</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsay</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirsch</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation of the <italic>Candida albicans</italic> gene for orotidine&#x02019;5&#x002b9;-phosphate decarboxylase by complementation of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> ura3 and <italic>E. coli</italic> pyrF mutations</article-title>. <source>Molec Gen Genet</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>198</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6394964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>[44]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vande Velde</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuchar&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schrevens</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Towards non-invasive monitoring of pathogen&#x02013;host interactions during Candida albicans biofilm formation using in vivo bioluminescence</article-title>. <source>Cell Microbiol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>130</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23962311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>[45]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kuchar&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tournu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holtappels</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>In Vivo efficacy of anidulafungin against mature candida albicans biofilms in a novel rat model of catheter-associated candidiasis</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>4474</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4475</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20660685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>[46]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pertea</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pertea</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Transcript-level expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with HISAT, stringtie and ballgown</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1650</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1667</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27560171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>[47]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Anders</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huber</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <chapter-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</chapter-title>. In: <source>Genome Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>. p. <fpage>11</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>[48]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brackman</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Breyne</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Rycke</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The quorum sensing inhibitor Hamamelitannin increases antibiotic susceptibility of Staphylococcus aureus biofilms by affecting peptidoglycan biosynthesis and eDNA release</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>20321</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>[49]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Klotz</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chasin</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Powell</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Polymicrobial bloodstream infections involving Candida species: analysis of patients and review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>406</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17888612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>[50]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vila</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Montelongo-Jauregui</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hussian</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <chapter-title>Comparative evaluations of the pathogenesis of Candida auris phenotypes and Candida albicans using clinically relevant murine models of infections</chapter-title>. In: <source>mSphere</source>. <year>2020</year>. p. <fpage>5</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0051"><label>[51]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filipe</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tomasz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Fluorescence ratio imaging microscopy shows decreased access of vancomycin to cell wall synthetic sites in vancomycin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>3627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3633</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0052"><label>[52]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Okshevsky</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rikke</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of extracellular DNA in the establishment, maintenance and perpetuation of bacterial biofilms</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24303798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0053"><label>[53]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beltrame</surname>
<given-names>CO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>C&#x000f4;rtes</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonelli</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Inactivation of the autolysis-related genes lrgB and yycI in Staphylococcus aureus increases cell lysis-dependent eDNA release and enhances biofilm development in vitro and in vivo</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e0138924</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26406329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0054"><label>[54]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cue</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lei</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>CY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic regulation of the intercellular adhesion locus in staphylococci</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22919618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0055"><label>[55]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Gara</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>ica and beyond: biofilm mechanisms and regulation in Staphylococcus epidermidis and Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>270</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17419768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0056"><label>[56]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Valle</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toledo-Arana</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berasain</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>SarA and not sigmaB is essential for biofilm development by Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1075</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1087</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12753197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0057"><label>[57]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Resch</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenstein</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nerz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Differential gene expression profiling of Staphylococcus aureus cultivated under biofilm and planktonic conditions</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>2663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2676</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15870358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0058"><label>[58]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Guerra</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borgogna</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Epic immune battles of history: neutrophilsvs.Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28713774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0059"><label>[59]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vandenesch</surname>
<given-names>FGL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henry</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Staphylococcus aureus hemolysins, bi-component leukocidins, and cytolytic peptides: a redundant arsenal of membrane-damaging virulence factors?</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0060"><label>[60]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Paulander</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Varming</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bojer</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The agr quorum sensing system in Staphylococcus aureus cells mediates death of sub-population</article-title>. <source>BMC Res Notes</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>503</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30041686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0061"><label>[61]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>George</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muir</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of agr quorum sensing in virulent staphylococci</article-title>. <source>Chembiochem</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>855</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17457814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0062"><label>[62]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between the agr locus and the presence of virulence genes and pathogenesis in Staphylococcus aureus using a Caenorhabditis elegans model</article-title>. <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27915107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0063"><label>[63]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Manna</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheung</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>sarU, a sarA homolog, is repressed by SarT and regulates virulence genes in Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12496184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0064"><label>[64]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Todd</surname>
<given-names>OA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noverr</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <chapter-title>Candida albicans impacts Staphylococcus aureus alpha-toxin production via extracellular alkalinizatio</chapter-title>. In: <source>mSphere</source>. <year>2019</year>. p. <fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0065"><label>[65]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Todd</surname>
<given-names>OA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fidel</surname>
<given-names>JPL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harro</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <chapter-title>Candida albicans augments Staphylococcus aureus virulence by engaging the staphylococcal agr quorum sensing system</chapter-title>. In: <source>mBio</source>. <year>2019</year>. p. <fpage>10</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0066"><label>[66]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noverr</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Candida albicans-Staphylococcus aureus polymicrobial peritonitis modulates host innate immunity</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2189</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23545303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0067"><label>[67]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lorenz</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohlsen</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karch</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Human antibody response during sepsis against targets expressed by methicillin resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0068"><label>[68]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Garcia-Perez</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Math&#x000e9;</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Humblet-Baron</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <chapter-title>A Framework for understanding the evasion of host immunity by Candida biofilms</chapter-title>. In: <source>Front Immunol</source>. <year>2018;</year>. p. <fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0069"><label>[69]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Riordan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Staphylococcus aureus capsular polysaccharides</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>234</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14726462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0070"><label>[70]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Doroshenko</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tseng</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howlin</surname>
<given-names>RP</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Extracellular DNA impedes the transport of vancomycin in Staphylococcus epidermidis biofilms preexposed to subinhibitory concentrations of vancomycin</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>7273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25267673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0071"><label>[71]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Siala</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuchar&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>SAB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vleugels</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The antifungal caspofungin increases fluoroquinolone activity against Staphylococcus aureus biofilms by inhibiting N-acetylglucosamine transferase</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms13286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>