<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The expression profiling of these 97 genes that fragment the Golgi showed two main Golgi fragmentation subsets within the Golgi genes. The first GF-subset of genes (56 genes) demonstrated upregulation in Cluster 3. The second GF-subset (15 genes) demonstrated upregulation in Cluster 4. The remaining genes (26 genes) showed either a stable low expression or unclear expression pattern across all clusters (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01399-f005">Figure 5</xref>a). This could suggest that cells in Cluster 4 exhibit a high likelihood of Golgi fragmentation whereas cells in Cluster 3 exhibit a high likelihood of Golgi condensation. DEGs between clusters 3 and 4 were extracted by a two-class unpaired response test using SAMseq (FDR &lt; 0.05 and fold change &gt; 1). Five genes (
 <italic>RPS27A</italic>, 
 <italic>TUBA1B</italic>, 
 <italic>RPL4</italic>, 
 <italic>RPL34</italic> and 
 <italic>RPS12</italic>) have been classified as significantly upregulated in Cluster 3, whereas 748 genes were significantly upregulated in Cluster 4 (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-22-01399">Supplementary Data S2</xref>). During the dissemination of breast cancer cells, they exhibit a loss of epithelial characteristics, which routinely is accompanied by upregulation of mesenchymal genes. This process is known as epithelial–mesenchymal transition (EMT). Several studies highlighted a strong association between the expression of EMT genes in circulating breast cancer cells and cancer progression, invasion and metastasis [
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. To investigate this association, we profiled the expression of 20 genes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-01399-f005">Figure 5</xref>b). These genes were nominated as EMT markers by Zhao and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B90-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Seven EMT genes (
 <italic>AKT1</italic>, 
 <italic>EGFR</italic>, 
 <italic>EPAS1</italic>, 
 <italic>ERBB2</italic>, 
 <italic>HIF1A</italic>, 
 <italic>SMAD3</italic> and 
 <italic>MET</italic>) were relatively upregulated in Cluster 3 comparing to Cluster 4. 
</p>
