<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the results of the differentially expressed gene analysis, the results of the two DEG groups were compared, and DEGs were defined with opposite expressions in the two groups as genes affected by RSV treatment in TNBC cells. Moreover, WB showed that apoptosis related proteins like Cleaved-Caspase 3 and BCL-2 were detected in MDA-MB-231 treated by RSV. In tumor therapy, apoptosis is a well-known mechanism of cell death, involving the activation of caspases (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Caspases are key mediators in programmed cell death or apoptosis, where caspase 3 catalyzes the specific cleavage of many key cellular proteins (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Additionally, BCL2 is originally characterized with respect to their roles in controlling outer mitochondrial membrane integrity and apoptosis (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The high expression of BCL2 is closely related to tumorigenesis, and the overexpression of BCL2 family proteins promotes the occurrence and development of tumors, while its inhibition is related to anti-tumor characteristics (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). These results indicate that RSV can reduce the survival rate of TNBC cells by promoting apoptosis. To this effect, a functional enrichment analysis showed that genes affected by the corresponding RSV in the treatment of TNBC were significantly involved in both the apoptotic signal pathway and P53 signal pathway. P53 is a tumor suppressor protein that regulates the expression of various genes including apoptosis, growth inhibition, inhibition of cell cycle progression, differentiation, and accelerated DNA repair (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). In general, p53 can regulate cell growth by promoting apoptosis and DNA repair under stress. However, when p53 mutates, it loses its regulatory function, leading to abnormal cell proliferation and tumor progression (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Apoptosis refers to programmed cell death, resulting in the orderly and effective removal of damaged cells, such as DNA damage or cell damage caused during development (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Apoptosis may be triggered 
 <italic>via</italic> intracellular signals (such as genotoxic stress) or external signals (such as the binding of ligands to cell surface death receptors) (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Deregulation of apoptotic cell death mechanisms is a feature of cancer. Here, the genes of TNBC cells treated by RSV were found to be significantly involved in signal pathways like apoptosis and P53, suggesting that RSV can activate apoptosis of TNBC cells.
</p>
