<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies have shown that POLD1 may be associated with the malignant proliferation of tumor cells and that a high expression of POLD1 is associated with the poor prognosis of breast cancer (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The present study found that the low expression of POLD1 in TNBC cells treated by RSV may be related to the treatment of RSV. Further experimentation demonstrated that as the RSV treatment concentration rose, the protein expression of POLD1 in TNBC cells gradually decreased. Molecular docking suggested that RSV may bind to POLD1, and POLD1 possesses a strong correlation with DEGs in the apoptotic pathway. Hence, a comprehensive regulatory landscape of RSV-treated TNBC cells was constructed. According to the network, POLD1 was observed to interact with ATM, which is a DNA damage response gene commonly mutated in cancer. ATM activation serves as a key factor in balancing between aging and apoptosis as well as autophagy (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). In this study, ATM was found to be highly expressed in RSV affected MDA-MB-231 cells, which may be related to its apoptosis promoting mechanism. A rescue experiment was then performed with POLD1 overexpression, demonstrating that the expression levels of POLD1, PCNA, and BCL-2 in MDA-MB-231 cells treated with RSV after the overexpression of POLD1 were higher than those in the RSV treated group, while the levels of Cleaved-Caspase3 and Cleaved-PARP1 reduced. Among them, PCNA was considered to be a molecular marker of proliferation due to its role in replication (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Here, the expression of PCNA treated with RSV decreased, while the proliferation ability of POLD1 overexpression treatment was relatively high, indicating that POLD1 has an effect on the proliferation of TNBC cells. In addition, PARP1 was discovered to be a molecular target of anti-tumor drugs. In melanoma, breast cancer, lung cancer, and other neoplastic diseases, the expression of PARP1 is often increased (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Therefore, the corresponding results demonstrate that POLD1 overexpression could reduce the apoptosis effect of RSV on MDA-MB-231 cells. Moreover, CCK8 and flow cytometry revealed that RSV can promote TNBC cell apoptosis, while the overexpression of POLD1 can reduce the apoptosis effect of RSV on MDA-MB-231 cells, further suggesting that RSV can mediate TNBC cell apoptosis by reducing the expression of POLD1.
</p>
