<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While sensitivity to the local structure around the metal center makes XAS an important tool for understanding the structure of TMNC materials, the heterogeneity of these catalysts and the sample-averaging nature of the XAS method is a serious obstacle. Commonly, Fe–N
 <sub>4</sub> species are considered to be important for the ORR activity of Fe-based TMNC materials, as demonstrated in refs (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref149">149</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref325">325</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref327">327</xref>, and 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref526">526</xref>−
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref533">533</xref>) using the XAS method and arguments similar to those presented in 
 <xref rid="sec6.1.5" ref-type="other">Section 
  <xref rid="sec6.1.5" ref-type="other">6.1.5</xref>
 </xref>. In particular, a good agreement between experimental Fe K-edge XANES spectra for TMNC catalysts and the results of theoretical XANES modeling for the Fe–N
 <sub>4</sub> moiety was demonstrated.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref149">149</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref327">327</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref526">526</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref534">534</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, contrary reports also exist that emphasize the role of CN
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> motifs and carbon-encapsulated Fe NPs. For example, Singh et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref524">524</xref>
 </sup> compared the ORR performance of two catalysts, Fe–C–N and CN
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>, where the latter was prepared by leaching the Fe-species with acid, although some Fe impurities still remained in the CN
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> sample. Both catalysts exhibited activity toward ORR, although XANES and EXAFS analysis suggested very different local environment for Fe in both cases, namely, carbide- or nitride-like structures in the Fe–C–N sample, and the presence of residual metallic Fe species in the CN
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> catalyst. This observation revealed that the Fe–N
 <sub>4</sub> species are at least not the only possible active species in the Fe-based TMNC materials.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref524">524</xref>
 </sup> Similarly, linear combination analysis of Fe K-edge XANES spectra from Fe-based TMNC materials carried out by Kobayashi et al. to quantify the contributions of different Fe species before and after the acid leaching demonstrated that even when the Fe–N
 <sub>4</sub> motifs were leached out, the catalyst remained active for ORR.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref535">535</xref>
 </sup> Selective poisoning of these type of catalysts using Cl
 <sub>2</sub> and H
 <sub>2</sub> treatments was employed by Varnell et al. to find the active species.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref272">272</xref>
 </sup> It was discovered that the Cl
 <sub>2</sub> treatment deactivated the catalyst, while H
 <sub>2</sub> restored its activity. Mössbauer spectra showed no Fe–N
 <sub>4</sub> species in the active H
 <sub>2</sub>-treated sample, while multiple Fe-containing species were present in the as-prepared sample. XANES and EXAFS analysis have shown that the Cl
 <sub>2</sub>-treated inactive catalyst had a structure similar to that of FeCl
 <sub>3</sub>·(H
 <sub>2</sub>O)
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub>. XANES and EXAFS analyses of the active samples (as-prepared and reactivated by H
 <sub>2</sub>-treatment) showed that Fe is predominantly metallic and has a bcc structure. From multiple-shell EXAFS data fitting and analysis of Fe–Fe CNs, it was concluded that Fe is present as 1–2 nm NPs, which was confirmed with TEM. These findings suggest that carbon-encapsulated Fe NPs can be active for ORR even in the absence of Fe–N
 <sub>4</sub> structural motifs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref272">272</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
