<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coexistence of two or more active metal ion centers in close proximity has been demonstrated to further improve the catalyst activity. For example, a Co-based TMNC material synthesized from a bimetallic-organic framework precursor showed activity 12-times higher than that of a conventional Co–N
 <sub>4</sub>-type catalyst, which was explained by the presence of Co
 <sub>2</sub>N
 <sub>5</sub> structural motifs, and whose signature (shortened Co–Co bond) was detected in the analysis of Co K-edge EXAFS spectra.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref543">543</xref>
 </sup> Enhanced catalytic performance is expected also for catalysts containing metal-ion centers of different types, especially those combining Fe and Co centers.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref506">506</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref544">544</xref>
 </sup> ORR catalysts prepared via high-temperature pyrolysis of a Co–Fe–N chelate complex were studied in ref (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref545">545</xref>). EXAFS measurements indicated that Fe–N
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> and Co–N
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> species do not survive the pyrolysis and form metallic clusters, which are removed during the subsequent acid treatment. The observed ORR activity was thus attributed to carbon species on the catalyst surface.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref545">545</xref>
 </sup> In contrast, more recent studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref546">546</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref548">548</xref>
 </sup> revealed that coexisting Fe–N
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> and Co–N
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> moieties can be stabilized, resulting in enhanced activity. The indicators of the presence of heterometallic species can be sometimes observed in the EXAFS data,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref547">547</xref>
 </sup> although they are hard to discriminate from metal–metal contributions due to the formation of larger metallic clusters.
</p>
