<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our data identified proteins related to biofilm growth that have previously been uncharacterized. iTRAQ analyses showed that the regulation of metabolism plays a key role during 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm growth. First, the iTRAQ quantitative data revealed that carbohydrate metabolism may be particularly important during 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm growth. It was reported that fructose bisphosphate aldolase and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase were significantly decreased in 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> biofilms (Allan et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In our study, there was a &gt;two-fold increase of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase in the tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation. In addition, the levels of fructose bisphosphate aldolase (fold change: 0.62) were down-regulated. It was reported that phosphoglycerate kinase was up-regulated in 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilms compared with planktonic cells by comparative proteomic analysis (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Similarly, biofilms of 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (Sauer et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus xylosu</italic>s (Planchon et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) exhibit up-regulated phosphoglycerate kinase. There was a &gt;11-fold increase in the level of phosphoglycerate kinase in the tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation. Phosphoglycerate kinase is a glycolytic enzyme that functions in the conversion of glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate into 1, 3-diphosphoglycerate. Glycolysis may play a pivotal role during 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm growth. Furthermore, histidine metabolism may play an important role in biofilm formation. Histidine kinase (fold change: 1.62) was up-regulated in the tylosin-inhibited biofilm formation. Compared with other amino acids, L-His had the strongest effect on biofilm induction (Cabral et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Histidine metabolism is also found to be involved in biofilm formation and is confirmed by gene disruption (Cabral et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Histidine kinase is an important signaling molecule in biofilm formation in gram-positive and negative bacteria (McLoon et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Shemesh and Chai, 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Grau et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In addition, several ABC transporter system proteins were significantly up-regulated in the tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation. This finding is consistent with the previous results of our laboratory showing that sub-MIC erythromycin inhibits 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation (Zhao et al., 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The carbohydrate substrate selection and fermentation determine ABC transporter proteins were significantly up-regulated in tylosin-treated cells, suggesting that 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> had the capability of metabolizing a wide range of carbohydrates during biofilm development (Hardy et al., 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Marion et al., 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Bidossi et al., 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Haertel et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Moreover, ABC transporters are important because they regulate respiration and biofilm formation, which in turn affect the rate of electricity production and bioremediation (Selvaraj et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Furthermore, in the mutants of a 
 <italic>pneumococcal</italic> biofilm screen, ABC transporters were shown to be defective in colonization (Munoz-Elias et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).
</p>
