<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cell surface proteins play a crucial role in biofilms. Within the biofilm, bacterial cells are embedded in a self-produced extracellular matrix. This matrix protects bacteria against a number of environmental insults. However, the matrix also confines bacterial access to fresh nutrients. Thus, the verified increase in the expression of transmembrane channels appears to be an essential requirement for the entrance of important nutrient-containing fluid (Costerton et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). In addition to acting, as channels, porins may act as potential targets for adhesion to other cells and may mediate cell attachment through binding to the proteins released for biofilm formation (Dallo et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The outer membrane proteins may mediate cell attachment through binding to the released proteins for biofilm formation. Membrane proteins such as OmpA mediate cell adhesion in 
 <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (Dallo et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The key developmental stages of biofilm development have been reported to be adhesion to surfaces, aggregation of micro colonies, and further expansion of the microbial community. The putative involvement of many genes encoding large cell surface proteins is adhesion to the epithelium and biofilm formation (Pridmore et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Walter et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Frese et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Pham (Pham et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) found increased expression of outer membrane proteins in the 
 <italic>Tannerella forsythia</italic> biofilm cells by using quantitative non-gel-based proteomic techniques. In our study, the expression of membrane-anchored lipoprotein, phosphoglycerate kinase, sugar ABC transporter permease, ABC superfamily ATP binding cassette transporter membrane protein and L-fucose isomerase changed; these proteins belong to membrane proteins and cell-surface proteins and might be involved in some molecular functions including catalytic activity, motor activity, nucleotide binding, protein binding and transporter activity. For example, phosphoglycerate kinase is a 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> surface protein that promotes cell adhesion and plays a key role in bacterial infection and invasion (Brassard et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Wang and Lu, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). We predicted that these membrane proteins might affect the bacterial cell-cell interaction. Thus, membrane proteins might play a significant role in biofilm formation.
</p>
