<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par53">In this study, we investigated TUBA1C expression levels in various types of tumors, which were identified from the TCGA database by using TIMER algorithm. Compared to normal tissues, TUBA1C expression was found to be higher in the following types of tumors: BLCA, BRCA, CHOL, COAD, ESCA, HWSC, KIRC, KIRP, LIHC, LUAD, LUSC, PRAD, READ, STAD, THCA, and UCEC (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). The data of LUAD patients was acquired from TCGA database and used to estimate the prognosticative value of TUBA1C. Our main goal was to figure out whether TUBA1C can be used as a prognosticative biomarker. Furthermore, we found that the expression of TUBA1C was extremely higher in LUAD than in normal tissues. (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). As shown in Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c and 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>g, the KM survival curve exhibited a high expression of TUBA1C in LUAD tissues, which indicated a poor prognosis of LUAD. Age, tumor grade, lymph node metastasis, and TUBA1C expression were considered as independent prognostic factors in multivariable analysis, which is illustrated as a forest boxplot in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d. By using the GEPIA database, we found that TUBA1C expression was significantly related to the following parameters: different disease states (tumor or normal) (P &lt; 0.05), pathological stage (P = 1.82e−04), overall survival (P = 3.8e−0.5), and disease-free survival (P = 0.047) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). By performing immunohistochemical analysis, we found that the expression level of TUBA1C was higher in tumor tissues than in normal tissues (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a–f). From our data, there is no correlation between the level of TUBA1C expression and clinicopathological parameters of lung adenocarcinoma (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Multivariable analysis demonstrated that only the TUBA1C expression was an independent prognostic factor in lung adenocarcinoma (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>h). All these findings suggest that TUBA1C is a prognostic biomarker of LUAD.
</p>
