<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par54">In this study, we found that various immune infiltration levels of LUAD could induce different expression levels of TUBA1C. By using CIBERSORT algorithm, we found that TUBA1C expression is strongly associated with infiltration levels of following immune cells: activated B cell, activated CD4 T cell, central memory CD4 T cell, effector memory CD8 T cell, eosinophils, gamma-delta T cell, immature B cell, immature dendritic cell, mast cell, memory B cell, natural killer T cell, regulatory T cell and type 2 T-helper cell (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Furthermore, TIMER and GEPIA databases showed how gene markers of different immune cells were related to TUBA1C expression. This may indicate that the tumor immune microenvironment (Tables 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) of LUAD was regulated by TUBAC1. It is a well-known fact that T cells and B cells comprise about two-thirds of lung TIICs, while the remaining lung TIICs are composed of tumor-associated macrophages (TAMs) and a small number of infiltrating dendritic cells and natural killer cells (NK) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Previous studies have thoroughly investigated the role of tumor- associated T cells in the development of lung cancer. These studies have reported that CD4 + Th1 cells and activated CD8 + T cells often elicited type I immune responses, which indicate a favorable prognosis of LUAD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]; however, Th2, Th17, and Foxp3 + regulatory T (Treg) cells were found to be associated with tumor progression and unfavorable prognosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In lung cancer patients, the tumor-infiltrating B cells have their own anti-tumor immunity. Moreover, the tumor-infiltrating B lymphocytes have been observed at all stages of lung cancer development. However, their morphology differed according to the stages of lung cancer and their histological subtypes. This indicates that B cells dominate during the progression of lung cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Many studies have proved that the expression level of many genes is related to poor prognosis and TIICs. By analyzing the TIMER database, we found that the expression of TUBA1C is negatively correlated to B cells and CD4 + T cells. These results indicate a poor prognosis of LUAD (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b, c).
</p>
