<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55">Although TUBA1C is a tubulin, we still do not know the mechanism through it regulates LUAD. First, we analyzed the protein-coding genes related to TUBA1C and its co-expression genes in LADC tissues. The top 10 protein-coding genes that positively correlated with TUBA1C are as follows: TUBA1B, PLK1, BIRC5, CCNA2, CCNB1, EPR1, MAD2L1, RAN, SKA3, and PACGAP1. On the other hand, the top 10 negatively correlated genes are as follows: CIRBP, VAMP2, CBX7, NICN1, C5orf53, FRY, CRY2, GNG7, CD302, and FXYD1 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Furthermore, STRING and Gene MANIA databases illustrated the protein interaction between TUBA1C and other partners (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The proteins related to TUBA1C perform following biological functions: they regulate the cell cycle, mitosis, DNA damage response, cell proliferation, and aging. Thereafter, GO and KEGG pathway analysis revealed that an up-regulated expression of TUBA1C is primarily related to cell cycle, p53 signaling pathway, glycolysis, and gluconeogenesis (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Previous studies have also reported that TUBA1C is associated with cell proliferation, and it also regulates cell cycle in many types of cancers. Furthermore, the expression of TUBA1C was reported to be correlated with p53 expression in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Previous studies have reported that tubulin regulates cell metabolism and glucose stress response, reducing the dependence of cells on glycolysis. These events ultimately promote cell survival in cancer patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. These results are helpful to understand the biological role played by TUBA1C in the development of LUAD. In future clinical practice, the expression of TUBA1C in lung adenocarcinoma tissue may be used to predict the prognosis and the efficacy of immunotherapy of patients.
</p>
