<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>By interrogating the proteome of the hypothalamic GT1-7 cell line as a model for studying AAS-induced regulatory processes of reproduction, we found that anabolic steroids modulate proteins associated to metabolism, cytoarchitecture, cellular homeostasis and hormonal regulation. Regarding possible direct androgen actions, it is worth mentioning that several of the identified proteins have androgen-response elements (ARE’s). Specifically, the Androgen Responsive Gene Database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://argdb.fudan.edu.cn" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://argdb.fudan.edu.cn</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] revealed that proteins involved in metabolism (GAPDH, PGAM1, ENOA) stress response (STIP1, HSP90B) drug detoxification (GSTM1-2), protein modification (PEBP1, PPIA, PDIA6), and signaling pathway (ERK), contain ARE’s. Although our findings provide a comprehensive molecular evaluation of how AAS might affect neurosecretory hypothalamic neurons, it is noteworthy to mention that 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies using cell lines provide limitations when extrapolating results 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. Among the limitations in our study is the lack of complexity in the intact hypothalamic architecture, including afferent connections from distinct hypothalamic nuclei and neurons. In this scenario, it is still missing the neuronal interaction through neuropeptide/neurotransmitter signaling between GnRH neurons, feeding-related neurons and those from the suprachiasmatic nucleus. Despite these limitations, cell lines have proven themselves to be good models that are helpful in order to understand the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> complexity by providing a simpler system that is easy to maintain. This system has a homogeneous population of neurons, where controllable variables can be studied [
 <xref rid="pone.0180409.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Therefore, differentially expressed proteins found in our study represent potential biomarkers of GnRH hypothalamic neurons for the detection of AAS-induced changes in reproductive function. It is then suggested that in steroid abusers, typical biological processes related to reproduction might be compromised through: i) activation of the biological machinery to reestablish cellular homeostasis after stressful and metabolic events, and/or ii) cellular proliferation and migration that might induce tumorigenic activity. Future studies will be needed to test these modulated proteins against the physiology of reproduction.
</p>
