<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Opisthorchis viverrini</italic> affects over 10 million people in different countries of Greater Mekong sub-region including Thailand, southern Vietnam, Lao PDR and Cambodia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In addition to the problems associated with infection in the definitive human host, chronic inflammation caused by this parasite has been strongly associated with development of cholangiocarcinoma (CCA, a fatal bile duct cancer). Indeed, the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC) has recognized 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>viverrini</italic> as a group I carcinogen [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The complex life cycle of the parasite involves piscivorous mammals (humans, cats and dogs) as definitive hosts, and prosobranch snails of the genus 
 <italic>Bithynia</italic> and freshwater cyprinid fish as first and second intermediate hosts, respectively. Snails become infected by the ingestion of parasite eggs, after which the miracidia hatch from the eggs and, subsequently, penetrate snail tissues developing into sporocysts, which undergo asexual reproduction through the stages of rediae and cercariae. The cercariae exit the snails and penetrate the skin of cyprinid fish hosts to encyst in the muscle and form metacercariae, the infective stage for humans, and which are acquired upon ingestion of undercooked or raw fish [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In the endemic regions of northeast Thailand, there is a high prevalence of 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>viverrini</italic> infection in humans and fish, although the prevalence of infected 
 <italic>Bithynia</italic> snails is low [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It has been found that the level of 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>viverrini</italic> infection in 
 <italic>Bithynia siamensis goniomphalos</italic> decreases over time, going from 62% infectivity at day 1 to less than 20% at 56 days post infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
