<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present study, we applied state-of-the-art mass spectrometry methodologies such as sequential window acquisition of all theoretical spectra (SWATH-MS) to quantify the protein profiles in the hemolymph of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>siamensis goniomphalos</italic> experimentally infected with 
 <italic>O</italic>. 
 <italic>viverrini</italic>. SWATH-MS, a novel technique in mass spectrometry, has recently shown excellent quantitation precision [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. This technique combines the advantage of precise quantitative accuracy of traditional shotgun proteomics and reproducibility of targeted data analysis similar to that obtained with selected reaction monitoring (SRM) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The SWATH-MS technique is performed in two separate steps. The first step (called label-free shotgun or data dependent acquisition (DDA) involves a label-free shotgun approach to create a library of precursors and transitions that are used in a second step (called data independent acquisition –DIA) to quantify proteins in a selected reaction monitoring (SRM) approach from any other sample [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In addition, this technique has been used for the identification and proteome-wide quantification of the different proteins in a complex protein sample [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. While the use of labeled quantitative proteomics techniques such as iTRAQ in 
 <italic>Bythinia</italic>-
 <italic>Opisthorchis</italic> interactions has proven to be valuable [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], the SWATH-MS technique is a compelling alternative to iTRAQ for protein quantitation of complex mixtures [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005104.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. By characterizing the differential protein expression in the hemolymph of fluke-infected 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>siamensis goniomphalos</italic> we have shed light on the molecular basis of the early stages of snail-parasite interactions, and provided information that might lead to the development of novel intervention tools to control parasite transmission by targeting the snail host stage.
</p>
