<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The intestinal extracellular matrix (ECM) is majorly constituted of collagen and is vital for the regulation of cell division, differentiation, proliferation, migration, growth, and apoptosis which signify its cruciality across the development and progression of cancer (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al., 2001</xref>). Collagen type XI alpha 1 (COL11A1) is a minor fibrillary collagen protein, that represents one of the two alpha chains of type XI collagen. Mutations in the COL11A1 gene and/or translational overexpression of COL11A1 protein due to the signaling defects are considered as the essential contributors of carcinogenesis in human colorectal cancer (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Raglow and Thomas, 2015</xref>). In this context, higher expression of COL11A1 protein has been reported in the cancerous tissue and has been found to be linked with poor progression-free and overall survival across the various types of cancers (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Raglow and Thomas, 2015</xref>). A microarray-based study reveals that the COL11A1 gene is associated with the disease progression and poor survival in ovarian cancer and regulates cell invasiveness required for tumor formation (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2014</xref>). Further studies have also established that COL11A1 gene attributes as a prognostic biomarker for human carcinoma-associated stromal cells and also stimulates cancer progression in lungs, breast, gastrointestinal tract, and pancreas (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">García-Pravia et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Vázquez-Villa et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Li A. et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Toss et al., 2019</xref>). All these reports collectively suggest that overexpression of COL11A1 in different cancerous tissues results in metastasis and recurrence of several human cancers (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">García-Pravia et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Vázquez-Villa et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Li A. et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Toss et al., 2019</xref>). COL11A1 is a highly specific biomarker of activated cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAFs) which remains conserved for epithelial cancer irrespective of the site and transformation within the cell undergoing neoplastic transformation, indicating that targeting fibroblast activation could be an effective therapeutic strategy for various cancer (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2016</xref>). In an another study, the COL11A1 along with the other two genes viz. THBS2 and INHBA have been found to be overexpressed in colon tissue indicating invasion-facilitated alteration in proteolysis of the extracellular matrix and used for developing high specificity biomarkers sensing cancer invasion and determining response against potential multi-cancer metastasis and therapeutic target (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2010</xref>). Particularly for colorectal cancer, previous researchers revealed that the expression of the COL11A1 gene is upregulated up to several folds in the stromal cells of affected colonic mucosa in comparison to the normal tissue (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al., 2001</xref>). Studies on left-sided and right-sided colon cancer, it has been found that COL11A1, TWIST1, insulin-like 5, and chromogranin A were upregulated across the right-sided colon cancer more significantly than that of the left-sided cancer, with a sharp downregulation in 3β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase protein (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2019</xref>). Several experiments on the transformed cells also display significant alteration in a number of cellular signaling pathways, including Wnt, TGF-β, RTK-RAS-PI3K, and TP53 signaling pathways which might be the crucial contributors of the neoplastic transformation (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Koveitypour et al., 2019</xref>). Although all these various studies imply that the COL11A1 gene is crucial in the progression of various cancer, however, the actual significance across the various clinicopathological factors including cancer-stage, nodal metastasis status, age group, etc., have not been documented comprehensively till date.
</p>
