<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">To uncover why 
 <italic>TFIIF</italic> was upregulated in the mandarin fish of Group X, the expressions of histone methyltransferases were analyzed based on transcriptome. The expression of histone-lysine N-methyltransferase 
 <italic>ezh1</italic> was significantly decreased in the Group X. Histone methyltransferases EZH1 and EZH2 catalyze the tri-methylation of H3K27, which serves as an epigenetic signal for chromatin condensation and transcriptional repression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In mice, Ezh1 was required for neonatal heart regeneration after myocardial infarction and overexpression of Ezh1 promoted heart regeneration by upregulating cardiac muscle growth genes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Furthermore, we observed the protein level of tri-methylation of histone H3 at lysine 27 was lower in the Group X, suggesting an active function of gene expression. The decreased abundance of histone H3K27me3 was also found in 
 <italic>FOXO1</italic> (
 <italic>forkhead box protein O1</italic>) in HFD (high fat diets) fed rats, which persisted even after 8 weeks of diet reversal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. In addition, the total DNA methylation level of 
 <italic>TFIIF</italic> was significantly higher in the mandarin fish of Group X than those of Group W. The mRNA level of 
 <italic>TFIIF</italic> was higher in fish of Group X, our results showed a positive effect of DNA methylation on gene expression. In soybean, the genome-wide methylation profiles showed that hyper-methylated genes had higher gene expression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], in ventricular septal defect patients, genome-wide DNA methylation data showed 12 hypermethylated genes had a higher gene expression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In Arabidopsis, upon loss of CpG methylation, there was target-specific enrichment of H3K27me3 in heterochromatin that correlated with transcriptional reactivation, it is suggested that there was an antagonistic effect between CpG methylation and H3K27me3 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. It is hypothesized that the lower 
 <italic>ezh1</italic> expression in the mandarin fish of Group X, could be contributed to the decreased methylation at ‘Lys-27’ of histone H3, and then up-regulating the expression and methylation of 
 <italic>TFIIF</italic> gene.
</p>
