<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0040">The MAPK cascade consists of MAPK kinase kinases (MAPKKKs), MAPK kinases (MAPKKs) and MAPK [
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. These are basically serine/threonine kinases (STKs) playing very important role in the regulation of key transcription factors (TFs) and pathway linked enzymes through phosphorylation/ dephosphorylation. MAPK signaling cascade has been reported to be triggered by several abiotic stresses in plant system [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. MAPK genes has been mostly characterized in Arabidopsis, for example - 
 <italic>AtMPK3</italic>, 
 <italic>AtMPK6</italic>, 
 <italic>AtMPK1</italic>, 
 <italic>AtMPK4</italic>, 
 <italic>MAPKK</italic>, and 
 <italic>MKK2</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Genome mining of 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> showed the presence of ∼110 genes linked with MAPK cascade kinases - 20 genes encodes for MAPK, 10 encodes for MAPKK, and 80 encodes for MAPKKK [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Similarly, genes involved in MAPK cascade has been reported and characterized in other closely related species, like rice, wheat, maize, etc. Genome mapping of rice showed the presence of 75, 8 and 17 MAPKKKs, MAPKKs, and MAPKs genes [
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. MAPK cascade also regulate ABA biosynthesis and in phosphorylation of various TFs like WRKY, HSF, etc. [
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The complex genome of wheat was also scanned for the presence of 
 <italic>MAPK</italic> and recently, 54 MAPK genes were identified [
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. MAPK cascade has not been much characterized in wheat especially for abiotic stress tolerance. MAPK cascade works as master switch (signaling/sensory protein molecule) in regulating the stresses by triggering the TFs and stress-associated genes [
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, very limited information on role of MAPK in thermotolerance of wheat is available on public domain.
</p>
