<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, mainly two different types of sodium metal‐based air battery systems have been studied, namely, nonaqueous (often termed as Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> battery) and hybrid batteries (often termed as Na–air battery). The use of O
 <sub>2</sub> and air simply means the sources used for oxygen supply. In nonaqueous Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> battery usually pure oxygen is supplied whereas in hybrid cells, air works as oxygen source. The cell structure of both types has a slightly different design and performance as illustrated in 
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>2</bold>
 </xref> and 
 <bold>Table</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">
  <bold>2</bold>
 </xref>. A typical, nonaqueous Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> battery is built up by the combination of metallic sodium as negative electrode and highly porous electrode as gas diffusion electrode (commonly known as electrocatalyst or air cathode).[qv: 6c] These two electrodes are separated by polymeric separator and immersed in an organic electrolyte (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). On the other hand, the hybrid Na–air cell involves the utilization of two electrolytes: an organic electrolyte as anolyte and an aqueous electrolyte as catholyte. The demonstrated configuration includes a Na‐ion conducting solid electrolyte membrane which separates the negative compartment to positive compartment having different electrolytes (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). The negative compartment design is the same as in conventional Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> batteries whereas, the positive electrode is inserted in aqueous electrolyte. The solid electrolyte membrane is used to avoid the direct contact between the metallic Na and the aqueous electrolyte; which would lead to major energy loss through the spontaneous exothermic reaction. Hence, the solid electrolyte membrane only allows the transport of Na
 <sup>+</sup> ions from the positive compartment to the negative and vice versa. Additionally, it also helps to prevent the growth of dendrites between the two electrodes which would lead to short circuits. In general, the energy storage mechanism in both cells involves the dissolution and plating of sodium metal at negative electrode during discharge and charge processes, respectively. However, on positive electrode ORR and oxygen evolution reaction (OER) takes place, when discharge and charge the cells.
</p>
