<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The diagnosis of Cushing’s syndrome/hypercortisolism was based on standard hormonal criteria: increased urinary free cortisol (UFC) in three 24 h urine collections, disturbances of cortisol circadian rhythm, increased serum cortisol levels accompanied by increased or not suppressed plasma ACTH levels at 8 a.m., and a lack of suppression of serum cortisol levels to &lt; 1.8 µg/dL during an overnight dexamethasone suppression test (1 mg at midnight). The pituitary etiology of Cushing’s disease was confirmed based on the serum cortisol levels or UFC suppression &lt; 50% with a high-dose dexamethasone suppression test (2 mg q.i.d. (lat. quater in die = four time a day) for 48 h) or a positive result of a corticotrophin-releasing hormone stimulation test (100 mg i.v. (intravenously)) and positive pituitary magnetic resonance imaging. In the group of SCAs, none of the patients had any evidence of hypercortisolism based on clinical signs and symptoms as well as basic laboratory tests. ACTH levels were assessed using IRMA (immunoradiometric assay) (ELSA-ACTH, CIS Bio International, Gif-sur-Yvette Cedex, France). The analytical sensitivity was 2 pg/mL (reference range: 10–60 pg/mL). Serum cortisol concentrations were determined by the Elecsys 2010 electrochemiluminescence immunoassay (Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany). Analytical sensitivity of the assay was 0.02 μg/dL (reference range: 6.2–19.4 μg/dL). UFC was determined after extraction (liquid/liquid with dichloromethane) by electrochemiluminescence immunoassay (Elecsys 2010, Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany)—reference range: 4.3–176 μg/24 h. Bilateral inferior petrosal sinus sampling was used as a routine investigation tool in any patient with proven ACTH-dependent Cushing’s syndrome and negative or equivocal MRI findings (intrasellar lesion ≤ 6 mm) [
 <xref rid="B21-jcm-10-00375" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]). A macroadenoma was defined as a tumor with at least one diameter exceeding 10 mm, and the tumor volume was assessed with the diChiro Nelson formula (height × length × width × π/6). Invasive growth of the tumors was evaluated using Knosp grading [
 <xref rid="B22-jcm-10-00375" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Tumors with Knosp grades 0, 1 and 2 were considered non-invasive, while those with Knosp 3 and 4 were considered invasive.
</p>
