<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">While we found that duplication of tumor suppressor genes is common in Afrotheria, genes that duplicated in the Proboscidean stem-lineage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3A,B</xref>) were uniquely enriched in functions and pathways that may be related to the evolution of unique anti-cancer cellular phenotypes in the elephant lineage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3C</xref>). Elephant cells, for example, cannot be experimentally immortalized (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Fukuda et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Gomes et al., 2011</xref>), rapidly repair DNA damage (<xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Sulak et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Hart and Setlow, 1974</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Francis et al., 1981</xref>), are extremely resistant to oxidative stress (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Gomes et al., 2011</xref>), and yet are also extremely sensitive to DNA damage (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abegglen et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Sulak et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">Vazquez et al., 2018</xref>). Several pathways related to DNA damage repair, in particular nucleotide excision repair (NER), were uniquely enriched among genes that duplicated in the Proboscidean stem-lineage, suggesting a connection between duplication of genes involved in NER and rapid DNA damage repair (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Hart and Setlow, 1974</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Francis et al., 1981</xref>). Similarly, we identified a duplicate <italic>SOD1</italic> gene in Proboscideans that may confer the resistance of elephant cells to oxidative stress (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Gomes et al., 2011</xref>). Pathways related to the cell cycle were also enriched among genes that duplicated in Proboscideans, and cell cycle dynamics are different in elephants compared to other species; population doubling (PD) times for African and Asian elephant cells are 13&#8211;16 days, while PD times are 21&#8211;28 days in other Afrotherians (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Gomes et al., 2011</xref>). Finally, the role of &#8216;mTOR signaling&#8217; in the biology of aging is well known. Collectively these data suggest that gene duplications in Proboscideans may underlie some of their cellular phenotypes that contribute to cancer resistance.</p>