<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Laser welding involves the melting of the interface of elements being welded by means of heat supplied to the previously mentioned area and result from the use of a highly concentrated beam of coherent light characterised by very high power density (i.e., restricted within the range of approximately 10
 <sup>2</sup> to 10
 <sup>11</sup> W/mm
 <sup>2</sup>) [
 <xref rid="B1-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Processes can be performed using the melt-in welding technique (as in classical arc welding) or with full joint penetration in one run or with many layers, with or without the filler metal, i.e., using the key-hole welding technique. Very high laser beam power density is responsible for the fact that welding linear energy is at the level of the minimum energy required to melt the joint. Therefore, the heat affected zone (HAZ) and the fusion zone are very narrow. At the same time, deformations of joints are so insignificant that welded elements, once finished, do not require additional mechanical treatment [
 <xref rid="B4-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Until recently, laser beam welding has seldom been implemented in the industry, mainly due to high investment costs and some technological problems. Presently, investing in laser beam welding no longer poses such a risk since, only a few years ago, everything indicates that the future market will be dominated by companies using laser technologies within a wide range. The foregoing results from the fact that many welding companies are increasingly interested in the application of technological lasers in production processes because it enables the introduction of such lasers for these companies to modernise during their production processes, start the production of technologically-advanced products, or manufacture new product generations. Very often, this process is used to join plates (of thicknesses exceeding 4 mm) since the application of the laser beam makes it possible to obtain high-quality joints without using the filler metal, which reduces costs and restricts the formation of welding strains [
 <xref rid="B10-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Now, laser welding is used in the ship-building or power generation industries, where it is necessary to make thick joints in high-strength steels, e.g., TMCP steels. The implementation of TMCP steels significantly decreases the time of welding works by reducing the preheating temperature or even eliminating the preheating process as such. In addition, the use of TMCP steel makes it possible to reduce the cross-sections of structural elements. As a result, welded structures with the same load capacity are now thinner and lighter. Furthermore, the use of TMCP steels reduces welding costs by decreasing the consumption of filler metals, shortening the time of welding processes, and reducing costs related to the straightening of structures and the testing of welds [
 <xref rid="B17-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. It should also be noted that the welding thermal cycle itself significantly differs from the classical thermomechanical treatment cycle (by being considerably more intense). As a result of the thermal welding cycle, carbide and nitride deposits are partially dissolved in austenite. In addition, rapid cooling leads to supersaturation of the α solution with micro-additives, i.e., C and N and/or their uncontrolled precipitation. During the welding of TMCP steels, the weld is provided with micro-additions such as niobium, vanadium, and titanium. During cooling, the previously mentioned micro-additions precipitate in the form of carbides and carbonitrides. The amount of precipitates depends on the rate of cooling. An increase in the rate of cooling is accompanied by an increase in the concentration of micro-additions in the solution. A similar situation can be noticed in the heat affected zone. The amount of micro-additions left in the solution significantly affects phase transformations during cooling as well as changes of properties following the heat treatment [
 <xref rid="B23-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This, in turn, results in an increase in the content of the products of the diffusionless and intermediate (bainitic) transformation. To a significant extent, the previously mentioned structures are responsible for the reduction of toughness. In cases of pure chemical elements, the stability of phases responsible for hardening can be presented on the basis of Gibbs-free enthalpy [
 <xref rid="B32-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-01312-f001">Figure 1</xref>). The analysis of the stability of hardening phases during the production of steel is impeded since the above-named phases are composed of constituents dissolved in the solution. During welding, the short time of heating, the size of the liquid metal pool, and high cooling rates impede the analysis of decomposition processes and the re-precipitation of hardening phases in the weld and in the HAZ (Heat Affectet Zone) area.
</p>
