<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the process of hardening, a significant role is played by the diffusion coefficient [
 <xref rid="B33-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. High diffusion coefficient values favour the fast formation of carbides and nitrides at high temperatures. The highest values of the diffusion coefficient in solution α are characteristic of interstitial elements such as carbon, nitrogen, and boron (D = 10
 <sup>−7</sup> cm
 <sup>2</sup>/s) and, among substitutional elements, titanium (D = 10
 <sup>−8</sup> cm
 <sup>2</sup>/s). Vanadium is characterised by a lower diffusion coefficient value than that of interstitial elements (D = 10
 <sup>−12</sup> cm
 <sup>2</sup>/s) [
 <xref rid="B35-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-materials-13-01312" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The microstructure of the tested S700MC steel is obtained by rolling with a controlled degree of deformation, deformation speed, and the appropriate sequence of precipitation processes. The welding process (method, linear energy) can naturally disturb this balance, which results in a significant deterioration of the plastic properties in both the HAZ and weld area. Different durability of Nb, V, and Ti nitrides and carbides is synonymous with their different ability to limit the growth of austenite grain in HAZ and a different impact on weld properties. Lack of control over the decay and re-separation of strengthening phases can affect the deterioration of the mechanical and plastic properties of the joints. A welding thermal cycle will have a significant impact on structural and phase changes as well as the durability of strengthening phases in the area of HAZ and weld. Therefore, the aim of the work was to explain the phenomenas occurring in the HAZ and welds, caused by the thermal cycle of the laser beam welding.
</p>
