<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The source of isolate variation in Mtz tolerance both in the presence and absence of drug, particularly in context of the 106-MtzR line, is not clear. There are unresolved chromosomal aberrations in all 3 MtzR isogenic lines [
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">88–90</xref>] as well nonsense mutations in multiple transcripts, including in NR-1 in 106-MtzR [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Western blots of protein post-translational modifications showed preexisting differences in 106-MtzS for KAc, K-MMe, and pY networks (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). Epigenetic regulation of transcriptional plasticity is implicated in MtzR and its stability, as the encystation–excystation process involves extensive epigenetic remodeling [
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] and restores Mtz susceptibility in formerly MtzR lines [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The lack of a histone H1 linker in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> has been proposed to shift reliance to histone modifications for chromatin remodeling and gene regulation [
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>], with acetylation and methylation already demonstrated as regulators of chromatin state for key processes of antigen switching and encystation [
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Although widespread changes were detected for KAc and K-MMe modifications between MtzR and MtzS lines, many of these occurred on nonhistone substrates (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). In contrast, cessation of Mtz selection produced significant changes, particularly on H3 and H4 modifications in MtzR lines (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">7</xref>, panel B) albeit in an isolate-dependent manner. Although histone acetylation generally correlates with transcriptional activation, methylation occurs in mono-, di-, and tri-methyl moieties that differentially influence gene expression and DNA methylation [
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Together, this indicates that a suite of epigenetically regulated fluctuations are likely to be occurring in transcription in 106-MtzR at 4 and 8 weeks and that MtzR may be regulated through different mechanisms in 713-MtzR. Given our emerging understanding of the links between histone modifications in oxidative stress responses [
 <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>], differences in Mtz- and oxygen-induced oxidative stress loads postulated in these lines may differentially influence epigenetic transcriptional phenotypes via epigenetic induction.
</p>
