<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub> in conjunction with H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> easily dissolves LFP-C, Zou et al. claimed that the combination appeared much more selective in the presence of large fractions of acid and peroxide consumers, such as NCM, LCO, and LMO. While they suggested that high ionic Fe-O bonds energy impedes dissolution of LFP [
 <xref rid="B43-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], we believe this is in contradiction with other publications demonstrating effective dissolution of LFP in H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub> [
 <xref rid="B93-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Instead, low molar ratio of H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub> over LFP coupled with H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> proved high Li selectivity over FePO
 <sub>4</sub> dissolution. This was demonstrated by Li et al. who performed selective leaching of LFP using H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub> and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> under gentle conditions (0.3 M H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub>, H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>/Li molar ratio of 2:1, 60 
 <italic>°</italic>C, and leaching time of 100 min) [
 <xref rid="B123-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. This resulted in the complete delithiation of LFP-C, and hence, lithium brine and the precursor for the synthesis of LFP were recovered. The process is illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-00801-f009">Figure 9</xref>. Similar processes were patented by Umicore [
 <xref rid="B124-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>] and Rockwood Lithium [
 <xref rid="B125-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. For the process patented by Umicore, the addition of oxidant is controlled by controlling the redox potential of the leach solution to at least 200 mV vs. Ag/AgCl reference electrode [
 <xref rid="B124-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. This process is also suitable for simultaneously treating the anode, which is made of graphite or LTO, and cathode. The patent does not mention whether the leaching residue remains as orthorhombic FePO
 <sub>4</sub> or other Fe-P rich phases. However, the harsh conditions prevailing in the reactor alter most probably the heterosite structure disabling any possibility to directly reuse it as cathodic material. In the process patented by Rockwood Lithium, Li is recovered from the mother liquor via electrodialysis or membrane separation [
 <xref rid="B125-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>].
</p>
