<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Starting from sulfuric acid leaching liquor obtained similar to Zou et al. [
 <xref rid="B43-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], Gratz et al. [
 <xref rid="B85-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] and Zheng et al. [
 <xref rid="B126-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>] applied purification process and element doping to obtain enhanced performance NMC (111). Zheng et al.’s process flowchart is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-00801-f010">Figure 10</xref>. First, Fe, Al, and Cu were removed from the leaching brine that contained transition metals via precipitation with NaOH. After adjusting the Co:Ni:Mn molar ratio to be 1:1:1, Ni
 <sub>1/3</sub>Mn
 <sub>1/3</sub>Co
 <sub>1/3</sub>(OH)
 <sub>2</sub> was co-precipitated using NaOH and NH
 <sub>4</sub>OH as alkaline/complexing agent for 48 h at pH 11 and a controlled temperature of 60 °C. Zheng et al. reported the results of four 7-day campaigns, where four 30 kg samples of blended spent LIBs with different proportions of LIBs types (LCO, NMC, LMO, LCO, LFP) were processed in a pilot-scale laboratory set-up [
 <xref rid="B126-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. The resulted solid Ni
 <sub>1/3</sub>Mn
 <sub>1/3</sub>Co
 <sub>1/3</sub>(OH)
 <sub>2</sub> products served as precursor for resynthesizing NMC after mixing with 5% excess Li
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub> and sintering at 450 °C and 900 °C. The obtained active material presented a d
 <sub>50</sub> from 10 to 14 µm and an electrochemical capacity ranging from slightly over 140 mAh/g to 152 mAh/g at C/5 [
 <xref rid="B126-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. These publications are part of process development and commercialization of a LIB recycling pilot plant for Battery Resourcers Inc (Worcester, MA, USA). Although the idea of precipitating the NMC (111) precursors directly from the leach liquor is attractive, this method is commercially more sensitive to market changes, and therefore less flexible than the production of individual Co, Mn, and Ni salt concentrates intended for new active materials production.
</p>
