<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RNA methylation modifications mainly include m
 <sup>6</sup>A, m
 <sup>5</sup>C, m
 <sup>1</sup>A, m
 <sup>7</sup>G, and so on. Previous studies have shown that these modifications play important roles in the stability, processing, and genetic information transmission of mRNA (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Jia, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Oerum et al., 2017</xref>). Known mutations in RNA-modifying enzymes are closely related to human diseases, including cancers, cardiovascular diseases, metabolic diseases, and mitochondrial-related defects (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Jonkhout et al., 2017</xref>). The degree of methylation of specific genes can be used as a diagnostic indicator of cancer (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Li W. et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Traube and Carell, 2017</xref>). 5-Methylcytosine (m
 <sup>5</sup>C) includes DNA and RNA methylation modifications, in which the methyl group is transferred to a specific base by using 
 <italic>S</italic>-adenosylmethionine (SAM) as a methyl donor under the catalysis of methyltransferase. m
 <sup>5</sup>C RNA modification has been found to be highly abundant in tRNA and rRNA (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Motorin et al., 2010</xref>). Meanwhile, high throughput sequencing has been used to verify the widespread presence of m
 <sup>5</sup>C in non-coding RNA and coding RNA (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Squires et al., 2012</xref>). It has been reported that m
 <sup>5</sup>C modification controls many functions: protein translational regulation, RNA processing, regulating stem cell function and stress response, and promoting tRNA stability and protein synthesis (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Aslan et al., 1967</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Blanco et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Tuorto et al., 2012</xref>). However, the involvement of m
 <sup>5</sup>C modification in GI cancer has not been systematically reported yet.
</p>
