<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the genes that was responsible for the enrichment of the “Defense response to virus” function was RSAD2 (Viperin) which was 2.4 logFC higher in lung tissue with lesion. This finding is also apparent in Behura et al. It identified differential expression of the RSAD2 gene in the BRSV infected steers in that study compared to uninfected normal control steers. Its finding was also in lung with lesion [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. RSAD2 expression is significantly upregulated by human RSV infection 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and it had an inhibitory effect on viral replication [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. It was also demonstrated that viperin production in bovine epithelial cells was increased with bovine RSV infection which caused reduction in virus replication [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. RSAD2 belongs to the group of interferon-stimulated antiviral genes and depends on type I interferons and active involvement of the JAK-STAT signaling pathway. Antiviral mechanisms of viperin are characterized by perturbed lipid rafts and promoted TLR7 and TLR9 signaling as reviewed [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Considering direct connection of RSAD2 with Type I interferons, we can see the opposite picture in group 6, where treatment was a combination of FPI and ibuprofen and started early (on day 3 after the infection). Viral load in this group was minimal and functions of “Type I interferon biosynthetic process” in lung lesions of this group were already down-regulated on day 10 after the infection. All this suggests that lung lesions are places of initial intensive replication of the virus where more extensive damage and oxidative stress impairs not only cells of local epithelial and stromal tissue, but also cells of innate and adaptive arms of the immune system and their functions.
</p>
