<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Reduction of stress in infected lungs of treated calves appears to be an effect of all treatments. Another stress-related gene that was differentially expressed in lung tissue with lesion is TMBIM6, which encodes BAX inhibitor 1. It is an anti-apoptotic protein protecting cells from endoplasmic reticulum associated stress which is characterized by accumulation of unfolded proteins and reactive oxygen species and can be caused by the infection and other stress-factors. BAX inhibitor 1 regulates reactive oxygen species (ROS) in endoplasmic reticulum [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. There is a report suggesting that BAX inhibitor 1 serves as an antiviral agent in influenza virus infected cells through the suppression of reactive oxygen species mediated cell death and upregulation of heme oxygenase-1 expression [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Interestingly, removal of reactive oxygen species by a scavenging agent reduced replication of the influenza virus.[
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In our study expression of the BAX inhibitor 1 was lower in lung tissue with lesion than in lung tissue without lesion suggesting that the lower level of its expression may have contributed to higher oxidative stress and led to the development of visible pathological changes. However, the cause-and-effect relationship in this process is not clear. It is possible that BRSV infection caused an undefined mechanism of suppression of the BAX inhibitor 1 or there may have been other mechanisms that caused oxidative stress, tissue damage and visible lesions. Both of these genes were differentially expressed, albeit statistically significantly only in the placebo group. This suggests that all treatment options reduce stress even in lesions of the lung of infected animals. These observations are consistent with Behuda et al who found that in tissues compared between BRSV infected steers and control steers differentially expressed genes were involved in oxidative phosphorylation, mitochondrial dysfunction, and hypoxia [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
</p>
