<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The same GO enrichment analysis also demonstrated differences in the innate immune response in lung tissue with lesion and lung tissue without lesion. One of these functions was granulocyte activation. Genes ANXA3 and/or FCGR3A were differentially expressed and levels of their expression were also significantly lower in lung tissue with lesion. This finding is also in concordance with significantly lower expression of complement components in lesions. This is another fact which suggests that immune mechanisms in lung lesions are impaired due to the stress or simply because immune cells are no longer attracted to these sites. KEGG pathway enrichment analysis of this gene set confirmed reduced immune function and even “Primary immunodeficiency” pathway (a collection of genes that are affected in cases of primary immunodeficiency and are therefore grouped under this heading) was enriched together with the “complement and coagulation cascades pathway”. Notably, genes that belong to GO terms and pathways, related to the vascular development also showed relatively lower expression, suggesting that despite that it was the 10
 <sup>th</sup> day after virus inoculation, restoration of the tissue in these parts of the lung was not as active as it was in lung tissue sites without lesion. It also can be explained by reduced function or presence of myeloid cells, such as macrophages in the lesion sites, and these cells play a central role in regulation of vascular remodeling and restoration of the lung tissue [
 <xref rid="pone.0246695.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].The overall scheme identified by analysis of differential gene expression in lung tissue with lesion in comparison with lung tissue without lesion may be characterized as a stress or oxidative stress with increased chaperon/heat shock proteins and depression of other functions, including all branches of the immune response. These stress related markers were reduced by all combinations of treatment. This result was based not only on functional analysis of differentially expressed genes but also on conducting GO enrichment analysis using data of the entire transcriptome. Our analysis is not limited to lists of only differentially expressed genes and uses data of all expressed genes to allow revelation of a broader picture and determination of general trends in the functional differences among treatment groups. This analysis confirmed some of the conclusions based on the differential gene expression, for example: depressed activation and differentiation of B cells, T cells, cytokine production and adaptive immune response generally in lesions. However, chemotaxis of immune cells, especially innate immune cells, was increased in lesion sites of most of the treatment groups. Differential gene expression suggested that there is probably a shortage or depressed functional activity of innate immune cells in lesions and increased chemotaxis is probably a local compensatory effect in response to the shortage.
</p>
