<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hybrid Na–air battery was first demonstrated by Hayashi et al. using NASICON as a ceramic separator in a seminal study published in mid‐2013.[qv: 34b] Since, then there has been continuous growth in this area and various attempts have been made to improve the performance of hybrid Na–air battery by using different nanostructured air electrodes. Though Hayashi et al. did not study the rechargeability of hybrid Na–air cells, they systematically studied how to improve the cell performance and lower down the resistance.[qv: 34b] Typical hybrid Na–air cells contain different kinds of interfacial resistances at Na metal/organic electrolyte, organic electrolyte/ceramic separator, ceramic separator/aqueous electrolyte, and aqueous electrolyte/air cathode interfaces. The total cell resistance, which eventually lowers the power density, was reduced more than half (from 440 to 210 Ω) when appropriate concentration of electrolytes, optimized thickness of NASICON, and highly porous and conducting air electrode were used.[qv: 34b] Subsequently, authors achieved more than twice power density ≈10 mW cm
 <sup>−2</sup> per effective area of ceramic separator with Pd‐catalyzed graphite plate as air cathode. Later, the same group reported a high energy density hybrid Na–air cell using Mn
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> catalysts on porous carbon electrode as air cathode.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">42</xref> Nevertheless, authors did not investigate the rechargeability of hybrid Na–air cell, but they achieved maximum of 21 mW cm
 <sup>−2</sup> power density at room temperature which was the highest value ever reported for alkali metal–air cells. In late 2015, Hashimoto and Hayashi used nanoporous gold as air electrode and carried out a comparative study using aqueous and nonaqueous electrolytes.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">52</xref> The authors used the same cell configuration except the catholyte and found that the cell with aqueous electrolyte is robust and displayed low overpotential gap (0.6 V for both charge and discharge), low resistance, and enormously improved power density (from 1.4 to 12.4 mW cm
 <sup>−2</sup>) and cyclic stability.
</p>
