<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At the same time, Sahgong et al. have demonstrated the rechargeability of hybrid Na–air cell using Pt/C as air electrode.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">53</xref> Herein, the air electrode was designed by preparing the slurry through the mixing of catalyst Pt/C with binder polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) in 
 <italic>N</italic>‐methyl‐2‐pyrrolidone (NMP) followed by its coating on a carbon paper. Using Pt/C as air electrode, the authors achieved 84.3% of energy efficiency and investigated the rechargeability of cell up to 18 cycles. However, the use of noble metal‐based air electrode is not promising due to their booming cost. Next, Cheon et al. synthesized graphitic nanoshell/mesoporous carbon nanohybrids (GNS/MC) as efficient bifunctional air electrode for hybrid Na–air battery.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref> GNS/MC was synthesized by solid state nanocasting method using SBA‐15 silica as a template which showed exceptional catalytic activity and durability for ORR and OER in alkaline medium. The high electrocatalytic performance of the GNS/MC was attributed to the contributions of residual transition metal (Ni and Fe) entities, nitrogen‐doped defect‐rich graphitic nanoshells, and the high specific surface area of the mesoporous structure. After systematically investigating electrocatalysts, the authors fabricated a hybrid Na–air cell (scheme was presented in 
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>9</bold>
 </xref>a; Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>b is the digital image of battery) which showed better overpotential gap of 115 mV than a cell made with Pt/C (179 mV) and Ir/C (364 mV) as air electrodes (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>c). Furthermore, the authors also achieved a maximum of 78.2 mW g
 <sup>−1</sup> in power density at 60 mA g
 <sup>−1</sup> in current density. The rechargeability of hybrid cell using GNS/MC as air electrode was examined up to 10 cycles. The observed galvanostatic charge–discharge profile as presented in Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0009" ref-type="fig">9</xref>d did not show any significant change in overpotential gap. Though GNS/MC showed lowest overpotential gap (0.115 V), yet the synthesis method is too complicated which cannot be employed for large‐scale production of the material.
</p>
