<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the quest of cost‐effective air electrodes, Senthilkumar et al. explored the possibility to use cobalt phosphate as efficient bifunctional air electrode.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">54</xref> The authors synthesized cobalt phosphate by simple precipitation followed by calcination method and functionalize a carbon paper electrode. The bifunctional electrocatalytic activity for ORR and OER was evaluated in alkali electrolyte by rotating ring‐disk electrode (RRDE) method. The electron transfer number associated with ORR was calculated to be ≈3.9 close to 4 which suggests that ORR occurred through a four‐electron transfer pathway, thus avoiding the formation of hydrogen peroxide. The electrocatalytic activity is associated with the formation of di μ‐oxo bridge within cobalt phosphate. The hybrid Na–air cell using cobalt phosphate as air electrode displays an overpotential gap of 0.23 V at 0.01 mA cm
 <sup>−2</sup>. The hybrid Na–air cell showed stability up 50 cycles at very low current density far from practical applications. Like in this last study, a typical design found in the literature for air electrodes include the coating of microporous carbon electrodes with a catalyst layer composed of electroactive (nano)particles bound together with a polymeric binder.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">55</xref> Typically, polymeric binders, such as PVDF, are used to enhance the physical integrity of the coating and avoid delamination with the electrode substrate. There are several drawbacks of using polymeric binders: First, their electrical insulating character leads to the formation of a barrier for the transport of electrons between the carbon electrode and the electroactive particles; and for the transport of ions between the electrolyte and the electroactive particles. Second, some polymer binders such as PVDF was readily attacked by superoxide (O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>) formed as intermediate discharge product that leads the formation of fluorinated salt (NaF) and hydrogen peroxide hence limits the discharge capacity of the battery.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">56</xref> Finally, the use of binder increases the total weight of the electrode and also requires an additional step to mix and combine the materials during the electrode preparation process.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">55</xref> In that context, there is a motivation to find new strategies to avoid those polymeric binders. Khan et al. have grown α‐MnO
 <sub>2</sub> nanowires on reduced graphene oxide (rGO) coated carbon paper and used this binder free electrode as air electrode for hybrid Na–air battery.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">36</xref> This binder‐free electrode preparation involves coating of porous rGO on carbon microfiber followed by growth of α‐MnO
 <sub>2</sub> nanowires on top of rGO coated carbon paper as shown in 
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0010" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>10</bold>
 </xref>. Generally, MnO
 <sub>2</sub> crystallizes in different phases, namely, α, β, and γ, and among them α‐MnO
 <sub>2</sub> was found to have superior electrocatalytic activity than other phases.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">57</xref> When MnO
 <sub>2</sub> crystallizes in α‐phase, it tends to form 2 × 2 tunnel structures formed by edge‐sharing MnO
 <sub>6</sub> and corner sharing MnO
 <sub>6</sub> octahedra. These tunnel structures due to their size can accommodate positive ions to balance the negative charges during the electrocatalytic activity process. In this case, MnO
 <sub>2</sub> nanowires crystallize in the α‐phase and display good electrocatalytic activity in alkaline solutions. The resulting hybrid Na–air cell displayed 0.7 V of overall overpotential gap at a current density of 15 mA g
 <sup>−1</sup> when charged and discharged up to 25 h each. Interestingly, it was observed that urchin‐shaped α‐MnO
 <sub>2</sub> on rGO coated carbon paper showed better performance than flake‐shaped MnO
 <sub>2</sub> on rGO coated carbon paper. The urchin‐shaped MnO
 <sub>2</sub> formed V‐shaped structures with highly exposed active sites which allow an enhanced diffusion and contact of the electrolyte to the air electrode, and an efficient transportation of Na
 <sup>+</sup> ions and electrons. Hence, the morphology of the electroactive layer affects greatly the performance of the hybrid Na–air cell.
</p>
