<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Later in 2016, in another work, Liang et al. exfoliated graphene from pyrolytic graphite and used this five layered exfoliated graphene as air electrode for hybrid Na–air cells.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">58</xref> With that air electrode, the maximum power density (13.8 mW cm
 <sup>−2</sup>) was slightly higher than with a pyrolytic graphite air electrode (12.4 mW cm
 <sup>−2</sup>). Carambola‐shaped VO
 <sub>2</sub> nanostructure was also utilized as air electrode for hybrid Na–air battery.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">43</xref> The authors followed the same strategy as above, i.e., the carambola‐shaped VO
 <sub>2</sub> were grown on rGO coated carbon paper, also resulting in a binder free air electrode (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0011" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>11</bold>
 </xref>a). The hybrid Na–air cell displayed 0.64 V of overall overpotential gap, maximum of 104 mW g
 <sup>−1</sup> power density, and good cyclic stability up to 50 cycles (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0011" ref-type="fig">11</xref>b,c). The good performance of the cell was attributed to the carambola‐shaped morphology of VO
 <sub>2</sub> with well exposed arms facilitating a proper diffusion of air and electrolyte and preventing electrode polarization. Dual phase MnCo
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> with N‐doped rGO was also explored as bifunctional electrocatalyst for hybrid battery.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref> The composite material showed comparable ORR and higher OER performance than Pt/C which was credited to the dual‐phase of cobalt manganese spinel nanoparticles and N‐doping in rGO that improves the conductivity and catalytically active sites. The coupling of N‐doped rGO with MnCo
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> helps to form a conducting network which improves the conductivity of the composite. Additionally, dopants in carbon matrix increase the active site which also enhances the catalytic activity of system.[qv: 2e] Thus, the fabricated cell displayed 2.75 V versus Na discharge, 3.14 V versus Na charge potential, and 0.39 V of overall overpotential gap with good cyclic stability up to 25 cycles.
</p>
