<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In another study, Khan et al. explored the possibility of using 3D SnS
 <sub>2</sub> as air electrode for hybrid Na–air cell.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">60</xref> On galvanostatic charge–discharge 3D SnS
 <sub>2</sub> displayed 0.45 V discharge overpotential whereas, 0.07 V charge potential which leads to 0.52 V overall overpotential gap and 83% electrical energy efficiency. The vertically grown and self‐assembled ultrathin 3D SnS
 <sub>2</sub> nanosheets of nanopetals displayed maximum of 300 mW g
 <sup>−1</sup> power density and rechargeability up to 40 cycles. Various other materials such as Ni nanoparticles,
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">61</xref> bismuth rhodium oxide,
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref> Bi
 <sub>2</sub>Ru
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>7</sub>,
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">63</xref> MOF‐derived carbon,
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref> Tl
 <sub>2</sub>Rh
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>7,</sub>
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">64</xref> hollow double walled Mn
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub> nanocubes,
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">65</xref> and single crystalline Tl
 <sub>2</sub>Ru
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>7</sub> nanoparticles
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">66</xref> were also employed as air electrodes and studied systematically to improve the performance of hybrid Na–air cells (
 <bold>Table</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-tbl-0004" ref-type="table">
  <bold>4</bold>
 </xref>). Kim et al. synthesized phosphate functionalized Bi
 <sub>2</sub>Rh
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>6.8</sub> as pyrochlore oxide and use it as a bifunctional air electrode for hybrid Na–air batteries.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref> The synthesized material displayed the lowest potential gap (170 mV) between ORR and OER. This performance was attributed to the improvement in surface chemical activity due to the functionalization with phosphate ions. In functionalized P‐Bi
 <sub>2</sub>Rh
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>6.8</sub> due to lower Pauling electronegativity χ
 <sub>r</sub> of P (χ
 <sub>r</sub> = 2.19) compared to O (χ
 <sub>r</sub> = 3.44), the —OPO(OH)
 <sub>2</sub> surface groups promote a fast‐redox kinetics at the Bi and Rh centers during ORR and OER processes (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-fig-0012" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>12</bold>
 </xref>). Authors proposed as “Therefore, oxidation of the Rh and Bi ions in P‐Bi
 <sub>2</sub>Rh
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>6.8</sub> was easily achieved because less energy is required to extract electrons during the ORR and OER, resulting in the fast catalyst kinetics and improved surface reactivity of the P‐Bi
 <sub>2</sub>Rh
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>6.8</sub>.”
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref> The prepared material integrated in the air electrode leads to a cell with 0.17 V overpotential gap and 181.2 mW g
 <sup>−1</sup> power density at 120 mA g
 <sup>−1</sup> current density.
</p>
