<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">Here, we explore the lasting effects of prenatal T on adult behavioral plasticity and genome-wide patterns of gene expression and methylation in male zebra finches (
 <italic>Taeniopygia guttata</italic>). Zebra finches are a good study system because they have numerous genes that are potential targets of epigenetic regulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Zebra finch embryos also express steroid receptors during early development (prior to endogenous T production) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. We injected zebra finch eggs with T or a vehicle control the morning eggs were laid. Embryos are in the earliest stages of development at this point [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] and, based on work in other altricial songbirds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] and more well-known mammalian models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], injections should coincide with a time just prior to when de novo methylation patterns are starting to become established. We measured aggression in sexually mature adult males. Then, using transcriptome profiling (RNA-Seq) and whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (MethylC-Seq), we examined patterns of gene expression and DNA methylation in steroid-sensitive brain regions containing the vertebrate social behavior network, the hypothalamus (HYPO) and nucleus taenia of the amygdala (TnA) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The TnA is involved in social arousal and responses to same-sex conspecifics in songbirds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], while the HYPO plays a central role in neuroendocrine function, regulating many of the neurotransmitters and hormones associated with aggression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Overall, this study provides novel insight into whether prenatal T can generate lasting changes in behavior alongside altered gene expression and methylation.
</p>
