<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4811924</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00384</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sub-MIC Tylosin Inhibits <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> Biofilm Formation and Results in Differential Protein Expression</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Shuai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yanbei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/335542/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Yulin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/335545/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Honghai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/335550/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Jingwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/335551/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Jianqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/335554/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Yonghui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/335556/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Chang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/335557/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yanhua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/268378/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Pharmacy, College of Veterinary Medicine, Northeast Agricultural University</institution><country>Harbin, China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Biotechnology, Heilongjiang Vocational College for Nationalities</institution><country>Harbin, China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Etienne Giraud, Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique, France</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Rui Vitorino, University of Aveiro, Portugal; Raymond Allan, University of Southampton, UK</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Yanhua Li <email xlink:type="simple">liyanhua1970@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>384</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Wang, Yang, Zhao, Zhao, Bai, Chen, Zhou, Wang and Li.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Yang, Zhao, Zhao, Bai, Chen, Zhou, Wang and Li</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> (<italic>S.</italic>suis) is an important zoonotic pathogen that causes severe diseases in humans and pigs. Biofilms of <italic>S. suis</italic> can induce persistent infections that are difficult to treat. In this study, the effect of tylosin on biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis</italic> was investigated. 1/2 minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) and 1/4 MIC of tylosin were shown to inhibit <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation <italic>in vitro</italic>. By using the iTRAQ strategy, we compared the protein expression profiles of <italic>S. suis</italic> grown with sub-MIC tylosin treatment and with no treatment. A total of 1501 proteins were identified by iTRAQ. Ninety-six differentially expressed proteins were identified (Ratio &#x0003e; &#x000b1;1.5, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Several metabolism proteins (such as phosphoglycerate kinase) and surface proteins (such as ABC transporter proteins) were found to be involved in biofilm formation. Our results indicated that <italic>S. suis</italic> metabolic regulation, cell surface proteins, and virulence proteins appear to be of importance in biofilm growth with sub-MIC tylosin treatment. Thus, our data revealed the rough regulation of biofilm formation that may provide a foundation for future research into mechanisms and targets.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>proteomics</kwd><kwd><italic>S. suis</italic></kwd><kwd>biofilms</kwd><kwd>tylosin</kwd><kwd>iTRAQ</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="50"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6710"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> (<italic>S. suis</italic>) is an important zoonotic pathogen that causes a wide range of diseases in pigs, including meningitis, septicaemia, pneumonia, endocarditis, and arthritis (Gottschalk et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). In addition, this pathogen is an emerging zoonotic agent and an important public health issue in East and Southeast Asia (Sriskandan and Slater, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Gottschalk et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). During a single outbreak in China in 2005, more than 200 human cases of <italic>S. suis</italic> were reported, with a death total of 39 (Yang et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Current studies show that <italic>S. suis</italic> can cause persistent infections by forming biofilms <italic>in vivo</italic> (Wang et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p><p>Biofilms are assemblages of microorganisms characterized by cells that are irreversibly attached to a substratum and embedded in a matrix of self-produced extracellular polymeric substances such as exopolysaccharides (EPS), proteins, nucleic acids and other substances; this type of sessile community-based existence is a critical characteristic for bacterial persistence (Davey and O'Toole, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). The physical and biological properties of the biofilm, such as slow growth and mechanical barrier, have a substantial role in the development of increased antimicrobial tolerance. Because the bacteria in chronic infections are aggregated and are in close proximity, genes coding for resistance to antimicrobials can be passed horizontally from one bacterium to the another (Bjarnsholt et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The bacteria in biofilms could be 1000-times more difficult to kill by antibiotics than the same organism growing planktonically (Gilbert et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). Therefore, the control of biofilms is understood to be crucial.</p><p>Apart from surgical intervention (when applicable), antibiotics are the main option for the treatment of biofilm infections (Bjarnsholt et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Previous studies showed that macrolides successfully inhibited <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm formation and reduced its virulence when used at sub-inhibitory concentrations (Fujimura et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). In addition, a sub-minimal inhibitory concentration of erythromycin can inhibit <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation (Zhao et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Tylosin, a macrolide antibiotic produced by <italic>Streptomyces fradiae</italic>, is widely used as a veterinary medicine. However, there is still not much effective research of sub-MIC tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis in vitro</italic>.</p><p>At present, most of the available information regarding biofilm formation by drug intervention is based on transcriptomic analyses. However, a limitation of transcriptomic analysis for identifying biofilm-regulated gene network raised concerns among investigators. The method of proteomics is thought to be an essential complement to transcriptomic analysis for discovering key regulators of biofilm (Sauer, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Different immunogenic components of planktonically grown <italic>S. suis</italic> proteins such as secreted or cell wall-associated proteins had been studied by using immunoproteomic assays (Zhang and Lu, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2007a</xref>,<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; Geng et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Additionally, our lab found that quorum-sensing played a crucial role leading to biofilm formation through quantitative proteomic analysis of <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm inhibited by sub-MIC erythromycin treatment <italic>in vitro</italic> (Zhao et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, there are no reports regarding the proteomic analysis of sub-MIC tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis in vitro</italic>.</p><p>We identified several proteins in sub-MIC tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis</italic> by using iTRAQ technology in this study. The findings from the present study may provide a theoretical foundation for therapy of <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm infection and provide references for finding new potential therapeutic targets.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Growth of <italic>S. suis</italic> planktonic cells</title><p><italic>S. suis</italic> (ATCC 700794) was grown in Todd-Hewitt yeast Broth (THB; Summus Ltd., Harbin, Heilongjiang, China) for 16&#x02013;18 h at 37&#x000b0;C with constant shaking for biofilm assays (Wang et al., <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Observation by scanning electron microscopy (SEM)</title><p>Mid-exponential growth phase cultures of <italic>S. suis</italic> ATCC 700794 were adjusted to an optical density of 0.1 at 600 nm (OD600). Then, 2 mL cultures were transferred to the wells of a 6-well microplate containing an 11 &#x000d7; 11 mm sterilized rough glass slide (Mosutech Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China) on the bottom. After culturing for 72 h at 37&#x000b0;C without shaking, the glass slide was removed with tweezers, and the biofilms on the rough glass slide were washed with sterile PBS. The remaining biofilms were fixed with fixative solution [4% (w/v) paraformaldehyde, 2.5% (w/v) glutaraldehyde, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> in 0.2 M cacodylate buffer, pH 7.2] for 6 h and washed three times with 0.1 M PBS 10 min each, then fixed in 2% osmium tetroxide containing 2 mM potassium ferrocyanide and 6% (w/v) sucrose in cacodylate buffer. The samples were dried, gold sputtered with an ion sputtering instrument (current 15 mA, 2 min) and observed using SEM (FEI Quanta, Netherland).</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of tylosin on biofilm formation determined by the TCP assay</title><p>Mid-exponential growth phase cultures of <italic>S. suis</italic> were adjusted to 0.2 of OD600. Then, 100 &#x003bc;L of cultures were added to each wells of a 96-well microplate with equal volume of tylosin solution with the final concentrations of 1/2 MIC (0.25 &#x003bc;g/mL), 1/4 MIC (0.125 &#x003bc;g/mL), 1/8 MIC (0.0625 &#x003bc;g/mL), and 1/16 MIC (0.03125 &#x003bc;g/mL), respectively. In addition, a negative control (with THB alone) and a positive control (with bacteria alone) were also included. After incubation at 37&#x000b0;C for 72 h without shaking, the medium was removed by aspiration and the wells were washed three times with sterile physiological saline. The remaining attached bacteria were fixed with 200 &#x003bc;L of 99% methanol (Guoyao Ltd., China) per well, and the plates were emptied after 15 min and left to dry. Then, the plates were stained for 5 min with 200 &#x003bc;L of 2% crystal violet (Guoyao Ltd., China) per well. The excess stain was rinsed off by placing the plate under running tap water. After the plates were air dried, the dye bound to the adherent cells was resolubilized with 200 &#x003bc;L of 33% (v/v) glacial acetic acid (Guoyao Ltd., China) per well. The amount of released stain was quantified by measuring the absorbance at 570 nm with a microplate reader (DG5033A, Huadong Ltd., Nanjing, Jiangsu, China). The reported values are the means of three measurements. The experiments were performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>Colony forming unit (CFU) enumeration</title><p>Overnight cultures of <italic>S. suis</italic> were adjusted to an OD 600 of 0.2. Then, the bacteria were inoculated into 96-well microtiter plate wells containing 200 &#x003bc;L of THB alone (untreated wells) or adding the tylosin solution with the final concentrations of 1/4 MIC (0.125 &#x003bc; g/mL). In addition, a negative control (with THB alone) and a positive control (with bacteria alone) were also included. After incubation at 37&#x000b0;C for 72 h without shaking, the medium was removed by aspiration, and the wells were washed three times with sterile physiological saline. Biofilm cells were removed from wells by sonication for 5 min in 200 &#x003bc;L of THB. The cell suspensions (<italic>n</italic> = 3) underwent 10-fold dilutions in THB, and 100 &#x003bc;L of each dilution was spot plated onto THB soft-agar plates and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 24 h. All the experiments were performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of protein extracts</title><p>For biofilm cultures, <italic>S. suis</italic> was grown in THB in 100 mm polystyrene petri dishes at 37&#x000b0;C for 24 h. Then, the supernatant was removed and the dishes were washed twice with Tris-HCl buffer (50 mM, pH 7.5). The biofilms were detached by scraping. After being sonicated for 5 min (Bransonic 220; Branson Consolidated Ultrasonic Pvt. Ltd., Australia), the cells were centrifuged at 12,000 &#x000d7; g for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Then, the cell pellets were washed twice with Tris-HCl buffer (Wang et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Protein digestion and iTRAQ labeling</title><p>Protein digestion was performed according to the reported FASP procedure (Wisniewski et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). In brief, 200 &#x003bc;g of proteins at two different conditions (1/4 MIC of tylosin treated cells and nontreated cells) were added into 30 &#x003bc;L STD buffer (4% SDS, 100 mM DTT, 150 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0) and ultrafiltered (Microcon units, 30 kD) with UA buffer (8 M Urea, 150 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0). To block reduced cysteine residues, 100 &#x003bc;L 0.05 M iodoacetamide was added into UA buffer and incubated for 20 min in the dark. The filters were washed three times with 100 &#x003bc;L UA buffer and twice with 100 &#x003bc;L DS buffer (50 mM triethylammoniumbicarbonate at pH 8.5). Finally, the proteins were digested with 2 &#x003bc;g trypsin (Promega) in 40 &#x003bc;L DS buffer at 37&#x000b0;C for 16&#x02013;18 h. Then, the resulting peptides were collected as a filtrate. The peptide content was estimated by UV light spectral density at 280 nm using an extinctions coefficient of 1.1 of 0.1% (g/l) solution calculated on the basis of the frequency of tryptophan and tyrosine in vertebrate proteins.</p><p>For the iTRAQ labeling, the peptides were labeled with the 8-plex iTRAQ reagent by following the manufacturer's instructions (Applied Biosystems). Each iTRAQ reagent was dissolved in 70 &#x003bc;L of ethanol and added to the respective peptide mixture. The peptides from the <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilms treated by tylosin were labeled with 115 isobaric reagent, and the peptides from the nontreated <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilms were labeled with 116 isobaric reagent. Then, the samples were multiplexed and vacuum dried. Three independent biological experiments were performed.</p></sec><sec><title>Peptide fractionation with strong cation exchange (SCX) chromatography</title><p>SCX chromatography using the AKTA Purifier system (GE Healthcare) was used to fractionate the iTRAQ labeled peptides. After being reconstituted and acidified with 2 mL buffer A (10 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> in 25% of ACN, pH 2.7), the peptides were loaded onto a PolySULFOETHYL 4.6 &#x000d7; 100 mm column (5 &#x003bc;m, 200 &#x000c5;, PolyLC Inc., Maryland, U.S.A.). Then, the peptides were eluted at 1 ml/min with a gradient of 0&#x02013;10% buffer B (500 mM KCl, 10 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> in 25% of ACN, pH 2.7) for 2 min, 10&#x02013;20% buffer B for 25 min, 20&#x02013;45% buffer B for 5 min, and 50&#x02013;100% buffer B for 5 min. The elution was monitored by absorbance at 214 nm, and the fractions were collected after every 1 min. The collected fractions (~30 fractions) were combined into 10 pools and desalted on C18 Cartridges [Empore&#x02122; SPE Cartridges C18 (standard density), bed I.D. 7 mm, volume 3 ml, Sigma]. Each pooled fraction was concentrated by vacuum centrifugation and reconstituted in 40 &#x003bc;l of 0.1% (v/v) trifluoroacetic acid and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C for LC-MS/MS analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Liquid chromatography (LC) electrospray ionization (ESI) tandem Ms (MS/MS) analysis by Q exactive</title><p>Experiments were performed on a Q Exactive mass spectrometer that was coupled to Easy nLC (Thermo Fisher Scientific). A sample (10 &#x003bc;L) of each fraction was injected for the nano LC-MS/MS analysis. The peptide mixture (5 &#x003bc;g) was loaded onto a C18-reversed phase column (Thermo Scientific Easy Column, 10 cm long, 75 &#x003bc;m inner diameter, 3 &#x003bc;m resin) in buffer A (0.1% formic acid) and separated with a linear gradient of buffer B (80% acetonitrile and 0.1% formic acid) at 250 nl/min controlled by IntelliFlow technology for 140 min. MS data were acquired using a data-dependent top10 method dynamically choosing the most abundant precursor ions from the survey scan (300&#x02013;1800 m/z) for HCD fragmentation. Determination of the target value was based on predictive Automatic Gain Control (pAGC). The dynamic exclusion duration was 60 s. Survey scans were acquired at a resolution of 70,000 at m/z 200, and the resolution for HCD spectra was set to 17,500 at m/z 200. The normalized collision energy was 30 eV, and the underfill ratio, which specifies the minimum percentage of the target value likely to be reached at maximum fill time, was defined as 0.1%. The instrument was run with the peptide recognition mode enabled.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence database searching and data analysis</title><p>The MS/MS spectra were searched using the MASCOT engine (Matrix Science, London, UK; version 2.2) in the Proteome Discoverer 1.3 (Thermo Electron, San Jose, USA.) against the Uniprot <italic>S. suis</italic> fasta database (38,369 sequences, downloaded March 4th, 2013) and the decoy database. False discovery rates (FDR) were calculated by running all spectra against a decoy database using the MASCOT software. To identify proteins, the following options were used: Peptide mass tolerance = 20 ppm, MS/MS tolerance = 0.1 Da, Enzyme = Trypsin, Missed cleavage = 2, Fixed modification: Carbamidomethyl (C), iTRAQ 8plex (K), iTRAQ 8plex (N-term), Variable modification: Oxidation (M). The quantification was performed based on the peak intensities of the reporter ions in the MS/MS spectra. The ratio of label 115 and 116 represents the expression of proteins with the protein identification confidence of a 1% FDR (Unwin et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The proteins were considered over expressed when the iTRAQ ratio was above 1.5 and under expressed when the iTRAQ ratio was lower than 0.67. The Proteome Discoverer tool was used to categorize the proteins detected by Gene Ontology (GO) annotation according to the cellular component, biological process and molecular function.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Effect of tylosin against biofilm formation <italic>In vitro</italic> by the TCP assay</title><p>We evaluated the action of tylosin on biofilm growth <italic>in vitro</italic>. The MIC against <italic>S. suis</italic> was 0.5 &#x003bc;g&#x000b7;mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Tylosin at 1/2 MIC and 1/4 MIC caused a significantly higher reduction in the biofilm-forming ability of <italic>S. suis</italic> compared with positive control (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). However, there was no pronounced effect for 1/16 MIC and 1/8 MIC of tylosin on biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis</italic> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of tylosin at different concentrations on <italic>S. suis</italic> ATCC 700794 biofilm formation</bold>. The data are expressed as the means &#x000b1; standard deviations. Significant decrease (<sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) compared with control biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis in vitro</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-00384-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Direct observation of biofilm formation <italic>In vitro</italic> by sem</title><p>SEM analysis was performed to observe the 1/4 MIC of tylosin treated cells and nontreated cells biofilm formation by <italic>S. suis</italic> under same growth conditions. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, the surface of the glass slide is almost entirely covered by the aggregates and microcolonies of <italic>S. suis</italic> when growth was carried out in the culture medium without tylosin. However, when the culture medium was added to 1/4 MIC of tylosin, the biofilms were characterized by the presence of small clusters of cells interspersed amongst individual cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). This result showed that the biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis</italic> was inhibited by the tylosin of 1/4 MIC <italic>in vitro.</italic></p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis</italic> without tylosin. <bold>(B)</bold> Biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis</italic> with 1/4 MIC tylosin treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-00384-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Colony forming unit (CFU) enumeration</title><p>To better assess action of tylosin on biofilm quantitatively, the CFUs of <italic>S. suis</italic> were counted. The viability of <italic>S. suis</italic> treated with 1/4 MIC of tylosin was different from the viability of untreated <italic>S. suis</italic>. The number of CFUs/mL in treated biofilms (5.3 log<sub>10</sub> CFUs/mL) was significantly fewer than in nontreated biofilms (6.5 log<sub>10</sub> CFUs/mL; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). The number of CFUs/mL in treated biofilms (5.3 log<sub>10</sub> CFUs/mL) was significantly fewer than in nontreated biofilms (6.5 log<sub>10</sub> CFUs/mL; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The findings demonstrated that 1/4 MIC of tylosin remained effective in decreasing the viability of <italic>S. suis</italic>.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of 1/4 MIC of tylosin on <italic>S. suis</italic> ATCC 700794 biofilm formation by colony forming unit (CFU) enumeration</bold>. The data are expressed as the means &#x000b1; standard deviations. Significant decrease (<sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) compared with control biofilm formation of <italic>S. suis in vitro</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-00384-g0003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sub-MIC tylosin inhibits biofilm formation and differentially expressed proteins by iTRAQ</title><p>A total of 1501 proteins were identified by iTRAQ. Detailed information is shown in the Supplementary File. A ratio of proteins with &#x0003e;1.5 or &#x0003c; 0.67 (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) was considered to be differentially expressed. Based on this criterion, 96 differentially expressed proteins were identified in 1/4 MIC tylosin treated cells and nontreated cells. Detailed information could is shown Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. These proteins were detected by GO annotation. Thirty-five proteins were deleted from the database. The remaining 61 proteins were classified into biological process, molecular function and cellular component (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The results regarding the biological process were as follows: single-organism process (8, 13%), response to stimulus (4, 7%), localization (4, 7%), biological adhesion (1, 2%), cellular component organization or biogenesis (6, 10%), cellular process (25, 41%), biological regulation (3, 5%), metabolic process (30, 49%). The results regarding molecular function were as follows: binding (29, 48%), nucleic acid binding transcription factor activity (1, 2%), transporter activity (3, 5%), structural molecule activity (5, 8%), catalytic activity (25, 41%). The results regarding cellular component were as follows: organelle (6, 10%), virion (1, 2%), cell (13, 21%), extracellular region (1, 2%), membrane (6, 10%), macromolecular complex (8, 13%).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>List of differentially expressed proteins in tylosin treated cells</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Accession</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Description</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fold change<sup>a</sup></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SDH9">G7SDH9</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.555777</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4W1G9">A4W1G9</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphotransferase system cellobiose-specific component IIC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.521547</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SA24">G7SA24</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cold-shock DNA-binding domain protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.394546</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="F4EDP5">F4EDP5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.568016</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="R4NL31">R4NL31</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MF3-like protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63094</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="E9NQ29">E9NQ29</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPS16V</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.452748</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5KZ73">G5KZ73</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADH:flavin oxidoreductase/NADH oxidase family protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.459622</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S4C2">G7S4C2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major membrane immunogen, membrane-anchored lipoprotein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643938</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A8CUL3">A8CUL3</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Integrase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46773</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SM99">G7SM99</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type I site-specific restriction-modification system, R (Restriction) subunit and related helicase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.506277</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SLJ0">G7SLJ0</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative competence-damage inducible protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.564703</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4W1W3">A4W1W3</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F0F1-type ATP synthase, subunit a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.586873</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7RZW0">G7RZW0</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sugar ABC transporter permease</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.508325</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S2T8">G7S2T8</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol dehydrogenase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.610195</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SDG9">G7SDG9</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laminin binding protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.524593</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="R4NLJ6">R4NLJ6</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligopeptide ABC transporter, periplasmic oligopeptide-binding protein OppA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.644177</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S371">G7S371</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose-bisphosphate aldolase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.623705</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="M1UGE2">M1UGE2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.647168</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4VZM2">A4VZM2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell cycle protein GpsB</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.631018</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4W2D2">A4W2D2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cation transport ATPase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.676356</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5L1V6">G5L1V6</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein L9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6638821</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SEP2">G7SEP2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.502566</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4VVZ3">A4VVZ3</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA dimethylallyltransferase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.510883</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S5B8">G7S5B8</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-isopropylmalate dehydrogenase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.513117</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SA68">G7SA68</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UDP-N-acetylmuramate&#x02013;alanine ligase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.656503</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5L098">G5L098</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulator Spx</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.514636</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="E8UKC3">E8UKC3</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.507837</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SFU4">G7SFU4</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.543591</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4VV99">A4VV99</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA repair protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.545594</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4W2Z7">A4W2Z7</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FMN-dependent NADH-azoreductase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.527496</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="F4EC05">F4EC05</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57743</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="C6GNL8">C6GNL8</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30S ribosomal protein S21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.545471</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="K7ZNG8">K7ZNG8</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA recombination/repair protein (Fragment)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.558023</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S3K5">G7S3K5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC-type cobalt transport system, ATPase component</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.583854</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SM56">G7SM56</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribosomal RNA small subunit methyltransferase H</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.594936</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A2VC24">A2VC24</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muramidase-released protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.579304</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4W3C1">A4W3C1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative phosphotyrosine protein phosphatase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60975</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S4U0">G7S4U0</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.596783</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SP92">G7SP92</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.658448</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S7E3">G7S7E3</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Helicase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.516925</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="M1VK55">M1VK55</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycosyltransferase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.662795</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S3P9">G7S3P9</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.673475</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4W106">A4W106</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal transduction histidine kinase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62492</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="B0M0G7">B0M0G7</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphomethylpyrimidine kinase (Fragment)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.633436</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A5JSJ7">A5JSJ7</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.681661</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5L226">G5L226</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type III restriction-modification system, restriction endonuclease subunit</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.697991</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S7K4">G7S7K4</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.645719</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="B9WY95">B9WY95</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidase M20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.647536</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S4T2">G7S4T2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branched-chain alpha-keto acid dehydrogenase subunit E2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.673032</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5KX48">G5KX48</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC-type uncharacterized transport system, permease component</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.705109</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S178">G7S178</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.774886</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="M1VDL7">M1VDL7</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter permease protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.942183</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S6Z3">G7S6Z3</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.956584</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="J7KIA5">J7KIA5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abortive infection bacteriophage resistance related protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.999106</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SJZ7">G7SJZ7</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primosomal protein N'</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.720079</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SHW7">G7SHW7</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.001559</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="Q9EZW2">Q9EZW2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elongation factor Tu (Fragment)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.739971</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4VVJ5">A4VVJ5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.141695</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="M1VJZ8">M1VJZ8</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zeta toxin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74309</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5L2V0">G5L2V0</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADPH:quinone reductase and related Zn-dependent oxidoreductase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79706</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="R4NU43">R4NU43</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aromatic amino acid aminotransferase gamma @ N-acetyl-L,L-diaminopimelate aminotransferase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.144605</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4W296">A4W296</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.837367</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SKQ0">G7SKQ0</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CHAP domain containing protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.179882</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="B9WVD6">B9WVD6</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein (Fragment)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.226792</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5L2N5">G5L2N5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-fucose isomerase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.859887</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="B9WTA1">B9WTA1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.290848</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="B9WXU6">B9WXU6</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC transporter related protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.873566</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G8DU82">G8DU82</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transposase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.376768</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S242">G7S242</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative ABC transporter</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.883471</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="A4VZ91">A4VZ91</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein L32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.915877</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SDX6">G7SDX6</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50S ribosomal protein L7/L12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.918196</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5KZ86">G5KZ86</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphatidylserine/phosphatidylglycerophosphate/ cardiolipin synthase-like protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.965488</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SIQ5">G7SIQ5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.451703</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S7J2">G7S7J2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.481527</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SPA1">G7SPA1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative scaffolding protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.584249</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S7A9">G7S7A9</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAD-dependent pyridine nucleotide-disulfide oxidoreductase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.970356</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S8Q2">G7S8Q2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peptidase M22 glycoprotease</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.978772</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="M1TIM7">M1TIM7</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methylated DNA-protein cysteine methyltransferase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.161583</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SBK2">G7SBK2</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elongation factor Ts</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.266517</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="M1VE47">M1VE47</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fic/DOC family protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.606274</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="M1UFP9">M1UFP9</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiamine-phosphate synthase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.298028</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S535">G7S535</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose-6-phosphate aldolase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.553516</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5L351">G5L351</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NsuB</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.694988</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="B9WUV5">B9WUV5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcriptional regulator, DeoR family</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65073</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="R4NW55">R4NW55</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid replication protein Rep and AAA-class ATPase domain protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.779765</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7RZ18">G7RZ18</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sortase-like protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.791504</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="S6B433">S6B433</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RecN protein (Fragment)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.007243</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5KZR3">G5KZR3</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutathione S-transferase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.262393</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="R4NLK5">R4NLK5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSU ribosomal protein S1p</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46851</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="R4NWB6">R4NWB6</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.306942</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5L259">G5L259</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NADP-dependent glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase, putative</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.781098</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="D5AFN4">D5AFN4</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xaa-Pro dipeptidyl-peptidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.095053</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SMG3">G7SMG3</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elongation factor G</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.667679</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7SD52">G7SD52</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ABC superfamily ATP binding cassette transporter, membrane protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.201581</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G5L1N9">G5L1N9</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoid DNA-binding protein</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.796473</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="G7S8P5">G7S8P5</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphoglycerate kinase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.34908</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Fold change<sup>a</sup>, the ratio of different expression level between Sub-MIC tylosin treated cells and nontreated cells</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Annotation of differentially regulated protein (ratio &#x0003e;1.5 or &#x0003c; 0.67) functions by Gene Ontology (GO)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-07-00384-g0004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>A TCP assay is based on the ability of bacteria to form biofilms on the bottom of tissue culture plates and is mainly used to identify the formation of bacterial biofilms (Mathur et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Okajima et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Presterl et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Bacteria are grown in cell culture plates, and the quantity of a biofilm is detected by staining the wells with crystal violet according to the correlation between OD values and biofilm formation (Mathur et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>).</p><p>To further confirm <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation, the structure of the <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm was identified by scanning electron microscopy (SEM). The biofilm examination relied heavily on SEM. Because of its high magnification, the biofilm microstructure is observed clearly. These findings further confirm that <italic>S. suis</italic> can form biofilms <italic>in vitro</italic>. Although these procedures have their advantages, the TCP procedure lacks specificity and sensitivity because crystal violet stains all of the components of the biofilm and could potentially stain non-biofilm material. More specific and sensitive techniques can be performed to assess each of the individual components. This method is good for screening purposes.</p><p>Tylosin is a frequently used drug for the treatment of <italic>S. suis</italic> infection. Upon treatment with this antimicrobial agent, <italic>S. suis</italic> is inevitably exposed to a sub-inhibitory level of the agent. Therefore, we studied its effect in sub-inhibitory concentrations on <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation. Tylosin can inhibit <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation at sub-inhibitory concentrations in a dose-dependent manner. In addition, the inhibition of biofilm formation varied among the antimicrobial agents. Numerous reports have showed biofilm formation in the presence of sub-inhibitory concentrations of antimicrobial agents (Dunne, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Carsenti-Etesse et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>; Rupp and Hamer, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Rachid et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Yang et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Our results are in agreement with these previous findings. Our results showed a better activity of tylosin against <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation. However, further studies should be conducted to confirm and clarify the relationship between the relative adherence-inhibiting properties of tylosin and their mechanisms. These results may provide information regarding the clinical use of antimicrobial agents against biofilm-forming bacteria.</p><p>Our data identified proteins related to biofilm growth that have previously been uncharacterized. iTRAQ analyses showed that the regulation of metabolism plays a key role during <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm growth. First, the iTRAQ quantitative data revealed that carbohydrate metabolism may be particularly important during <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm growth. It was reported that fructose bisphosphate aldolase and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase were significantly decreased in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> biofilms (Allan et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In our study, there was a &#x0003e;two-fold increase of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase in the tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation. In addition, the levels of fructose bisphosphate aldolase (fold change: 0.62) were down-regulated. It was reported that phosphoglycerate kinase was up-regulated in <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilms compared with planktonic cells by comparative proteomic analysis (Wang et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Similarly, biofilms of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (Sauer et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) and <italic>Staphylococcus xylosu</italic>s (Planchon et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) exhibit up-regulated phosphoglycerate kinase. There was a &#x0003e;11-fold increase in the level of phosphoglycerate kinase in the tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation. Phosphoglycerate kinase is a glycolytic enzyme that functions in the conversion of glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate into 1, 3-diphosphoglycerate. Glycolysis may play a pivotal role during <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm growth. Furthermore, histidine metabolism may play an important role in biofilm formation. Histidine kinase (fold change: 1.62) was up-regulated in the tylosin-inhibited biofilm formation. Compared with other amino acids, L-His had the strongest effect on biofilm induction (Cabral et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Histidine metabolism is also found to be involved in biofilm formation and is confirmed by gene disruption (Cabral et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Histidine kinase is an important signaling molecule in biofilm formation in gram-positive and negative bacteria (McLoon et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Shemesh and Chai, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Yang et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Grau et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In addition, several ABC transporter system proteins were significantly up-regulated in the tylosin inhibiting biofilm formation. This finding is consistent with the previous results of our laboratory showing that sub-MIC erythromycin inhibits <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation (Zhao et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The carbohydrate substrate selection and fermentation determine ABC transporter proteins were significantly up-regulated in tylosin-treated cells, suggesting that <italic>S. suis</italic> had the capability of metabolizing a wide range of carbohydrates during biofilm development (Hardy et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Marion et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Bidossi et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Haertel et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Moreover, ABC transporters are important because they regulate respiration and biofilm formation, which in turn affect the rate of electricity production and bioremediation (Selvaraj et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Furthermore, in the mutants of a <italic>pneumococcal</italic> biofilm screen, ABC transporters were shown to be defective in colonization (Munoz-Elias et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).</p><p>Cell surface proteins play a crucial role in biofilms. Within the biofilm, bacterial cells are embedded in a self-produced extracellular matrix. This matrix protects bacteria against a number of environmental insults. However, the matrix also confines bacterial access to fresh nutrients. Thus, the verified increase in the expression of transmembrane channels appears to be an essential requirement for the entrance of important nutrient-containing fluid (Costerton et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). In addition to acting, as channels, porins may act as potential targets for adhesion to other cells and may mediate cell attachment through binding to the proteins released for biofilm formation (Dallo et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The outer membrane proteins may mediate cell attachment through binding to the released proteins for biofilm formation. Membrane proteins such as OmpA mediate cell adhesion in <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (Dallo et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The key developmental stages of biofilm development have been reported to be adhesion to surfaces, aggregation of micro colonies, and further expansion of the microbial community. The putative involvement of many genes encoding large cell surface proteins is adhesion to the epithelium and biofilm formation (Pridmore et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Walter et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Frese et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Pham (Pham et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) found increased expression of outer membrane proteins in the <italic>Tannerella forsythia</italic> biofilm cells by using quantitative non-gel-based proteomic techniques. In our study, the expression of membrane-anchored lipoprotein, phosphoglycerate kinase, sugar ABC transporter permease, ABC superfamily ATP binding cassette transporter membrane protein and L-fucose isomerase changed; these proteins belong to membrane proteins and cell-surface proteins and might be involved in some molecular functions including catalytic activity, motor activity, nucleotide binding, protein binding and transporter activity. For example, phosphoglycerate kinase is a <italic>S. suis</italic> surface protein that promotes cell adhesion and plays a key role in bacterial infection and invasion (Brassard et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Wang and Lu, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). We predicted that these membrane proteins might affect the bacterial cell-cell interaction. Thus, membrane proteins might play a significant role in biofilm formation.</p><p><italic>S. suis</italic> virulence proteins related to infection, persistence and competitive fitness were mostly down regulated when sub-MIC tylosin was used to inhibit biofilm formation. There was a &#x0003e;1.5-fold decrease in the level of NADH oxidase. NADH oxidase regulates competence, virulence, and pneumococcal persistence by its actions as an oxygen sensor, in detoxifying oxygen, and in increasing the efficiency of glucose breakdown (Auzat et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>) and plays an important role in <italic>pneumococcal</italic> infection in animal models of pneumonia (Yu et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). NADH oxidase is encoded by <italic>nox</italic>. The virulence and persistence in mice of a blood isolate was attenuated by a <italic>nox</italic> insertion mutation (Auzat et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). Thus, this protein appears to be of major importance in the growth of biofilms.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our study suggested that sub-MICs of tylosin could inhibit <italic>S. suis</italic> biofilm formation <italic>in vitro</italic>. We used a robust and reliable comparative proteomic technique (iTRAQ) to compare the abundances of proteins from 1/4 MIC of tylosin treated cells and nontreated cells. Finally, in sub-MIC tylosin inhibiting cells, we identified 96 differentially expressed proteins when the protein had a fold-change of more than a ratio &#x0003e;1.5 or &#x0003c; 0.67 (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Our proteomic data suggested general changes in metabolism (such as phosphoglycerate kinase) and surface proteins (such as ABC transporter proteins) involved in biofilm formation. Overall, our results indicated that <italic>S. suis</italic> metabolic regulation, cell-surface proteins, and virulence proteins appear to be of importance in biofilm growth by sub-MIC tylosin treatment. Thus, our data revealed the rough regulation of biofilm formation that might potentially be utilized to manage biofilm infections of <italic>S. suis</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>SW the design whole experiment. YL directed the completion of the experiment. YY, YZhao, HZ, JB, JC, YZhou, CW provided help during the experiment.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31472231) and Guangdong Technology Research Center for Traditional Chinese Veterinary Medicine and Natural Medicine (No.20141020002). We thank Shanghai Applied Protein Technology Co. Ltd. for the help with iTRAQ.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2016.00384">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2016.00384</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table1.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skipp</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jefferies</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faust</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall-Stoodley</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Pronounced metabolic changes in adaptation to biofilm growth by <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e107015</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25188255?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25188255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Auzat</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapuy-Regaud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Bras</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogunniyi</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Thomas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>The NADH oxidase of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>: its involvement in competence and virulence</article-title>. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1018</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1028</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1999.01663.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10594826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bidossi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Decorosi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colomba</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozzi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>A functional genomics approach to establish the complement of carbohydrate transporters in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e33320</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0033320</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22428019?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22428019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjarnsholt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciofu</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Givskov</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoiby</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Applying insights from biofilm biology to drug development - can a new approach be developed?</article-title>
<source>Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>808</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd4000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24080700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24080700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brassard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quessy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Cloning and purification of the <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> serotype 2 glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase and its involvement as an adhesin</article-title>. <source>Vet. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2004.05.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15288930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15288930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parreira</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumbo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poza</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Proteomic and functional analyses reveal a unique lifestyle for <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> biofilms and a key role for histidine metabolism</article-title>. <source>J. Proteome Res.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>3399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3417</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr101299j</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21612302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21612302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carsenti-Etesse</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durant</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Entenza</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondain</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Effects of subinhibitory concentrations of vancomycin and teicoplanin on adherence of staphylococci to tissue culture plates</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>921</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>923</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.37.4.921</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8494393?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8494393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeBeer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korber</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Biofilms, the customized microniche</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>176</volume>, <fpage>2137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2142</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8157581?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8157581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dallo</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Denno</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weitao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Adhesion of <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> to extracellular proteins detected by a live cell-protein binding assay</article-title>. <source>Ethn. Dis.</source>
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1 Suppl. 1</issue>):<fpage>S1-7-11</fpage>. <?supplied-pmid 20521377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20521377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Microbial biofilms: from ecology to molecular genetics</article-title>. <source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>867</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.64.4.847-867.2000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11104821?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11104821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Effects of subinhibitory concentrations of vancomycin or cefamandole on biofilm production by coagulase-negative staphylococci</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>393</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.34.3.390</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2334150?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2334150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frese</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannock</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loach</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The evolution of host specialization in the vertebrate gut symbiont <italic>Lactobacillus reuteri</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e1001314</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001314</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21379339?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21379339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujimura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Combined efficacy of clarithromycin plus cefazolin or vancomycin against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilms formed on titanium medical devices</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>484</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2008.06.030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18790609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18790609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Identification and characterization of novel immunogenic proteins of <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> serotype 2</article-title>. <source>J. Proteome Res.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>4132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4142</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr800196v</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18630869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18630869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Biofilm susceptibility to antimicrobials</article-title>. <source>Adv. Dent. Res.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>167</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/08959374970110010701</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9524452?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9524452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title><italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> infections in humans: the Chinese experience and the situation in North America</article-title>. <source>Anim. Health Res. Rev.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1466252307001247</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17692141?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17692141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calzas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title><italic>Streptococcus suis</italic>: a new emerging or an old neglected zoonotic pathogen?</article-title>
<source>Future Microbiol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>391</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb.10.2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20210549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20210549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grau</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ona</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallegos-Monterrosa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mhatre</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>A duo of potassium-responsive histidine kinases govern the multicellular destiny of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>mBio</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e00581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00581-15</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26152584?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26152584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haertel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eylert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petruschka</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gierok</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grubmueller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Characterization of central carbon metabolism of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> by isotopologue profiling</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>287</volume>, <fpage>4260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4274</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.304311</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22167202?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22167202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magee</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caimano</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yother</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Essential role for cellular phosphoglucomutase in virulence of type 3 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>2309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2317</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.69.4.2309-2317.2001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11254588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marion</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aten</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodiga</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Identification of an ATPase, MsmK, which energizes multiple carbohydrate ABC transporters in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<volume>79</volume>, <fpage>4193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.05290-11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21825065?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21825065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singhal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fatma</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Detection of biofilm formation among the clinical isolates of Staphylococci: an evaluation of three different screening methods</article-title>. <source>Indian J. Med. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0255-0857.19890</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16505551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16505551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLoon</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodkin-Gal</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Losick</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Spatial regulation of histidine kinases governing biofilm formation in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>193</volume>, <fpage>679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>685</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01186-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21097618?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21097618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munoz-Elias</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcano</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camilli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Isolation of <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> biofilm mutants and their characterization during nasopharyngeal colonization</article-title>. <source>Infect. Immun.</source>
<volume>76</volume>, <fpage>5049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5061</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00425-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18794289?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18794289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okajima</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayakawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tochikubo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Biofilm formation by <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> on intraocular lens material</article-title>. <source>Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>2971</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2975</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.05-1172</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16799041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16799041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noirel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A quantitative proteomic analysis of biofilm adaptation by the periodontal pathogen <italic>Tannerella forsythia</italic></article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>3130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200900448</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20806225?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20806225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Planchon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desvaux</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chafsey</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebraud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Comparative subproteome analyses of planktonic and sessile <italic>Staphylococcus xylosus</italic> C2a: new insight in cell physiology of a coagulase-negative staphylococcus in biofilm</article-title>. <source>J. Proteome Res.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1797</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1809</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr8004056</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19253936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19253936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Presterl</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchomel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichmann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassnigg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graninger</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effects of alcohols, povidone-iodine and hydrogen peroxide on biofilms of <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Antimicrob. Chemother.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>420</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkm221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17586808?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pridmore</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desiere</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilanova</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barretto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittet</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The genome sequence of the probiotic intestinal bacterium <italic>Lactobacillus johnsonii</italic> NCC 533</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>2512</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2517</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0307327101</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14983040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14983040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rachid</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlsen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziebuhr</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Effect of subinhibitory antibiotic concentrations on polysaccharide intercellular adhesin expression in biofilm-forming <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic></article-title>. <source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>3357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3363</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.44.12.3357-3363.2000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11083640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11083640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rupp</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Effect of subinhibitory concentrations of vancomycin, cefazolin, ofloxacin, L-ofloxacin and D-ofloxacin on adherence to intravascular catheters and biofilm formation by <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Antimicrob. Chemother.</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>161</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/41.2.155</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9533456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9533456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The genomics and proteomics of biofilm formation</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2003-4-6-219</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12801407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12801407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camper</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> displays multiple phenotypes during development as a biofilm</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>184</volume>, <fpage>1140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1154</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.184.4.1140-1154.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11807075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11807075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumantran</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhary</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Prediction and classification of ABC transporters in <italic>Geobacter sulfurreducens</italic> PCA using computational approaches</article-title>. <source>Curr. Bioinform.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>172</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1574893608999140109113236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shemesh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A combination of glycerol and manganese promotes biofilm formation in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> via histidine kinase KinD signaling</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>195</volume>, <fpage>2747</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2754</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00028-13</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23564171?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23564171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sriskandan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Invasive disease and toxic shock due to zoonotic <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic>: an emerging infection in the East?</article-title>
<source>PLoS Med.</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e187</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030187</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16594733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16594733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unwin</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whetton</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Simultaneous analysis of relative protein expression levels across multiple samples using iTRAQ isobaric tags with 2D nano LC-MS/MS</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>1574</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1582</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2010.123</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21085123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21085123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chagnaud</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannock</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loach</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dal Bello</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>H. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A high-molecular-mass surface protein (Lsp) and methionine sulfoxide reductase B (MsrB) contribute to the ecological performance of <italic>Lactobacillus reuteri</italic> in the murine gut</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>71</volume>, <fpage>979</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>986</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.2.979-986.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15691956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15691956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Adhesion activity of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase in a Chinese <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> type 2 strain</article-title>. <source>Berl. Munch. Tierarztl. Wochenschr.</source>
<volume>120</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2376/0005-9366-120-207</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17555040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17555040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Comparative proteomic analysis of <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> biofilms and planktonic cells that identified biofilm infection-related immunogenic proteins</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e33371</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0033371</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22514606?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22514606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Reduced virulence is an important characteristic of biofilm infection of <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>
<volume>316</volume>, <fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2010.02189.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21204925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21204925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zougman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraj</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Universal sample preparation method for proteome analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1322</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19377485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19377485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The role of the QseC quorum-sensing sensor kinase in epinephrine-enhanced motility and biofilm formation by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell Biochem. Biophys.</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>398</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12013-014-9924-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24676679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24676679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.-Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>H.-Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.-G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.-P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>An outbreak of human <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> serotype 2 infections presenting with toxic shock syndrome in Sichuan, China</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue za Zhi</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16792880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16792880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Emodin affects biofilm formation and expression of virulence factors in <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> ATCC700794</article-title>. <source>Arch. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>197</volume>, <fpage>1173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1180</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-015-1158-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26446827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26446827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonetto</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingraham</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalker</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Characterization of the <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> NADH oxidase that is required for infection</article-title>. <source>Microbiology 147(Pt 2)</source>, <fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-147-2-431</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11158360?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Identification of immunogenic cell wall-associated proteins of <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> serotype 2</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>3506</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3515</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200800007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18686301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18686301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007a</year>). <article-title>Immunoproteomic assay of membrane-associated proteins of <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> type 2 china vaccine strain HA9801</article-title>. <source>Zoonoses Public Health</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>259</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1863-2378.2007.01056.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17803514?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17803514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007b</year>). <article-title>Immunoproteomics of extracellular proteins of Chinese virulent strains of <italic>Streptococcus suis</italic> type 2</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>4468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4476</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200700294</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18022935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18022935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Quantitative proteomic analysis of sub-MIC erythromycin inhibiting biofilm formation of S-suis <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Proteomics</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2014.12.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25579403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25579403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>