<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to the rapid division and proliferation of cancer cells, the synthesis and metabolism of nucleic acids and proteins are increased compared with those in normal cells. Thus, the associated protein content is increased [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] relative to normal cells. Elongation factor 1-alpha 2 has been reported in the literature as a potential marker for cancer [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The proteasome subunit alpha type is significantly increased in all cancers, consistent with literature reports [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Protein ubiquitination and subsequent proteolysis and degradation by the proteasome are important mechanisms in the cell cycle, cell growth and differentiation, gene transcription, signal transduction, and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Proteasomes hydrolyze cells and control apoptosis. Proteosomes bind to the p21 protein and inhibit p21 protein activity [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], leading to cell cycle disorders and, ultimately, cancer. Therefore, the increased expression of this protein in cancer cells inhibits the tumor-suppressing effect of p21. The proteasome subunit alpha type may be significantly associated with the protein metabolism in the body, and its expression is associated with cancer [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The spermatogenesis-associated protein is a spermatogenesis-related protein that is mainly found in mammalian tissues and is significantly elevated in prostate cancer tissues [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], testicular cancer tissues [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and breast cancer tissues [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The expression of spermatogenesis-associated 6 (SPATA6) is significantly elevated in testicular cancer, and inhibition of SPATA6 expression can cause cancer cells to die [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. SPATA20 is significantly elevated in cholangiocarcinoma [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Our results are consistent with those reported in the literature.
</p>
