<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Transmembrane protein 143 was present at different levels in different stages of lung cancer and may be important in the early diagnosis and prognosis of cancer. These results are novel and have not been reported. E-cadherin acts as an invasion suppressor and a classical tumor suppressor gene. E-cadherin is a biomarker for cancer [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and is attenuated and reduced in many cancers [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>–
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], especially in lung and breast cancers. E-cadherin loss in tumor cells leads to decreased adhesion between tumor cells, which favors epithelial-mesenchymal transition [
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and promotes the ability of tumor cells to invade and metastasize. In metastatic lung cancer (stages III and IV), E-cadherin protein levels were significantly lower than those in nonmetastatic stages (I and II). Fibronectin can regulate cancer and the migration of cancer cells, which is closely associated with the prognosis of tumor formation and development. However, the mechanisms underlying this relationship are unclear [
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Fibronectin is a biomarker [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>–
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], which is upregulated in cancer, and our results are consistent with the literature. Fibronectin 1 can bind to cancer cells and favors metastasis and invasion [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Cancer prognosis studies demonstrate that the higher the level of fibronectin 1 in vivo, the worse the prognosis and survival rate [
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. When cancer occurs, fibronectin 1 expression increases, promoting adhesion and invasion of cancer cells and increasing the damage to normal tissues. Therefore, fibronectin 1 is also an important indicator of cancer prognosis. After cancer treatment, if fibronectin 1 levels are still high, the prognosis is poor.
</p>
