<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>
   <bold>Evaluation of biofilm formation of 
    <italic>S. aureus</italic> lrg mutants defective in cell autolysis regulation (∆lrgA and ∆lrgB)
   </bold>. 
   <italic>S. aureus</italic> WT and derived mutants ∆lrgA and ∆lrgB biofilms were grown for 24 hrs in the wells of 96-well plates at 37°C. (a) 
   <bold>Biofilm metabolic activity</bold>. Based on MTS assay on 24 hr-biofilms, ∆lrgB exhibited reduced metabolic activity (**, p &lt; 0.01) compared to the WT strain, whereas ∆lrgA activity was comparable to that of the WT. (b) 
   <bold>Biofilm biomass</bold>. Crystal violet staining indicated comparable biofilm biomass for the mutant strains and WT. (c) 
   <bold>Evaluation of biofilm vancomycin susceptibility with and without DNAse treatment</bold>. 24 hr-biofilms were treated with vancomycin alone or in combination with DNAse (0.625 mg/ml) for 24 hrs and metabolic activity was quantified using the MTS-assay. Based on comparative assessment of metabolic activity of treated and untreated biofilms, ∆lrgB exhibited slightly reduced susceptibility to vancomycin compared to WT (p = 0.0147 at 200 µg/ml), which was completely reversed upon DNAse treatment. ∆lrgA was more susceptible to vancomycin than the WT at lower vancomycin concentrations concentrations (p = 0.0008 at 50 µg/ml), however no significant effect was seen upon DNAse treatment. Data set obtained in this experiment (C) was analyzed as analyzed by 2-WAY ANOVA using the Multiple Effect analysis (Mixed Model). For all experiments in this figure: *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.001; ns, not significant
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0005_OC" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0005_PB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </alternatives>
</fig>
