<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 6.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>(a) 
   <bold>Comparartive evaluation of eDNA content in single- and mixed-species biofilms</bold>. No significant differences in amounts of eDNA was noted in 
   <italic>C. albicans</italic> and 
   <italic>S. aureus</italic> single species biofilms. Significantly more eDNA was present in mixed biofilms compared to single species biofilms, individually and combined. (b-d) 
   <bold>Effect of DNAse treatment on biofilm structure and 
    <italic>S. aureus</italic> susceptibility to vancomycin
   </bold>. 24 hr-preformed single- and mixed-species biofilms were treated with vancomycin alone or in combination with DNAse (0.625 mg/m;) for 24 hrs at 37°C. (b) 
   <bold>Vancomycin susceptibility of DNAse-treated and untreated biofilms</bold>. After sonication to disrupt biofilms, cell suspensions were diluted and plated on species-specific media for CFU enumeration. Results show DNAse treatment did not impact 
   <italic>S. aureus</italic> susceptibility to vancomycin in single species biofilm; however, DNAse treatment significantly sensitized 
   <italic>S. aureus</italic> to vancomycin in mixed-species biofilms. DNAse alone was used as negative control and showed no significant effect on biofilm viability compared to untreated controls. (c, d) 
   <bold>CLSM analysis of vancomycin diffusion through DNAse-treated and untreated 
    <italic>S. aureus</italic> single and mixed biofilms
   </bold>. Fluorescently-labeled vancomycin (green/white) was added to 24 hr pre-formed single- and mixed-species biofilms, with or without DNAse (0.625 mg/ml). 
   <italic>S. aureus</italic> was stained with concanavalin A (ConA; magenta) and 
   <italic>C. albicans</italic> with calcofluor-white (blue). Representative reconstructed Z-stacks are shown. (c) 
   <bold>
    <italic>S. aureus</italic> single-species biofilm
   </bold>. DNAse treatment resulted in a more dispersed distribution of vancomycin (green/white) throughout the layers of the biofilm. (d) 
   <bold>Mixed-species biofilms of 
    <italic>C. albicans</italic> and 
    <italic>S. aureus</italic>
   </bold>. Unlike the effect on 
   <italic>S. aureus</italic> single-species biofilm, DNAse treatment resulted in significant disruption of mixed biofilm structure, which was comcomittant with increase in vancomycin signal (green/white). Bars = 40 µm. For all experiments in this figure: ns, not significant; *, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.001; ****, p &lt; 0.0001. Graph error bars show the standard error of the mean (SEM)
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0006_OC" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1894834_F0006_PB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </alternatives>
</fig>
