<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38">The transporter proteins expressed in grass halophyte 
 <italic>Urochondra</italic> are in accordance with the previous studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. De Vos et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup> reported genes responding to salt stress in 
 <italic>Artemia</italic> and identified the transporter proteins i.e. Lipid transporter proteins, metal transporters proteins, ion transporter proteins and salt-dependent proteins. Genes involved in transport and kinase activities are highly enriched under salt stress in both root and leaf trancriptome of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>.</italic> NHX proteins are ubiquitous membrane proteins which play important role in the ion homeostasis by sequestration of additional Na
 <sup>+</sup> in vacuoles or removal of excess Na
 <sup>+</sup> from the cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup>. In our study, the expression of gene encoding Na
 <sup>+</sup>/H
 <sup>+</sup> exchanger (
 <italic>Urochondra</italic>_DN33781_c0_g1_i1) was up-regulated along with the salinity stress. Similarly, in a previous study, the 
 <italic>Arabidopsis ABC transporter</italic>, AtABCG36, was found to promote salinity stress adaptation by reducing the shoot sodium content
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> maintains the salt tolerance ability by regulating uptake and accumulation of Na
 <sup>+</sup>, K
 <sup>+</sup> and Cl
 <sup>−</sup> through up-regulation of selective stress-related transporters
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, in our data, up-regulation of a larger number of ABC transporter genes was observed in 
 <italic>Urochondra</italic> at moderate or higher levels of salinity.
</p>
