<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">Different processes of biological, cellular or molecular function having important role in various pathways were identified through functional annotation of differentially expressed genes. The mechanism of salt tolerance is a complex process having different physiological, cellular, metabolic and molecular responses. The role of genes in imparting salinity tolerance including osmolytes, protein kinases, transcription factors and ion transporters have been reported earlier
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. Most important pathways identified for tolerance mechanism include SOS (salt overly sensitive) pathway, proline metabolism, calcium-signaling, plant hormone signalling and MAPK (mitogen-activated protein kinase) signalling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. Functional annotation of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> revealed 26% of the ESTs belonging to stress-related proteins, followed by nucleic acid metabolism (17%) while a considerably high number (13%) of ESTs had no known protein function that included hypothetical and predicted proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. In 
 <italic>Suaeda salsa</italic>, DEGs mapped to oxidative phosphorylation, ribosome, starch and sucrose metabolism, amino sugar and nucleotide sugar metabolism, protein processing in endoplasmic reticulatum and plant hormone signal transduction were significantly annotated
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Differential expression of unigenes in leaves (3,856 DEGs) and roots (7,157 DEGs) of 
 <italic>Beta vulgaris</italic> depict different mechanism for salt tolerance at 200 and 400 mM NaCl
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. GO and KEGG database enrichment analysis identified differentially expressed genes for signal transduction, protein phosphorylation and redox regulation in roots and leaves. Differential expression of 77,250 unigenes (48,682 upregulated and 28,568 downregulated) have been reported in 
 <italic>S. salsa</italic> at 30% NaCl in leaves and roots, respectively
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. Through KEGG pathway analysis, transcripts for amino acid metabolism, carbohydrate metabolism, fatty acid metabolism and nitrogenous compound were differentially expressed at 500 mM NaCl in 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, in 
 <italic>Urochondra,</italic> many differentially expressed genes for regulation mechanisms in the nucleus, such as DNA-templated transcription (regulation) and post transcriptional modifications were identified, suggesting salt stress activates gene regulatory networks.
</p>
