<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">In present experiment, the total DEGs identified that encode transcription factors (TFs) mainly belong to various families such as BTB/POZ, WRKY, MYB, NAC, DREB, AP2-EREBP, bHLH, bZIP, MADS, and SBP. Major plant transcription factor families such as bZIP, NAC, AP2/ERF, and MYB orchestrate regulatory networks underlying abiotic stress tolerance
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. The DEGs that encode MYB transcription family were the largest group highly expressed under salinity. The Myb TFs are regarded as active players in the drought and salinity stress signalling in plants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. The DEGs encoding Myb-related protein Myb4 (DN37753_c2_g1_i9) and Myb family protein-like (DN35501_c2_g1_i2) were found to be up-regulated under 30 dS/m, 40 d/ m and 50 dS/m salinity (Supplementary file 
 <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). The results obtained are consistent with the previous studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. Genes encoding transcription factor MYB2 expressed differentially under drought stress in plant 
 <italic>Populus Canadensis</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>.</italic> The TFs are also considered as important regulators under salt stress. The up-regulation of ABA-responsive proteins (DN33328_c2_g1_i1) in 
 <italic>Urochondra</italic> along with down-regulation of transcription factor WRKY40 (DN39291_c1_g1_i1) with increasing salinity level indicated that WRKY40 may act as a negative regulator for ABA-responsive genes as have been reported in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. In plant transcriptomics, WRKY are one of the major regulatory transcription factors having various roles in management of plant biotic and abiotic stress responses. It has been reported that WRKY transcription factors play an role in signalling networking of plants thereby acting as regulators as well as repressors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. WRKY40 binds directly to the W-box Cis-acting element and hence inhibits the gene expression of DREBIA, MYB2, AB14, AB15, ABF4, the ABA responsive genes. WRKY40, WRK70, WRK41, WRKY3, WRK15, WRK35, WRK18 were all down-regulated in response to drought in the drought sensitive chickpea genotype
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. In contrast, WRKY24 and WRK23 were up-regulated in the tolerant genotype. In 
 <italic>Urochondra</italic> too, the expression of WRKY was found up-regulated under salinity. WRKY TFs not only have the ability to modulate gene expression in response to plant stress but also in the plant defence mechanism as they form a highly interacting regulatory network
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
