<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The high penetration depth of hard X-rays in the XAS method provides obvious advantages for 
 <italic>in situ</italic> and 
 <italic>operando</italic> studies by ensuring sufficient flexibility in the choice of sample environment geometry and materials used. However, in many cases, spectroscopical investigations in the soft X-ray range (with X-ray energies below 5 keV) can provide important clues about catalyst structure.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref112">112</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref113">113</xref>
 </sup> For example, L-edges (and even M-edges) of transition metals can be accessed in soft X-ray/UHV experiments, which may be more sensitive to the oxidation state of the catalyst than K-edges. This fact was employed by Kornienko et al. for the determination of the oxidation state of Co in CoS
 <sub>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </sub> catalysts for water splitting (hydrogen evolution reaction)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref114">114</xref>
 </sup> and by Cheng et al. and Zhu et al. to determine the Ni oxidation state in Ni-based MOF catalysts for oxygen reduction/evolution reactions and urea oxidation reaction, respectively.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref115">115</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref116">116</xref>
 </sup> Hydride formation in the presence of hydrogen in Pd-based electrocatalysts for CO
 <sub>2</sub> electroreduction, in turn, can be conveniently followed by using XAS at L-edges of Pd.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref117">117</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, information from the K-edges of light elements can provide important complementary insight about the structure of multielement catalysts,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref114">114</xref>
 </sup> or that of the electrolyte,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref84">84</xref>
 </sup> interactions between adsorbates and catalysts,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref118">118</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref119">119</xref>
 </sup> and structural motifs in carbon-based materials that are currently used as nonprecious metal catalysts for the CO
 <sub>2</sub> electroreduction and oxygen reduction reactions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref120">120</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref123">123</xref>
 </sup> An excellent review on the measurements and interpretation of O K-edge XAS was recently published by Frati et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref83">83</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
