<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">Overall, we screened 135 (39 + 96) DE lncRNAs and 1360 (764 + 596) DE mRNAs in pineal gland at follicular and luteal phases between high and low prolificacy STH sheep (WW vs ww). GO annotation and KEGG enrichment analysis of top 20 terms indicated that DE mRNAs were enriched in reproduction-related pathways such as GnRH, cGMP-PKG, thyroid hormone, MAPK, phototransduction, circadian rhythm, steroid biosynthesis, hippo, mTOR and melanogenesis. It is well known that productive cycle of mammals is regulated through association or acting alone of hypothalamic-pituitary-thyroid (HPT) axis and hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal (HPG) axis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In the HPT axis, thyrotropin-releasing hormone (TRH) produced in hypothalamus stimulates pituitary to secrete thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH), which promotes TH synthesis in the thyroid gland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In the HPG axis, GnRH in hypothalamus regulates synthesis and secretion of FSH and LH in the anterior pituitary. These two hormones stimulate gonadal estrogen synthesis by binding to their receptors for affecting development and maturation of follicles and the ewes litter size. Estrogen in turn positively or negatively acts GnRH synthesis, and affects 
 <italic>FSHβ</italic> gene expression, a hormone specific 
 <italic>β</italic> subunit that is mainly regulated by GnRH [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In the process, binding of GnRH to its receptor activates signaling cascades like MAPK, PI3K-Akt [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. MAPK pathway is essential for cell proliferation and differentiation, survival, death and transformation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. PI3K-Akt can interact with mTOR pathway to effectively regulate growth hormone in pituitary [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Additionally, pathways as hippo modulates organ size growth by controlling stem cell activity, proliferation and apoptosis. For instance, its’ effect on the development of pituitary progenitor cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Our results showed that DE genes like 
 <italic>AKT3</italic>, 
 <italic>MYC</italic>, 
 <italic>PIK3CB</italic>, 
 <italic>MAP2K2</italic>, 
 <italic>PLCB1</italic> and 
 <italic>TEAD1</italic> related to thyroid hormone, MAPK, cGMP-PKG, hippo, and up regulated, while 
 <italic>CTNNB1</italic>, 
 <italic>YAP1</italic>, 
 <italic>PIK3CG</italic>, 
 <italic>TEAD1</italic>, 
 <italic>CAMK2A</italic>, 
 <italic>CACNA1D</italic> mainly related to hippo, thyroid hormone, cGMP-PKG, AMPK, GnRH, oxytocin, circadian entrainment, and down regulated, which implied the important roles of these genes mainly involved in regulation of hormone-related pathways. It’s worth exploring their function in pineal gland as candidate genes.
</p>
