<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Co-expression analysis of differential lncRNA-mRNA and functional prediction of target genes revealed that lncRNA affects sheep fecundity by modulating genes associated with above signaling pathways and biological processes. In 
 <italic>FecB</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>BB</italic>
 </sup> genotype sheep, 
 <italic>XLOC_466330</italic> and the targets (
 <italic>RRM2B</italic>, 
 <italic>GSTK1</italic>) up regulated at follicular phase, which related to GSH metabolism. Whereas 
 <italic>XLOC_391199</italic> and the target (
 <italic>STMN1</italic>), 
 <italic>XLOC_503926</italic>, 
 <italic>XLOC_517836</italic> and the target (
 <italic>RAG2</italic>) up regulated at luteal phase, which mainly enriched in MAPK, FoxO signaling pathways, respectively. In 
 <italic>FecB</italic>
 <sup>++</sup> genotype sheep, 
 <italic>XLOC_347557</italic> and the target (
 <italic>GPX2</italic>), 
 <italic>XLOC_532771</italic> and the targets (
 <italic>LOC101111397</italic>, 
 <italic>RRM2B</italic>), 
 <italic>XLOC_339502</italic> and the target (
 <italic>GPX1</italic>), 
 <italic>XLOC_028449</italic> and the target (
 <italic>GSTK1</italic>) up regulated at follicular phase, which also related to GSH metabolism. Meanwhile, 
 <italic>105,604,037</italic> and the target (
 <italic>MGST1</italic>), 
 <italic>XLOC_187711</italic> and the target (
 <italic>DLG4</italic>) down regulated at the same phase that related to GSH metabolism and hippo signaling. Wherein 
 <italic>GSTK1</italic> and 
 <italic>RRM2B</italic> involved in GSH metabolism at follicular phase, but their targeted regulators lncRNAs were markedly different among two 
 <italic>FecB</italic> genotypes. 
 <italic>RRM2B</italic> gene encodes p53R2, and p53R2 is expressed at all phases of cell cycle to ensure ample supply of mitochondrial DNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. 
 <italic>GSTK1</italic> gene encodes a member of GSTK superfamily of enzymes that function in cellular mitochondria and peroxisomes detoxification during GSH metabolism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], a critical pathway protecting cells from free radicals and oxidative damage, could increase intracellular NADPH [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. With increase of NADPH oxidase, ROS level tend to be low, whereas the level of intracellular ATP enhanced, as well as mitochondrial activity, which promote oocyte maturation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], and so forth, the other DE genes involved in GSH metabolism were also novel direction of interest for their effects on the downstream reproductive system.
</p>
