<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The miRNAs have been demonstrated to play a significant role during seed development in plants (Rodrigues &amp; Miguel, 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Functional analysis of miR156 revealed its important role during embryogenesis in Arabidopsis via regulating 
 <italic>SPL</italic> (Nodine &amp; Bartel, 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) and grain filling associated with seed size/weight determination in rice (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). miR156 was also identified and shown to target 
 <italic>SPL</italic> during seed development in soybean, maize, barley, and wheat (Curaba et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Li, Liu, et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Meng et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Shamimuzzaman &amp; Vodkin, 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>), suggesting the conserved roles of miR156 in seed development across diverse plant species. In this study, we also found that members of the miR156 family were differentially expressed between the two chickpea cultivars. Moreover, their target 
 <italic>SPL</italic> genes exhibited the antagonistic expression pattern between the two cultivars, suggesting the possible role of miR156 in the regulation of seed development and seed size/weight in chickpea too. The role of another transcription factor, 
 <italic>GRF4,</italic> is well established to govern seed development and seed size/weight determination in Arabidopsis and rice (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Debernardi et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Li, Gao, et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). GRF regulates cell growth and division via activating the brassinosteroid signaling pathway (Tang &amp; Chu, 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). The overexpression of miR396 at embryogenesis stages was associated with smaller seed size, whereas reduced expression of miR396 resulted in larger seed size in Arabidopsis and rice (Debernardi et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Li, Gao, et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). In chickpea, miR396 showed higher expression at the embryonic (S1) stage of the small‐seeded cultivar as compared to large‐seeded cultivar and its target gene, 
 <italic>GRF4,</italic> exhibited antagonistic expression pattern with respect to miRNA, i.e., greater expression in the larger‐seeded cultivar. This observation suggests a role of miR396‐GRF in seed size/weight determination in chickpea. Interestingly, miR397 has been reported to positively regulate seed yield in rice and Arabidopsis (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). In these studies, over‐expression of miR397 exhibited increased seed yield via repression of 
 <italic>LACCASE</italic> (
 <italic>LAC</italic>) like gene (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Higher expression of the 
 <italic>LAC</italic> gene has been shown to accumulate higher lignin content in the cell wall (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Lignin provides rigidity to the cell wall and thereby may regulate seed size in smaller‐seeded cultivar showing higher expression of 
 <italic>LAC</italic>. In chickpea, miR397 was found to be highly expressed in the large‐seeded cultivar and shown to target 
 <italic>LAC</italic> transcript. Additionally, miR398 was found to target multiple genes, including those encoding copper ion binding proteins and transporters. miR398 has been widely studied and increased stress tolerance by modulating copper/zinc superoxide dismutase and transporter proteins in plants (Zhao et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). In a recent study, overexpression of miR398 increased seed yield in rice (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="pld3299-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>).
</p>
