<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The metabolism can provide energy and materials required for all biological processes, such that the balance between catabolic and anabolic pathways is essential to meet various biological needs of living organisms [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Viruses are obligate intracellular parasites that obtain all energy and materials necessary for infection and replication in hosts. Generally, viruses can generate their own suitable intracellular microenvironment for their viral life cycle by altering the host’s cellular metabolic network [
 <xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. By analyzing the DEGs, we found that the levels of IGF1R, ACLY, HMGCR, HMGCS1, ACSS2, INSIG1, and LPIN1 genes were significantly up-regulated during the BVDV life cycle. The IGF-1 receptor (IGF1R) binds with highest affinity to the insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1), while ligand binding, in turn, regulates gene transcription, as well as the glucose, lipid, and protein metabolisms, in addition to cell growth and differentiation [
 <xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The ACLY gene is related to intramuscular fat deposition in cattle, which is of great significance for improving the quality of breeding beef [
 <xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. HMGCR, HMGCS1, and ACSS2 are mainly associated with improved growth performance and meat quality [
 <xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38–41</xref>]. The lipid phosphate phosphohydrolase (LPIN), also known as the lipoprotein gene, is a family of genes that can bidirectionally regulate the fat metabolism [
 <xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. LPIN1 is a key gene for regulating the formation and differentiation of adipose tissue, and studies have shown that non-expression, normal expression, and over-expression of the LPIN1 gene can cause dramatic changes in fat deposition [
 <xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. INSIG, SCAP, and SREBPs together constitute the INSIG-SCAP-SREBPs transfer system, which is stored in the form of complexes in the endoplasmic reticulum. Intracellular cholesterol can affect the activation of the INSIG-SCAP-SREBPs, which in turn regulates the transcription of low-density lipoprotein receptors. Ultimately, feedback regulates the cellular intake of exogenous cholesterol [
 <xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Significantly, these up-regulated genes are mainly related to the lipid metabolism, indicating that BVDV may alter the host lipid metabolism to promote self-survival during BVDV life cycle. Further investigation 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> will be required to confirm these findings.
</p>
