<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, 156 significantly DE lncRNAs in BVDV-infected MDBK cells were obtained, including 72 up-regulated lncRNAs and 84 down-regulated lncRNAs. We found that the location of the lncRNAs in the genome appeared to be nonrandom, indicating a link between lncRNA function and genomic location. Using RNA interference, a previous study found that a group of human lncRNAs act as enhancers to activate their adjacent genes, such as SCL, SNA1, and SNA2 by cis action [
 <xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], demonstrating the co-expression relationship between lncRNA and its nearby protein-coding genes. Other findings have reported that the lncRNA-mediated cis-regulation of adjacent gene transcription is ubiquitous and a major mode in gene regulation of mammalian [
 <xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Therefore, understanding the cis-regulation of lncRNA is crucial to reveal the biological significance of lncRNAs. In this study, several lncRNAs (LOC112443855, LOC112448807, LOC100847453, and LOC101904128, among others) were identified in cis-regulation with apoptosis-related protein-coding genes during BVDV infection. Autophagy is also a crucial mechanism in host resistance to infection, and several studies have reported that BVDV infection significantly increased cellular autophagy in MDBK cells [
 <xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Our Illumina sequencing data also demonstrated that some lncRNAs targeted autophagy-related genes ATG4D, ATG16L1, ATG16L2, and ATG5. Moreover, lncRNA provides more complexity for gene regulatory networks and some lncRNAs function through trans-acting, such as LOC107132573. We also found that the expression levels of several lncRNAs were significantly increased in BVDV-infected MDBK cells, including LOC101902030, LOC107132820, LOC107131785, LOC101905509, and LOC104972797. Moreover, their target protein-coding genes were MRPL14, ESPNL, GABPB1, KIAA0895L, and RIMS2, which were located in trans-position (
 <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). 
</p>
