<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>KEGG pathway enrichment analysis for DEGs could help to understand the signal transduction pathways that are activated or inhibited in host cells after BVDV infection and provide insights into the interactions between BVDV and its host. Our Illumina sequencing analysis of the alterations in gene expression of BVDV-stimulated MDBK cells provided important data on the specific aspects of molecular pathogenesis and virus–host interactions. Previous study has shown that BVDV strain NADL-infected MDBK cells were significantly enriched for target genes of lncRNAs that were involved in host immune responses, such as T cell receptor signaling pathway, TNF signaling pathway, and Jak-STAT signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], which were also found the enrichment of these target genes in the related pathways in our study. Moreover, in this study, we also found that many differentially expressed genes in cytopathic biotype BVDV-infected MDBK cells showed significant enrichment in NOD-like receptor signaling pathway, NF-κB signaling pathway, Hippo signaling pathway, and apoptosis pathway. All of these signaling pathways are involved in the regulation of MDBK cells stimulated by BVDV, providing useful data for the development of novel preventive or therapeutic strategies against BVDV. We also found that the significantly DE cis-and trans-acting lncRNAs contributed to regulation of autophagy signaling pathway, cytokine–cytokine receptor interaction, PI3K-Akt signaling pathway, and PPAR signaling pathway associated with the host immune response to BVDV infection. Undoubtedly, the transcriptome data obtained by RNA-seq will help us better understand the molecular mechanism of BVDV infection and host immune responses involved in host–virus interaction. Several DEGs detected in BVDV-infected MDBK cells were novel, alternative splicing isoforms, or related to signaling pathways. The expression of virus resistance genes could be part of the mechanisms by which BVDV escapes from the host immune defense system. Our data would provide a useful scientific reference for improving our understanding of the roles of host lncRNAs in the modulation of BVDV replication and pathogenesis.
</p>
