<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">In the present study, reproductive-stage water-deficit stress imposed on the parents of Australian durum wheat varieties showed significant impacts at the physiological level. In crops, photosynthesis plays a central role in energy metabolism, being a key physiological trait for assessing plant fitness under adverse conditions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. In general, water-deficit stress inhibits the photosynthesis process in the leaves, mainly due to oxidative damage in the photosynthesis apparatus, which can be reflected by significantly reduced chlorophyll content
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Here, during early to mid-stages of grain fill (10–30 DPA), under water-deficit stress, DBA Artemis progeny plants from the stressed parents had significantly higher chlorophyll content than those progeny originating from the control parents (Fig. 0.1). Moreover, in DBA Artemis, although progeny from both the control and stressed parents showed significantly reduced stomatal conductance under water-deficit stress, the rate of reduction compared with its control was less evident in the progeny from the stressed parents (Fig. 0.1). The results suggest that transgenerational stress had potentially beneficial impacts on the photosynthetic and the transpiration processes in the next generation. Leaf stomatal conductance controls the gas exchange and water vapour diffusion between plants and the atmosphere
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. Under water-deficit stress, stomatal conductance plays a key role in coordinating the CO
 <sub>2</sub> availability and cellular water relations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Plants can benefit from stomatal closure under water-deficit stress to maintain a higher cellular water potential, but high rate of stomatal closure can significantly inhibit the CO
 <sub>2</sub> assimilation process
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, less reduced stomatal closure in the progeny plants from the stressed parents can be considered as an adaptive change to allow for greater stomatal opening, which would contribute to higher cellular water turgidity and less oxidative damage to the photosynthetic apparatus, as reflected by the higher chlorophyll content. Efficient photosynthesis under water-deficit stress will have positive impacts towards successful reproductive development, which ultimately affects crop yield and grain quality
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
