<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">The positive impacts of transgenerational stress was significant on selected yield components as well as grain quality characteristics in the current study. In DBA Artemis, the harvest index significantly increased in the progeny from the stress parents compared with progeny from the control parents. Notably, when exposed to stress, progeny from the stressed parents produced the highest 1000-grain weight and grain protein content. The grains of progeny from the stressed parents also had higher flour yellowness (b*), which is a preferential grain quality trait that gives the grain its amber colour. Similarly, in bread wheat, drought stress applied at reproductive stages in the previous generation had positive impacts on the yield components and grain quality traits in the successive generation when exposed to salt stress
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. The progeny of stressed parents performed better with respect to productive tiller number, grains per spike, grain yield and harvest index when compared to progeny of well-watered parents
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. The transgenerational effects of water-deficit stress can be partially explained by changes in seed provisioning and nutrient composition of wheat grains. In the bread wheat study, seeds from the stressed crops had a higher percentage of protein and total soluble phenolics than the well-watered seed source
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, our previous research
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> has also shown that the grain protein content of DBA Artemis was significantly increased by water-deficit stress, while the total phenolic content remains unaffected (DBA Artemis was denoted as breeding line L2 in the previous study, with the variety commercially released post-publication). Changes in the concentration of grain nutrients were mainly affected by limited water availability during reproductive development. The accumulation of stress proteins in developing wheat grains can significantly increase under water-deficit stress, which would also affect the protein–protein interaction network
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. The stress-responsive miRNA-guided regulation of storage protein biosynthesis could play a key role here
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. The accumulation of stress proteins, storage metabolites and compounds with antioxidant properties (such as phenolics) in maternal plants may potentially facilitate more growth-effective metabolic processes and a swift response in progeny plants upon recurring stress conditions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. The decrease of specific miRNAs under water-deficit stress can lead to higher expression of protein synthesis-related genes and increased accumulation of protein bodies in wheat grains
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. Future research could further explore the association between changes in individual grain nutrients and progeny stress performance. It is also worth noting that the impacts of transgenerational stress varied depending on the genotype, and therefore might not be generalised within a crop species. In the current study, the beneficial effects of the parental stress treatment was predominantly observed in DBA Artemis, which has lower tolerance to water-deficit stress than DBA Aurora. Similarly in rice, varieties with contrasting drought resistance levels showed genotypic differences in response to successive generations of drought stress training
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. At the molecular level, the stress-sensitive variety had a higher rate of stable transmission of DNA methylation variations across generations when compared with the stress-tolerant variety
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, cross-generational stress improvement could potentially be more effective in germplasm that are less tolerant to abiotic stress, but have other superior agronomic traits for breeding purposes. However, further experimental evidence using different stress-tolerant varieties should be sought. Future research could therefore include a diverse germplasm panel with different sensitivity levels to stress, and investigate both the physiological and molecular level. It is also worth noting that differences in the grain traits from the control and stressed parents could have contributed to the varied crop performance in the next generation. Our previous report had characterised the grain weight per plant, 1000-grain weight, total protein content, total starch content and phenolics content of the grains harvested from control and stressed parents
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, the water-deficit stressed DBA Aurora parents produced bigger grains than the control parents (significantly higher 1000-grain weight) while no significant difference was observed in DBA Artemis. Grains from the stressed parents of both varieties had significantly higher grain protein content compared with the control. For total starch content and total phenolic content, both traits remained unaffected for DBA Artemis but decreased significantly in the stressed DBA Aurora parents. Research has shown that a difference in parent seed size and seed reserves (such as storage proteins and carbohydrates), can significantly affect the growth rate of the progeny particularly during seedling stages, thereby potentially influencing final crop performance
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. Future research should further explore the associations between different parental seed traits (morphological or quality aspects) and progeny growth traits (yield, morphological or physiological) in durum wheat germplasm.
</p>
