<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">Cross-generation stress improvement relies on changes in the genetic and/or epigenetic regulation at the molecular level. Here, we investigated the effects of transgenerational water-deficit stress on the miRNA-guided gene regulation using three next-generation sequencing omics platforms. Overall, in the flag leaf, there were a higher number of stress-responsive DEMs and DEGs in the progeny from the stressed parents compared with the progeny from the control parents (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">S5</xref>), suggesting that the miRNA and mRNA populations were more responsive under the effects of transgenerational stress. Specifically, miRNA-mRNA modules that have exhibited significant differential regulatory patterns between progeny with different sources have been noted. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> shows the significant miRNA-mRNA modules with antagonistic regulatory patterns (from Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM20" ref-type="media">S15</xref>) that are involved in key biological pathways (e.g. ko04075—plant hormone signal transduction, and ko00710—carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms). The functional targets in the plant hormone signal transduction pathway include genes like auxin response factor, protein phosphatase 2C, TIFY-domain proteins, and jasmonic acid-amido synthetase (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The functional targets in the carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms pathway include genes like malate dehydrogenase, fructose-bisphosphate aldolase and ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Under water-deficit stress, up-regulation of functional targets induced by lower miRNA expression could contribute to the accumulation of protective proteins and metabolites, increasing the chances of plant fitness and survival. For example, in the flag leaf tissue of DBA Artemis, a target of bdi-miR394, a glutathione reductase gene was significantly up-regulated in the stress-treated progeny from the stressed parents, and showed the highest expression level across all treatment groups (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Glutathione reductase plays a key role in the ascorbate–glutathione (Asc-Glu) cycle, which promotes the scavenging of reactive oxygen species (ROS). In cowpea and common bean plants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>, increased glutathione reductase gene expression and protein activity has significantly contributed to the capacity of stressed plants to maintain cellular homeostasis through an enhanced antioxidant capacity. Moreover, the Asc-Glu cycle in the chloroplast can provide antioxidant protection to the photosynthetic pigments through effective detoxification of the excess ROS, which can contribute to a higher photosynthesis efficiency in the plant
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. In bread wheat, increased expression of genes in the Asc-Glu cycle had contributed to stable photosynthetic capacity under drought stress, as shown by a high photosynthetic rate and chlorophyll content
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. High stomatal conductance was also maintained to achieve better balance of water loss and CO
 <sub>2</sub> assimilation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly in the current study, the stress-primed progeny showed higher chlorophyll content and stomatal conductance in accordance with higher expression of the glutathione reductase gene. Here, the positive transgenerational effects via miRNA regulation in durum provides a new option to enhance crop performance. In the flag leaf tissue of DBA Artemis, the expression of bdi-miR394 was significantly lower in both the control and stressed progeny from the stressed parents compared with the control progeny from the control parents, which showed no statistical difference to the stressed progeny from the control parents (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In this case, the results suggest that in DBA Artemis, the less stress-tolerant variety, the miR394-glutathione reductase module was primed under the transgenerational effects, and the lowered miR394 abundance allowed for rapid accumulation of glutathione reductase upon stress occurrence. This could serve the stress adaptation process via maintaining the cellular redox balance and allowing for enhanced photosynthetic performance. However, given that the glutathione reductase gene did not show any significant change in the flag leaf of DBA Aurora (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), this mechanism appears not to be active in DBA Aurora. For bdi-miR394, it showed higher expression in the stressed progeny from the control parents and control progeny from the stressed parents, while stressed progeny from the stress parents showed no significant difference to the control progeny from the control parents (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). In DBA Artemis, the ata-miR167b-3p and cytidylate kinase pair which also showed transgenerational stress-induced expression may also contribute to the photosynthetic process via the role of cytidylate kinase in energy management in the chloroplast
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. Further studies could investigate the expression patterns of these modules across different vegetative and reproductive stages under the effects of transgenerational stress, with links to the physiological performance, to determine whether they can be used as early indicators of a broader adaptive response.
</p>
