<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">Another example of the transgenerational effects on miRNA regulation is the pair of osa-miR827 and the EamA-like transporter family. Similar to bdi-miR394, in DBA Artemis, the expression of osa-miR827 in the flag leaf was significantly lower in the progeny from the stressed parents, compared with the control progeny from the control parents (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Its target gene, the EamA-like transporter family member, correspondingly showed significantly higher expression in the progeny from the stressed parents (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). However, neither osa-miR827 or the target gene exhibited any significant expression change in the flag leaf of DBA Aurora (Supplementary Figs. 
 <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S2</xref>,
 <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). The MtN21/EamA-like transporters were first considered as nodulin proteins, but with emerging new functions in amino acid and auxin transport in non-nodulating species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. Studies in Arabidopsis demonstrate that members in this family are novel vacuolar facilitators of auxin transport that are required for cellular auxin homoeostasis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. So far, the MtN21/EamA-like transporters have not been functionally characterised in durum wheat. However, interestingly, the EamA-like transporter gene has been reported in several major QTL studies in cereal crops. In bread wheat, it is located underlying major QTLs for kernel weight
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup> as well as spike number per unit area
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>. The possible contribution of the EamA-like transporters towards abiotic stress tolerance has also been noted. In Egyptian spring barley
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>, a molecular marker associated with increased proline content, increased chlorophyll content, and decreased reduction in grain yield under heat stress encodes an EamA-like transporter family protein with potential positive functions towards thermo-tolerance. In chickpea, several single nucleotide polymorphisms were found in the MtN21/EamA-like transporter genes, which showed significant association with better crop yield performance under drought conditions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
 </sup>. In durum wheat, the transgenerational effects on the osa-miR827 and EamA-like transporter module could have similar positive impacts towards maintaining chlorophyll content and yield stability, as observed in DBA Artemis under water-deficit stress but not in DBA Aurora where the transgenerational effects were less pronounced. Future research could aim to determine and validate the exact function(s) of osa-miR827 and the EamA-like transporter in both stress-tolerant and -sensitive durum varieties, thereby exploring any possible relationship between auxin transport and transgenerational memory.
</p>
