<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Over the past decade, flexible electronics
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup> have undergone rapid developments in the fields of wearable
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> and implantable devices
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>, flexible displays
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>, and even flexible radio frequency identification tags
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. Li-ion battery is the most developed energy supply technology that satisfies high demands in energy, power, and long cycle life
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. For these reasons, flexible Li-ion batteries have gained particular attention as a future energy storage solution for lightweight and flexible devices
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. The widely used method for fabricating Li-ion electrodes (i.e., web-coating method), however, is unable to adequately satisfy these requirements
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, Cu and Al metal foils, which are generally used as current collector and support to spread the cathode or anode ink, lose contact with the active material during repeated bending
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, the conventional method usually employs costly binders (such as polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF)) that are dissolved in solvents (e.g., N-methyl-2-pyrrolidone (NMP)), which are characterized by high toxicity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. Drying such electrodes also consumes a significant amount of energy because of their high boiling point (204.3 °C) and low vapor pressure (e.g., 1 mm Hg at 40 °C for NMP)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. A greener process that employs sodium carboxymethyl cellulose as a low-cost binder and water as solvent has been reported
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>; however, some major problems have to be resolved. Water-based electrodes exhibit agglomeration effects, poor ink homogeneity, and residual moisture after drying, which considerably reduce the cycle life of the battery
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. According to the cost modeling proposed by Wood 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>, the composite electrode materials and current collectors account for practically 50% of the cost of a Li-ion battery. Furthermore, to avoid corrosion problems that result from contact with electrolytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>, the use of a current collector, especially an Al foil, significantly reduces the battery’s energy density. For instance, the Al current collector represents 40% of the total mass of an LFP electrode with an active material loading of approximately 6 mg·cm
 <sup>−2</sup>.
</p>
