<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">To resolve the foregoing problems, free-standing electrode films are proposed as a low-cost alternative to fabricate flexible Li-ion electrodes. Free-standing films are generally fabricated according to a paper-making process that is well-known and appropriate for producing substantial amounts of electrodes. Recently, paper
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>, textile
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>, and other organic substrates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> are reported to be potential components for flexible electrodes because of their good flexibility; however, they cannot be used alone because of their poor electronic conductivity. In view this, self-standing films made of two-dimensional (2D) or unidimensional (1D) carbons have been developed in parallel. These afford a high electronic conductivity and a strong network mainly because of the π-stacking effect (2D carbon) or the interlacing of carbon fibers (1D carbon). For instance, flexible LFP and LTO electrodes made of graphene as a 2D carbon are reported by Shi 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Alternatively, the use of 1D carbons, such as carbon nanotubes (CNT) or vapor-grown carbon fibers (VGCF) is also proposed to generate a solid 3D network in which the porosity is filled with redox active materials
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. The cost of such electrodes, however, limits the scale-up of this fabrication method. To maintain good electronic conductivity without affecting film integrity, a mixture of cellulose fibers with 2D or 1D carbons are often reported in literature as a less expensive option for fabricating self-standing electrode films. Cornell 
 <italic>et al</italic>. fabricated an LFP composite electrode made of 1D polyacrylonitrile carbon fibers (CF) and TEMPO-oxidized cellulose nanofibrils as binder
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. The electrode exhibits a high Young’s modulus of approximately 201±12.7 MPa and an electrical conductivity of 95S·cm
 <sup>−1</sup>; it delivers ~121 mAh·g
 <sup>−1</sup> when cycled at C/10 versus a self-standing CF electrode. In another study, an LFP free-standing flexible composite electrode was prepared by the vacuum filtration method with 2D graphene and nanofibrillated cellulose additives
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, the paper-making process also allowed the electrodes (cathode and anode) and the separator to be integrated into a single flexible and strong structure resulting from successive filtration steps
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. Numerous examples of cathodes (LFP
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>), anodes (MoS
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>, graphite
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>, Si
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>), and even full Li-ion cells (LFP/graphite
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, LFP/LTO
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>) have been successfully prepared through the paper-making process using different forms of cellulose as binder. Finally, several works have reported flexible electrodes for batteries and supercapacitors that employ cellulose as substrate
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup> or binder
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Most fabrication methods, however, still involve the use of organic solvents, synthetic binders, or high-cost materials that are not easily disposed.
</p>
