<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">In this paper, a green, inexpensive, rapid, and innovative process for fabricating self-standing Li-ion electrodes is presented. This proposed method particularly avoids the use of resistive and costly binders (i.e., PVDF) as well as volatile and toxic solvents (e.g., NMP). Based on the paper-making process, the method includes the filtration of an aqueous solution that contains millimetric cellulose fibers (FB) with carbon or a mixture of different carbons and redox active materials (LFP, PTCDA, graphite, or LTO). The preparation time of the electrode is considerably reduced because the grinding, component mixing (conductive additive, binder, anode/cathode material), and slurry preparation steps are replaced by a single step to produce a self-standing film. The present method also allows the amount of carbon in the film to be increased because aluminum and copper current collectors are not used. The first steps that is performed is the deposition of cellulose and carbon fibers to form an integrated carbon-rich current collector. The second step involves the formation of the cathode or anode film on the freshly deposited carbon layer. Following this method, both conventional binders and current collectors are not utilized, thus considerably reducing the fabrication cost of the battery. Moreover, substituting the mass of Al/Cu foils with carbon and cellulose fibers results in stronger electrodes and a more conductive film, thereby leading to better performances. This process could also be less expensive than the casting method, which is commonly used in the fabrication of Li-ion electrodes, because low-cost and abundant materials are used (water, PTCDA, and raw cellulose fibers). Tables 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">SI1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">SI2</xref> in the Supporting Information report the price of raw materials used for making electrodes and a cost estimation of both the conventional and the new fabrication method to clearly show the cost saving of our method. In order to facilitate the dispersion of carbons (including graphite as active material) and LFP in water, water-soluble groups, such as aryl-COOH and aryl-SO
 <sub>3</sub>H moieties, are attached to their surface by diazonium chemistry. Generally, self-standing electrodes reported in literature do not employ such modified carbons or modified LFP, making the proposed process innovative and unique. In this process, commercially available cellulose fibers are utilized with no additional transformations to obtain shorter fibers or modified Z-potentials. In most cases, such as in the paper-making industry, aluminum sulfate hydrate is used as a flocculating agent before carbon is added
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. This adjuvant is utilized to neutralize the negative charge present in the cellulose fibers by aluminum cations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. This compound, however, can further react inside the battery; hence, it is removed from our fabrication process. In recent works, it has been demonstrated that microfibrillated cellulose and highly refined cellulose fibers dispersed in water can be effectively used as binder to elaborate self-standing negative electrodes with excellent electrochemical and mechanical performances
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. To obtain fibers in the diameter range of 5–250 nm, acid hydrolysis, and chemical and enzymatic treatments are necessary. These steps, however, incur additional costs and increase preparation time
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
