<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are few available studies on ACY-3. It has been reported that ACY-3 mainly localizes to the cytoplasm of proximal tubule epithelial cells, participates in the detoxification process of foreign substances in kidney, and is associated with nephrotoxicity induced by metabolic products (mercapturic acid)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Many toxic substances can be excreted from the body through the mercapturic acid metabolic pathway
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>. The mercapturic acid metabolic pathway plays an important role in the protection of kidney functions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. Masereeuw 
 <italic>et al</italic>. reported
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref> that in the renal proximal tubule brush border, multidrug resistance-associated protein 2 (MRP2) is responsible for the secretion of mercapturic acid into the urine. ACY-3 can catalyse the deacetylation of mercapturic acid, and the product of this reaction is non-toxic. However, with the action of cysteine-S-conjugated β-lyase, toxic substances are produced in the kidney. The precise enzymatic reaction in this metabolic process is still not clear. Mouse ACY-3 is composed of 4 homologous monomers. Each monomer is approximately 35 kDa. ACY-3 localizes to the apical membrane of epithelial cells in the S1 segment of the renal proximal tubule. The resistance of ACY-3 to toxic substances in the kidney, thereby achieving protection of mitochondria in the S1 segment, can be explained by the following mechanisms: (1) reduction of the chance of activation of cysteine-S-conjugates (the production of toxic substances in the kidney is catalysed by mitochondrial cysteine-S-conjugated β-lyase); and (2) possible maintenance of the mercapturic acid gradient in cells and lumens through interaction with other proteins to promote the excretion of mercapturic acid by MRP2
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. The results of this study indicated that ACY-3 was present in the kidney tissues of both MT−/− and MT+/+ mice and that the level of ACY-3 in the kidney tissues of MT−/− mice was slightly higher than in MT+/+ mice. Upon DU exposure, ACY-3 levels decreased significantly in the kidney tissues of both MT−/− and MT+/+ mice. The reduction of ACY-3 expression in MT−/− mice was even more significant, with ACY-3 expression being nearly undetectable in these mice. These results suggested that after DU intoxication, the level of ACY-3 in kidney tissues changed significantly; thus, the kidney was more prone to injury. MT could reduce this injury to some extent. Due to the loss of the MT gene, MT−/− mice exhibited significantly decrease in ACY-3 expression levels; therefore, ACY-3 might not exert a protective function on DU-induced mitochondrial injury and apoptosis. Thus, MT−/− mice were more sensitive to DU-induced nephrotoxicity. Further in-depth studies are still required to understand the roles of ACY-3 in DU intoxication and protection roles by MT.
</p>
