<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ETHE1 is a mitochondrial sulfur dioxygenase discovered in recent years. ETHE1 exhibits a molecular weight of 30 kDa and is associated with energy production. The protein is homodimeric and contains a metallo-β-lactamase domain. ETHE1 is involved in metabolic homeostasis in mitochondria and can bind to nuclear transcription factors and translocate to the cytoplasm to inhibit p53-induced apoptosis
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. Studies
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref> have shown that a defect in the ETHE1 gene can induce a severe mitochondrial disease (ethylmalonic encephalopathy), causing energy metabolism disorders in cells. The results of this study showed that ETHE1 levels in the kidney tissues of MT−/− and MT+/+ mice decreased significantly after DU exposure, suggesting the possibility of increased cell apoptosis. The reduction of ETHE1 expression observed in MT−/− mice was even more significant. In addition, exogenous MT could significantly increase the survival of HEK 293 cells after DU exposure, and the survival rate of ETHE1 siRNA-treated cells was lower than that of the negative control cells (transfected with empty vectors). These results further indicated that ETHE1 is involved in the DU-induced nephrotoxicity process. MT might reduce DU-induced kidney cell injury partially through inhibiting the reduction of ETHE1. The results of this study also suggested that DU exerted its cytotoxicity function and promoted kidney cell apoptosis through the reduction of ETHE1, which might represent a new route of DU intoxication. Further analyses confirmed that ETHE1 mainly localized in the mitochondria and that following DU exposure, HEK293 cells subjected to ETHE1 knockdown through siRNA interference exhibited higher apoptosis rates compared with the negative control cells. Exogenous ETHE1 protein could significantly relieve the reduction of the mitochondrial membrane potential, alleviated the swelling of mitochondria under TEM and reduce cell apoptosis after DU exposure, suggesting that ETHE1 might be involved in DU-induced cell apoptosis and could be a new DU toxicity-sensitive protein.
</p>
