<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The striatum plays an important role in a wide range of neurological disorders including obsessive-compulsive disorder, Huntington’s and Parkinson’s disease, and drug addiction [
 <xref rid="B1-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Substance abuse is one of several neurological diseases that involves specific cell types in the brain. For example, psychostimulants such as cocaine block the reuptake of dopamine leading to increased synaptic concentrations of neurotransmitter. Subsequently, this leads to aberrant signaling in specific sub-types of the γ-aminobutyric acid producing (GABAergic) medium-sized spiny neurons (MSNs) that comprise 95% of the neurons of the striatum [
 <xref rid="B5-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Although morphologically similar, there are two large sub-types of striatal MSNs that differ in their projection patterns as well as in their expression of D1- or D2-classes of dopamine receptors [
 <xref rid="B8-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Although the “direct” pathway dMSNs express relatively high levels of the D1 dopamine receptor (D1R), “indirect” pathway iMSNs express high levels of the D2 dopamine receptor (D2R) [
 <xref rid="B8-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. D1 and D2 dopamine receptors are differentially coupled to either increased or decreased cAMP signaling, respectively. Thus, exposure to psychostimulants results in opposite patterns of phosphorylation by cAMP-dependent protein kinase of important intracellular targets such as DARPP-32 in intermixed sub-populations of MSNs [
 <xref rid="B9-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Biochemical analysis of striatum, in the absence of separation of different MSN cell types, leads to an averaging of the increased or decreased signals, and a loss of important information [
 <xref rid="B10-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. 
</p>
