<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since D1R- and D2R-MSNs, as with many other of the 500–1000 types of neurons and glia, exhibit distinct patterns of gene expression [
 <xref rid="B12-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], it is essential to develop complementary approaches to enable quantitative MS/proteomic analyses of specific neuronal cell types and their organelles and sub-cellular compartments. These approaches will further our understanding of changes in protein expression or localization, as well as of differential post-translational protein modifications by obviating dilution effects from analyzing multiple cell types together and by improving signal to noise ratios for proteins in the targeted cell type [
 <xref rid="B10-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Isolation of specific neural cell types is challenging due to their nonuniformity, intermingling, and complex projections to different brain regions. Two approaches that are being used to address this challenge are laser capture microdissection (LCM) [
 <xref rid="B14-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and fluorescence-activated cell (FACS) [
 <xref rid="B15-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and nuclear (FANS) [
 <xref rid="B18-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] sorting in conjunction with transgenic and viral tools to isolate cell type- and organelle-specific proteomes. A central feature of many of these methods is the use of transgenic mouse lines that express fluorescent proteins as affinity tags on specific proteins in specific neuronal cell types. These include Translating Ribosome Affinity Purification (TRAP) lines that were designed to profile mRNA translation in defined cell types [
 <xref rid="B21-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and that allow isolation of nuclei from specific cell types using FANS [
 <xref rid="B18-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. TRAP analyses revealed that dMSNs expressing the D1R have vastly different translational profiles than the iMSNs that express the D2R [
 <xref rid="B21-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Moreover, FANS analyses demonstrated that cocaine induces a significantly different pattern of histone modification in these two populations of mouse MSNs [
 <xref rid="B18-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. 
</p>
