<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>We thank Charles Duyckaerts (Neuroceb, GIE Neuro-CEB BB-0033-00011) for providing the brain samples. We would also like to thank Dr. Tarciso Velho, Pierre Dourlen, and Fabien Delahaye for reading and suggestions on the paper. The results published here are in whole or in part based on the data obtained from the AMP-AD Knowledge Portal (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://adknowledgeportal.synapse.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://adknowledgeportal.synapse.org/</ext-link>). Study data were provided by the following sources: The Mayo Clinic Alzheimer’s Disease Genetic Studies, led by Dr. Nilufer Taner and Dr. Steven G. Younkin, Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, FL using samples from the Mayo Clinic Study of Aging, the Mayo Clinic Alzheimer’s Disease Research Center, and the Mayo Clinic Brain Bank. Data collection was supported through funding by NIA grants P50 AG016574, R01 AG032990, U01 AG046139, R01 AG018023, U01 AG006576, U01 AG006786, R01 AG025711, R01 AG017216, R01 AG003949, NINDS grant R01 NS080820, CurePSP Foundation, and support from Mayo Foundation. Study data include samples collected through the Sun Health Research Institute Brain and Body Donation Program of Sun City, Arizona. The Brain and Body Donation Program is supported by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (U24 NS072026 National Brain and Tissue Resource for Parkinson’s Disease and Related Disorders), the National Institute on Aging (P30 AG19610 Arizona Alzheimer’s Disease Core Center), the Arizona Department of Health Services (contract 211002, Arizona Alzheimer’s Research Center), the Arizona Biomedical Research Commission (contracts 4001, 0011, 05-901, and 1001 to the Arizona Parkinson’s Disease Consortium) and the Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson’s Research. Study data were also provided by the Rush Alzheimer’s Disease Center, Rush University Medical Center, Chicago. Data collection was supported through funding by NIA grants P30AG10161 (ROS), R01AG15819 (ROSMAP; genomics and RNAseq), R01AG17917 (MAP), the Illinois Department of Public Health (ROSMAP), and the Translational Genomics Research Institute (genomic). For ROSMAP, additional phenotypic data can be requested at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.radc.rush.edu" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.radc.rush.edu</ext-link>. Part based on the data generated from postmortem brain tissue collected through the Mount Sinai VA Medical Center Brain Bank and were provided by Dr. Eric Schadt from Mount Sinai School of Medicine. This work was co-funded by the European Union under the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) and by the Hauts de France Regional Council (contrat no.18006176), the MEL (contract_2016_ESR_05), and the French State (contract no. 2018-3-CTRL_IPL_Phase2) to MRC. This work was also funded by the Lille Métropole Communauté Urbaine and the French government’s LABEX DISTALZ program (Development of innovative strategies for a transdisciplinary approach to Alzheimer’s disease) to J.C.L. D.M.C. and L.I.C.C. are supported by Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES) scholarships.
 </p>
</ack>
