<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2">
 <label>Fig. 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>CircRAB11FIP1 (hsa_circ_0005630) regulated the autophagic flux of epithelial ovarian cancer cells.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>A</bold> Regulating network analysis among circRNAs, miRNAs, and mRNAs. 
   <bold>B</bold>, 
   <bold>C</bold> Torin 1 was used to treat the SKOV3 and A2780 cell lines. qPCR was conducted to detect circRNA 24 h later. 
   <bold>D</bold> CircRAB11FIP1 expression levels of 30 pairs of epithelial ovarian cancer and non-carcinoma tissue samples. 
   <bold>E</bold> CircRAB11FIP1 expression levels in serum samples from 70 epithelial ovarian cancer and 30 matched non-carcinoma tissue samples. 
   <bold>F</bold> CircRAB11FIP1 expression levels were detected by qPCR. The LC3 level was measured by western blot analysis following circRAB11FIP1 silencing in SKOV3 cells, together with circRAB11FIP1 ectopic expression in A2780 cells. 
   <bold>G</bold> LV6-NC or LV6 was transfected into A2780 cells, and 3-MA or BAFA1 was added. western blot analysis was conducted to measure the LC3 level 48 h later. 
   <bold>H</bold>–
   <bold>J</bold> LV2-1, LV2-2, or LV2-NC was transfected into SKOV3 cells. LV6 or LV6-NC was transfected into A2780 cells. Later, confocal microscopy was performed to analyze the distribution of mRFP-GFP-LC3. 
   <bold>K</bold> RT-PCR was performed to detect specific circRNAs in SKOV3 and A2780 cells using convergent or divergent primers. Bp, base pair, a size marker. 
   <bold>L</bold> RT-PCR was carried out to amplify the full-length has_circRNA_005630 (circRAB11FIP1) in A2780 and SKOV3 cells, whereas AGE was used to confirm these amplified products. 
   <bold>M</bold> Sanger sequencing was performed to verify the head-to-tail splicing of circRAB11FIP1. Error bar stands for standard error. 
   <sup>*</sup>
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05. Scale bar = 5 µm.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41419_2021_3486_Fig2_HTML" id="d32e505" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
