<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, for the reliable determination of particle shapes from XAS data, several conditions need to be fulfilled. Similarly as with the interpretation of particle sizes, the NP geometry will affect significantly the XAS data only for small particles with sizes less than 4–5 nm. In the case of shape determination, this requirement is even more stringent because the number of different shapes that can fit the given set of CNs, within the analysis uncertainty, increases significantly with increasing particle size. Thus, without additional information, particle shapes can be determined only for particles smaller than 1–2 nm. Next, while for the determination of NP sizes information from the first coordination shell is, in principle, sufficient, information from at least a few coordination shells is required to resolve unambiguously the most representative NP shape, which means that high quality EXAFS data are required or advanced data approaches need to be used. Finally, the most critical requirement is the need of narrow particle size and shape distributions. Some of the synthesis methods that fulfill such requirement include colloidal chemistry approaches such as inverse micelle
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref284">284</xref>
 </sup> and dendrimer encapsulation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref286">286</xref>
 </sup> methods. However, even if the as-prepared samples do have well-defined NP size and shape distributions, this may change under reaction conditions, rendering advanced XAS data analysis inapplicable.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref280">280</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, the extraction of particle shape information from XAS data is typically restricted to as-prepared model systems and a limited number of experimental conditions. In the case of 
 <italic>in situ</italic> data interpretation, the analysis of NP shapes is usually limited to a simplified argument that a decrease (increase) in the first shell CNs can be an indication of the NPs becoming flatter (more spherical with less NP/support contact).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref280">280</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref287">287</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref288">288</xref>
 </sup> For example, Grunwaldt et al. used this approach and analysis of apparent coordination numbers from 
 <italic>in situ</italic> EXAFS to demonstrate reversible changes in the shape of Cu/ZnO catalysts for methanol synthesis under wet and dry syngas conditions, resulting in more spherical and more disk-like NP shapes, correspondingly.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref288">288</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, Mistry et al. used 
 <italic>in situ</italic> EXAFS to follow the transformation of Pt NPs on γ-Al
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub> from flattened (2D) to a more 3D-like shape as a result of an increase in the hydrogen coverage that also leads to a modified (weaker) NP/support interaction (
 <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">16</xref>
 </xref>c).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref287">287</xref>
 </sup> In the case when different particle models may fit the obtained set of coordination numbers, information from other techniques, for instance, microscopy (e.g., STEM) measurements, becomes instrumental by providing an independent estimate of the NP size and helping to resolve the degeneracy.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref73">73</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref279">279</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref283">283</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref284">284</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
