<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">The presence of color in flowers, fruits and other organs and tissues, plays several biological functions mostly driven by the adaptive behavior of plants in response to the environment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. But in turn, plant organ pigmentation has served as a natural genetic marker since the early works of Mendel
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. Anthocyanins are flavonoid pigments that accumulate in plant cell vacuoles
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup> and are mainly responsible for most tissue and organ coloration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. Genetic analyses using model plant species like Arabidopsis, petunia and maize allowed the identification of most structural genes in the anthocyanin biosynthesis pathway as well as the main regulatory genes controlling pigment synthesis. In carrot, anthocyanin pigmentation is responsible for the purple phenotype
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. Two main genes, 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>
 <italic> and P</italic>
 <sub>3</sub>, have been identified in chromosome 3 and suggested to be responsible for the two independent mutations underlying the domestication of purple carrots
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Despite several carrot structural genes from the anthocyanin biosynthesis pathway have shown expression correlation with the purple phenotype
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>, none of them co-localize with 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>
 <italic> and P</italic>
 <sub>3</sub>. A similar situation occurs in other plants like grapevine, where accumulation of anthocyanins correlated with the expression of several structural genes of the pathway but none of them co-localized with the ‘color locus’ in chromosome 2
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. Finally, this discrepancy was solved by a study describing an insertion mutation in the promotor of a R2R3–MYB TF (i.e. 
 <italic>VviMybA1</italic>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup> explaining the lack of color of white grapevine cultivars. In the same direction, several recent works
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup> focused on the role of carrot TFs putatively involved in the regulation of anthocyanin biosynthesis in purple genotypes, particularly those belonging to the ‘MBW’ complex (i.e., R2R3–MYB, basic helix–loop–helix -bHLH- and WD-repeat TFs). Two recent reports showed that three R2R3–MYB TFs are involved in the 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>
 <italic> and P</italic>
 <sub>3</sub> loci: 
 <italic>DcMYB113</italic> has been suggested to correspond to 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>, while 
 <italic>DcMYB6</italic> and 
 <italic>DcMYB7</italic> were proposed as the two main candidate TFs underlying the carrot root anthocyanin pigmentation in the 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>3</sub> locus
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. However, knockdown and overexpression functional analyses demonstrated that 
 <italic>DcMYB7</italic> (but not 
 <italic>DcMYB6</italic>) is the 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>3</sub> gene controlling purple pigmentation in carrot roots
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Likewise described for the grapevine 
 <italic>VviMybA1</italic> gene
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup>, non-purple carrot genotypes seems to arise by an insertion mutation in the promoter region of 
 <italic>DcMYB7</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>, yet the authors imply the existence of an additional genetic factor suppressing the expression of 
 <italic>DcMYB7</italic> in non-purple pigmented peridermal carrot root tissues.
</p>
