<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Centrifugation method was employed to establish the entrapment efficiency of the co-loaded loratidine and sulpiride nanoemulsion (Prabhakar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Briefly, 2.0
 <bold> </bold>mL sample was centrifuged at 3500
 <bold> </bold>rpm for 15
 <bold> </bold>minutes. The aqueous phase or the supernatant was separated, while the residue was washed two times with distilled water and recentrifuged to ensure entire separation of the free drugs. The separated supernatants were added together, mixed with equivalent volume of ethanol, and mixed for five minutes using a vortex mixer. The amount of free loratadine and sulpiride was established by measuring the spectrophotometric absorbance at 395 and 218
 <bold> </bold>nm respectively using a-1900PC UV-Vis spectrophotometer (Shanghai Puyuan Instrument Co., LRD, China) and adopting ultraviolet spectroscopy chemometric technique (Gad et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Sood et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The drug amounts entrapped in the oil phase were estimated by calculating the difference between the total drug amount incorporated and the free drug amount detected in the aqueous phase. Entrapment efficiency (%EE) was computed using the subsequent equation: 
 <disp-formula id="M0001">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="IDRD_A_1872741_M0001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="d2e618">
    <mi mathvariant="normal">EE</mi>
    <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
    <mo>(</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal">%</mi>
    <mo>)</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
    <mfrac>
     <mrow>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
      <mi mathvariant="italic">entrapped</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
      <mi mathvariant="italic">drug</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi>W</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
      <mi mathvariant="italic">initial</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
      <mi mathvariant="italic">drug</mi>
     </mrow>
    </mfrac>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
    <mn>100</mn>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
