<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">The silhouette of the thermal gradient that the material experienced during heat treatment can be guessed from the overview in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. However, the detailed analysis in Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> reveals the transition zones at which the material crossed the transition temperatures depending on the fast austenitising and short holding time depicted in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>. The transformation temperatures Ac
 <sub>3</sub>, Ac
 <sub>1e</sub> and Ac
 <sub>1b</sub> are determined at the depths of 2500 μm, 4400 μm and 5000 μm, respectively. The performed hardness measurement corroborates these depths fairly well with average hardness of 650HV1 at the surface coinciding with the predicted 628HV10 of the quenched martensite described in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref> until a depth of about 2000 μm. While they were attained with a differing load on the Vickers indenter, the resulting hardness values can be assumed to be comparable, as the indentation size effect only starts taking effect at the micro scale (100 gf indentation load)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. The subsequent hardness drop can be attributed to the incomplete dissolution of ferrite, which has not completely transformed into the austenitic phase during the heating process, as seen in Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b–d</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. An even steeper drop towards the base hardness begins below 4200 μm and corresponds to further increasing amounts of ferrite and the beginning appearance of pearlite (see Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b,c</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), indicating the temperature during austenitisation only slightly exceeding Ac
 <sub>1b</sub> and thus starting the pearlite to austenite transformation but not completing it.
</p>
