<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The physical origin of the postedge structure in XANES is analogous to that in EXAFS. Therefore, this portion of the XANES spectra is sensitive to the same structure descriptors such as coordination numbers and average interatomic distances. In fact, due to the much larger sensitivity of XANES features to multiple-scattering contributions, and larger effective mean-free path lengths in the XANES region, XANES can be even more sensitive than EXAFS to the details of the materials structure, such as bonding angles and different crystallographic phases.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref186">186</xref>
 </sup> Deciphering the features in the postedge region of XANES is, however, challenging. For decades, they have been interpreted only via a comparison with those for reference materials with known structure, or via semiempirical relationships. For example, the shifts of the postedge features can be linked to changes in the interatomic distances:
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref187">187</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref188">188</xref>
 </sup>
 <disp-formula id="eq15">
  <graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m022" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>15</label>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and 
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> are the positions of a certain XANES feature in similar materials with characteristic interatomic distances 
 <italic>d</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and 
 <italic>d</italic>
 <sub>2</sub>, respectively. See refs (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref188">188</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref189">189</xref>) for the derivation of this relationship, sometimes referred to as Natoli’s rule.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref190">190</xref>
 </sup> Recently, Friebel et al. used this rule to monitor the changes in the interatomic distances around copper extracted from HERFD XANES data of a Cu monolayer deposited on a gold single crystal used as a catalyst for CO
 <sub>2</sub> electroreduction
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref191">191</xref>
 </sup> and to follow changes in metal–oxygen interatomic distances in Fe–Ni oxide catalysts for OER.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref192">192</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
