<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results from the cell viability assay (
 <xref rid="pone.0145542.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>) indicate that when the 
 <italic>me</italic>_SWH-treated MSCs were cultured in CM a continuous increase in cell number can be observed because proliferation is one of the characteristics of stem cells. In the early stages of neural induction in NIM, although the increase in the number of cells was less than that in CM, some cells underwent cell division because of the stimulation by growth factors SHH, bFGF, and FGF8. However, the increase in cell number slowed down after 2 days of induction, suggesting that cells cease to grow before entering the differentiation phase. The peak number of cells was observed on the fourth day, and most cells were found to be neuron-like at this time. It is obvious that the PI3K/Akt pathway plays a key role in cell survival. When the Akt inhibitor was present in the NIM medium, the cells were unable to sustain growth and entered apoptosis, which is consistent with previous findings [
 <xref rid="pone.0145542.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0145542.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The secretion of BDNF by the differentiating cells in NIM (shown in 
 <xref rid="pone.0145542.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>) allowed cells to maintain their survival level. However, if the BDNF receptor tyrosine receptor kinase B (TrkB) inhibitor k-252a was also present in the NIM, the inhibition of BDNF binding gradually led to cell apoptosis. The PI3K–Akt signaling pathway has been found to be a major pathway mediating neuronal survival [
 <xref rid="pone.0145542.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. According to the literature, the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway plays a critical role in mediating survival signals in a wide range of neuronal cell types [
 <xref rid="pone.0145542.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Binding of BDNF to TrkB leads to the activation of Akt and eventually to the survival of neuronal cells. The increase in TrkB expression level with time suggested an uptake of the secreted BDNF by the differentiating cells for the suppression of apoptosis. Further, the binding of BDNF to TrkB activates CREB transcriptional pathways that collaborate with Akt-dependent pathways to support neuronal survival [
 <xref rid="pone.0145542.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. These pathways are outlined in 
 <xref rid="pone.0145542.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>.
</p>
