<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="pone.0248103.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0248103.t002</object-id>
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Changes in protein expression between metformin- and insulin-treated cells.</title>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic id="pone.0248103.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0248103.t002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <colgroup span="1">
    <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
   </colgroup>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
      <bold>proteins (12) with differential expression compared to untreated controls (|log</bold>
      <sub>
       <bold>2</bold>
      </sub>
      <bold>FC| ≥ 0.5) that were regulated by metformin and hyperinsulinemia in the same way</bold>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">upregulated:</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD69, FCER2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">downregulated:</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COL1A1, EGFR, FLOT1, IL1B, IL2, IL15, IRS2, KDR, RP9, S100B</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
      <bold>proteins (8) with significantly differential expression compared to untreated controls (|log</bold>
      <sub>
       <bold>2</bold>
      </sub>
      <bold>FC| ≥ 0.5 and 
       <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05) that were significantly higher expressed after metformin treatment compared to hyperinsulinemia
      </bold>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">CTSL, F3, GUSB, LGALS1, LGMN, NT5E, PI3, PLAUR</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
      <bold>proteins (24) with significantly differential expression compared to untreated controls (|log</bold>
      <sub>
       <bold>2</bold>
      </sub>
      <bold>FC| ≥ 0.5 and 
       <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05) that were significantly higher expressed during hyperinsulinemia compared to metformin treatment
      </bold>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">AMFR, CCND2, CD63, CDCP1, CDH5, CEACAM8, EGF, ERBB3, ETS2, EZR, GDF15, GPX4, IRF4, MPP3, PLCG2, SELE, SIGLEC5, SORL1, SPP1, THBS1, TM9SF2, VEGFA, VTCN1, WNT2B</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
      <bold>proteins (8) without differential expression compared to untreated controls (|log</bold>
      <sub>
       <bold>2</bold>
      </sub>
      <bold>FC| &lt; 0.5), but with significantly differential expression between metformin treatment and hyperinsulinemia</bold>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">ERBB3, ETS2, GDF15, GPX4, LGALS1, LGMN, NT5E, THBS1</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </alternatives>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="t002fn001">
   <p>A total of 44 proteins were differentially expressed between metformin and insulin-treated groups, of which only 12 proteins were regulated in the same way. The remaining 32 proteins were regulated in different ways by metformin and insulin, of which 8 proteins were significantly higher expressed after metformin administration, whereas 24 proteins were significantly more prominent during hyperinsulinemia. A total of 8 proteins were differentially expressed between both treatments groups without notable changes compared to the respective untreated control samples.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
