<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Graphene oxide (GO) is an amphiphilic two-dimensional material generally exfoliating from graphite oxide [
 <xref rid="B1-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Many models on GO such as the Lerf–Klinowski structural model [
 <xref rid="B5-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], the dynamic structural model [
 <xref rid="B8-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and the two-component structural model [
 <xref rid="B9-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] reveal that the majority of oxygen functions in GO are epoxy and hydroxyl with few carboxyl and carbonyl existing on the edge [
 <xref rid="B10-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. These groups are active and could be modified to obtain different materials: the carboxyl group reacts with thionyl chloride to produce high-efficiency photovoltaic materials [
 <xref rid="B12-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]; N-vinylcarbazole could grow on the surface by the hydroxyl group [
 <xref rid="B13-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]; amine nucleophiles undergo ring-opening reaction with epoxy groups [
 <xref rid="B14-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Meanwhile, GO has been regarded as a promising two-dimensional energetic material in catalysis and energy storage fields. However, the thermodynamic property of GO is unstable to undergo exothermic disproportionation reactions readily [
 <xref rid="B15-nanomaterials-11-00058" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and these hydrophilic oxygen-groups lower the storage behavior of GO. To solve these problems and realize the energetic functionalization of graphene sheets, it is necessary to modify the oxygen-containing groups of GO.
</p>
