<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Accumulating evidence suggests that AS and APA are not independent processes. The spliceosome and CPA complex are intimately interconnected and functionally intertwined (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Martinson, 2011</xref>). For example, U1 snRNP, a major component of the spliceosome, protected pre-mRNAs from premature APA splicing. Distinct from its role in splicing, this resulted in differences in mRNA length and isoform expression (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kaida et al., 2010</xref>). CPA positions trending to usage of proximal polyadenylation sites with a decrease in U1 level yielded mRNAs with shorter 3′ UTRs and alternatively spliced isoforms (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Berg et al., 2012</xref>). Several splicing factors have been found to influence polyadenylation (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Millevoi et al., 2006</xref>). CPSF1 plays a non-canonical role in AS regulation because the CPSF complex usually interacts with the spliceosome (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Lutz et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Kyburz et al., 2006</xref>). Although CPSF1 is the main component of the CPSF complex, it serves AS roles in addition to regulating the APA process. For example, CPSF1 promotes head and neck squamous cell carcinoma growth by regulating AS in cancer-associated genes, such as AKT2, HRAS, TGFBI, and UBE2C (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Sakai et al., 2020</xref>). CPSF1 causes a splicing switch to inhibit the expression of AR variants and blocks the androgen-independent growth of CRPC cells (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Van Etten et al., 2017</xref>). CPSF1 regulates the AS of exon 6 in interleukin 7 receptor (IL7R), which is essential for T-cell development and maintenance (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Evsyukova et al., 2013</xref>). AS cleavage and APA are significant contributors to mRNA transcriptome diversity (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Di Giammartino et al., 2011</xref>). These reactions are carried out by the spliceosome and CPA macromolecular complex composed of constant proteins along with the participation of numerous dynamic partners. We chose one representative gene, CMPK1, to validate the RNA-seq results as it was altered in both APA and AS following knockdown of CPSF1 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS7">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>). CCK8 results indicated that overexpression of CMPK1 rescued the effect of CPSF1 knockdown on the cellular phenotype (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS7">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>).
</p>
