<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Precisely, a composition-dependent elastic constant database for C–S–H is developed using high-throughput MD simulation. MD simulations have been exhaustively used to investigate the structure of C–S–H
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>, exploring information that are not feasible in traditional experiments, despite recent advances in characterization. Such, MD-simulation-based database generation follows fundamental laws of physics and thus, helps to avoid non-physical solutions. However, the accuracy of MD simulations depends on the choice of interatomic potential. Here, reactive forcefield (ReaxFF)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> has been adopted which has been shown to yield a good correlation between the simulated and experimental responses of C–S–H
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. While a large dataset is generated using physics-based MD simulations, supervised ML techniques are leveraged which explore the information by learning a pattern from the data generated by MD simulations. As discussed earlier, the application of ML techniques on cementitious materials is limited. A few studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> have applied various ML techniques on experimental compressive strength data for concrete at the macro-scale. While these studies addressed the macro-scale relationship of a single target (such as compressive strength) from multiple inputs such as change of mixture proportions or starting materials for concrete, this paper evaluates multiple elastic constants (C
 <sub>11</sub>, C
 <sub>22</sub>, C
 <sub>33</sub>, C
 <sub>44</sub>, C
 <sub>55</sub>, C
 <sub>66</sub>, C
 <sub>12</sub>, C
 <sub>13</sub>, and C
 <sub>23</sub> ) of the primary binding phase (C–S–H) with varying fraction of CaO, SiO
 <sub>2,</sub> and nanoconfined water.
</p>
