<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="featured" id="fig01" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Fig. 1.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Phenotypic evolution of M/LWS pigments in Rodentia and Afrotheria. (
   <italic>A</italic>) Values of λ
   <sub>max</sub> for M/LWS for extant and ancestral taxa. The values obtained in this study by either direct measurement (*) or estimation from critical sites (†). Published λ
   <sub>max</sub> values are based on either direct measurements or sequence-based predictions (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Dataset S1</ext-link>). Across the two clades, branches and λ
   <sub>max</sub> values are colored by wavelength sensitivity, as yellow (550 nm to 556 nm), green (≤549 nm), and blue (490 nm). Gray indicates no value. Predicted values are shown in italics. For branches leading to gerbil and elephant-shrew, all amino acid substitutions are shown, with critical sites identified here underlined. Other focal branches show known critical substitutions only (bold) (
   <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). For gerbil and elephant-shrew, recorded absorbance peaks (difference spectra) and λ
   <sub>max</sub> values for all three pigments are shown. (
   <italic>B</italic>) Phylogenetic tree showing position of the focal orders Rodentia and Macroscelidea (
   <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Published λ
   <sub>max</sub> values for each mammalian order are shown as either ranges (black bars) or single point values (black triangles). The λ
   <sub>max</sub> values measured in this study are indicated by red triangles (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.2002235117/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Dataset S1</ext-link>).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="gra1" xlink:href="pnas.2002235117fig01" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
