<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] treated AISI 1045 carbon steel by high power diode laser (HPDL) and CO
 <sub>2</sub> laser. According to their work, performing the LSTH using HPDL with a rectangular beam shape produced a higher quality product than did the CO
 <sub>2</sub> laser transformation hardening process with a circular beam spot. For high power diode laser surface hardened samples, the hardened depth in each sample was almost unchanged and surface melting was avoided. Otherwise, for the CO
 <sub>2</sub> laser surface hardening samples, the results showed that melting of the surface layer occurred. Bojinovic et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] simulated an LSTH process of austenitic stainless steel (50CrV4). Telasang et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] studied the LSTH of AISI H13 steel, which hardened up to 800 Vickers. Additionally, wear and corrosion resistance were investigated in their study. They observed that when LSTH was conducted with a laser energy density of 75 J/mm
 <sup>2</sup>, an excellent fretting wear behavior was obtained as compared to that in as-received tool steel. Bien et al. [
 <xref rid="B15-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] performed LSTH of C80U steel by a CO
 <sub>2</sub> continuous wave laser. The results showed that the microstructure including highly defected fine-plate martensite with a specified number of imperfectly dissolved cementite and a small amount of retained austenite phase was obtained when C80U steel was melted by optical discharge plasma. Cordovilla et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] simulated LSTH of AISI 4140 and compared the simulation results with experimental data. Guarino et al. [
 <xref rid="B17-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] improved the fatigue life of AISI 1040 steel by a high-power diode laser treatment. Their results revealed that the laser treatment considerably raised the fatigue life of AISI 1040 steel. The mechanical properties of low carbon steel sheets subjected to laser surface hardening were investigated by Syed et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Abboud et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] studied the material responses in surface treatment of ferrous alloys by high power laser. Different laser parameters (i.e., power, laser scanning speed (LSS), spot size, and laser energy absorption) were investigated in CO
 <sub>2</sub>, Nd:YAG, and diode laser. Netprasert et al. [
 <xref rid="B20-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] used a nanosecond pulse laser for investigation of the hardening of AISI 420. The results showed that the micro-hardness increased from 242 HV to 1700 HV and the depth of the hardened layer was in the 60–80 µm range. Yazici et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] investigated the effect of different processing temperatures on wear properties of R260 grade rail steel. They studied the mechanical properties, surface hardness, tribological properties, and microstructure of high-power diode laser treated specimens. Lesyk et al. [
 <xref rid="B22-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] compared the effects of the ultrasonic impact treatment with those of laser heat treatment on the AISI D2 steel. Moreover, the twi treatments were combined and it was found that the surface wear losses were decreased by 77%. Barka et al. [
 <xref rid="B23-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] used a finite difference method (FDM) for simulating the LSTH process of AISI 4340 steel. They compared the results of the simulation with experimental data. Casalino [
 <xref rid="B24-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] used the finite element model (FEM) analysis to study the laser treatment for recovery of deformation that was induced by surface laser hardening. Recently, Athanasiou revealed brittle-fracture statistics from intermittent patterns formed during femtosecond laser exposure [
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Moreover, he designed a monolithic micro-tensile tester for investigating the silicon dioxide polymorph micromechanics, which was fabricated and operated using a femtosecond laser [
 <xref rid="B26-materials-12-03136" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
