<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Heat shock proteins (HSPs) and molecular chaperones play important roles in protein homeostasis, cell physiology, and protection against stressors 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>. HSPs involve not only in protein folding/refolding, trafficking and degradation but also in the control of cell growth, differentiation, apoptosis and tissue repair 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>. Recently, roles of HSPs in promoting cancer cell survival and overexpression of HSPs in malignancies have been greatly noticed 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>. Elevated HSP70 levels protect cancer cells from apoptosis and cellular pressures attributed to enhanced growth and accumulation of mutant proteins 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>. Abnormal levels of HSP70 have been implicated in breast cancer cell growth 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> and tumorigenesis of Rat-1 fibroblasts 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>. Similarly, we observe that TNFα upregulates HSP70 expression level, contributing to promoted cell migratory ability and suppressed apoptosis of HepG2 cell. Thus, we propose that silencing HSP70 may increase sensitivity to the antitumor drug for HCC cells as previously described for other malignancies 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>. Overexpression of HSP90 has been observed in several types of tumors such as acute myeloid leukemia and is linked with poor prognosis 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>. HSP90 may act as an oncogenic chaperone attributing to its protective function on mutant and oncogenic proteins from degradation. Molecular chaperone calnexin is a type-I integral membrane protein in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) which facilitates the processing of N-linked glycoprotein synthesis 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>. Interestingly, HSP90 is not been identified in our proteomic analysis; therefore, the expression of HSP90 needs further investigation.
</p>
