<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, we analyzed the correlation between these hub genes and clinical features, and several meaningful results were obtained. The first was that the expression of these genes was significantly correlated with the T-stage, with differences in the expression of the genes in the different stages. In all three genes, this significance was observed, and the difference in their expression between T1 and all other stages became increasingly significant with increasing staging. We also observed such differences in pathological staging. This supports that the expression of these genes was significantly correlated with tumor progression. Interestingly, the expression levels of 
 <italic>CCR8</italic> and 
 <italic>P2RY14</italic> in tumor tissues were significantly correlated with gender, with women showing significantly higher levels of gene expression than men. The expression of 
 <italic>CCR4</italic>, although non-significant, showed a similar tendency. However, these findings have not been reported in previous studies. Notably, a similar result was seen in a previous analysis of TME scores, with male patients having significantly lower immune scores than females. Related studies have found significant differences in incidence, outcome, and response to immunotherapy across tumors (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). For example, in urothelial bladder carcinoma, although the incidence was lower in women than in men, the disease’s aggressiveness and mortality were higher in women than in men (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Similar to these studies, we grouped the data by gender in this study and found that female patients had a poorer prognosis than male patients (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, HR= 1.328 (0.981 to 1.799)) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
  <bold>Figure 2D</bold>
 </xref>). Although we found that immune scores were higher in women than in men, the results showed that the prognosis of female patients was not better than men as expected from the immune scores. Therefore, it is reasonable to assume that although females have more immune infiltrates and highly expressed hub genes than males, this is not sufficient to have a decisive impact on the survival prognosis. The reasons for this may be related firstly to the smaller sample size of women and more likely, to the fact that female HNSCC patients differ significantly from men at the molecular level (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). These results suggest that there may be differences in TME between male and female patients. No significant gender-related pathways were also found in the results of the KEGG enrichment analysis. We may need to do more gender-related studies to reveal the possible underlying mechanisms.
</p>
