<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The relative fraction of tumor infiltrated immune cells are estimated by Cibersort software using the FPKM RNA-seq expression data. By correlation and differential analyses, we found that the content of these immune-related cells in tumor tissues was closely associated with the three hub genes’ expression. We found that both in 
 <italic>CCR4</italic>, 
 <italic>CCR8</italic>, and 
 <italic>P2RY14</italic>, the abundance of CD8 T-lymphocytes was significantly higher in the group with high expression of these genes than in the lower expression group. T cells expressing CD8 usually differentiate into cytotoxic T-lymphocytes after being activated and are able to kill tumor cells specifically. Therefore, studies have confirmed that the higher the level of CD8+ T cells, the stronger the body’s anti-tumor immune response and the better the prognosis of patients (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). In all of the three hub genes, we also found that the content of M0 macrophages was significantly lower in the high-expression group of the gene. The primary function of macrophages is phagocytosis and digestion of cellular debris and pathogens, and activation of other immune cells. M0 macrophages are non-activated macrophages without any inflammatory or tumor-associated function and can be transformed into classically activated M1 macrophages and alternatively activated M2 macrophages (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). M1 macrophages have a primary anti-tumor role, distinguishing tumor cells from healthy cells, recognizing and then killing tumor cells by mediating cytotoxic effects. In contrast, the role of M2 macrophages is to promote the growth and metastasis of tumors. In this study, we found that the content of M0 macrophages was significantly reduced in the high expression group while M1 macrophages were increased although there was no significant difference, while there was no significant change in M2 macrophages, which suggested an enhanced anti-tumor immune response in the high expression group. These results are also consistent with the changes in immune status caused by altered CD8 T cells. Furthermore, in the present study, we found that, like the other two key genes, high expression of the 
 <italic>CCR8</italic> gene was significantly associated with an enrichment of Tregs in tumor tissue, which in turn predicted a better prognosis. This is consistent with previous findings in colorectal cancer, which suggested that enrichment of Tregs in tumors favors a better prognosis (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Salama et al. found that improved survival associated with a high density of tumor-infiltrating FOXP3(+) Tregs in colorectal cancer (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). These results confirm the influence of hub genes on different types of tumor immune cells and also preliminarily reveal possible mechanisms that may influence the microenvironment and prognosis.
</p>
