<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Worldwide, the research on secondary batteries has gained much interest due to the increasing demand of batteries for powering electronic goods and transport systems (HEV). Lithium batteries are dominating the current market in energy storage area, due to their high power with minimized size, which is desirable for portable electronic applications [
 <xref rid="B1-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. As of now, due to increase in prices and limited distribution of lithium around the globe, researchers are on the threshold of searching the alternates [
 <xref rid="B5-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Sodium-ion batteries have gathered attention in the last few decades due to their equivalent electrochemical properties and rich abundance in earth crust that is considered to be the best economic alternative to the Li-ion system [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, there are some snags still existing in the sodium-ion battery technology due to their larger ionic radii and sluggish kinetics during the intercalation process, which cause lower performance. Subsequently, there is a need to solve these problems in an alternative ways with innovative simple ideas [
 <xref rid="B8-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Basically, the performance of a battery is based on their electrodes, electrolyte, and ionic conduction properties of the membranes. According to the sequential studies, the performance and life of a battery is limited by the separator membranes and liquid electrolyte. Still, in all types of solid-state battery systems, the parting of electrodes is provided by the ion-conducting polymers, glasses, and porous crystalline ceramics materials. These membranes are present in lithium ion battery prototypes, which have good cyclability, performance, and long life [
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In contrast, the sodium-ion battery has not thrived to an appreciable level, because the larger Na-ions need separator membranes with highly amorphous natured membrane with larger pore size for free kinetic during the charge/discharge process. Basically, the glass fiber type separators are used for sodium batteries due to their high porosity and good ionic conductivity; however, the leakage of electrolyte makes them unsuitable for practical application where they can cause flammability and explosion of risk associated [
 <xref rid="B10-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. To overcome these problems, currently the polymer-based separator membranes soaked in liquid electrolytes are suitable for ionic conduction and are leakage-free as safe separator membranes [
 <xref rid="B12-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The Poly(vinylidene fluoride) (PVdF) is one of the most widely used polymers as membrane materials in the industry for its significant properties like higher thermal and hydrolytic firmness with superior anti oxidation with worthy mechanical forming properties [
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In addition, the high dielectric constant and strong electron-withdrawing functional groups (C–F) making them much more interesting materials for membrane preparation [
 <xref rid="B16-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Many reports are available for PVdF membranes with various preparation techniques, such as surface modification, physical mixing, chemical splicing, etc. [
 <xref rid="B18-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, the blending of PVdF with inorganic materials is very interesting because of their suitable operation for forming membranes with good ion conducting nature [
 <xref rid="B19-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Yang et al. [
 <xref rid="B20-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] reported that poly(vinylidene difluoride-co-hexafluoropropylene) PVdF-HFP-based gel–polymer electrolyte exhibited an ionic conductivity of 0.16 mS cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at ambient temperature. Kumar et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] reported PMMA–EC–PC–NaClO
 <sub>4</sub>-based gel–polymer electrolyte for sodium ion battery with notable ionic conductivity of 3.4 mS cm
 <sup>−1</sup> and Harshlata et al. [
 <xref rid="B22-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] reported polymer electrolyte membrane prepared by phase inversion technique for Sodium ion conduction with ionic conduction value of 0.3 Ms cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at room temperature. Janakiraman et al. [
 <xref rid="B23-polymers-12-00405" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] prepared a porous PVdF-HFP-based separator-cum-gel polymer electrolyte for sodium-ion battery whose ionic conduction value was 1.13 mS cm
 <sup>−1</sup>.
</p>
