<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MEFs are fibroblasts derived and isolated from mouse embryos. When cultured in vitro, MEFs display spindle-like features that are typical of many fibroblasts [
 <xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53–55</xref>]. MEFs are used extensively as a cellular ‘scaffolding’ tool in stem cell biology in maintaining the growth of primitive undifferentiated cells such as mouse- and human-induced pluripotent or embryonic stem cells [
 <xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Moreover, in addition to adipocytes, MEFs display multilineage differentiation ability for the production of effector cell types, including osteocytes, chondrocytes and neurons [
 <xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32–34</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57–59</xref>]. Most studies of adipocytes illustrate MEF adipogenic potential through observation of cellular morphological changes, such as lipid accumulation during differentiation, or by evaluating endogenous expression of known gene markers. In this study, MEFs were also observed to develop morphological changes associated with adipogenesis. MEFs accumulated lipids, shown by ORO staining, known to target lipid triglyceride droplets [
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. This accumulation was measured quantitatively with spectrophotometry [
 <xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Temporal lipid accumulation was assessed at 0, 3, and 5 days in cells in non-treated, basal medium, and differentiation medium groups. These time points were chosen due to sufficiency of lipid formation in MEFs when exposed to differentiation factors, as observed previously [
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Where continues incubation of MEFs with differentiation factors can lead continuous cell death [
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], which will have biases towards exploring RNA-Seq data especially when targeting DEGs related to adipocyte or fat formation. Thus, a beginning (day 0), intermediate (day 3), and a terminal (day 5) time point was designated for this study. Further to this, the change from differentiation media to basal media was used to revive existing formed fat cells and explored its genotypic nature via transcriptome analysis. The differentiation media used in this study contained known inducing factors, including dexamethasone, insulin and 3-isobutyl-1-methylxanthine (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1a</xref>). Although non-homogenous in lipid content, a positive linear increment in lipid droplets was seen in treated as opposed to non-treated cells. In parallel, similar increments were observed at the gene level with the expression of a lipolytic protein secreted during adipogenesis that is an in vivo feature of adipocytes including 
 <italic>aP2, Lpl</italic>, and 
 <italic>Adipoq</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Consistent with other studies, the present study observed formation of adipocyte-like features in vitro from MEFs under exposure of enhancing adipogenic factors. However, due to heterogenous population observed in MEFs, these observations do suggest that 3T3-L1 still remains to be an optimum model to study the functional aspect of adipogenesis and its metabolism. Yet, MEFs use as a model in AT development can be further explored and potentially utilized to study adipogenesis.
</p>
