<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The magnitude of expression of DEGs might affect their capacity to affect adipogenesis. However, other factors may also play central roles in various processes, such as maintaining growth, proliferation, and functionality of adipocytes during differentiation. Hence, a PPI network of DEGs based on RRA [
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] identified through the GO terms was constructed, and the top 30 genes with the highest node degrees were selected. Several ranked genes are known to have major regulatory roles in adipogenesis. These genes include protein kinase B (PKB) gene (
 <italic>Akt1</italic>) (the highest-ranked gene), known as a major contributor for maintaining adipocyte and adipose tissue mass through insulin signalling [
 <xref rid="cit0083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Moreover, glycogen synthase kinase 3-β gene (
 <italic>Gsk3b</italic>) was identified. This gene negatively regulates the Wnt pathway during lineage commitment towards adipogenesis in mouse embryonic stem cells. The gene product inhibits retinoic acid receptor β and negatively inhibits brown adipocyte programming [
 <xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Interestingly, cyclin D1 (
 <italic>Ccnd1</italic>), a cell cycle regulator that downregulates during the early phases of adipogenesis in mesenchymal stem cells [
 <xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>], is downregulated specifically in treated cells in the current study. Some DEGs, significantly induced with treatment, also showed high node degrees, including 
 <italic>Adipoq, Cebpa, Slc2a4, Fabp4 (aP2), Retn, Scd1, Lpl, Cebpb</italic> and 
 <italic>Adrb3</italic>. These genes are known as regulators of adipogenesis and are involved in lipid metabolism, transcription, and endocrine functions in adipocytes. Consistently, genes reported in this study reflect the magnitude of signalling necessary for adipogenesis and AT as functioning tissue. Results may support the use of MEFs as a cellular model for adipocyte differentiation in vitro. However, as mentioned previously, more in-depth study of GO terms in molecular function and cellular component categories, as well as KEGG pathways, might improve understanding of adipogenesis in MEFs.
</p>
