<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The majority of genes and their interactions play pivotal roles in maintaining adipose tissue function and properties including lipid, glucose and caloric metabolism, regulation to adipocyte size and lineage commitment, epigenetic and gene transcription regulatory activities, and cell cycle regulation [
 <xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0089" ref-type="bibr">89–105</xref>] (Supplementary 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4</xref>). For instance, the 
 <italic>Gsk3b</italic> gene maintains adipogenic lineage commitment during differentiation of mouse embryonic fibroblasts [
 <xref rid="cit0084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>] and shows the second-highest number of degrees in the PPI network. This gene was commonly observed in the current data at both timepoints, suggesting an important and conserved role in adipocyte differentiation. The marked sequential changes in the expression of several genes during differentiation treatment suggest initiation or inhibition of various pathways for many biological functions. In light of this, several studies have noted, and demonstrated in vitro, the reduced proliferation activity during adipogenesis [
 <xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0106" ref-type="bibr">106–108</xref>]. For instance, the deletion of cyclin D1 (
 <italic>Cdk1</italic>) gene result in decrease expression of histone deacetylase (
 <italic>Hdac1</italic>) and increase of 
 <italic>Pparg</italic> and therefore adipogenesis [
 <xref rid="cit0109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Although mitotic clonal expansion prior to adipogenesis remains to have conflicting views [
 <xref rid="cit0110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>], these mechanisms have been characterized in murine models such as 3T3-L1 and mesenchymal stem cells [
 <xref rid="cit0086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. In this study, similar trend of proliferation activity was observed in MEFs with 
 <italic>Hdac1</italic> downregulated at day 3 of differentiation along with 
 <italic>Cdk1</italic>. These downregulation effects were restored back at day 5, suggesting that the differentiation cocktail might play a potent inhibitory role. Interestingly, the PPI data in this study showed 
 <italic>Hdac1</italic> to be highly ranked with 9 degrees at day 3, which also included direct interaction with 
 <italic>Cebpa</italic> and 
 <italic>Cebpb</italic>. Though the association of 
 <italic>Hdac1</italic> and 
 <italic>Cebp</italic> family of transcription factors have been observed in MEFs [
 <xref rid="cit0111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>], 3T3-L1 [
 <xref rid="cit0112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>], and other cell lines [
 <xref rid="cit0113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>], this study systematically identified 
 <italic>Hdac1</italic> having to play a pivotal role during adipogenesis in MEFs. Nonetheless, other factors identified here can attribute more to the nature aspect of adipogenesis in MEFs, which will require further analysis.
</p>
