<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">More than 400 tumors from aGCT patients of diverse ethnicities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] showed one single mutation in the Forkhead box L2 transcription factor gene FOXL2: Cys134Trp (c.402C &lt; G) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], however its role in the onset of aGCTs is still matter of investigation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The mutation is not present in other cancers. FOXL2 is expressed in the ovarian granulosa cells (GCs) and plays a key role during the development of female reproduction system and in its maintenance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Potential FOXL2 targets revealed by ChIP and RT-PCR implicated its involvement in follicular and craniofacial development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. It has been also shown that FOXL2 affects collagen synthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Nicol et al
 <italic>.</italic> carried out the first ChIP-seq on mouse FOXL2
 <sup>WT</sup> in order to find its direct target [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In 2011, Benayoun et al. demonstrated that FOXL2 plays a key role in the homeostasis of GCs and its failure leads to ovarian aging and tumorigenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. This mutation hyperactivates aromatase and downregulates GC apoptosis pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Whole transcriptome analysis of 10 aGCT patient samples showed that the FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> acts as a hypomorphic mutant on the normally FOXL2
 <sup>WT</sup> activated genes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Another transcriptomic study on several stage 1 and stage 3 aGCT samples identified 24 genes whose expression significantly fluctuated between stages [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. More recently, whole genome sequencing of a large aGCTs cohort indicated 
 <italic>TP53</italic> and 
 <italic>DICER1</italic> as potential drivers in these tumors and found a higher mutational burden in recurrent tumors, as compared to primary AGCTs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. However, these molecular events are not frequent as FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup>. Recent publications investigated the FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> pathogenicity from a transcriptional perspective. Notably, Carles et al. developed an inducible FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> stable luteinized cell line (SVOG3e) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] which demonstrated that FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> mutation may precisely alter DNA binding specificity. The study revealed low numbers of target genes and the authors noted the SVOG3e cell line may not respond appropriately to FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup>. This may be possibly due to the absence of the needed partner SMAD3. Indeed, it is well known that SMAD3, a central element of the TGFβ pathway, is essential for the FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In line with this, a recent study by Weis-Banke et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], showed that FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> and the TGFβ pathway are together two important potential therapeutic targets. Indeed, using FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> overexpression and silencing molecular approaches in a non-luteinized GC cell line (HGrC1) treated with TGFβ, they showed that SMAD4 is also an important FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> partner and the TGFβ/FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> molecular events trigger the expression of oncogenic, EMT, and stemness pathways in an aGCT model [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. It is well accepted that TGFβ has an important role in tumor progression and involves SMAD mediators that control expression of hundreds of genes in different ways in diverse contexts and physiologies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] although additional investigations are needed to find its specific action(s) in aGCTs.
</p>
