<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Raloxifene, but not other SERM, activates the proteasome and reduces proteins in the insoluble fraction in females. (A) Venn diagram indicating the number of genes significantly (adjusted 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) upregulated by estrogen, tamoxifen, or raloxifene treatment compared to the vehicle control in female c57BL/J6 mice (n = 4). (B) Venn diagram indicating the number of genes significantly (adjusted 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) downregulated by estrogen, tamoxifen, or raloxifene treatment compared with the vehicle control in female c57BL/J6 mice (n = 4). (C) Venn diagram indicating the number of genes significantly (adjusted 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) upregulated by estrogen, tamoxifen, or raloxifene treatment compared with the vehicle control in male c57BL/J6 mice (n = 4). (D) Venn diagram indicating the number of genes significantly (adjusted 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) downregulated by estrogen, tamoxifen, or raloxifene treatment compared with the vehicle control in male c57BL/J6 mice (n = 4). (E) Proteasome activity following raloxifene treatment in the indicated tissues in females (n = 4). (F) Proteasome activity following raloxifene treatment in the indicated tissues in males (n = 4). (G) Differential gene expression (Log2 fold change) of proteasome subunits compared to vehicle control in female c57BL/J6 mice following raloxifene treatment. Solid bars indicated significant (adjusted 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) changes vs vehicle control. (H) Expression (log2 fold change) of proteasome subunits compared with vehicle control in male c57BL/J6 mice following estrogen treatment. Solid bars indicated significant (adjusted 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) changes vs vehicle control. (I) Schematic of the isolation and processing of insoluble protein fractions. (J) Coomassie stain of the insoluble fraction from spinal cord lysate separated by SDS polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. (K) Quantification of panel I. *
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05. (L) Representative trap assay on insoluble fraction from the indicated groups stained by ponceau. (M) Quantification of trap assay in J.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="bqaa221_fig2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
