<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Raloxifene increases proteasome subunit and DUB expression in female mice. (A) Serum concentration of raloxifene in humans (measured 6 hours after 60 mg oral dosage), G93A SOD1 mice treated with raloxifene subcutaneous pellets (measured 24 hours after pellet removal), or C57 mice treated with 2.5 mg/kg subcutaneous injection 2×/day for 3 days (measured 24 hours after the final injection). (B) Immunoblot for SOD1 in the insoluble fraction of spinal cord lysates collected from G93A SOD1 mice sacrificed after 60 days of treatment. (C) Densitometry analysis of panel I. *
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05. (D) Immunoblot of SOD1 from the soluble fractions in the SOD1-G93A mice in the indicated groups. Actin was used as loading control. (E) Quantification of the SOD1 relative to actin from panel D (left panel) or of the insoluble to soluble ratio (right panel). (F) Diagram of proteasome subunits that are significantly (
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) different in G93A mice compared with NTG controls, raloxifene treated G93A mice compared with placebo treated controls, or raloxifene treated (acute treatment) C57 mice treated compared with vehicle treated control mice. (G) Differential gene expression (log2 fold change) of deubiquitinases (DUBs) in raloxifene-treated female SOD1-G93A mice compared with placebo controls. (H) Differential gene expression of DUBs in female SOD1-G93A mice compared to female nontransgenic mice. (I) Differential gene expression (log2 fold change) of DUBs in raloxifene treated male SOD1-G93A mice compared with placebo controls. (J) Differential gene expression of DUBs in male SOD1-G93A mice compared with female nontransgenic mice. (K) Model of the mode of action of raloxifene in females (pink) and estrogen in males (blue). Raloxifene stimulates the deubiquitination of proteins to facilitate their processing by the proteasome, promotes the transcription of several proteasome subunits and proteasome assembly. Collectively these effects lead to increased proteasome activity, which decreases SOD1-G93A aggregates and results in delayed disease progression in the SOD1-G93A model of ALS.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="bqaa221_fig5" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
