<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We provide the first demonstration of CNTN1 upregulation in CRPC in vivo (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f006">Figure 6</xref>), which extends the reported CNTN1 oncogenic functions in PC [
 <xref rid="B34-genes-12-00257" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-genes-12-00257" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. This observation was further supported by the enrichment of a gene set facilitating breast cancer resistance to endocrine therapy (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). The 10 leading-edge genes can predict PC recurrence with a high level of certainty in two independent cohorts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f010">Figure 10</xref>). These LE genes consist of genes that are either under-examined or novel in PC (
 <xref rid="genes-12-00257-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). For the former four genes (
 <italic>TMEM45B</italic>, 
 <italic>NANS</italic>, 
 <italic>GPR110</italic>, and 
 <italic>SRD5A3</italic>), we demonstrated upregulations of TMEM45B, NANS, and SRD5A3 in PC initiation and metastatic progression as well as significant increases of all four genes in LNCaP cell-derived CRPCs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f003">Figure 3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f006">Figure 6</xref>). For the five genes novel to (unknown or with function not clear to PC, see 
 <xref rid="genes-12-00257-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), C1orf106 exhibits consistent differential expression in PCs vs. normal prostate tissues, PCs with or without TMPRSS2-ERG fusion, and mPCs compared to primary PC (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f003">Figure 3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f004">Figure 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f005">Figure 5</xref>). Consistent with ARFGEF2 protein expression being detected in a subclass of bone metastatic CRPCs [
 <xref rid="B52-genes-12-00257" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], we observed its differential expression in PCs with TMPRSS2-ERG fusion vs. those without the fusion (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f004">Figure 4</xref>), mPCs vs. primary PCs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f003">Figure 3</xref>B), as well as CRPC vs. androgen-sensitive PCs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="genes-12-00257-f006">Figure 6</xref>). Collectively, this investigation reveals multiple novel observations that might be relevant to biological processes underlying PC initiation and progression.
</p>
