<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Doxorubicin (DOX) is a structurally related cytotoxic antineoplastic antibiotic. As an effective anti-neoplastic agent, it is recommended for use in the therapy against several cancers such as leukemia, sarcoma, and many other solid organ tumors [
 <xref rid="B1-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Nevertheless, DOX, like many cytotoxic drugs, has the disadvantage of non-specificity, which means that normal cells are destroyed as well as the cancerous tissues. Other numerous side effects of DOX toxicity, such as leukopenia and cardiotoxicity, limit the applicability of this drug [
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. For this reason, there is a justified need for the search for drug carriers that, without changing or weakening the mechanisms of drug action, would effectively and selectively transport the drug molecules to areas requiring treatment with minimum side effects. Over the past few decades, scientists have proposed and characterized many potential molecular-transport systems using microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B8-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], liposomes [
 <xref rid="B11-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], polymers [
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], dendrimers [
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], cyclodextrins [
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], and biomolecular motors [
 <xref rid="B17-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Despite several advantages of these proposed systems, most of them have so far proved to be insufficiently developed to be used in living organisms because of their toxicity, in vivo instability, or biochemical reactivity as well as issues with target-specific delivery or release [
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Recently, attention has been focused on carbon nanomaterials, especially carbon nanotubes (CNTs), that provide many adaptation and application possibilities. Modulating the physicochemical properties of nanotubes through their functionalization is a key aspect of the potential applications of these exceptional materials in many fields [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Particularly high interest in modified carbon nanomaterials is associated with biomedical applications of CNTs [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] that are possible thanks to their chemical stability, bio-functionality, and biological compatibility. It is worth noting that CNTs have been successfully used for faster absorption of an antifungal antibiotic—amphotericin B [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Multiwalled carbon nanotubes (MWCNTs) modified with diaminotriethylene glycol have enabled the incorporation of antibiotic and fluorescein isocyanate, and the obtained systems do not exhibit negative effects on the human cells [
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The undeniable advantage of CNTs, besides previously mentioned drug-targeting ability, are their own therapeutic anticancer properties after exposition to an infrared light source because they tend to generate heat up to 70–160 °C in a few seconds and thus produce hyperthermia [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In 2007, Gannonand and co-authors presented surprisingly optimistic results of experiments on living organisms that confirmed the effectiveness and selectivity of using CNT in the new photodynamic therapy [
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. An important argument indicating the distinctive application prospects of carbon nanomaterials is advanced studies of molecular complexes of folic acid photosensitizer from the porphyrin group and CNTs [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. It has been demonstrated that the release of particles from carbon nanotubes can be stimulated by pH conditions [
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. This correlation opens great possibilities of using CNTs as cancer drug carriers as the tumor microenvironment is more acidic than the normal cells [
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-21-08230" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Therefore, there is much hope related to the possibility of using modified multiwalled carbon nanotubes as a platform or system for transporting many therapeutic or biologically active compounds such as drugs, DNA, and proteins into living organisms. Considering the needs of drug carrier design, the properties of carbon nanotubes, and the possibilities of their surface modification, it seems logical that they constitute a very attractive and important object of research. 
</p>
