<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">The intricate cardiomyocyte differentiation involves a complex interplay of signalling pathways and gene regulatory networks
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>, families of activating transcription factors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>, transcription enhancers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>
 </sup> and epigenetic mechanisms
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
 </sup>. The analysis of the calcium signaling pathway from the WPR perspective (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b) revealed substantial differences between the atrium and ventricle from the same side, as expected given the important but distinct roles of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> in the physiology of the two types of chambers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>
 </sup>. However, we found practically no difference for this pathway between the two atria and between the two ventricles, a possible indication of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>-homeostasis similarity in the left and right heart. Also, practically no difference was found for the β-adrenergic receptor genes between the two ventricles. Differences were rather found between the ventricle and the atrium of the same side for associated membrane proteins involved in ion transport as effectors, subunits of the Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup> pumps, Na
 <sup>+</sup>/Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> exchangers (NCX), L-type Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> channels and voltage-dependent Na
 <sup>+</sup> channel subunits. We found also significantly larger expression in ventricles for the angiotensin II receptor type Ia (
 <italic>Agtr1a</italic>) whose abnormal expression was linked to hypertension and cardiac hypertrophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup>. These results are relevant for the roles of adrenergic signaling and internal calcium dynamics in the “fight-or-flight” response to sympathetic nerve stimulation, essential for the positive inotropic response to stress-generating situations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
