<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">Some ion channels (listed in Supplementary Tables 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>) also feature differential atrio-ventricular expression. Thus, 
 <italic>Kcnj5</italic>, encoding the inward-rectifier K
 <sup>+</sup> channel K
 <sub>ir</sub>3.4, a type of G protein-gated ion channel contributing the acetylcholine-activated current, is preferentially expressed in the atria, accounting for the specificity of vagal control of heart rate and conduction velocity. Point mutations of this channel (a.k.a. 
 <italic>GIRK4</italic> or 
 <italic>KATP1</italic>) may result in a peculiar type of long QT syndrome (LQT-13), as well as in familial hyperaldosteronism type III
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Kcnq1</italic> encoding Kv7.1 or KvLQT1, the ion channel contributing the slow component of the cardiac delayed rectifier K
 <sup>+</sup> current 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>Ks</italic>
 </sub>, is also preferentially expressed in atria. This ion channel, activated by β-adrenergic stimulation, provides a “repolarization reserve” that is very useful during physical exercise
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>; it is also the cause of the most widespread type of long QT syndrome, LQT-1
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. Although evidenced in isolated human ventricular cardiomyocytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>, patch-clamp experiments on isolated mouse ventricular myocytes failed to identify a distinct 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>Ks</sub>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. The levels of expression of certain chloride channels (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>) were higher in atrial myocardium (
 <italic>Clcc1, Clic3, Clcn42</italic>—possibly involved in stretch activation and cell volume regulation), while others were preferentially expressed in ventricles (
 <italic>Clcn1, Clcn3</italic> and 
 <italic>Clic5</italic>).
</p>
