<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38">The expression levels of ion channels of the transient receptor potential (TRP) family, shown in Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>, are even more interesting. Thus, while most TRP genes show equal expression in the four heart chambers, 
 <italic>Trpm4</italic> and 
 <italic>Trpm7</italic> are predominantly expressed at the atrial level. 
 <italic>Trpm4</italic> was shown to be present at sino-atrial node level, where it influences pacemaking
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>; its properties, such as selective permeability for monovalent cations, activation by calcium and reversal potential between + 10 and + 30 mV, are superposable to those of the “sustained inward” Na
 <sup>+</sup> and K
 <sup>+</sup> current (
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>st</sub>) identified in sino-atrial pacemaker cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Trpm7</italic> performs an astounding diversity of functions, including intracellular Mg
 <sup>2+</sup> homeostasis and transport of Zn
 <sup>2+</sup>, Cu
 <sup>2+</sup>, Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. Its presence in ventricular
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup> and atrial
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup> cardiomyocytes was demonstrated by electrophysiology and mRNA expression. Several studies reported increased TRPM7 basal current levels in human atrial cardiomyocytes dissociated from patients with coronary heart disease or arterial hypertension
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>, speculating about its role in atrial fibrillation, fibrosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
 </sup> and electrical remodelling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>. Other important TRP channel with preferential ventricular over atrial expression is 
 <italic>Trpc3</italic>, important in both store-operated and receptor-operated Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> entry
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Trpc3</italic> overexpression induces myocardial hypertrophy via calcineurin/NFAT in transgenic mice
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>, while left ventricular pressure overload by transverse aortic constriction or angiotensin-II infusion upregulated TRPC non-selective cation current levels in cardiomyocytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
