<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5.</label>
 <caption>
  <title>MIA impacts cortical lamination during development.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>a</bold>) Coronal fetal brain sections from E17.5 saline (control) and MIA offspring show altered lamination pattern. Immunostaining using antibodies to identify deep cortical lamination layers using CTIP2 (green), and TBR1 (red) markers as well as markers of postmitotic neurons, SATB2 and CUX1, in more superficial cortical layers in brains derived from saline (control) or MIA injected dams. Representative images are shown. CTIP2/TBR1 overlap, represented by yellow color, was generally present in control brains, compared to fully laminated deep layers in MIA brains (no overlap illustrated by adjacent green and red rectangles). Boxes indicate magnified areas used for quantification and CTIP2/TBR1 overlap analyses. Scale bars = 100 µm. (
   <bold>b</bold>) TBR1/CTIP2 lamination overlap occurrence is present in all control brains but absent in the majority of MIA samples at E17.5. Brains from three MIA litters and two control litters were co-stained with TBR1 and CTIP2 cortical markers (as shown in a-b) and analyzed for lamination overlap occurrence (n = 4 control, n = 6 MIA). While all control brains showed lamination overlap between TBR1/CTIP2 layers, absence of TBR1/CTIP2 lamination overlap was observed in four out of six analyzed MIA brains. (
   <bold>c</bold>) Representative images of SATB2 and TBR1 staining at higher resolution show a change in cell morphology consistent with a difference in migration between MIA and control groups at E17.5. (
   <bold>d</bold>) Schematic representation illustrates the oval-radially migrating cell body shapes in control brains and the more rounded cell body shape in the MIA brains typical of static cells after migration. (
   <bold>e</bold>) MIA-induced reduction in TBR1+, CTIP2+, but not in SATB2+ cell counts (n = 4–5 brains per condition, TBR1 p=0.0138; CTIP2 p=0.0119; SATB2 p=0.306). (
   <bold>f</bold>) Significant decrease in CTIP2 and increase in SATB2 thickness indicates relative expansion of more superficial layers in MIA brains at E17.5 (Layer-specific thickness analysis: n = 4–8 per condition, TBR1 p=0.081; CTIP2 p=0.024; SATB2 p=0.039; CUX1 p=0.430, two tailed Student’s t-test). (
   <bold>g</bold>) Representative caudal and rostral coronal sections of E17.5 control and poly(I:C) brains stained with DAPI show no obvious cortical dysplasia or gross anatomy alterations. Yellow shading represents neocortical areas considered for thickness measurements. nCtx: neocortex, Th: thalamus, St: striatum, HC: hippocampus, Cp: caudate-putamen. (
   <bold>h</bold>) Quantification of cortical thickness measured at 30% and 70% distance from the dorsal midline and cortical hemispheric circumference indicates no differences in overall thickness of these neocortical regions (n = 5 control, n = 8 poly(I:C); caudal 30% p=0.5252; caudal 70% p=0.2481; rostral 30% p=0.4459; rostral 70% p=0.4583, two tailed Student’s t-test).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="elife-60100-fig5" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
