<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 6.</label>
 <caption>
  <title>MIA alters development of neuronal and glial cell types in fetal offspring at E17.5.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>a–j</bold>) Coronal fetal brain sections from three independent E17.5 saline litters (n = 4 control) and four independent MIA litters (n = 6 MIA) were immunostained for cell-type markers. (
   <bold>a,b</bold>) Altered distribution and numbers of GFAP+ cells (radial glia and astrocytes) in MIA samples. (
   <bold>c-j</bold>) Reduced sub-population of interneurons and oligodendrocytes using OLIG2, PDGFRα, DLX2, and GAD67. (
   <bold>k-p</bold>) Quantification of the cell density in (
   <bold>c-j</bold>). Overall MIA-associated increase in OLIG2+ cells (
   <bold>k</bold>), with further specific increased PDGFRα+ cells representing oligodendrocytes (
   <bold>l</bold>), and no change in overall DLX2+ interneurons (
   <bold>m,o</bold>), but increased overall number of DLX2+/GAD67+ interneurons (
   <bold>n,p</bold>) are observed in MIA neocortex. Student’s t-test: OLIG2 p=0.0134; DLX2+/GAD67+ cells p=0.0004. Bin quantification analyses of PDGFRα+, DLX2+, and GAD67+ immunoreactive cells in zones 1–3 (Z1 to Z3) indicate that changes are not restricted to a particular zones of the neocortex. Arrows denote co-labeled cells. Scale bars in (a-h) = 100 µm and in (i-j) = 30 µm. Abbreviations: neocortex (nCtx); marginal zone (mz); ventricular zone (VZ). (
   <bold>q</bold>) RPKM trajectories of the cell identity markers tested in (
   <bold>a-k</bold>) across the developmental time-points of the study show parallel differences in mRNA expression of cell-type markers following MIA induction. 
   <italic>Gfap</italic> and 
   <italic>Olig2</italic> mRNA was significantly upregulated in MIA samples at E17.5. 
   <italic>Dlx2</italic> was significantly downregulated at E17.5, with no significant changes observed for 
   <italic>Gad1</italic> (encodes GAD67) or for 
   <italic>Pdgfra</italic> (not shown).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="elife-60100-fig6" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
