<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral myocarditis (VMC) can produce nonspecific interstitial myocardial inflammation and necrosis, leading to malignant arrhythmias, heart failure, and even sudden cardiac death in young patients [
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The development of VMC can be divided into three phases. First, the entry of the virus into myocytes causes myocardial damage and induces the host’s innate immune system to remove the pathogens. The second phase is characterized by adaptive immune and autoimmune responses. In this stage, activation of T cells, cytokines, and antibodies begin to target on the normal organs, which aggravates cardiac damage and impairs contractile function. In the third phase, persist autoimmune processes in the myocardium can cause myocardial remodeling and lead to the development of dilated cardiomyopathy [
 <xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The current researches on VMC are mainly focused on the last two phases. CD4⁺ T cells, also known as Th cells, are recognized as playing crucial roles in mediating the immune response in these phases [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Some studies have reported inflammatory responses are significantly reduced in CD4 knockout mice with myocarditis [
 <xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Recently, subsets of Th cells, including Th1, Th2, Th17, and Treg cells, have been reported to exhibit differential, or even opposing, effects on the pathogenesis of myocarditis [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Huber et al. discovered that male mice were more susceptible to developing VMC from coxsackievirus B3 (CVB3) infection than were female mice [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Immune response to CVB3 is dominated by Th1 cell-mediated immunity in male mice, while VMC immune mediation occurs via Th2 in female mice. Interestingly, the development of myocarditis was significantly inhibited in male VMC mice that were transplanted with Th2 cells from female mice [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Fairwearher and colleagues reported that Th1 responses increased acute inflammation, yet this response protected against CVB3 myocarditis by inhibiting viral replication and Th2 responses. Th2 responses reduced CVB3 myocarditis by inhibiting inflammation, but can promote progression to dilated cardiomyopathy by stimulating cardiac remodeling [
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Many studies have shown that Th17 cells and their cytokines promote the development of myocarditis [
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In contrast, Treg cells have powerful anti-inflammatory effects on myocarditis, and maintaining the balance between Th17 and Treg cells is crucial in murine and human myocarditis [
 <xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In distinct myocarditis models, the peak time point of acute myocarditis was different, the CVB3-only model was d 7, the hybrid-CVB3 model was d 10, and the experimental autoimmune myocarditis was d 21 [
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In VMC pathogenesis, multiple cytokines are activated that are closely related to those seen during differentiation of the Th cell subsets.
</p>
