<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, anti-inflammatory mechanisms mediated by the nervous system have generated considerable interest. Autonomic nervous system dysfunction with sympathetic activation and vagus withdrawal contribute to the progression of VMC [
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Our previous studies indicated that excessive sympathetic activation upregulates levels of inflammatory cytokines that aggravate inflammatory lesions, whereas carvedilol, the nonselective β-blocker, alleviated the inflammatory response [
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13–15</xref>]. The vagus nerve, involved in control of heart rate and in hormone secretion, is also an immunomodulator. The cholinergic anti-inflammatory pathway (CAP) is mediated by the vagus nerve, which is the longest cranial nerve that dominates most of peripheral organs and relies on the α7-nicotinc acetylcholine receptor (α7nAChR) to alleviate the inflammatory response and to repair immune injury from VMC [
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Signal transmission and activation of CAP is dependent upon the vagus nerve, and α7nAChR bond with ligands to regulate the signaling pathway and modify inflammation. Activating the efferent fibers of the vagus nerve regulates systemic and local inflammatory responses via CAP [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Our previous studies demonstrated that activation of CAP with the α7nAChR agonist nicotine alleviates the inflammatory response [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and right cervical vagotomy aggravates VMC by inhibiting CAP [
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, the effect of the vagus nerve on differentiation of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells has not been studied in VMC mice. Therefore, in this study, we examined the potential effects of the vagus nerve on differentiation of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell subsets. Furthermore, we investigated the effects of cervical vagotomy in a murine model of myocarditis infected with CVB3. Finally, we examined the underlying mechanism of Th cell differentiation after activation or inhibition of α7nAChR in CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells.
</p>
