<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most definitive strategy to identify the direct zoonotic origins of SARS-CoV-2 is to isolate related viruses from animal sources.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>
 </sup> Unlike SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, whose direct zoonotic origins were identified to be civets
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>
 </sup> and camels,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>
 </sup> respectively, soon after their outbreak, the clue for SARS-CoV-2 remains elusive as the first reported case of infection was suggested not to be associated with the Huanan Seafood and Wildlife Market.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>
 </sup> As a result, a large number of animals have to be sampled to isolate viral strains that are highly similar to SARS-CoV-2 (e.g., &gt;99% genome identity); this is a formidable task that would require extensive effort. In this regard, our work presents a fast, yet reliable approach for screening potential animals for further analysis. Our result suggests that many mammals are likely to be potential intermediate hosts of SARS-CoV-2, which is consistent with a few recent studies.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref>
 </sup> Here, the ACE2 proteins of 285 species were assessed because their sequences were of good quality. In reality, there are more animals whose ACE2 proteins have not been sequenced yet. Thus, although 96 mammals in this study were predicted to have an effective ACE2 receptor capable of binding SARS-CoV-2 Spike, it does not necessarily mean that the real intermediate host must be one of them. The list may be further screened by considering the living environment of animals. For instance, some mammals like whales and dolphins live in the water, and therefore the chance for them to transmit bat viruses to humans may be extremely low, considering that bats are terrestrial animals.
</p>
