<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have shown that HSPGs are co-receptors for the SARS-CoV-2 infection [
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Due to their negative charges, HSPGs help to recruit SARS-CoV-2 to the cell surface by interacting with the viral spike protein, thereby increasing the local concentration of the viral spike protein for more effective subsequent binding with ACE2. A recent computational model suggested that a positively charged binding groove located at the viral spike protein RBD might be the putative binding site for the negatively charged HSPGs [
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Binding study using surface plasma resonance assay showed that the monomer and trimer forms of SAS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein bind to heparin with 
 <italic>K
  <sub>d</sub>
 </italic> values of 4.0 × 10
 <sup>−11</sup> and 7.3 × 10
 <sup>−11</sup> M, respectively [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In addition to SARS-CoV-2, SARS-CoV similarly relies on HSPGs as an anchor for viral attachment [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Likewise, HCoV-NL63 is also known to utilize its membrane protein to bind to HSPGs and facilitate tethering of virions to the host cell surface [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. A drug repurposing screening identified several compounds targeting HSPGs and HSPGs-dependent endocytosis pathways as potent entry inhibitors for SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Given the importance of HSPGs in coronavirus cell entry, it is plausible that compounds interfering with the binding between virus and HSPGs might inhibit viral replication. In this context, the endogenous natural protein LF becomes a prominent candidate due to its strong binding with HSPGs. Indeed, LF was previously shown to inhibit the SARS-CoV pseudovirus infection by blocking its interaction with HSPGs [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. However, the antiviral activity of LF against infectious coronaviruses including SARS-CoV-2, HCoV-OC43, HCoV-NL63, and HCoV-229E has not been reported. Nevertheless, these results collectively suggest that HSPGs are a promising antiviral drug target for broad-spectrum antivirals against coronaviruses. In this study, we investigated the antiviral activity and mechanism of action of lactoferrins (BLF and HLF) against multiple coronaviruses. New findings and highlights of our study include: (1) BLF and HLF have broad-spectrum antiviral activity against infectious SARS-CoV-2, HCoV-OC43, HCoV-NL63, and HCoV-229E viruses in cell culture. It is noted that in parallel to our study, two preprints in biorxiv independently confirmed the antiviral activity of LF against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. (2) The inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 pseudovirus replication by BLF is not cell dependent, suggesting BLF might offer protection against SARS-CoV-2 infection in multiple tissues and organs. (3) The antiviral mechanism of action of BLF is through binding to host cell surface HSPGs (
 <xref rid="F0008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8(F)</xref>). Using SARS-CoV-2 pseudovirus and HCoV-OC43 as representative examples, we have shown that BLF inhibits viral attachment to the host cell and has no effect on viral entry and subsequent replication processes. The antiviral activity of BLF is diminished dose-dependently by exogenously added heparin. (4) BLF has synergistic antiviral effect with the FDA-approved SARS-CoV-2 antiviral remdesivir in cell culture. Collectively, this study provided compelling evidence to support the translational potential of LF as broad-spectrum antivirals for coronaviruses including SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
