<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">Furthermore, both radiotherapy and chemotherapy targeted pathways of innate immunity that are also deregulated in COVID-19. Mechanisms of resistance against viral infection include early non-specific responses, and late cell-mediated and humoral immune responses during the stage two acute disease (pneumonia) phase to allow recovery in COVID-19 patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. In patients with active co-morbidities that induce an immunodeficient state however, their impaired immune system does not effectively combat the acute viral pneumonia, thereby predisposing progression into the stage three severe or critical COVID-19
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, radiotherapy appears to be suppressing expression of some type I IFN response genes (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>); type I IFN responses are required initially to limit the viral burden of disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, leukopenia and lymphopenia, which have been consistently noted in 32% and 82% of SARS-CoV-2-infected cancer patients, respectively
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. Conversely, chemotherapy (cyclophosphamide) stimulates neutrophil activation and degranulation (Supplementary Fig. 3), which have been noted to occur in the hyperinflammatory response of severe COVID-19 cases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. These data are consistent with studies that have demonstrated that SARS-CoV-2-infected cancer patients have more severe events if they had a recent history of treatment with chemotherapy, targeted therapy, radiotherapy, or immunotherapy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. Understanding how to modify the timing of radiation and chemotherapy to avoid exacerbating the innate immunity dysregulation observed with COVID-19 may be important to guide clinical management of cancer patients requiring treatment during active infection.
</p>
