<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hydrometallurgical processes are used to extract and recover valuable metals from minerals or inorganic compounds using water as solvent [
 <xref rid="B112-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. This method is of great interest for battery recycling research because it is known to be low cost, involves little energy consumption, and exhibits good environmental footprint [
 <xref rid="B10-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, such advantages may be argued depending on flowsheet complexity, reagent schemes, effluent toxicity, and water consumption. Several review papers have described hydrometallurgical recycling processes [
 <xref rid="B4-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. Most of these review papers covered only the recycling of transition metal oxide LIBs and rarely mentioned the recycling of LFP batteries except for the review published by Wang et al., which only described process related to LFP recycling [
 <xref rid="B116-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. In addition, other review papers described the industrial operations or general situation of the recycling industry [
 <xref rid="B8-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Our paper offers an update on the hydrometallurgical recycling processes at different stages: Academic development stage, patented, or industrially in operation. We also propose an industrial application critical view of the processes in development. Lastly, we also include an in-depth review of LFP battery recycling.
</p>
