<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) have become a popular choice in the field of energy storage due to their graphene-like two-dimensional (2D) layered structure, in which lithium ions tend to migrate among the 2D layers due to the weak van der Waals interactions (Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Cook et al., 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Among a variety of TMDs, MoS
 <sub>2</sub> is an ideal anode material for lithium ion batteries because its proper interlayer spacing endows this material a higher theoretical specific capacity (Kadam et al., 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Santhosha et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). However, its poor conductivity and large volume variations have limited its application as an advanced anode material. To address the above issues, MoS
 <sub>2</sub> has been engineered into different nanostructures and nanocomposites (Kadam et al., 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Santhosha et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Sun et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Wang M. et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Wang Y. et al., 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Xie et al., 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Zhu et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Recently, due to its excellent electrical, thermal and mechanical properties, graphene has been used to combine with MoS
 <sub>2</sub> to form an anode material for lithium-ion batteries (Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Tan et al., 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Anwer et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The high mechanical strength and extraordinary conductivity of graphene greatly improve the structure stability and the electrical performance of the graphene-based MoS
 <sub>2</sub> nanocomposites. However, large volume changes occurred when lithium ions were embedded in the MoS
 <sub>2</sub> layers and preferentially interacted with S layers to form Li–S bonds. The significant capacity degradation triggered by the changes in MoS
 <sub>2</sub> volume still can not be eliminated. Moreover, the solid-electrolyte interphase (SEI) layer produced by organic electrolyte decomposition deforms and fractures during the expansion and contraction of MoS
 <sub>2</sub>. The new SEI on the newly exposed MoS
 <sub>2</sub> surface results in low coulombic efficiency. The gradual accumulation of SEI further impedes the transfer of lithium ions. By self-assembling 2D MoS
 <sub>2</sub> nano-sheets into three-dimensional (3D) layered porous nano-spheres with uneven surfaces, the capacity of the MoS
 <sub>2</sub> electrodes can be further improved. As we known, two-dimensional single-layer nanosheets are highly resistant to volume changes, while highly uneven surfaces ensure more active sites (Wang M. et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Qi et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). It was predicted that the self-assembly of 3D hierarchical MoS
 <sub>2</sub> nano-flowers with open architecture will maximize the advantages of 2D MoS
 <sub>2</sub> nanosheets. Additionally, the conventional chemical exfoliation process will introduce oxygen functional groups to form a single layer of graphene oxide (GO). The loss of π system leads to a poor conductivity of GO. GO have to be reduced to the reduced GO (rGO) to reconstruct the sp2 hybridized network before binding to MoS
 <sub>2</sub>. Although GO can be partially reduced through high-temperature annealing or chemical reduction, large aggregates are easily formed under van der Waals force. Moreover, MoS
 <sub>2</sub> nanostructures tend to separate from the rGO/GO surfaces due to the weak interaction between rGO/GO and MoS
 <sub>2</sub>. Therefore, the assembly of micron-scale 3D hierarchical MoS
 <sub>2</sub> pore nanospheres on the surface of rGO nanosheets was a major challenge.
</p>
