<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our research group has a model to study the effects of H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> in plant stress responses: a transgenic 
 <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cv. Xanthi line overproducing H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> constitutively. This is due to the expression of the transgene 
 <italic>CchGLP</italic> of 
 <italic>Capsicum chinense</italic> Jacq, which encodes for an Mn-superoxide dismutase (Mn-SOD). The 
 <italic>CchGLP</italic> gene is involved in the natural resistance to geminivirus in accession BG-3821 of 
 <italic>C. chinense</italic> from Yucatán, México [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The expression of CchGLP in 
 <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> xanthi nc resulted in several transgenic lines, of which two lines stood out: Line 8 (L8) with a high gene expression and high H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> production; and Line 1 (L1) with low gene expression and low H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> production, which is considered as azygous control. Both transgenic lines presented a characteristic phenotype against biotic and abiotic stress of resistance and susceptibility, respectively, to geminivirus infection [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], drought [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and heavy metals [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In previous works, different omic profiles were determined to elucidate the molecular elements involved in the resistance phenotype of the transgenic line at different molecular levels: proteomic [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], metabolomic [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], transcriptomic [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and miRNAs profiles [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The L8 has shown a higher occurrence of metabolism and cell growth and differentiation-related proteins, and metabolites related to phenylpropanoid metabolism, osmotic process, and amino acid metabolisms [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Likewise, the differential transcriptomic between these two lines displayed genes associated with primary metabolism and cellular functions as cell wall reinforcement and secondary metabolism as phenylpropanoids, terpenoids, alkaloids, and steroid hormone biosynthesis [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In the case of the miRNAs differential profile, the results were associated mainly with the structural molecular activity and proton-transporting type ATPase [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00178" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].
</p>
