<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One MCF-7 and one 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> K-12 cell pellet were lysed and sonicated in a buffer containing 4% SDS, 25 m
 <sc>m</sc> HEPES pH 7.6 and 1 m
 <sc>m</sc> DTT. Total protein amount was estimated (DC protein assay, Bio-Rad, Hercules, California). Samples with different spiked in amounts of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> protein extract (3 replicates with 7.5 μg, 4 with 15 μg and 3 with 45 ug) in MCF-7 background (70 μg of protein extract) were prepared. Protein digestion (LysC and trypsin, sequencing grade modified, Thermo Scientific, Waltham, Massachusetts) was performed using a modified SP3-protocol (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In brief, each sample was reduced with 1 m
 <sc>m</sc> DTT and alkylated with 40 m
 <sc>m</sc> Chloroacetamide. Sera-Mag SP3 bead mix (20 μl) was transferred into the protein sample together with 100% Acetonitrile to a final concentration of 70%. The mix was incubated under rotation at room temperature for 18 min. The mix was placed on the magnetic rack and the supernatant was discarded, followed by two washes with 70% ethanol and one with 100% acetonitrile. The beads-protein mixture was reconstituted in 100 μl LysC buffer (0.5 
 <sc>m</sc> Urea, 50 m
 <sc>m</sc> HEPES pH: 7.6 and 1:50 enzyme (LysC) to protein ratio) and incubated O/N. Finally, trypsin was added in 1:50 enzyme to protein ratio in 100 μl 50 m
 <sc>m</sc> HEPES pH 7.6 and incubated O/N. The peptides were eluted from the mixture after placing the mixture on a magnetic rack, followed by peptide concentration measurement (Bio-Rad DC Assay). Before labeling, samples were pH adjusted using TEAB pH 8.5 (50 m
 <sc>m</sc> final concentration). Thirty-five micrograms of each sample were labeled with an isobaric TMT-tag (Thermo Scientific). Labeling efficiency was determined by LC-MS/MS before pooling of samples. Sample clean-up was performed by solid phase extraction (SPE strata-X-C, Phenomenex, Torrance, California). Purified samples were dried in a SpeedVac.
</p>
