<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, at least three human pathogenic mycoplasmas are known to form biofilms. The most common biofilm-forming mycoplasmas are 
 <italic>U. urealyticum</italic> and 
 <italic>U. parvum</italic>. A clinical survey indicated that 9 out of the 11 clinical isolates of 
 <italic>U. urealyticum</italic> and 
 <italic>U. parvum</italic> were found to form biofilms, but these 9 strains were completely sensitive to clarithromycin regardless of the type of growth [
 <xref rid="cit0172" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>]. 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> can form a volcano-like biofilm; P1, neuraminidase, and sialyllactose are involved in adherence to the surface and biofilm formation [
 <xref rid="cit0173" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>]. Different strains manifest diverse potential for biofilm formation within 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic>; for example, the type 2 strain formed more prolific biofilms than the type 1 strain [
 <xref rid="cit0174" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>]. The biofilms formed by 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> possess a characteristic tower structure, which endue the function of protecting them from the lytic effects of the complement system and gramicidin [
 <xref rid="cit0175" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>]. Moreover, as the biofilms mature, 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> cells undergo morphologic changes; however, the altered motility has no more than a minor role in biofilm development [
 <xref rid="cit0176" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>]. Feng et al. also discovered that H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and H
 <sub>2</sub>S production and CARDS TX levels peaked at the early stage of biofilm formation and decreased over time, while antibiotic and complement resistance increased over time [
 <xref rid="cit0177" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>], suggesting that the virulence of individual bacteria may be reduced after 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> reaches a chronic infection stage. Although some reports have shown that 
 <italic>M. hominis</italic> is detected in the “amniotic fluid sludge” regarded as a biofilm, it remains controversial whether 
 <italic>M. hominis</italic> can form biofilms since it was mixed with other bacteria in those experiments [
 <xref rid="cit0178" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>].
</p>
