<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Experiments have confirmed that in a glass coverslip model with an air-liquid interface, 
 <italic>M. putrefaciens, M. cottewii, M. yeatsii, M. agalactiae</italic>, and 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> produce prolific biofilms, all of which are highly resistant to stressors, such as heat and desiccation [
 <xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Conversely, Mmm small colonies (SCs) cannot produce biofilms under this condition [
 <xref rid="cit0170" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]; however, when attached to a solid surface, Mmm SCs produce biofilms and are resistant to heat, osmotic shock, and oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="cit0144" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Interestingly, several glycolytic enzymes or extracellular matrix-binding adhesins, such as pyruvate dehydrogenase and EF-Tu, are upregulated when Mmm SC is grown as an adherent biofilm [
 <xref rid="cit0144" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>], which demonstrates that surface adherence may be an essential process, and that glycolytic enzymes may play a role in biofilm formation and disease initiation by Mmm SC. Correspondingly, the production of biofilm by 
 <italic>M. putrefaciens</italic> and 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> did not affect the minimal inhibitory concentrations of any antibiotic tested [
 <xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0170" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. Additionally, it is known that all 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> isolates can produce biofilms and are correlated with different molecular types or Vsp species. Among them, the expression of VspB and VspO, but not VspF, was found in all biofilm-producing isolates. Nevertheless, the ability of 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> to produce biofilms does not necessarily correlate with its pathogenicity [
 <xref rid="cit0077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Furthermore, 
 <italic>M. arginini</italic> camel isolates also form biofilms on the surface of polystyrene, but their biofilm-forming ability is rather weak owing to the poor production of catalase [
 <xref rid="cit0156" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>].
</p>
