<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0240">Given the natural inhalation relationship between laryngeal administration and dry powder inhalation, it is of great interest to transform conventional DPIs from pulmonary delivery to throat disease therapy. In this study, the DPIs carrier of CD-MOF with highly uniform inhalable particle size of 1–5 μm was modified using SCU to enhance the laryngeal anchoring of the CD-MOF particles as a novel carrier for laryngeal delivery. The laryngeal deposition rate was successfully evaluated using NGI. The flowability of the powder combined with the emptying rate (98.56 ± 0.30%) indicated that the powders were efficiently released from the capsule container. Efficient encapsulation of glycosides of SCU (payload of 27.21 ± 0.75%) significantly shifted the deposition characteristics of CD-MOF particles from the lungs to the larynx. At a flow rate of 65 L/min, the laryngeal deposition rate of SCU@CD-MOF was 57.72 ± 2.19%, while CD-MOF was 29.16 ± 3.11%. Furthermore, DEX was used as a model drug co-encapsulated with SCU in CD-MOF, which verified that SCU could target CD-MOF particles to the larynx. It was possible to achieve better therapeutic effects on laryngeal inflammation than other routes of administrations with less dosage and reduced systemic side effects of glucocorticoids. Molecular simulation combined with characterizations successfully supported the efficient SCU loading into the CD-MOF cavities, and enabled gaining insights on the configuration of SCU in CD-MOF and its contribution to the surface free energy of the SCU@CD-MOF, which possibly defined the enhanced laryngeal anchoring. The phenomenon that SCU successfully increased laryngeal deposition of CD-MOF suggests that it is of great significance to screen inactive glycosides with similar physicochemical properties to SCU as excipients for the administration of laryngeal therapeutic drugs. In a word, the inhalable CD-MOF carrier has great potential in laryngeal drug delivery as a new strategy for laryngeal administration.</p>
