<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The schematic formation process of the materials is illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-10-00249-f001">Figure 1</xref>. A typical procedure to synthesize the B-SFO@C sample is as follows: 0.2 M SnCl
 <sub>4</sub> aqueous solution containing 0.1 g mL
 <sup>−1</sup> of citric acid and 0.2 M K
 <sub>4</sub>[Fe(CN)
 <sub>6</sub>] aqueous solution containing 0.1 g mL
 <sup>−1</sup> of citric acid was simply mixed with a volume ratio of 3:1 at room temperature and a clear gel was obtained after a few minutes. Then, the as-prepared gel was freeze-dried overnight. Subsequently, the obtained xerogels were firstly pyrolyzed at 400 °C in air for 2 h, and then carbonized at 600 °C in N
 <sub>2</sub> for 2 h. The resulting product was washed with the distilled water and ethanol to remove the impurities and dried at 100 °C in air. The final products were designated as B-SFO@C. B-SFO was prepared by the similar procedure except for replacing N
 <sub>2</sub> with air. B-SO@C was prepared by removing the Fe
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub> in B-SFO@C by etching with a 0.5 M oxalic acid solution. Simply, the selective leaching was achieved by dispersion of the B-SFO@C products into a 0.5 M oxalic acid aqueous solution by ultrasonication for 30 min and then the robust agitation overnight. The pure carbon framework was derived by following procedures. The B-SFO@C is dispersed into 2 M NaOH aqueous solution by ultrasonication for 30 min. After that, the above suspension was transferred into a 100 mL Teflon-lined stainless-steel autoclave and subjected to hydrothermal treatment at 180 °C for 24 h to remove the SnO
 <sub>2</sub>. Subsequently, the obtained products were dispersed into 0.5 M oxalic acid aqueous solution by ultrasonication for 30 min and then stirred over night to remove Fe
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>. The resulting products was collected by centrifugation, washed three times with DI water and ethanol, and then dried in an oven at 100 °C to get the carbon matrix.
</p>
