<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The aim of this study was to identify biomarkers for brain metastases of gynecological malignancies, which have a different protein expression profile compared with primary tumors. Identification of proteins that are up-regulated or down-regulated in metastatic tumors may facilitate the detection and/or treatment of metastasis cancer. Therefore, we performed a comparative proteomic analysis of primary and metastatic gynecological cancers by LC–MS/MS analysis of proteins extracted from FFPE samples. Western blotting and immunohistochemistry were also performed to confirm the results of LC–MS/MS analysis. Until recently, protein extraction from formalin-fixed tissues was thought to be impossible because fixation by formalin creates strong intermolecular covalent bonds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. However, successful protein extraction protocols have been established based on the heat-induced antigen retrieval technique widely applied for immunohistochemistry and proteomic analysis by LC–MS/MS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In the present study, the protein expression profile of metastatic tumors was compared with that of primary tumors using extracts of FFPE samples. By LC–MS/MS and scaffold analysis, 76 proteins were identified in 3 primary tumors and 101 proteins were found in 3 metastatic tumors. These proteins were related to a variety of biological processes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). To find candidate proteins, the 129 proteins that we identified were divided into 15 categories based on biological processes. Comparison of the distribution of these proteins between the primary and metastatic tumors showed differences in the expression of proteins related to metabolic, developmental, and multicellular organismal processes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). Eight candidate proteins were selected that were predominantly or exclusively expressed by either the primary or metastatic tumors (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Several of the proteins identified in this study have been reported previously as possible metastasis-related proteins, including TAGLN2, TPI-1, ENO1, phosphatidylethanolamine binding protein (PEBP1), and mitochondrial ATP synthase alpha-subunit (ATP5A). TAGLN2 is a poorly characterized member of the calponin family. Its closest homologue is Transgelin 1/SM22a, an actin cross-linking protein [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] that is thought to undergo down-regulation as an early marker of transformation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. A recent study suggested that TAGLN2 has a negative influence on metastasis suppressing the invasive capacity of tumor cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. TPI-1 is an enzyme that catalyzes the reversible transformation of 
 <sc>d</sc>-3-glyceraldehyde phosphate into dihydroxyacetone phosphate. Dihydroxyacetone phosphate is then transformed into 
 <sc>d</sc>-3-glyceraldehyde phosphate to continue the glycolytic pathway, so TPI-1 has an important role in the process of glycolysis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Changes of enzyme activity have been reported under normal and pathological conditions, and overexpression of TPI-1 may activate both energy production and protein synthesis/degradation in rapidly growing tumor cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Another study suggested that metabolic changes are associated with markedly enhanced survival and proliferation of breast cancer in the brain metastasis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. ENO1 is a glycolytic enzyme that catalyzes the conversion of 2-phosphoglycerate into phosphoenolpyruvate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. ENO1 is the frequently deregulated in various types of cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In addition, ENO1 is more highly expressed in metastatic cancer cells compared with primary cancer cells, suggesting an oncogenic role of ENO1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. PEBP1 was originally identified as an endogenous inhibitor of Raf, and it negatively regulates the Raf/MEK/ERK-signaling cascade [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. It has been well established that PEBP1 suppresses the metastatic spread of tumor cells, and, moreover, the down-regulated expression of PEBP1 is observed in a number of human cancers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. ATP5A was identified in tumor metastasized to liver and was overexpressed in metastatic tumor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].
</p>
