<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The eligible solid electrolyte applied in practical lithium batteries should possess ionic conductivity not lower than 10
 <sup>−3</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at room temperature. The commonly used ICEs such as LLTO, LLZO, LAGP, and LATP could meet this requirement,
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref> while the ionic conductivity of the most SPEs is far from 10
 <sup>−3</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> under room temperature.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref> The ionic conductivity is mainly determined by the transfer mechanism. In the phase of bulk ICEs, the Li ion transfer mainly depends on the motion of vacancies or interstitial ions that results in fast ion conduction,
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref> while the migration of ions in polymer matrix under an electric field is related to the breaks/formations of coordination bonds during the local segmental motions of polymer chains, which mainly occurs in the amorphous sections.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref> For the active filler‐reinforced SCEs, both of the aforementioned ion‐conducting mechanisms exist and extraordinary synergistic effects are achieved. The ceramic phase acts as plasticizer, which reduces the polymer crystallinity and increases the portion of amorphous structure and hence improves the mobility of Li ions.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref> In addition, the acidic groups on the surface of ceramics have strong affinity with anions, which helps the dissociation of lithium salts, resulting in increased concentration of free Li ion.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">58</xref> Furthermore, numerous vacancies generally exist on the surfaces of ceramics, which allows Li ions to hop among vacancies and thus provides a faster pathway than polymer electrolytes.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">60</xref> At last, the high ionic conductivity of ICEs also could effectively enhance the ionic conductivity of SCEs.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">55</xref> However, as the intrinsic low ionic conductivity of SPEs limits the large enhancement of the total ionic conductivity of SCEs. As a result, the ionic conductivity of SCEs is still not sufficient for practical application in all‐solid‐state battery at room temperature. 
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>2</bold>
 </xref> summarizes the ionic conductivity of SCEs reported in previous researches. It could be seen that the ionic conductivity of most as‐prepared samples is lower than 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> in the temperature ranging from 20 to 40 °C, while that of some samples could reach the order of 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup>. The conductivity evolution demonstrates that the strategies to take advantages of both SPEs and ICEs may be the best way to construct the SCEs for all‐solid‐state batteries with higher performance at wide working temperature.
</p>
