<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Tracing the motion paths of Li ions in SCEs gives an insight into enhancement of the ion‐transfer mechanism, which is beneficial to the structure design of SCEs.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">61</xref> The pathways for Li ion transport in SCEs involve the polymer phase, ceramic bulk phase, and interface region between SPEs and ICEs. It is still not clear to determine the dominated pathway during Li ion migration. Great efforts have been devoted to revealing the truth about Li ion migration.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">64</xref> Hu and co‐workers
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref> tracked the transport pathways of lithium ions in 50 wt% LLZO‐P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> electrolyte using selective isotope labeling and high‐resolution solid‐state Li NMR. They found that upon cycling of the symmetric battery (
 <sup>6</sup>Li/LLZO‐P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub>/
 <sup>6</sup>Li), the replacement of 
 <sup>7</sup>Li by 
 <sup>6</sup>Li ions mainly occurred in the LLZO ceramic phase and the Li ion migration of SCEs is governed by LLZO phase (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>3</bold>
 </xref>a). Whereas, in 5.0 wt% LLZO‐PAN/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> composite electrolyte, the Li ions prefer to transport through the LLZO‐modified PAN phase rather than the unmodified PAN regions according to the results of solid‐state 
 <sup>6</sup>Li NMR (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b).
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">52</xref> Zheng and Hu
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">64</xref> also examined the effects of active filler concentration on Li ion transport pathways in LLZO‐P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiTFSI system (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). It is found that with the increase in the fraction of LLZO phase, the main ion transport pathway shifts from polymer to ceramic phase. The Li ion transport pathways greatly depend on the composition and structure of SCEs. When the content of ceramic filler is slight, the Li ions prefer to migrate through polymer phase or the modified interface between polymer and ceramic. As the amount of filler increases, the prior conductive path transfers to the ceramic phase due to the formation of continuous ionic conductive network by ceramic fillers. Li et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">65</xref> observed the space charge region (≈3 nm) by transmission electron microscope (TEM) at the Ga‐LLZO/PEO interface. The conduction model demonstrated that the enhanced ionic conductivity could be ascribed to the ionic conduction in the space charge regions and the percolation of the space charge regions.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">65</xref> In addition, combining the calculation and experimental results, a similar behavior has been found in the LATP/PEO composite electrolyte as well.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">66</xref> The LATP in PEO could establish low‐energy barrier hopping channels along the surface for Li ion migration. The inherent ionic conductivity of the interphase between PEO and LATP is three to four times higher than that of PEO/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> with 10 wt% LATP nanoparticles, while at high LATP nanoparticle loading, the Li conduction mainly depends on direct contact between nanoparticles. However, recently, Zagórski et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">67</xref> found that the polymer phase highly contributes to the long‐range Li ion transport rather than the ion‐conducting Li
 <sub>6.55</sub>Ga
 <sub>0.15</sub>La
 <sub>3</sub>Zr
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>12</sub> particles, and the polymer is constrained between ceramic particles at high filler loading (above 40 vol%), leading to restricted chain mobility and thus limited ionic conduction. In sum, as shown in 
 <bold>Table</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">
  <bold>1</bold>
 </xref>, the Li ions in SCEs may transport through polymer phase, ceramic bulk phase, and the interface region between polymer and ceramic, which is greatly depended on the types, content, and morphology of ICEs. Furthermore, the interphase between polymer and ceramic filler undoubtedly creates fast transport channel for lithium ion. Constructing a continuous high‐efficient Li ion transport channel with sufficient interphase could greatly improve the ionic conductivity of SCEs. Therefore, it seems quite necessary and significant to regulate the morphology of ceramic fillers embedded in SCEs.
</p>
