<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Depleted uranium (DU) is the remaining product after natural uranium is refined and condensed for nuclear fuel-uranium (
 <sup>235</sup>U). The 
 <sup>235</sup>U content in DU is quite low, instead, DU is mainly composed of 
 <sup>238</sup>U. Because of its high penetrability and low price, DU is widely used in counterweights, radiation-protective clothing, and military activities; however, it may cause serious threats to health
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. DU is a heavy metal and can emit α and β particles; thus, it exhibits both heavy metal toxicity and radiotoxicity. The kidney is the major target organ of acute DU exposure, and DU can cause severe necrosis of renal proximal tubule endothelial cells, ultimately leading to acute renal failure or even death
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. The following mechanisms of action underlie the nephrotoxicity of DU
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>: (1) altering ion transport in cells to inhibit the oxidative phosphorylation of mitochondria and utilization of adenosine triphosphate (ATP); (2) altering the expression of certain genes (associated with inflammation, oxidative stress, and homeostasis); and (3) increasing oxidative stress levels and decreasing anti-oxidation in cells, thus increasing DNA damage and promoting apoptosis. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying DU-induced nephrotoxicity are more complex, requiring in-depth studies to identify valuable sensitive molecular targets. The biological effect of low-dose DU chronic exposure may be different from acute DU exposure. Chronic uranium exposure induced increasing glutathione in rats without any nephrotoxicity
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>. Vicente Vicente 
 <italic>et al</italic>. reported
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref> that, chronic uranium exposure could decrease the aminoglycoside toxicity threshold and predispose to acute renal failure.
</p>
