<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">BMSCs refer to the mesenchymal stem cells derived from the bone marrow. They serve as the progenitors for osteocyte, chondrocytes, and other cell types involved in the formation of skeletal tissues, hematopoiesis-supporting stroma, and adipose tissues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Additionally, BMSCs exhibit a high potential to differentiate into a large spectrum of other specialized human cell types, including cardiac myocytes, neural cells, renal cells, liver hepatocytes, corneal cells, blood cells, and even myogenic cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Benefiting from their multi-faceted differentiation capabilities, high portability, and relatively low immunogenicity, BMSCs have been regarded as ideal candidate stem cells for the treatment of various human disorders over the past decades [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In adult skeletal tissues, BMSCs primarily differentiate into two cell types: osteoblasts and adipocytes. The biased differentiation of BMSCs toward adipocytes may lead to a decrease of osteoblast cells and OP pathogenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Therefore, the various regulatory factors that can promote BMSC osteogenic differentiation may represent potential therapeutic drugs for treating OP [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. As described above, the indole hormone, MEL, was previously reported to modulate BMSC stemness and osteogenic differentiation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], but little is known about its underlying mechanism(s). In the present study, we first confirmed the role of MEL in enhancing the osteogenic differentiation of human BMSCs. This hormone was then further used to develop a cell model for investigating the molecular mechanisms underlying its role in BMSC differentiation.
</p>
