<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Epigenetic events mediated by non-coding RNAs such as circRNAs and microRNAs perform critical roles in the regulation of stem cell fates and differentiation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Although multiple circRNAs are known to mediate the osteogenic differentiation of BMSCs and OP pathogenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], the implications of circRNAs in MEL-regulated BMSC differentiation and OP development remain largely unknown, and the MEL on circRNA expression also remain largely unknown as only one study reported that MEL changed the expression of circRNAs in valvular interstitial cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. To study this phenomenon, we conducted a large-scale characterization of differentially expressed circRNAs in human BMSCs following MEL treatment by deep RNA sequencing. The results showed significant alterations of the circRNA profiles in MEL-treated human BMSCs, suggesting a potential role for circRNAs in BMSC differentiation regulation by MEL. It is well known that the major biological functions of circRNAs are mediated by their substantial effects on gene expression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. We also identified changes in the gene expressional profiles by RNA sequencing and observed significant expression differences for many functional genes in MEL-treated BMSCs. These were closely associated with various biological processes and signaling pathways, including metabolism, PI3K-AKT, and FOXO signaling cascades. Among them, the FOXO signaling pathway was previously shown to mediate osteogenesis and glucocorticoid-induced OP [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Furthermore, the PI3K-AKT signaling pathway has been implicated in the osteogenic differentiation of BMSCs resulting from glucagon-like peptide 1 receptor activation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The significant changes in circRNA and mRNA expression identified in the present study indicate that the regulation of BMSC differentiation by MEL is driven by complex signaling mechanisms. This warrants further investigations and may lead to new discoveries for OP prevention and treatment.
</p>
