<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">Previous reports demonstrated that the gene expression-regulating functions of circRNAs are mainly mediated by targeting miRNAs as sponges to modulate gene expression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. We also predicted by a bioinformatics analysis that circ_0003865 sponges miR-3653-3p, miR-4775, and miR-6509-3p to regulate the expression of the 
 <italic>GAS1</italic> gene. The expression of all three microRNAs was significantly increased by MEL treatment in human BMSCs, but only the expression of miR-3653-3p was increased by circ_0003865 silencing. This suggests that miR-3653-3p is a specific target of circ_0003865 in human BMSCs. Furthermore, circ_0003865 overexpression promoted the expression of miR-3653-3p in human BMSCs treated with MEL. Additionally, we showed that miR-3653-3p overexpression greatly elevated ALP expression, RUNX2, and OPN and promoted the osteogenic differentiation of BMSCs. More importantly, miR-3653-3p inhibitors significantly mitigated the circ_0003865 silencing-induced promotion of BMSC osteogenic differentiation, which validates the mediating role of miR-3653-3p in circ_0003865-regulated BMSC differentiation. GAS1 is an inhibitor of the G0 to S phase transition during cell cycle progression and regulates the Hedgehog concentration gradient and related signaling pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] that also suppress muscle stem cell renewal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In the present study, the first time we showed that the GAS1 expression in BMSCs could be suppressed by MEL treatment, enhanced by circ_0003865, and repressed by miR-3653-3p. We also confirmed the direct association between circ_0003865 and miR-3653-3p and the binding of miR-3653-3p with 
 <italic>GAS1</italic> gene sequences using a luciferase reporter assay. This demonstrates the existence of a novel circ_0003865/miR-3653-3p/GAS1 axis in MEL-regulated BMSC osteogenic differentiation.
</p>
