<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pioneered by O’Grady et al. in the 1980s, the application of 
 <italic>operando</italic> XAS for the understanding of Pt catalysts for ORR has a long history.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref358">358</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref359">359</xref>
 </sup> Starting from these early works, the analysis of the shape and intensity of Pt L
 <sub>3</sub>- and L
 <sub>2</sub>-edge white lines was in the focus, providing important clues about the Pt oxidation state, adsorbates, and the d-band occupancy. Indeed, since the L
 <sub>3</sub> and L
 <sub>2</sub>-edge WLs correspond to the excitations of the electrons from the 2p
 <sub>3/2</sub> and 2p
 <sub>1/2</sub>-shells to partially vacant 5d-shells, the intensity of this feature is directly correlated with the number of holes in the d-shell, and can be used to probe the Pt oxidation and the charge transfer between Pt and adsorbed species. Generally, upon an increase in the applied potential, an increase in the WL magnitude is also observed, which is commonly associated with the 5d band becoming empty and electron withdrawing by the adsorbed oxygen species. The increase of the WL gets especially pronounced at potentials higher than 0.8 V versus RHE, where the formation of surface oxides is observed, as evidenced also by a Pt–O contribution appearing in the EXAFS spectra.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref176">176</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref474">474</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref476">476</xref>
 </sup> The relation between the WL intensity and the adsorption of oxygen species was demonstrated, for instance, by Erickson et al, who compared 
 <italic>in situ</italic> Pt XAS data under N
 <sub>2</sub> and O
 <sub>2</sub> atmospheres.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref141">141</xref>
 </sup> It was found that at all applied potentials the sample under N
 <sub>2</sub> had a lower WL intensity than that of the same sample under O
 <sub>2</sub>, highlighting the interaction between the catalyst and oxygen species. The enhancement in the WL intensity is especially pronounced for smaller Pt NPs, as observed by Mukerjee, McBreen et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref475">475</xref>
 </sup> suggesting stronger particle-adsorbate interactions (including poisoning) at the prevalent undercoordinated Pt sites. This finding allows one to rationalize the observation that the ORR activity decreases with decreasing particle size.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref263">263</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref362">362</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, a recent XANES study by Liu et al. demonstrated that the undesired oxidation of carbon-supported ultradispersed Pt species can be prevented by doping the carbon support with nitrogen, resulting in a more durable and highly efficient catalyst for ORR.
</p>
