<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hence, we developed DIscBIO (DIscovery of single-cell transcriptomics BIOmarkers). DIscBIO is an open-source, multi-algorithmic pipeline that provides an opportunity to analyze scRNA-seq data for any organism with a taxonomy ID. It allows biomarker discovery using decision trees and gene enrichment analysis in a network context from single-cell sequencing read counts through clustering and differential analysis. DIscBIO is implemented as an R package [
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] published on the Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN). It can be run either in command-line mode or through a computational pipeline using Jupyter notebooks [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. DIscBIO allows users to conveniently construct, analyze, visualize and tune scRNA-seq data interactively. DIscBIO notebooks integrate R code with explanatory text and output data and images in a sequential narrative. The notebooks allow R users to understand the different steps of the pipeline and learn how to apply it to analyze their own data. Importantly, they do not need to worry about the non-trivial task of connecting the different packages. However, in order to do meaningful analyses, they still need to understand the implemented methods, their possible options or parameters and their limitations. We believe that users with some programing skills will be able to tune individual parameters while more experienced programmers can fully edit and extend the pipeline to their needs. We also provide a cloud version using Binder [
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] that allows users with very limited programming skills to run the pipeline even without installing the programming language R, Jupyter, or any of the software that the pipeline integrates. In order to produce the cloud-hosted Binder version, the repository includes a specification of all the software used, which enables automatic or manual reproduction or modification of the necessary computational environment needed to execute the pipeline on any computational resources [
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-22-01399" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. DIscBIO facilitates the creation of publication-ready plots for researchers with all levels of programming proficiency. 
</p>
