<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Metaproteomics can measure microbial gene expression and help identify genes underlying a phenotype. For example, by analyzing the metaproteome of a uropathogenic biofilm grown in a bladder catheter, Lassek and colleagues [
 <xref rid="ppat.1009245.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] were able to identify the bacterial community structure and specific functional roles of these microbes. They found that catheters were dominated by 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>Morganella morganii</italic>, and 
 <italic>Bacteroides</italic> sp. Also, the comparison of the metaproteome to in vitro cultures of 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>morganii</italic> revealed that iron limitation is one of the major challenges for the bacteria in the bladder environment, which they overcome by high expression of genes for siderophore production and the respective receptors. Apart from that, each bacterium employed a different strategy for nutrient acquisition, while, for example, 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>aeruginosa</italic> abundantly expressed proteases and amino acid uptake transporters, 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>morganii</italic> is able to take up sugars and degrade urea. Moreover, the comparison of urine protein profiles of long-term catheterized patients and healthy individuals revealed elevated level of proteins that might be associated with the innate immune system. In another study, Patnode and colleagues [
 <xref rid="ppat.1009245.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] recently combined metaproteomics with multispecies transposon mutagenesis to identify which bioactive carbohydrates in 34 dietary fiber preparations were degraded by specific 
 <italic>Bacteroides</italic> species in the colon, with the ultimate goal of developing microbiota-directed foods. The authors examined how gene expression and the metaproteome changed in a defined microbial community when the mouse host was feeding on different dietary fiber preparations, showing, for example, that arabinan from pea fiber is a key nutrient source for at least 3 
 <italic>Bacteroides</italic> species, and how these 3 species directly compete with each other for polysaccharides in the gut.
</p>
