<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>WTAP, as an important component of the m6A methyltransferase complex, does not have N6-methyladenine methyltransferase activity but is required for efficient RNA methylation in vivo and for the localization of METTL3 and METTL14 to nuclear speckles.
 <xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> WTAP has been found to be strongly related to the development of many diseases, including autoimmune diseases.
 <xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Tong et al
 <xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> found that mice with the specific deletion of m6A methyltransferases in regulatory T cells would develop severe autoimmune diseases such as enlarged lymph nodes and an enlarged spleen, indicating that WTAP and other methyltransferases are closely related to T cell function and involved in the occurrence of immune diseases. TNFRSF10A, also known as TRAIL-R1 or DR4, is a member of the tumor necrosis factor receptor family, which can regulate cell function and so on.
 <xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> TNFRSF10A can not only induce apoptosis but also inhibit inflammation, and its ligands can activate the NF-κB pathway and promote cell proliferation and migration.
 <xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> Li et al
 <xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> found that TNFRSF10A was involved in apoptosis induced by endoplasmic reticulum stress, and TNFRSF10A knockout reduced the expression level of TNFRSF10B, thereby protecting cells from apoptosis. RIPK2 is the downstream target of the pattern recognition receptors NOD1 and NOD2 and is closely related to inflammatory diseases.
 <xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Usluoglu N et al
 <xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> found that RIPK2 knockout could reduce the phosphorylation of p38MAPK, ERK and Ikappa B, leading to a reduction in the inflammatory factor IL-12. In addition, Krieg A et al
 <xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> also found that the inhibition of endogenous RIPK2 significantly reduced cell apoptosis. JAK3 belongs to the intracellular nonreceptor tyrosine kinase family, which mediates the signal produced by cytokines and is transmitted through the JAK-STAT signal pathway.
 <xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Some studies have reported that JAK3 plays an extensive role in the pathogenesis of many autoimmune diseases.
 <xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> Byung-Hak Kim et al
 <xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref> found that the upregulation of JAK3/STATs is closely associated with arthritic inflammation, and JAK3 antagonists inhibit JAK3 activity to reduce inflammation in the body. From our verification results, there were divergences in m6A methylation and mRNA expression levels in these genes. This suggests that the pathogenesis of RA is related to changes in the RNA methylation levels of these genes.
</p>
