<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) have an increased risk of suffering from various malignancies. This study aimed to identify specific biomarkers that can detect lung adenocarcinoma (LAC) in T2DM patients for the early diagnosis of LAC.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">The clinical information of hospitalized T2DM patients diagnosed with various cancers was collected by reviewing medical records in Wuxi People’s Hospital Affiliated to Nanjing Medical University from January 1, 2015, to June 30, 2020. To discover diagnostic biomarkers for early-stage LAC in the T2DM population, 20 samples obtained from 5 healthy controls, 5 T2DM patients, 5 LAC patients and 5 T2DM patients with LAC (T2DM + LAC) were subjected to sequential windowed acquisition of all theoretical fragment ion mass spectrum (SWATH-MS) analysis to identify specific differentially-expressed proteins (DEPs) for LAC in patients with T2DM. Then, these results were validated by parallel reaction monitoring MS (PRM-MS) and ELISA analyses.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">Lung cancer was the most common malignant tumor in patients with T2DM, and LAC accounted for the majority of cases. Using SWATH-MS analysis, we found 13 proteins to be unique in T2DM patients with early LAC. Two serum proteins were further validated by PRM-MS analysis, namely, pregnancy-zone protein (PZP) and insulin-like growth factor binding protein 3 (IGFBP3). Furthermore, the diagnostic values of these proteins were validated by ELISA, and PZP was validated as a novel serum biomarker for screening LAC in T2DM patients.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4">Our findings indicated that PZP could be used as a novel serum biomarker for the identification of LAC in T2DM patients, which will enhance auxiliary diagnosis and assist in the selection of surgical treatment at an early stage.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Supplementary Information</title>
  <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12935-021-01861-8.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
