<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">The microstructure of the initial quenched martensite is a key factor in determining the performance of RPVs. Park 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup> reported that the strength of a quenched Ni–Cr–Mo low alloy steel with a fully martensitic microstructure is significantly higher than that of the quenched microstructure composed of bainite. Similarly, compared with bainite, tempered martensite is more susceptible to temper embrittlement. Raoul 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup> found that, in high-P (0.017%) A533 steel, P segregation in martensite is considerably higher than that in bainite. Furthermore, Lee 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup> determined the effect of martensitic fraction on the cleavage fracture toughness of a Ni–Cr–Mo steel. The results revealed that the fraction of martensite increases with increasing quenching cooling rate, thereby resulting in a decrease in the fraction of large carbides. Marini 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup> investigated the effect of bainitic and martensitic microstructures on the embrittlement of an A508 steel subjected to neutron irradiation. The results revealed that, compared with the fully bainitic microstructures, the martensitic microstructures are more susceptible to non-hardening embrittlement. Gurovich 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> have reported that the critical brittleness temperature of the initial state of a VVER-100 RPV steel increases with the grain size. Moreover, the concentration of P on the grain boundaries increases with increasing duration of the embrittlement heat treatment and, in turn, will accelerate temper embrittlement. Although these studies have elucidated the influence of the initial microstructure on the mechanical properties of Ni–Cr–Mo steels, the relationship among the microstructure, impact toughness, and temper embrittlement of SA508Gr.4N steels remains unclear.
</p>
