<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Even when the overall structure of the catalyst is known, the determination of the occupancies of different nonequivalent sites can still be a challenging and important task because tracking their evolution under reaction conditions can be the key for elucidating the nature of the active species. An illustrative example in this case includes the materials with Co-based spinel-like structures that currently are actively investigated for applications in OER and ORR.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref329">329</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref331">331</xref>
 </sup> In these materials, metal cations coexist in 2+ and 3+ states. Moreover, two crystallographically nonequivalent sites are available, with tetrahedral (Th) and octahedral (Oh) arrangement of oxygen atoms, correspondingly. In the normal spinel structure (such as that of Co
 <sub>3</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>), Th sites are occupied by 2+ cations, while Oh sites are occupied by 3+ cations. In the inverse spinel structure, 2+ cations occupy half of the Oh sites, while the other half and all the Th sites are occupied by 3+ cations. In the spinels doped with different transition metals, the occupancies of Th and Oh sites can change. Moreover, the cations can get further oxidized under OER conditions and redistribute between Th and Oh sites. The actual active site for the OER in this material is still a matter of debate, with both octahedrally coordinated 3+ sites
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref330">330</xref>
 </sup> and tetrahedrally coordinated 2+ sites
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref332">332</xref>
 </sup> considered as candidates in the literature. Probing the occupancies of different sites under catalyst working conditions, and their correlation with catalytic activity, is a promising path to address this question. Because XAS is sensitive to both the oxidation state and the atomistic structure of the catalyst, it is a very suitable tool for this task.
</p>
