<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>XANES can also be a powerful tool for the speciation of different site occupancies in complex materials. If the XANES spectra corresponding to each particular site are known, the site-occupancies can be found by simple linear combination analysis (LCA), that is, by fitting the experimental spectrum with a linear combination of spectra for different sites and chemical species. The obtained weights of different site-specific spectra will then correspond to site occupancies in the material. The challenge here is to obtain the site-specific reference spectra. It is often impossible to extract them from experimental measurements since well-ordered materials, where only sites of one given type are occupied, rarely exist. It has been demonstrated that the usage of theoretically simulated 
 <italic>ab initio</italic> XANES spectra for different characteristic structural motifs is a viable alternative.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref202">202</xref>
 </sup> In particular, the occupancies of three possible locations of Pd atoms in ligand-protected PdAu
 <sub>24</sub> cluster (
 <xref rid="fig20" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig20" ref-type="fig">20</xref>
 </xref>b) can be refined by using linear combinations of 
 <italic>ab initio</italic> calculated
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>
 </sup> site-specific XANES spectra, yielding a good agreement with experimental Pd K-edge data. Findings from XANES were later corroborated by EXAFS measurements.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref334">334</xref>
 </sup> These molecular systems are considered to be highly promising and stable model catalysts in multiple reactions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref334">334</xref>
 </sup> In particular, similar clusters were found to be highly active for CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref335">335</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref336">336</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
