<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mitochondria are the sites of OXPHOS involved in the regulation of inflammatory stimulating in many diseases (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). ATP in endothelial cells is mostly provided by glycolysis rather than OXPHOS (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). As a result, the function of OXPHOS is neglected. Mitochondria play a role in endothelial inflammatory stimulation mainly by regulating the production of nitric oxide (NO) (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) and reactive oxygen species (ROS) (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), as well as the dynamics of intracellular [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>] signaling (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). A previous study showed that ROS production plays an important role in coronary dysfunction in KD (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In our study, the OXPHOS in HCAECs was stimulated by KD sera compared with HC sera, accompanied by the increment in the CAL+ group compared with the CAL– group, indicating that there may be a large number of ROS produced. A previous study reported that OXPHOS can regulate nuclear factor (NF)-κb signaling pathway in tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α-stimulated endothelial inflammation (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The expression of E-selectin is mainly dependent on the NF-κb signal pathway (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In a previous study, OXPHOS uncouplers can reduce the expression of adhesion molecules through the NF-κB signaling pathway both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). NF-κb signaling pathway is important in KD, IVIG can significantly inhibit the activation of NF-κb signaling pathway to reducing the incidence of CAL (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In the present study, OXPHOS inhibitor can alleviate the expression of E-selectin, suggesting that the reduction of the ROS production and NF-κb pathway may be involved in the underlying mechanism of protecting endothelia from inflammation.
</p>
