<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig2">
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Identification of differentially expressed molecules in liver and skeletal muscle of 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice
  </p>
  <p>(A) The log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of differentially phosphorylated proteins (DPPs) whose ratio significantly changed between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice. Red, the increased DPPs; blue, the decreased DPPs. See also 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S2</xref> and 
   <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>.
  </p>
  <p>(B) Histogram of log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the expression of genes between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice (left). Red, the increased differentially expressed genes (DEGs); blue, the decreased DEGs. The log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the indicated DEGs (right). See also 
   <xref rid="mmc3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>.
  </p>
  <p>(C) Histogram of log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the expression of proteins between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice (left). Red, the increased differentially expressed proteins (DEPs); blue, the decreased DEPs. The log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the indicated DEPs (right). See also 
   <xref rid="mmc4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S3</xref>.
  </p>
  <p>(D) Histogram of log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the amounts of polar metabolites between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice (left). Red, the increased differentially expressed metabolites (DEMs); blue, the decreased DEMs. The log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the indicated DEMs (Right). See also 
   <xref rid="mmc5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>.
  </p>
  <p>(E) The log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the amounts of the increased differentially expressed lipids (DELs) in the liver between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice. See also 
   <xref rid="mmc6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S5</xref>. (F) The log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of gene expression of inferred TFs, which are the DETFs. Data are shown as the mean of mice replicate (number indicated in 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">transparent methods</xref>). See also 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S13</xref> and 
   <xref rid="mmc7" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S6</xref>.
  </p>
  <p>See 
   <xref rid="mmc2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref> for the unabbreviated names of the phosphorylated molecules. Metabolites are abbreviated as follows: ATP, Adenosine triphosphate; GSH, Glutathione; G6P, Glucose-1-phosphate; F6P, Fructose-6-phosphate; F1,6P, Fructose-1,6-bisphosphate; PEP, Phosphoenolpyruvate; Pantothe, Pantothenate; beta-Ala, beta-alanine. Note that error bars are not provided because the fold change of averaged values of WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice were used.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
