<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig5">
 <label>Figure 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Identification of differentially expressed metabolites in blood from 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice
  </p>
  <p>(A and B) Metabolomic analysis using CE-MS in the blood of WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice. Histogram showing distribution of log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the amount of blood polar metabolites between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice (A). The log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of the amounts of the indicated DEMs in the blood between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice (B). Metabolites are abbreviated as follows: 2-AminoBut, 2-aminobutanoate; beta-Ala, beta-alanine; GSSG, Glutathione disulfide. Note that error bars are not provided because the fold change of averaged values of WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice were used. See also 
   <xref rid="mmc9" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S8</xref>.
  </p>
  <p>(C) The log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of polar metabolites measured in the liver, skeletal muscle, and the blood between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice. The value of log
   <sub>2</sub> fold changes of polar metabolites in the liver (
   <italic>x</italic> axis) and skeletal muscle (
   <italic>y</italic> axis) between WT and 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice are shown in scatterplot. The color of each node indicates whether the metabolite is increased DEMs (Magenta) or decreased DEMs (Cyan) in the blood of 
   <italic>ob</italic>/
   <italic>ob</italic> mice.
  </p>
  <p>(D) The number of the DEMs classified by metabolite class of KEGG database in the liver, skeletal muscle, and blood. Note that we did not measure lipidome in blood. See also 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S11</xref>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr5" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
