<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The advent of lithium ion batteries (LIBs) has significantly mitigated the crisis of fossil fuels
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1</xref> and they have become an integral part of our modern life by ubiquitously powering various of modern electronics such as mobile phones, laptops, electric vehicles (EVs), unmanned aircraft, etc. However, the state‐of‐the‐art LIBs dominating the market can hardly satisfy the soaring need for next‐generation energy storage devices of higher energy density.
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2</xref> Superior electrode material and advanced battery technology are critically required. Recently, lithium metal anode has drawn tremendous attention worldwide due to its low potential (−3.04 V vs SHE) and ultrahigh specific capacity (3860 mA h g
 <sup>−1</sup>, 10 times as that of graphite)
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref> and it has been generally acknowledged that it is the most promising anode candidate for next‐generation high energy density batteries. In fact, it was used as an important anode for primary batteries in early 1970s. Nevertheless, several main issues summarized as follows still impede its further commercialization as an essential secondary battery component. The first one is the infinite volume change due to its “hostless” feature, which would inevitably lead to pulverization of the electrode and the failure of batteries. The second one is the formation of Li dendrite, which is the main cause for internal short circuit, decreased cycle life expectancy and low Coulombic efficiency.
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref> Besides, the irreversible reaction between Li and nonaqueous electrolyte also consumes large amount of Li and electrolyte.
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref> Overall, the development of Li anode faces enormous challenges.
</p>
