<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Breakthroughs in improving the electrochemical performance of Li metal anode may bring a renaissance of the lithium metal battery (LMB) technology. To this end, researchers have explored many strategies to improve the electrochemical performance of Li metal anode such as interfacial modifications,
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref> engineered anodes,
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> artificial solid electrolyte interface (SEI) films,
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref> protective coating layers,
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref> and chemical pretreatments.
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref> In addition, a number of theoretical models were also built to describe the nucleation and growth mechanisms of Li dendrite.
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref> Chazalviel's model describes the inversely proportional relationship between the time of dendrite growth and the current density (τ ≈ J
 <sup>−2</sup>). According to this theory, constructing 3D skeleton/Li composite to substitute Li is an effective strategy to improve cycle lifespan because the 3D skeleton can not only reduce local current density and guide homogeneous Li deposition, but also minimize the volume change, which cannot be accomplished by other modification ways.
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref> Tremendous efforts on designing and constructing various Cu‐ and C‐based 3D skeleton current collectors were proposed.
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs1513-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref> However, these two kinds of skeletons are not lithiophilic. Moreover, the Li‐free characteristic of these skeletons makes them complicated for their application in Li–O
 <sub>2</sub> and Li–S batteries. A more suitable and technically simple 3D skeleton/Li composite anode for LMBs is highly desirable.
</p>
