<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group>
 <app id="appendix-1">
  <title>Appendix 1</title>
  <boxed-text position="float" orientation="portrait">
   <p>Summary of duplicate gene annotations associated with 
    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4C,D</xref>.
   </p>
   <p>BRD7:</p>
   <p>Three manatee copies, but tml_BRD7_3 has PMSs. Overall high sequence similarity.</p>
   <p>BUB3:</p>
   <p>#manatee=#elephant.</p>
   <p>PMS in loxafr #2–3, PMS in triman #2–3.</p>
   <p>High AA conservation even in pseudogenes.</p>
   <p>Casp9:</p>
   <p>Two extra elephant copies are identical in AA sequence but hits only encompass a 47-AA hit that is highly conserved with matching domain in CASP9.</p>
   <p>CD14:</p>
   <p>#Manatee = #Elephant, all four copies are highly conserved.</p>
   <p>CNOT11:</p>
   <p>9/11 elephant copies do contain PMS; however, many of these are still mostly full length and highly conserved. The ones with an early PMS are less well conserved.</p>
   <p>COX20:</p>
   <p>Second elephant copy has two PMSs, but is still well conserved.</p>
   <p>HMGB2:</p>
   <p>2/4 elephant copies have PMSs, all copies highly conserved. Manatee 2/3 copies have PMS, lower conservation.</p>
   <p>LAMTOR5:</p>
   <p>Only one elephant copy has a PMS; three very highly conserved copies, others with conserved domains.</p>
   <p>LIF:</p>
   <p>Manatee's have 4 of 13 copies previously reported in elephants. See 
    <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">Vazquez et al., 2018</xref>.
   </p>
   <p>TP53:</p>
   <p>Elephant: 9/19 with PMSs. Low N' conservation, but high conservation on C' end. See 
    <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Sulak et al., 2016</xref>.
   </p>
   <p>STK11:</p>
   <p>Very highly conserved, with divergence in the second copies in the elephant and manatee.</p>
   <p>SOD1:</p>
   <p>Highly conserved elephant copies. Manatee copies are only partial hits, with moderate conservation.</p>
   <p>PRDX1:</p>
   <p>Extremely strong conservation for main copies. Second elephant copy is a partial hit and has some divergence from the main elephant copy.</p>
   <p>MAPRE1:</p>
   <p>2/3 elephant copies have early PMSs, but with subsequent ATGs. Very high conservation in main and 1/2 duplicate elephant copies, only partial hits on third copy. Very high conversation between manatee copies.</p>
   <p>MAD2L1:</p>
   <p>7/9 elephant copies have PMSs. 2/6 manatee copies have PMSs. However, all copies are very highly conserved.</p>
  </boxed-text>
 </app>
</app-group>
