<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most studied mycoplasmas possessing adhesins are 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> and 
 <italic>M. genitalium</italic>. The common characteristic of these two mycoplasmas is the formation of a flask-shaped and filamentous tipped structure known as terminal organelle. The most predominant adhesins in 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> are P1 and P30 [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. P1 is a remarkably versatile molecule that forms a complex with P30, P40, and P90; these colocalize to the tip of the terminal organelle to perform different functions, such as receptor recognition and gliding motility [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Schmitt et al. has found that the P1 complex also contains P65, DnaK, C-terminal truncated forms of DnaK and P1, pyruvate dehydrogenase E1 α subunit (PDHA), HMW1, and HMW3 to coordinate the adherence of 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> to host cells [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The P30 adhesin, originally regarded as an accessory protein, plays a role in localizing P1 to the terminal organelle and is involved in cell development [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]; the amino acid sequence of P30 holds substantial homology with some eukaryotic proteins in humans, indicating that P30 could be associated with the occurrence of certain autoimmune diseases [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. P1 and P30 are highly immunoreactive; monoclonal anti-P1/P30 antibodies can inhibit cytadherence while the lack of P1/P30 protein(s) causes no adhesion [
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Recently, the immunoreactive protein P116 was also regarded as an 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> adhesin. Similar to P1, P116 is sensitive to trypsin [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, the exact function of the P116 adhesin warrants further investigation.
</p>
