<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Upon cytadherence initiation, the adhesins require a stable primary association with certain biological macromolecules on the host tissues; the extracellular matrix (ECM) is a typical example of these macromolecules and includes fibronectin (Fn), plasminogen (Plg), heparin, fibrinogen, vitronectin, mucin, sialylated molecules, oligosaccharides, glycolipids, and glycoproteins [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The well-characterized ECM-binding adhesins for 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> are elongation factor thermo-unstable (EF-Tu) and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The carboxyl regions of EF-Tu and the amino acids 340 to 358 within the Fn-binding region 2 are critical for Fn-
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> interactions [
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. However, anti-GAPDH serum did not affect the adherence of 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> to HeLa cells [
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], suggesting that GAPDH has a limited influence on adhesion. Similarly, the pyruvate dehydrogenase E1 β subunit (PDHB) of 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> is a Fn- and Plg-binding adhesin [
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Sialylated molecules are a class of host targets discovered in recent years that can bind to mycoplasma adhesins, such as 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> P1 and P30, 
 <italic>M. genitalium</italic> P110 and ureaplasmas [
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25–27</xref>]. Certain surface-exposed glycolytic enzymes of mycoplasmas, have recently been recognized as adhesins that participate in pathogen-host interactions. For example, 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> contains nine glycolytic enzymes, including alpha-enolase (Eno), pyruvate kinase (PK), GAPDH, pyruvate dehydrogenases A–C, lactate dehydrogenase, phosphoglycerate mutase, and transketolase, all of which interact with some ECM components, such as Fn, Plg, fibrinogen, vitronectin, lactoferrin, and laminin, to play a potential role in 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> adherence and invasion [
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Recently, the chaperones DanK and GroEL of 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> were demonstrated to combine with ECM [
 <xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], indicating that the chaperones are multifunctional and participate in the process of adhesion and dissemination in 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> infections. Few typical ECM-binding adhesins are listed in 
 <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. 
</p>
