<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par47">In the present work, an alternative method for fabricating Li-ion electrodes inspired of the paper-making process is proposed. The use of aluminum/copper current collectors, costly binders, and harmful solvents (NMP) are avoided in this fabrication method. These are replaced with non-modified cellulose, which is an abundant, natural, and low-cost polymer. The simple and rapid process is easily scalable and only uses water as solvent to prepare a suspension composed of redox active material, conductive carbon, and cellulose fibers. After successive filtrations, a self-standing electrode film is formed. It is made of an approximately 20-µm thick strong carbon current collector over which the electrode composite (cathode/anode material and carbon) is deposited. Water-soluble carbons and LFP are also produced to reduce the preparation time and facilitate the dispersion of electrode materials in water. The better repartition of these carbons in the electrode results in an improved electrochemical performance. Flexible LFP, PTCDA, graphite, and LTO electrodes with good mechanical resistance are obtained. The electrodes remain intact after punching, cycling, and opening of cells. The electrochemical performances of auto-supported electrodes are similar to those generally reported for LFP, PTCDA, graphite, and LTO casted on metal current collectors according to the conventional doctor blade casting method. The results of long cycling experiments conducted on full LFP/LTO and LFP/graphite batteries indicate that these cells have a remarkably good stability with high specific capacities. An all-organic prototype PTCDA/graphite battery without a transition metal is prepared and electrochemically tested. It is among the first self-standing batteries composed of organic redox molecules and biodegradable components reported in literature. Although the discharge capacity is relatively low, and the cyclability is not considerably stable, the concept of a battery that is both inexpensive and biodegradable is demonstrated. Further experiments, such as the optimization of the balance between cathode and anode masses and anode prelithiation, will be planned to achieve the fabrication of a full organic battery with a stable capacity of approximately 120 mAh·g
 <sup>−1</sup>. Moreover, organic cathode materials with a higher redox potential or higher specific capacity (e.g., 2,3-diamino-1,4-naphthoquinone (250 mAh·g
 <sup>−1</sup>))
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup> will be tested. In continuing this project, efforts will be focused on recycling electrodes that utilize a green process. A second-life battery made of recycled materials will be assembled and tested.
</p>
