<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, many attempts have been made to design and fabricate yarn-shaped energy storage devices with different materials and existing technologies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>
 </sup> to enable their adaption to daily deformations (i.e., bending, folding, etc.) and complex or extreme shape changes (i.e., rolling and twisting).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>
 </sup> For instance, yarn-shaped lithium-ion batteries (LIBs) were fabricated by sequentially depositing thin layers of cathode, gel electrolyte, anode, and current collector layer onto a carbon fiber or by preparing fibrous cathode and anode materials through 3D printing.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>
 </sup> However, the complex material deposition techniques and the strict requirements for specific equipment severely hindered the large-scale production of the yarn-shaped LIB. Kwon et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>
 </sup> further simplified the preparation process by adopting nickel-tin alloy or polymer electrodes without complex deposition techniques. Specifically, they used a liquid electrolyte [1 M lithium hexafl uorophosphate (LiPF
 <sub>6</sub>) in ethylene carbonate (EC) and propylene carbonate (PC) (1:1 by volume) containing 3 wt % vinylene carbonate] which may easily cause flammability and leakage issues. Moreover, Peng et al. assembled environmentally friendly fiber-shaped batteries without complex deposition techniques from electrode materials of multiwalled carbon nanotube fibers and gel electrolytes, which still had low ionic conductivity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>
 </sup> or high raw material cost (∼$40 g
 <sup>–1</sup>).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>
 </sup> Although numerous efforts have been made in the development of yarn-shaped LIBs, an ideal yarn-shaped battery with good safety performance, flexibility, low cost, and simple process is still awaiting to be achieved for wearable electronic applications.
</p>
