<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, ideal cathode materials possess the following merits:
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>
 </sup> high potential capacity and reversibility for lithium intercalation/de-intercalation, excellent compatibility with electrolytes, low-cost raw materials, and simple preparation process. Compared with other cathode materials, lithium iron phosphate (LFP) has higher energy density (theoretical specific capacity of 170 mA h·g
 <sup>–1</sup>), less health or environmental issues, and longer cycle life.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>
 </sup> Ideal anode materials
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref>
 </sup> normally have low potential but high capacity for lithium intercalation/de-intercalation, little irreversible capacity during the first cycle, and excellent mechanical stability together with low cost, simple preparation process, and less environmental pollution. As one of the commercially available LIB anode materials, graphite has high electronic conductivity, high lithium insertion capacity (theoretical specific capacity of 372 mA h·g
 <sup>–1</sup>), low lithium insertion potential (0.1 V),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>
 </sup> and subtle volume change of the layered structure before/after lithium insertion. As for the ideal polymer electrolytes,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>
 </sup> the following requirements such as high ionic conductivity, large lithium-ion migration number, good thermal stability, wide electrochemical window, excellent mechanical properties and processability, low cost, and environmental friendliness should be met. The poly(vinylidenefluoride-hexafluoro-propylene) (PVDF-HFP) copolymer is an ideal gel electrolyte material, which maintains high dielectric constant, excellent heat resistance, and good mechanical properties and reduces the crystallinity of the system.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
