<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Four adult specimens of 
 <italic>A. plicata</italic> were collected from the Muskingum River in Devola, Ohio, USA, below Devola Lock and Dam #2 (39.468703 N, − 81.489303 W) on 19 September 2014. None of the mussels were gravid at time of collection. Upstream of this location is mostly valley with limited agriculture in the floodplain and a few small towns. The river is impounded by a series of low-head dams and associated locks. The drainage area covers 7440 mi
 <sup>2</sup> and average flow during the study period was 8280 ft
 <sup>3</sup>/s
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. This species was chosen because it is common, not listed by state or federal agencies, and found in a wide variety of habitats
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Mussels were transported (~ 3 h) to the Columbus Zoo and Aquarium Freshwater Mussel Conservation and Research Center (FMCRC) in Powell, Ohio, USA in insulated coolers filled with water from the collection site and equipped with an air pump. At the FMCRC, mussels were housed in a 1.5 × 1 m tank with approximately 5 cm of gravel sediment and 10 cm of water. The facility is supplied with stream-side, flow-through water from the Scioto River, which drains extensive agricultural areas from tributaries and flows through a few large towns. The drainage area covers 980 mi
 <sup>2</sup> and average flow during the study period was 1060 ft
 <sup>3</sup>/s
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. Because mussels were supplied with water from a natural river source, no additional food was provided. Gill tissue was sampled on 7 August 2015 (~ 11 months post-translocation) from each of 4 mussels in captivity (treatment group). That same day, gill tissue was also sampled from 3 mussels collected in the Muskingum River (control group). Less than 30 mg of gill tissue was biopsied from each individual to ensure a non-lethal sampling procedure. Each tissue sample was placed in a 2-mL RNase-free cryotube, snap frozen in liquid N
 <sub>2</sub>, and stored at − 80 °C. The Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee does not regulate the use of freshwater mussels.
</p>
