<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lithium-ion batteries (LIBs) exhibit a high energy/power density, high performance, and long life.
 <xref rid="cit1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> To date, transition metal oxides such as LiMO
 <sub>2</sub> (M = Co, Ni, 
 <italic>etc.</italic>), LiM
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub> (M = Mn, 
 <italic>etc.</italic>), and LiMPO
 <sub>4</sub> (M = Fe, Ni, 
 <italic>etc.</italic>) have been utilized as conventional cathode active materials for LIBs.
 <xref rid="cit5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> However, these inorganic materials contain expensive rare elements and/or exhibit poor rate performance due to the slow intercalation of lithium ions. Therefore, appropriate metal oxide host lattices have been explored to overcome this poor ionic diffusion.
 <xref rid="cit7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Studies on the application of redox-active organic compounds as cathode active materials have therefore become popular due to the high energy/power densities, low cost, diversity, and structural controllability of these compounds.
 <xref rid="cit8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Various organic materials such as organosulfur compounds,
 <xref rid="cit10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> organic carbonyl compounds,
 <xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> tetrathiafulvalene derivatives,
 <xref rid="cit16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> organic nitrogen compounds,
 <xref rid="cit18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> and organic radical compounds
 <xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> have been examined as potential cathode active materials. However, since these materials are molecular crystals assembled 
 <italic>via</italic> weak intermolecular interactions, the formation of robust porous structures is challenging, and instead, densely packed crystal structures in which lithium ions cannot penetrate efficiently are obtained. Recently, crystalline molecular porous materials such as covalent organic frameworks (COFs) and metal–organic frameworks (MOFs) have drawn attention as electrode materials.
 <xref rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> These porous materials can be constructed from redox-active organic ligands and generate a diffusion path for lithium ions by robust coordination and/or covalent bonds, which greatly improves battery performance. However, most MOFs and COFs contain non-redox-active linker units, such as carboxylates and imines, in their open frameworks, which results in lower energy densities,
 <xref rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> whereas some MOFs and COFs have been designed to include redox-active linkers.
 <xref rid="cit27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Despite the high potential of redox-active molecular organic compounds, a universal design strategy for the spontaneous formation of appropriate porous structures for ion diffusion has yet to be discovered to allow the application of such materials as cathode active materials with high rate performance.
</p>
