<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on the proposed design strategy, we synthesized a novel CT complex, namely, 
 <bold>PCT-1·DMF</bold>, where “PCT” indicates a porous charge-transfer complex. It has been reported that triphenylene derivatives and hexaazatriphenylene (HAT) derivatives spontaneously form alternate stacking structures.
 <xref rid="cit46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 <bold>PCT-1·DMF</bold> has a pseudo-hexagonal columnar structure composed of alternately stacked hexahydroxytriphenylene (HHTP) as a donor molecule and 1,4,5,8,9,12-hexaazatriphenylene-2,3,6,7,10,11-hexacarbonitrile (HAT-CN) as an acceptor molecule (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1b</xref>), where the voids between the columns are filled with solvent molecules (
 <italic>i.e.</italic>, 
 <italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylformamide, DMF). These DMF molecules can be removed by heating 
 <italic>in vacuo</italic>, and the resultant degassed phase, 
 <bold>PCT-1</bold>, maintains its columnar structure. Sorption experiments also demonstrated that the one-dimensional channels present between the columns can include guest molecules accompanied by lattice expansion. HAT derivatives have also been investigated as promising cathode active materials due to their reversible redox reactions.
 <xref rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> More specifically, the electron-deficient heterocycle core in HAT-CN affords a maximum of six reversible redox reactions,
 <xref rid="cit47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> and the intercolumnar voids present in 
 <bold>PCT-1</bold> are expected to act as diffusion paths for lithium ions. Furthermore, since HHTP is composed of three conjugated catechol units, a redox reaction involving up to six electrons can be expected. Thus, we prepared a lithium metal battery using 
 <bold>PCT-1</bold> as the cathode active material, and subsequently examined the rate performance of the obtained device.
</p>
