<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To address the issues related with undecomposed discharge products, poor round trip efficiency and cost associated with organic electrolytes, mixed electrolyte systems have been proposed. The mixed electrolyte, commonly known as hybrid electrolyte, implies a separation of the electrolytes into two compartments in the cell with a solid electrolyte membrane blocking oxygen and water diffusion but transporting cations. The membrane separates the nonaqueous electrolyte as anolyte and an aqueous electrolyte as catholyte (cell design is already explained).
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref> The use of an aqueous electrolyte on the gas diffusion electrode enables the discharge product to be the soluble sodium hydroxide (4Na(s) + O
 <sub>2</sub> + 2H
 <sub>2</sub>O → 4NaOH). The aqueous electrolyte also conveniently allows the source of oxygen to be air in contrast to the nonaqueous Na–O
 <sub>2</sub> battery which requires supply of pure oxygen because of side products generated by water vapor in air.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref> The energy density of an hybrid Na–air battery is not as high as hybrid Li–air battery (
 <bold>Table</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1498-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">
  <bold>3</bold>
 </xref>) but there are various other advantages associated with this system. In addition to the low price of sodium and the use of cost‐effective material as current collectors,
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">32</xref> the essential advantage lies in the higher ionic conductivities of Na
 <sup>+</sup> ions compared to Li
 <sup>+</sup> ions in organic,
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">33</xref> aqueous, and solid electrolytes which is due to the higher mobility of Na
 <sup>+</sup> ions in electrolyte solution.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">34</xref> Since, Li
 <sup>+</sup> ion has higher Lewis acidity than Na
 <sup>+</sup> ions hence, there exist higher Coulombic interaction between Li
 <sup>+</sup> cations and negatively charged species thereby leading to lower ionic mobility.
 <xref rid="advs1498-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref> Additionally, the solubility of sodium hydroxide in water is higher than lithium hydroxide which also helps improving the specific energy of the cell.[qv: 34b]
</p>
