<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">In this study, we investigate how steady-state GE, AS, and APA changes are coordinated in defining different classes of neurons using high-throughput RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) data. To this end, we first analyzed RNA-seq data
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup> generated from pyramidal neurons purified from the discrete regions of the mouse hippocampus, including proximal-distal, dorsal-ventral, and superficial-deep axes of CA1 and CA3 subfields. In addition to recapitulating previously observed
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup> GE differences between dorsal and ventral CA1 pyramidal neurons, we show that differential AS and APA account for a significant proportion of the variation between populations of this class of hippocampal neuronal subtype. In particular, differential AS predominantly accounts for transcriptomic variation between the proximal-distal axis, and significantly contributes to patterns distinguishing regionally separated CA1 and CA3 neurons, whereas differential APA predominantly accounts for transcriptomic variation between pyramidal neurons from other regions of the hippocampus. We next expanded our analysis to neurons across the nervous system, which identified co-regulated patterns of GE, AS, and APA that, to differing extents, discriminate neurons based on their age, region, and function. While genes affected by each of the three regulatory layers were concentrated in different subsets of genes with overlapping functional categories, in certain cases AS and APA uniquely controlled programs depending on the specific neuronal population. Taken together, our results highlight how GE, AS, and APA patterns collectively contribute to the shaping of the transcriptomes that drive neuronal specification. These findings highlight the importance of integrating multiple types of measurements from the same transcriptomic data to establish the molecular underpinnings of cell-type identity.
</p>
