<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Millions of people around the world suffer from some kind of central nervous system (CNS) disorder.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>
 </sup> A well-known example of such condition is Alzheimer’s disease and, as in many other cases, a possible cure may require the delivery of drugs to the brain. However, 98% of small-molecule drugs and almost all of the larger ones are unable to reach the brain because of the presence of the blood–brain barrier (BBB), which, among others, protects the brain from toxins and pathogens while allowing for the delivery of necessary nutrients and oxygen to the brain.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>
 </sup> The properties of the BBB are mainly determined by the endothelial cells, but they are induced and maintained by complex communication with other types of cells according to the needs of the CNS.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>
 </sup> In fact, the transfer of substances between the blood microcirculation system and the brain parenchyma can take place through a number of active (energy is required, e.g., ATP hydrolysis) and passive translocation mechanisms, where the latter are driven by concentration and electrostatic gradients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>
 </sup> These mechanisms and the way that they apply to different substances eventually determine the BBB 
 <italic>permeability</italic>, which can be expressed by two commonly used experimental descriptors: the steady-state concentration of a drug in the brain over the concentration in the blood (logBB) and the permeability–surface-area product (logPS).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>
 </sup> In general, the entry to the CNS depends on a range of factors characterizing a compound, such as molecular weight, lipid solubility, ability to form hydrogen bonds, amino acid composition, charge, and three-dimensional (3D) structure (conformation, flexibility, folding, and others).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>
 </sup> To this end, the role of many of these characteristics might manifest in model membranes because the rate of passive diffusion across a membrane is proportional to the partition coefficient of the compound between the membrane and the external medium.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>
 </sup> In this respect, the difficulty in traversing such membranes may constitute a measure of the 
 <italic>barrier</italic> that a substance needs to overcome, in this way providing important information for pharmacokinetics and rational drug design, which is the motivation of the current study. Thus, model membranes provide opportunities for prescreening various compounds with the aim of reducing the cost and enhancing the speed of the BBB-permeation analysis, for example, by estimating the partitioning free energy, which has been the focus of previous computational studies.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
