<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">In rapeseed, the most familiar type of CMS is 
 <italic>pol</italic> CMS, which is used worldwide for research purposes. Since its discovery in 1987, it has been found that abnormal transcription of the mitochondrial gene 
 <italic>orf224/atp6</italic> leads to the occurrence of 
 <italic>pol</italic> CMS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], but how the sterility gene 
 <italic>orf224</italic> contributes to the development of abnormal anther functioning remains to be explored [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Besides, the restoration gene of 
 <italic>pol</italic> CMS has been verified by map-based cloning [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]
 <italic>. Rfp</italic> (fertility-restorer) is a nuclear gene encoding a PPR protein located in mitochondria, and it ultimately leads to the malfunctioning of the sterility gene 
 <italic>orf224</italic>, thus allowing restoration of pol CMS-induced fecundity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. However, the mechanism of fertility restorer is not scrutinized. Anther examination in 
 <italic>B. napus</italic> showed that some proteins’ cumulative levels fluctuate considerably, including proteins related to energy and carbohydrate metabolisms, photosynthesis and flavonoid production, aldehyde dehydrogenase performance, and cell wall remodeling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. CMS’s occurrence is characterized by considerable differences in protein level, transcription level, and metabolic level. We will further analyze CMS’s causes and results through the combined analysis of proteomes, transcriptomes, and metabolomes to provide a new research basis for elucidating nuclear-plasmid interfaces. The discovery of new types of CMS may not only improve the cytoplasmic resources of cruciferous plants but also provide valuable resources for examining nuclear-plasmid interaction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In the development of multi-omics, nucleomics (including genomics and transcriptomics) reveal the underlying factors of life phenomena, proteomics reveals the external factors of life phenomena, and metabolomics reveals the final results phenomena. Therefore, by integrating the results of different monolayers of histology to realize the deeper excavation of the essence of life phenomena from cause to effect and from the surface to inward, we will have a more comprehensive and accurate understanding of the laws that reveal the characteristics of life [[
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]].
</p>
