<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ceramics in SCEs could absorb lithium polysulfides via chemical bonding and thus relieve the shuttle effect. Although the shuttle effect still exists in the SCEs‐based Li‐S batteries working at high temperature caused by the high flowability of polymer at high temperature,
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0129" ref-type="ref">129</xref> the SCEs, as well, play an important role on improving the performance of Li‐S batteries. For example, a composite electrolyte consisting of Al
 <sup>3+</sup>/Nb
 <sup>5+</sup> co‐doped cubic LLZO and P(EO)
 <sub>8</sub>/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> was prepared and applied in Li‐S battery (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0012" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>12</bold>
 </xref>a). In order to increase the ion/electron conductivity of sulfur cathode, active S materials were embedded into porous carbon foam decorated by LLZO nanoparticles (S@LLZO@C). As‐prepared all‐solid‐state Li‐S battery shows acceptable specific capacity (&gt;900 mAh g
 <sup>−1</sup> at 37 °C) and high coulombic efficiency (approaches 100%). The LLZO nanoparticles not only act as ion‐conductive fillers but also as interfacial stabilizer to reduce the interfacial resistance.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">48</xref> Judez et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref> reported a double‐layered composite electrolyte (LICGC) consisting of NASICON‐type Li
 <sub>2</sub>O‐Al
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>‐SiO
 <sub>2</sub>‐P
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>5</sub>‐TiO
 <sub>2</sub>‐GeO
 <sub>2</sub>‐LiFSI/PEO (sulfur cathode side) and Al
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>/LiFSI/PEO layers (Li metal anode side). In these all‐solid‐state Li‐S batteries, the Al
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>‐based electrolyte membrane remarkably improves the Li metal/electrolyte interface contact, resulting in high coulombic efficiency and good cycle performance (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0012" ref-type="fig">12</xref>b). Moreover, the LICGC‐based electrolyte membrane boosts the S utilization and cell areal capacity, avoiding the reaction with Li metal. The as‐fabricated Li‐S cell possesses a capacity of 518 and 0.53 mAh cm
 <sup>−2</sup> with a coulombic efficiency higher than 99% by the end of 50 cycles at 70 °C. Therefore, the multi‐layer composite electrolytes are regarded as the promising candidates for developing all‐solid‐state Li‐S batteries with high safety and performances. The novel SCE systems, which are stable with polysulfide species and could suppress their shuttle effect effectively, are critical to promote the development of the next generation Li‐S batteries.
</p>
