<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">We here also show that the exposure to acetic acid induces the differential expression of 127 over 137 RPGs (Supplemental Table S
 <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Moreover, we highlight that the relative ratio of 11 couples of ribosomal protein ohnologs is changed during acetic acid treatments. This is in agreement with the results of Ghulam et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>, that demonstrated that RPGs ohnologs relative content changes in cells that are exposed to stress. They also show that the repression of the major paralogs and/or the upregulation of the minor paralogs reduce the ratio of the major versus the corresponding minor ohnolog in the cells, increasing the frequency of the minor paralogs in the overall ribosome population. Our results confirm the overexpression of the minor paralogs in 3 of the couples of ohnologs described also in ref. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. This highlights that the changes of the ratios in favor of the minor paralogs occur also in the response to acetic acid (Supplemental Table S
 <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">4</xref>) and suggests that the patterns of changes may be specific of specific responses. Among these, also the two paralogs RPL1A and RPL1B (YPL220W and YGL135W, respectively) have an opposite trend in gene expression at 45 min, with the downregulation of RPL1B and the upregulation of RPL1A, respectively. It is also known that RPL1B is involved in proper mitochondrial function and morphology, roles that cannot be compensated by the paralog RPL1A, when RPL1B is not present in the cell
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. These effects suggest that the changes in the relative proportion of ribosomal protein ohnologs, that determine the re-organization of the ribosome stoichiometry, and occurring also during acetic acid treatments, may be dramatic for cellular organization and functioning.
</p>
