<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our results suggest two waves of transcriptional pathology following MIA. First, we found initial induction of immune, metabolic, and angiogenesis gene expression modules specific to MIA exposure and largely restricted to the days following MIA. There is overlap in the acute induction signatures identified here and acute changes reported in other mid-gestational MIA models, including those using a range of injection gestational ages and rat models of LPS (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Carpentier et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Meyer, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Meyer et al., 2006a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">O'Loughlin et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Richetto et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2017</xref>). Previous studies linked maternal immune challenge, prenatal brain hypoxia, and impacts on proliferation (
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Stolp et al., 2011</xref>), neurogenesis, and cortical lamination (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Carpentier et al., 2013</xref>). Thus, it is possible that the acute signatures identified here and mapped to the Green and YeMaBl modules as well as a subset of genes in the unassigned Grey module, capture a generalized response in fetal brain across mid-gestational MIA models. Notably, induction of hypoxia, cellular metabolism and neuroimmune transcriptional signatures, particularly captured here by the Green module, persist at reduced levels at least through P0, and may indicate lasting perturbation to these pathways. Significant association of the Grey unassigned module with the MIA phenotype was driven by a subset of genes that showed strong acute induction at E12.5 and E14.5. By altering WGCNA parameters, we could assign the Grey module genes to co-expression modules but those alterations increased splitting, resulting in a high number of modules and reduced module coherence without clarifying additional MIA-specific modules made up by the relevant Grey module MIA-associated genes. Thus, we opted for reduced splitting to capture major co-expression trends.
</p>
