<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Identifying the early biological processes triggered by MIA are of critical interest for understanding how MIA initiates pathology. Our analysis identified potential drivers of these induced signaling pathways, including targets of substantial interest such as 
 <italic>Vegfa,</italic> that link hypoxia, neurogenesis and cortical angiogenesis (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Argaw et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Takahashi and Shibuya, 2005</xref>). 
 <italic>Vegfa</italic> was upregulated in MIA-exposed animal at all time-points and was among the strongest DE genes at E12.5 and P0. 
 <italic>Vegfa</italic> is critical for cortical development promoting neurogenesis and neurite outgrowth, as well as angiogenesis (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bayless et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Mackenzie and Ruhrberg, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Rosenstein et al., 2010</xref>). Upregulation of 
 <italic>Vegfa</italic> is found in several NDDs and psychiatric disorders, including SZ and depression, and was also reported in a different MIA mouse model (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Arrode-Brusés and Brusés, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Hohman et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Iga et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Isung et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Kahl et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Lee and Kim, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Lizano et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2017</xref>). Induction of angiogenesis in the developing cortex also independently causes a transition from proliferative state to neuronal maturation (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bayless et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Javaherian and Kriegstein, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2016</xref>). Other genes of interest include 
 <italic>Pdk1</italic> (pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 1), which regulates glucose metabolism (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Newington et al., 2012</xref>), 
 <italic>Ldha</italic> (lactate dehydrogenase A), which facilitates glycolysis and participates in brain angiogenesis (
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2018</xref>), 
 <italic>Bnip3</italic> (BCL2 interacting protein 3), which is involved in cell death and mitochondrial autophagy (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Frazier, 2015</xref>), and 
 <italic>Il20rb</italic> (interleukin 20 receptor subunit beta), a receptor subunit for pro-inflammatory interleukins IL-19, IL-20 and IL-24 (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Akdis et al., 2016</xref>). The early perturbed pathways observable within hours of MIA induction may be critical initiating steps leading to the altered general timing of fetal brain development described here. Our findings expand understanding of the molecular basis of these MIA-induced initial perturbations and reveal potentially key drivers of these changes.
</p>
