<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The second component of the neurodevelopmental MIA signature defined here was perturbation to normal patterns of both proliferative and maturational neurodevelopmental modules that manifest several days after MIA induction. Initially, at six hours after MIA, there is a shift in expression of differentiation and neuronal maturation processes (e.g. synaptogenesis) to increased proliferative processes (e.g. positive regulation of cell cycle). This pattern parallels results described for the acute MIA response from other mouse and rat MIA models, where similar pathways were down- or up-regulated in fetal brain in the hours following MIA (
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Money et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Oskvig et al., 2012</xref>). At this developmental stage, our data suggest that MIA induces an acute expenditure of the neocortical, and potentially other, progenitor pools, which in turn leads to an expedited maturation of cells that would normally be generated later during development. Specifically, by E17.5, multiple progenitor and cell cycle markers were significantly decreased in the MIA brains while concordantly, we observed an increase in maturational markers and laminar position that resembled a more developed cortex. Finally, astrocytes, oligodendrocytes, GABAergic interneurons and radially migrating excitatory neuron precursors were effected, suggesting an unbiased impact on progenitors of multiple brain cell types. Although these findings are indicative of overall decreased neurogenesis by E17.5, specific birth-dating and time-course experiments are needed to test whether progenitor cells exit the cell cycle differently and if overall neurogenesis is perturbed beyond the E17.5 time-point reported here. Nonetheless, our time course RNA-seq design revealed that the transcriptional changes following MIA can be separated into discrete biological and temporal expression modules that support altered proliferation and maturation of cell types following MIA.
</p>
