<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Consistent with links between NDDs and developmental timing, atypical neurodevelopmental gene expression networks have been reported in a cortical neurodevelopmental model using autism-patient-derived induced pluripotent stem cells (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bayless et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Schafer et al., 2019</xref>). The majority of the ASD-relevant genes that were DE following MIA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1e</xref>) were associated with perturbation to the modules associated with neurodevelopmental processes. These ASD-relevant genes map to functional and biological pathways generally associated with ASD and NDDs, including gene regulation, neurogenesis, and synapse development, structure, and function. The broad pathway overlap and presence of up- and down-regulation among DE ASD-relevant genes supports their generalized relevance. These overlapping genes represent targets of interest for future studies investigating parallel mechanisms between genetic and MIA-associated NDD risk. Our findings suggest some aspects of the transition from neurogenesis to astrogenesis appear to occur at an earlier stage following MIA based on similar signatures of SOX9+ and GFAP+ cells reported in literature (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Bansod et al., 2017</xref>), and increased OLIG2+ cells and more mature GAD67+ DLX2+ interneurons in the cortex following MIA. These findings are additionally consistent with recent reports using poly(I:C) MIA models that identified perturbed GABAergic interneuron development (
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Thion et al., 2019</xref>), and maturation of GAD+ neuroblast after birth (
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Vasistha et al., 2020</xref>). Future work is needed to determine if and how MIA-associated dynamic transcriptional changes manifest postnatally and whether perturbation to embryonic development impacts cortical cytoarchitecture and function at later postnatal stages.
</p>
