<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">Our study is the first analysis of DARPP-32 protein expression levels in the NAc of the patients with schizophrenia and those of CaN in the postmortem brain tissue of the patients with bipolar disorder. We showed that the levels of DARPP-32 in the PFC of the patients with schizophrenia significantly decreased, while those of CaN tended to increase in the PFC of the patients with schizophrenia. On the other hand, levels of DARPP-32 and CaN showed no significant differences in the NAc of the patients with schizophrenia or bipolar disorder. Moreover, in the PFC we found that positive correlations between expressions of DARPP-32 and CaN and the expression ratio of DARPP-32/CaN were significantly lower in schizophrenia than controls. As aforementioned, the expression of DARPP-32 in the postmortem brain of patients with schizophrenia or bipolar disorder has been largely investigated. While the levels of DARPP-32 protein in the PFC were decreased in patients with schizophrenia and bipolar disorder
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>, findings relevant to the mRNA levels in these regions were inconsistent across studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. Alternatively, a few studies have investigated postmortem expression of CaN in the brains of the patients with schizophrenia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>, but no studies have analyzed this expression in bipolar disorder. These postmortem studies of DARPP-32 or CaN in schizophrenia and/or bipolar disorder are summarized in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Anyway, the most interesting findings in this study was that in the PFC there were positive correlations between DARPP-32 and CaN expression, and lower DARPP-32/CaN ratio in schizophrenia, which were firstly reported to the best of our knowledge. We could point out several suggestions from these results: (1) DARPP-32 and CaN were usually coexistent in the brain, even if in schizophrenia, (2) the balance between DARPP-32 and CaN was greatly disrupted in schizophrenia, and (3) these ware consistent with the results of the above previous postmortem studies review.
</p>
