<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">In a second independent sample set, we could confirm only 1 SNP, exm956405 (=rs1801028), that predicted CaN expression in the NAc. This SNP was identified as a novel missense nucleotide change causing an amino acid substitution of serine with cysteine at codon 311 (Ser311Cys) in 
 <italic>DRD2</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. An association study showed that Cys311 in 
 <italic>DRD2</italic> was significantly associated with schizophrenia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, clinical assessment found that patients with schizophrenia that exhibited the Cys311 allele spent less time sin the hospital, presented less severe negative symptoms, and were more often married compared to patients without Cys311
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. These results suggest that patients with schizophrenia that have the Cys311 allele may respond well to antipsychotic treatment and, as a result, shows relatively mild negative symptoms. A several meta-analyses also demonstrated this association
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. The tendency of this association was observed in our samples of this study (relative risk; 2.968, Fisher’s exact test; p = 0.071). It was further demonstrated that dopamine-induced internalization of DRD2 was impaired in the Cys311 variant of DRD2
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. Since the internalization of DRD2 contributes to its desensitization
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>, the desensitization of DRD2 may also be suppressed in patients with the Cys311 variant. Thus, the disturbance of DRD2 desensitization can prolong dopamine-induced DRD2-mediated signaling and accelerate the subsequent processes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Eventually, dephosphorylation of cAMP response element-binding protein (CREB) binds upstream of four CaN genes (
 <italic>PPP3CA</italic>, 
 <italic>PPP3CB</italic>, 
 <italic>PPP3CC</italic>, 
 <italic>PPP3R1</italic>; found through the ChIP-Atlas database at “chip-atlas.org”) and then decreases CaN expression. This assumed mechanism (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) was consistent with our finding that subjects with Cys311 in 
 <italic>DRD2</italic> featured lower levels of CaN in the NAc (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In other words, the C allele of rs1801028 was at risk for schizophrenia and was associated with lower CaN expression in the NAc.
</p>
