<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">The link between miRNA dynamics and traditional role of plant hormones has been proposed to be much complicated
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. These workers reported that differentially expressed miRNAs, namely miR156, miR149, miR167, miR397, miR1861 and miR1867 target genes related to hormone homeostasis and starch synthesis in rice during grain development. In our study, on a time scale, maximum number of unique miRNA reads was found on day 5 than on days 0 and 10 post anthesis in both SR-159 and SR-157 cultivars (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The total number of unique miRNAs was higher in SR-159 than SR-157 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a) and most of them expressed within the first 5 days after anthesis (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). Between the cultivars, overall expression of unique miRNAs with targets on ethylene pathway genes was higher in high sterile SR-159 than in low sterile SR-157 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c). In particular, the expression at anthesis (day 0) was higher in the former compared to the latter, when ethylene production culminates in rice spikelets resulting grain morbidity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> irrespective of cultivar difference
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. In comparison, the situation was just opposite for miRNAs with targets on IAA pathway (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d). It implied that ethylene evolution was causative for poor grain development and miRNAs participated in its synthesis. We reported earlier that IAA application facilitates development of apical spikelets while compromising with the basal ones
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup> and such discrimination in grain filling might have occurred in the present situation.
</p>
