<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The particle size of embedded ceramics has a significant effect on the ionic conductivity of SCEs. LAGP with different particle sizes was applied to modify the P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiTFSI electrolyte. The results show that the P(EO)
 <sub>18</sub>/LiTFSI solid electrolyte with 20% of the smallest LAGP particles (smaller than 500 nm) exhibits a maximum ionic conductivity of 6.76 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> and an electrochemical window up to 5.3 V versus Li
 <sup>+</sup>/Li at 60 °C.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref> In addition, Zhang et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">47</xref> presented that the Li‐salt‐free PEO with ≈40 nm LLZTO particles showed an ionic conductivity of 2.1 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at 30 °C, which is much higher than those of PEO with ≈10 µm and ≈400 nm LLZTO particles (3.8 × 10
 <sup>−6</sup> and 1.3 × 10
 <sup>−5</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup>, respectively) (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="advs1507-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>4</bold>
 </xref>). Based on the previous results, it can be concluded that the smaller particle with larger specific surface area and more abundant active sites could decrease the crystalline of polymer hosts and promote the dissociation of lithium salts more effectively, and thus provide more ion‐conducting highways for Li ions. Recently, Sun et al.
 <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">69</xref> mixed bimodal‐sized Li
 <sub>7</sub>La
 <sub>3</sub>Zr
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>12</sub> fillers into PVDF/LiClO
 <sub>4</sub> polymer electrolyte (X‐CPE), resulting in an ionic conductivity of 2.6 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> S cm
 <sup>−1</sup> at room temperature. Further characterization indicates that densely packed LLZO fillers with nano‐ and micro‐meter size contribute to the formation of long‐range Li ion pathways and thus high ionic conductivity. Obviously, the nano‐sized particles facilitate the ionic conductivity enhancement of SCEs and the smaller size produces the higher ionic conductivity. However, the ceramic nanoparticles are prone to agglomeration and phase separation in polymer matrix due to their high surface energy. In order to achieve high homogeneity of SCEs and avoid nonuniform Li ion transportation, some special shapes of ceramic fillers are developed to reduce the agglomeration as shown in the following content.
</p>
