<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="advs1507-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>a) Dependence of ionic conductivity of PAN/LiClO
   <sub>4</sub>, PAN/LiClO
   <sub>4</sub> with LLTO nanowires, and LLTO nanoparticles on temperature. Reproduced with permission.
   <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref> Copyright 2015, American Chemical Society. b) Illustration of electric‐field‐directed parallel alignment of LATP@PEGDA, resulting in improved ion conductivity. The electric‐field direction is indicated by the parallel arrow. Reproduced with permission.
   <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">76</xref> Copyright 2018, American Chemical Society. c) Schematic of vertically aligned and connected ceramic channels for enhancing ionic conduction and ionic conductivities of the three structures, the pure PEO/PEG, PEO/PEG/randomly dispersed LATP nanoparticles, and PEO/PEG/ice‐templated LATP nanoparticles electrolytes, at different temperatures. Reproduced with permission.
   <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">60</xref> Copyright 2017, American Chemical Society. d) The comparison of possible Li‐ion conduction pathways. Arrhenius plots of the composite polymer electrolytes with aligned nanowire arrays at various orientations, together with the data for the composite electrolyte with randomly dispersed nanowires and the filler‐free electrolyte. Reproduced with permission.
   <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref> Copyright 2017, Elsevier. e) Schematic representation of possible conduction mechanism in composite electrolytes with agglomerated nanoparticles and 3D continuous framework. Ionic conductivity of LLTO framework, LLTO nanoparticle, and silica particle composite electrolytes. Reproduced with permission.
   <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">55</xref> Copyright 2017, John Wiley and Sons. f) Schematic of SCEs produced by 3D printing technology and their Arrhenius plot of the lithium‐ion conductivity. Reproduced with permission.
   <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0080" ref-type="ref">80</xref> Copyright 2018, Royal Society of Chemistry. g) Schematic and Arrhenius plot of the lithium‐ion conductivity of flexible lithium‐ion conducting ceramic textile. Reproduced with permission.
   <xref rid="advs1507-bib-0082" ref-type="ref">82</xref> Copyright 2018, Elsevier.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-17" xlink:href="ADVS-7-1903088-g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
