<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, the actin cytoskeleton regulation of stem cell is essential for chondrogenesis 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref> where TGF-β rapidly activates PI3K/Akt pathway towards the reorganization of actin filament and cell migration 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>. However, this study demonstrates that cofilin-1 (CFL1), myosin light chain (MLC6B) and transgelin-2 (TAGLN2) were highly modulated in MSC towards chondrogenic lineage 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. CFL1 enhances the rate of dissociation of actin microfilaments, which in turn affects the mechanical properties and extracellular matrix assembly of the cells 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>. In contrary to CFL1, the expression level of MYL6B appears to be increasing in an ascending order from MSCs, cMSCs to ACs. In this study, cMSCs and ACs may have indicated the occurrence of cell contraction during the remodelling of collagen-GAG extracellular matrix (ECM) and acto-myosin fibril 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>. TGF-β has been reported to inhibit cofilin through non-Smad signalling pathways by activating Rho GTPases, ROCK and Limk2, thus shifting towards actin polymerization 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>. Our findings indicate that the complex interactions of ECM molecules may modulate cell-ECM attachment, resulting in initiation of chondrogenesis and maintenance of the chondrogenic phenotype 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>. Although hydrogel contraction could be beneficial for the production of cartilaginous constructs using MSCs, it is postulated that the transgelin associated cell-seeded scaffolds contraction might possibly affect cell migration and proliferation, hence resulting in poorly functional chondrocytes. In this study, TAGLN2 was significantly down-regulated in cMSC (p&lt;0.01). Absence of TAGLN2 has shown to increase the activity of Rho GTPase 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref> that phosphorylates MYL6B and induces formation of stress fibres 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>. The underlying mechanism behind the association of TAGLN2 down-regulation in cMSCs compared to the AC is unclear, therefore further comparative analysis may be required in order to provide further insights to the role of TAGLN2 in chondrogenesis.
</p>
