<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42">Among the upregulated mitochondrial proteins was the molecular chaperone HSPA1L, a member of the 70-kDa heat shock protein (HSP70) family that is localized to the mitochondrial matrix and whose coding gene is located on chromosome 6p21 in the HLA class III region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Other studies have shown that HSP70 appears to be upregulated during infection with HPAI virus compared to during infection with LPAI virus This chaperone is involved in a variety of cellular processes, including folding and transport of newly synthesized polypeptides, proteolytic activation of misfolded proteins, and formation and dissociation of protein complexes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The ECHS1 protein is found in mitochondria, peroxisomes, and smooth endoplasmic reticulum. The upregulated protein enoyl-CoA hydratase, encoded by ECHS1 on chromosome 10, is a 160-kDa hexamer enzyme consisting of 290 amino acids and is located in the mitochondrial matrix. ECHS1 is associated with mitochondrial short-chain and medium-chain fatty acid β-oxidation and branched-chain amino acid catabolic pathways, as well as other catabolic pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In the absence of hepatitis B virus infection, the ECHS1 gene was subjected to RNA interference and was found to promote apoptosis after transfection into HepG2 cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. However, in Xiao et al.’s study in hepatitis B virus-infected HepG2 cells, ECHS1, a binding protein of hepatitis B virus surface antigen, promoted HepG2 cell apoptosis. The coexistence of ECHS1 and hepatitis B virus surface antigen changed the expression of Bcl-2 family proteins; specifically, 12 proapoptotic proteins were upregulated, and 8 antiapoptotic proteins were downregulated [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The results of this study are consistent with those obtained after RNA interference in the absence of hepatitis B virus infection, indicating that not all viruses can use ECHS1 as a binding protein for viral surface antigens, thereby promoting apoptosis. Related studies have confirmed that influenza virus can induce apoptosis. In our study, the difference in BAX expression detected by Western blotting showed that the level of endogenous apoptosis induced by HPAIV was higher than that induced by LPAIV. Endogenous apoptosis leads to mitochondrial swelling, disappearance of internal cristae and permeabilization, a possible reason for the difference in the virulence of these two viruses. In addition, downregulation of ECHS1 protein expression affects the fatty acid β oxidation pathway and reduces the replication ability of RNA viruses such as measles virus, vesicular stomatitis virus, and Semliki Forest virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Our results revealed that the expression of ECHS1 protein was upregulated in the H5N1 virus-infected group compared with that in H9N2 virus-infected group, which may explain why the H5N1 virus is more pathogenic than the H9N2 virus.
</p>
