<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Lizard capacity to self-detach or amputate their tail in flight response from predators is known as the shedding of the tail or caudal autotomy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. These stages include exudation of excessive blood loss; minimizing muscle and bone tissue damage; controlled vascularisation; promotes wound epithelium and further unsegmented remodelling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. The detachment of tail activates multiple cellular responses which spurts the blastema mediated cell proliferation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>, angiogenesis, remodelling and generating a replacement. Studies related to the patterning of successful regenerated autotomized tail or replica consists mainly of nerve cells networking, unsegmented cartilaginous, muscle cells, blood vessels and differential remodelling of cells which make this an interesting research to comprehend the cellular and molecular mechanisms associated with the developmentof regenerated tail
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. With the elucidation of the genes and their associated proteins involved in regeneration, there can be a possibility of understanding why in human’s regeneration is restricted as compared to anamniotes. This also might pave in giving insights into spinal injuries and the fabrication of replacement therapies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. Research on the regeneration of tail and its governing molecular mechanism in other lizard species like 
 <italic>Podarcis muralis</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>; 
 <italic>Hemidactylus flaviviridis</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>; Green Anole
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>; and also in other vertebrates like axolotl
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup> have been carried out related to histology, proteomics and genomics
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Though many genes or proteins have been known still the underlying mechanisms of these molecules remains ambiguous. In this study for the first time we have used common house Gecko, 
 <italic>Hemidactylus frenatus</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> as a model animal to study the genes/proteins associated with tail regeneration particularly during the initial stages of tail regeneration. 
 <italic>Hemidactylus frenatus</italic> have been studied generally for their behavioural, habitat diversification and regenerative abilities
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
