<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NOL6 encodes a nucleolar RNA-associated protein that is associated with the early stage of ribosome biosynthesis (
 <xref rid="b63-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Dong 
 <italic>et al</italic> (
 <xref rid="b64-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>) found that NOL6 is highly expressed in human prostate cancer and that knockdown of NOL6 inhibits the proliferation and mitosis, and increases the apoptosis of human prostatic carcinoma cells (PC-3). In the current study, NOL6 was found to be upregulated in NFPAs that became recurrent within 1 year compared with those recurring after &gt;5 years, suggesting that NOL6 could be a critical gene in prognostic development and a potential target for NFPA treatment. MOV10 belongs to the RNA helicase superfamily of proteins and could regulate mRNA stability and translation (
 <xref rid="b65-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Nakano 
 <italic>et al</italic> (
 <xref rid="b66-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>) demonstrated that the mRNA and protein levels of MOV10 in cancer cells, such as human leukemia and human cervical carcinoma cells, were higher compared with those in normal cells. In addition, MOV10 has been revealed to promote the angiogenesis of glioma by binding circ-DICER1 (
 <xref rid="b51-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). These studies indicated that MOV10 could be critical in tumorigenesis. DCP1A is a protein-coding gene for mRNA-decapping enzyme 1a, and several studies have revealed that DCP1A is upregulated in tumor tissues, such as malignant melanoma, colorectal carcinoma and gastric cancer (
 <xref rid="b67-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>–
 <xref rid="b69-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). In addition, Tang 
 <italic>et al</italic> (
 <xref rid="b67-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>) and Wu 
 <italic>et al</italic> (
 <xref rid="b68-ol-0-0-12525" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>) reported that the high expression of DCP1A in colorectal carcinoma is correlated with poor prognosis, which is consistent with the current results, thus indicating that the other present PCGs and lncRNAs could also be prognostic indicators for NFPA.
</p>
