<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Energy and materials, important pillars of the modern developing society, are closely related to human civilization. Rechargeable lithium-ion batteries, an environmentally friendly and new green energy, have wide applicability in the fields of energy storage and transportation (Song et al., 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The ever-increasing demand for high current charge-discharge capability, high energy density, and long service life has driven the development of the lithium battery industry (Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Olivine phase lithium iron phosphate (LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>) is one of the focused cathode materials in lithium-ion batteries (Padhi et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">1997a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). It has many superior properties, such as that Fe is low-cost and environmentally benign, that the covalently bonded PO
 <sub>4</sub> groups make the chemical properties more stable and prolong service lifetime, and that it has a high theoretical capacity (170 mAhg
 <sup>−1</sup>) and flat voltage plateau (3.45 V vs. Li/Li
 <sup>+</sup>). However, LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> materials have some drawbacks, such as inferior electronic conductivity (ca.10
 <sup>−9</sup>–10
 <sup>−10</sup> Scm
 <sup>−1</sup>) as well as slow one-dimensional lithium ion diffusion, which is a formidable obstacle to the high performance of lithium-ion batteries (Goodenough and Kim, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Dathar et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). A considerable number of methods have been adopted with the aim of alleviating the above shortcomings. These methods can be categorized into two main classes: particle size control (Prosini et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Zhao et al., 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and conductive material coating (Chang et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Han et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Ma et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Tao et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).
</p>
