<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Small particle size can decrease the migration distance of lithium ions from the interior to the surface and increase the diffusion rate (Lim et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Hai et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Li et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Xiao et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Various techniques, including solid-state reaction (Zheng et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), sol-gel (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) hydrothermal (Kiyoshi et al., 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Chang et al., 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), co-precipitation (Park et al., 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and microwave heating (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Beninati et al., 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Guo et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), are adopted to control particle size. Moreover, surface coating with conductive material can increase the electronic conductivity between particles (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Fathollahi et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Ahn et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and provide paths in all directions for the fast transmission of electrons (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Jang et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Fan et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Graphene with high electrical conductivity has been adopted to improve the cycling stability and rate capability of cathode material (Ding et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Shi et al., 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Tang et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Ding et al. (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) prepared nano-structured LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/graphene using co-precipitation and sintering at 700°C for 18 h under argon flow. Shi et al. (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) prepared graphene-wrapped LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/C using a microwave-assisted hydrothermal method, followed by sintering at 600°C for 2 h under H
 <sub>2</sub>/Ar flow. Zhou et al. (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) first synthesized LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> nanoparticles by a hydrothermal method and then synthesized LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/graphene from LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> nanoparticles and graphene oxide nanosheets by spray-drying and annealing processes. Tang et al. (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) synthesized LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/graphene by mixing three-dimensional graphene prepared by chemical vapor deposition and LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub> prepared by solid-state reaction in a N-methyl pyrrolidinone (NMP) suspension. The above experimental methods are very complicated, and most of them require long-term high-temperature treatment and atmosphere protection, which lead to high energy consumption and cost. Additionally, the graphene and active materials agglomerate easily and distribute unevenly. Therefore, simplifying the preparation technology and obtaining a product with a small and homogeneous distribution remain great challenges for preparing LiFePO
 <sub>4</sub>/graphene composites. Microwave heating is a convenient, economical, and environmentally friendly route for the preparation of graphene composites in a way that addresses the deficiency of graphene modification. Microwave heating can simplify the reduction step of graphene oxide, as, due to the microwave-absorbing properties of graphene oxide, microwave irradiation can restore it into graphene directly without any reductive agent and atmosphere.
</p>
