<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">In the present study, the 104 differentially expressed transcripts in F5 follicles were compared with the 249 transcripts differentially expressed in F1 follicles. A total of 67 transcripts showed a clear consistent regulation tendency between the two granulosa subpopulations (Gp and Gd) in both follicles (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). Among the transcripts, the receptor genes 
 <italic>NGFR</italic> and 
 <italic>PTGER3</italic> were found to be differentially expressed in Gp cells and Gd cells. As shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B, 
 <italic>NGFR</italic> is highly expressed in Gp cells of F1 and F5 follicles (G5p: 19.45, G1p: 13.04), however, it is weakly expressed in Gd cells of F5 and F1 follicles (G5d: 1.66, G1d: 0.18). This finding was further confirmed by qRT-PCR analyses (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C). 
 <italic>NGFR</italic> can activate Raf kinase-MAPK/ERK signaling cascade
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>. Although there has not been adequate evidence supporting the hypothesis that this receptor regulates the proliferation of granulosa cells, there was a previous report suggesting that NGFR signaling plays a significant role in the shaping of neural tube in chick embryos
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. Future study on the roles of NGFR signaling in the control of Gp proliferation and functions will be required. Similar to that of 
 <italic>NGFR</italic>, the gene encoding prostaglandin E2 receptor subtype 3 (PTGER3) also displays a differential expression profile in Gp and Gd cells and its expression are much lower in F1 follicles (G1p: 6.04, G1d: 1.00) (G5p: 17.04, G5d: 9.33). It is reported that, like mammalian PTGER3, chicken PTGER3 activation can inhibit cAMP accumulation and stimulates the MAPK/ERK pathway
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. The differential expression of PTGER3 also hints that PTGER3 signaling and its activation of the downstream MAPK/ERK signaling pathway may be involved in the control of granulosa cell proliferation.
</p>
