<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">EGFR signaling has been reported to play critical roles in the control of ovarian granulosa cell proliferation, differentiation and apoptosis in chickens, mammals and teleosts
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, we found that EGFR is abundantly expressed in both Gp and Gd cells. In addition, no statistical difference in EGFR expression levels was detected between Gp and Gd cells of F5 and F1 follicles. Our finding contrasts the report of a previous study, in which EGFR was shown to be differentially expressed in Gd and Gp cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, our finding is slightly different from another report that the EGFR expression level is high in small follicles and small yellow follicles, but decreases in F2 and F1 follicles
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>. </italic>The F1 and F5 follicles harvested for the transcriptome analysis in our study are the large follicles belonging to the third and the final growth phase of ovarian follicles. To meet the need of the fast growth of large preovulatory follicles and keep pace with the rapid yellow yolk incorporation into these large follicles, it was suggested that Gd cells may increase its intercellular space and modulate its cell morphology
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. The abundant consistent expression of EGFR in both Gp and Gd cells strongly supports the role of EGFR signaling in granulosa cell proliferation to cover the growing oocyte surface in large preovulatory follicles. However, the abundant expression of EGFR in Gd and Gp cells raises an interesting question regarding the source of EGFR ligands. It was reported that the GD secretes factors to regulate granulosa cell proliferation and steroidogenesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Their immunocytochemical analysis demonstrated that EGF is present in the GD. Our previous study revealed that HB-EGF, an EGFR ligand, is abundantly expressed in the oocyte and granulosa cells. In vitro studies revealed that EGF and other EGFRL (eg HB-EGF) can regulate granulosa cell proliferation, inhibit apoptosis, and decrease basal P4 production
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>
 </sup>. On the other hand, the addition of anti-EGF antibody abolished the ability of the GD-conditioned medium to stimulate granulosa cell proliferation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup>. All these findings, together with the report of EGFR ligands are either derived from the oocyte (or GD) or granulosa cells, support the hypothesis of the continual involvement of EGFR signaling pathway in regulating granulosa cell proliferation, differentiation, and function along follicular growth.
</p>
