<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent genome-wide studies have focused on cell-specific metabolism in cyanobacteria by comparing gene transcript levels under different growth conditions or stage-specific gene expression signatures in response to nitrogen step-down. RNA sequencing was used to study transcript expression levels in filaments at different periods of nitrogen step-down using a mixture of heterocysts and vegetative cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Using samples collected during the differentiation in three developmental states, a DNA microarray containing 6,893 gene fragments were was used to identify differentially expressed genes (DEGs) regulating the differentiation of heterocysts, akinetes, and hormogonia in the cyanobacterium 
 <italic>Nostoc punctiforme</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Similarly, seven genes encoding transcriptional regulators that respond to nitrogen deprivation in 
 <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. strain PCC 7120 were identified by oligonucleotide microarray technology, and the results for an 
 <italic>nrrA</italic> deletion mutant suggested that 
 <italic>nrrA</italic> facilitates heterocyst development [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. However, vegetative cells in the mycelium samples were not separated from heterocysts in the filamentous cyanobacteria. Therefore, the function of vegetative cells and heterocysts may have been biased in sequencing and bioinformatics analysis. Compared with vegetative cells, heterocysts cells of 
 <italic>Anabaena</italic> have thicker walls and better resist adverse external environments, providing a theoretical basis for the separation and purification of the two types of cells. In general, two strategies are used to isolate and purify heterocysts from the mycelium: sonication treatment [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] or lysozyme treatment [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Vegetative cells easily crack during these treatments, resulting in the isolation of heterocysts without vegetative cells. Heterocysts can be isolated from mycelium containing both vegetative cells and heterocysts of 
 <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. strain 7120 with lysozyme for RNA-Seq analysis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0248155.g001">Fig 1</xref>). We evaluated important candidate genes involved in nitrogen fixation and photosynthesis in vegetative cells and heterocysts from 
 <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. strain PCC 7120 at the transcriptome level and provide insight into the molecular mechanisms of nitrogen fixation and photosynthesis in both cell types.
</p>
