<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ORR can follow one of the two possible pathways. In the 2-electron (2e) process (partial reduction), hydrogen peroxide is formed as the reaction product. In the 4e process (full reduction), water is formed as the final product. Because of a higher efficiency of the 4e process, and due to the high reactivity of the peroxide formed in the 2e process, the 4e process is more attractive for practical applications.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref472">472</xref>
 </sup> The 4e process is facilitated by Pt and Pt-alloy catalysts, while the 2e process takes place, for instance, on Hg, Au, graphite, and different oxide-based materials.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref263">263</xref>
 </sup> For both processes, the first step is the adsorption of oxygen on the catalyst surface. The catalyst activity is thus determined by the balance between the binding energies of the adsorbed oxygen species, reaction intermediates, and products: oxygen species should be adsorbed tightly enough so that the reaction can occur. At the same time, a too strong interaction between the catalyst and intermediates will result in catalyst poisoning.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref472">472</xref>
 </sup> This principle is visualized in the famous “volcano” plots introduced by Norskov and others, which show that the near-optimal binding properties, and hence, maximal ORR activity is expected for Pt and Pt-based materials.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref472">472</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref473">473</xref>
 </sup> The sensitivity of 
 <italic>in situ</italic> XAS to the presence of adsorbates, bond-lengths and bond-strengths between catalyst and adsorbate has been widely used to rationalize the structure–property relationship in the materials for ORR.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref141">141</xref>
 </sup> Strategies like the control of the particle size, control of the exposed facets, alloying of Pt with another metal to introduce lattice strain or to tune the catalyst electronic structure have been proposed for improving the adsorbate binding at Pt-based catalysts, and XAS has been very instrumental for understanding the effect of these parameters on the catalytic activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref263">263</xref>
 </sup> At the same time, due to the high costs of platinum, significant efforts have been invested in the development of nonprecious metal catalysts for ORR, including transition metal–nitrogen doped carbon materials. The sensitivity of XAS to the complex structural motifs encountered in these materials and their 
 <italic>in situ</italic> transformations has been also widely exploited.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
