<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Conceptually similar to measurements in fluorescence mode are XAS measurements in total electron yield mode, where the X-ray absorption probability is also assessed indirectly through monitoring the intensity of a secondary process. In this case, the excitation created by the incident X-rays decays by the emission of Auger electrons. Similarly as with the fluorescence measurements, the emission intensity can be often considered proportional to the absorption coefficient. Because of the short mean free path of the Auger electrons emitted (ca. 1–5 nm, dependently on the energy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref83">83</xref>
 </sup>), the detected signal is limited to the sample surface (and not affected by self-absorption). For the method to work, the sample also needs to be electrically conductive, which is not usually a problem in the studies of electrocatalysts. Conventional total electron yield measurements require vacuum conditions for the electron detection, and thus, their applicability for 
 <italic>in situ</italic> and 
 <italic>operando</italic> investigations of catalysts, and electrocatalysts in particular, is limited. However, conversion electron yield measurements can be used in liquid environment, where the XAS spectrum is measured at the conductive surface that is in the contact with the liquid.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref83">83</xref>
 </sup> For example, Velasco-Velez et al. recently demonstrated the usefulness of 
 <italic>in situ</italic> XAS in total electron yield mode to study the local structure of the electrolyte (water) near a gold electrode and its bias voltage dependence.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref84">84</xref>
 </sup> In their setup, a Si
 <sub>3</sub>N
 <sub>4</sub> membrane was used to separate the electrolyte in the electrochemical cell from the vacuum of the detection system, allowing them to collect oxygen K-edge XAS data in fluorescence mode, as well as in total electron yield mode at a gold electrode, 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>
 </xref>a. As shown in 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>
 </xref>b, the fluorescence and total electron yield modes resulted in significantly different XAS spectra, signifying the importance of the surface-sensitivity of the total electron yield measurements as well as the strong interaction between the water molecules and the gold electrode at the interface.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref84">84</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
