<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">These data are particularly interesting in contrast to dexamethasone-induced transcriptional changes. Surprisingly, treatments with fluoxetine approximate inflammatory 
 <italic>IL6ST</italic> and 
 <italic>NFBK1</italic> gene knockdowns more significantly than dexamethasone—a steroid routinely used to treat cytokine induced hyperinflammation. Administration of dexamethasone in porcine respiratory coronavirus-infected pigs downregulated 
 <italic>IL6</italic> in the early disease stages suggesting that corticosteroids such as dexamethasone may be beneficial to COVID-19 patients if administered during the early acute phase of infection 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. A study comparing over 2000 patients being treated with dexamethasone to over 4000 control patients receiving usual care showed that hospitalized patients receiving respiratory support such as mechanical ventilation or oxygen demonstrate lower 28-day mortality when treated with dexamethasone 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Concordance scores generated by comparisons of fluoxetine treatment and 
 <italic>IL6ST</italic> knockdown or 
 <italic>NFKB1</italic> knockdown are also distinctly higher than those comparing bupropion or paroxetine treatment with the same inflammatory gene knockdowns. This is striking given that both bupropion and paroxetine share monoamine neurotransmission profiles with fluoxetine. Previous reports describe the NF-kappaB family of transcription factors as regulating many pro-inflammatory target genes including 
 <italic>IL6ST</italic>
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Taken together, our data suggest that fluoxetine induces a reduction in IL6ST-mediated signal transduction via NF-kappaB-mediated transcriptional changes. These data also suggest that the anti-inflammatory action of fluoxetine is independent of its action on monoaminergic pathways. Instead, fluoxetine may manifest its anti-inflammatory character through a mechanism of action related to the suppression of inflammatory genes such as 
 <italic>IL6ST</italic> and 
 <italic>NFKB1.</italic>
</p>
