<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cetacean includes both toothless Mysticeti and enamel-less 
 <italic>Kogia</italic>. Relaxation of selective pressure was detected in both crown and stem Mysticeti (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1">Table S5</xref>), which is consistent with the archaic toothless mysticete, namely, all stem Mysticeti were toothless. For example, 
 <italic>Eomysticetus whitmorei</italic>, an edentulous species, was the geologically oldest mysticete (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Deméré et al., 2008</xref>). Molecular evidence shows 
 <italic>ACPT</italic> has been lost its function in LCA of Mysticeti. However, the inactivation time of 
 <italic>ACPT</italic> in Mysticeti is 14.05–16.30 Ma, which is much younger than the toothless mysticete (~30 Ma) and the split of Mysticeti (~25.9 Ma). Obviously, this is not consistent with the facts. It might be associated with relatively lower rates of frameshift accumulation during evolution of mysticete pseudogenes and long lifespan of mysticete (
 <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Meredith et al., 2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Whether adaptive or neutral, the shared single-base site deletion in 
 <italic>ACPT</italic> fills an important gap in our understanding of the macroevolutionary transition leading from the LCA of crown Cetacean to the LCA of crown Mysticeti. Stem physeteroids (sperm whales) are known from the Miocene and had teeth with enamel (
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Bianucci &amp; Landini, 2010</xref>). Our results provide support for loss of the intact 
 <italic>ACPT</italic> in 
 <italic>K. breviceps</italic>. ACPT was reported that play key roles in amelogenesis and differentiation of odontoblasts (
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Seymen et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2017a</xref>). Our result is in line with the enamel-less morphological structure in 
 <italic>K. breviceps</italic>.
</p>
