<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Structural disorder can also change under catalyst working conditions due to interactions with adsorbates. For example, unusually large Debye temperatures, obtained from fitting Debye–Waller factors extracted from EXAFS data, were observed in the presence of hydrogen for Pt NPs with sizes ∼1 nm supported on γ-Al
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref168">168</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref203">203</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref204">204</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref261">261</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref342">342</xref>
 </sup> By comparing results for size- and shape-selected particles of different shapes prepared via a micelle-encapsulation method, a correlation between the surface-to-volume ratio and the Debye temperature was observed (
 <xref rid="fig21" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig21" ref-type="fig">21</xref>
 </xref>a).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref204">204</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref261">261</xref>
 </sup> Nevertheless, based on theoretical simulations, these anomalies were in part attributed to a decreasing hydrogen coverage on the NP surface with increasing measurement temperature.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref261">261</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, Small et al. reported larger Debye–Waller factors for γ-Al
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>-supported Pt NPs measured under CO atmosphere as compared to NPs measured under H
 <sub>2</sub> and observed also a dependency of the Debye–Waller factors on the gas partial pressure.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref343">343</xref>
 </sup> In this study, the elastic energy associated with the lattice strain was also estimated as 
 <inline-formula id="d33e4521">
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="cr0c00396_m029.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, where 
 <italic>C</italic> is the Pt–Pt coordination number, κ is the effective force constant obtained from the temperature-dependency of the Debye–Waller factors (see 
 <xref rid="sec4.3" ref-type="other">Section 
  <xref rid="sec4.3" ref-type="other">4.3</xref>
 </xref>), and σ
 <sub>
  <italic>static</italic>
 </sub>
 <sup arrange="stagger">2</sup> is the static disorder.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref344">344</xref>
 </sup> All of these parameters can be obtained from EXAFS data fitting. While more work is still needed to determine the applicability of this approach, this study provides an interesting example of how EXAFS analysis can provide insight into the thermodynamic characteristics of the material. In particular, the results obtained by Small et al., 
 <xref rid="fig21" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig21" ref-type="fig">21</xref>
 </xref>b, suggest significant differences in the strain energies for NPs under different environments that may affect the equilibrium geometry of the NPs as well as their thermodynamic properties.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref343">343</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
