<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Superimposed onto regional differences is the control of cell identity and differentiation, and several well-characterised TFs serve as markers for musculoskeletal lineages. Chondrogenic cells express 
 <italic>PAX1</italic>, 
 <italic>PAX9</italic> and 
 <italic>SOX9</italic> and dermomyotomal myogenic progenitors are characterised by PAX3 and PAX7. Committed myoblasts express 
 <italic>MYF5</italic> and 
 <italic>MYOD</italic>, while MYOG and KLHL31 are markers for differentiated myocytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Other transcriptional regulators that are important in paraxial mesoderm include TCF15 (Paraxis), a bHLH TF required for somite epithelialization;
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> CDX (Caudal), which is necessary for axis elongation;
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> and MEOX1, which is involved in somite morphogenesis, patterning and differentiation, particularly of sclerotome-derived structures
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. In human, mutations of MEOX1 are found in patients with Klippel-Feil Syndrome, which is associated with fusion and numerical defects in the cervical spine as well as scoliosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Whilst the sequence of marker gene expression in paraxial mesoderm is well defined
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>, the epigenetic and genomic mechanisms that control these transcriptional programmes remain largely unknown. The identification of enhancers has improved through high-throughput sequencing assays and comparative genomic analysis, however, experimental validation of enhancer activity remains challenging. In this study, we assay spatiotemporal changes in both gene expression signatures and accessible chromatin that occur in differentiating paraxial mesoderm along the anterior–posterior axis. We define differentially accessible chromatin regions within 
 <italic>HOX</italic> genes that are associated with regional identities. Footprint analysis shows differential occupancy and coverage of binding sites along the axis for several TFs, including HOXA10, HOXA11, CDX2, LEF1 and RARA. CDX2 and LEF1 are both involved in similar processes during axis extention. However, network analysis shows that CDX2 and LEF1 footprints are associated with different expressed genes and there is little overlap in the genes they interact with. Correlating accessible chromatin with nearby expressed genes identifies cis-regulatory elements (CREs). We focus here on enhancers located upstream of 
 <italic>TCF15</italic> and 
 <italic>MEOX1</italic> and validate these in vivo, using electroporation of fluorescent reporters into gastrula-stage chick embryos. Time-lapse imaging shows the onset of enhancer activation in paraxial mesoderm and mutation of candidate TF motifs or epigenome modification leads to loss of gene expression and phenotypic changes. The 
 <italic>MEOX1</italic> CRE is evolutionary conserved in amphibians and human. Altogether our data characterises the accessible chromatin and gene expression landscapes in paraxial mesoderm, at different stages of somite maturation.
</p>
