<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>10 ml of induced overnight cultures (LB medium supplemented with arabinose 1% (w/v)) was harvested by centrifugation (10 min, 3000 x g, 4°C). The supernatant was discarded, and the bacterial pellets were washed by re-suspending in sterile PBS followed by centrifugation for 10 min at 3000 x g and 4°C. The washing step was repeated twice. Pellets were frozen for 30 min at −80°C and then resuspended in 1.1 ml protein resuspension buffer (1045 µl PBS, 11 µl PMSF solution (100 mM), 44 µl protein inhibitor complete (25x) (Roche, Mannheim, Germany). The samples were transferred to Lysing Matrix E tubes (MP Biomedicals, Eschwege, Germany) and processed with the Precellys24 tissue homogenizer (Bertin Technologies, Montigny-le-Bretonneux, France). The supernatants were transferred to new tubes and stored at −20°C until further use. The protein concentrations of the whole cell extracts were determined using the Protein Assay Dye Reagent Concentrate (BioRad, Munich, Germany) according to the manufacturer’s instructions in a Tecan Infinite F200 plate reader (Tecan, Crailsheim, Germany). 10 µg, 5 µg, and 2.5 µg of total protein extracts of EAEC strain 55989 
 <italic>agg3
  <sup>−</sup>
 </italic> harboring one of the plasmids pAAF/I, pAAF/III, pAAF/IV or pAAF/V, as well as 10 µg of EAEC strain 55989 
 <italic>agg</italic>3
 <sup>−</sup> (pBAD24) were subjected to SDS-PAGE and Western blotting according to the standard protocols described elsewhere [
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Polyclonal antibodies used for detection of AAF variant major subunits AggA to Agg5A expression were generated by Davids Biotechnologie GmbH (Regensburg, Germany). Primary antibodies were used in a 1:2000 dilution. For the detection of the primary antibodies an anti-rabbit antibody coupled with horseradish peroxidase (HRP) (Dianova, Hamburg, Germany) (1:15,000) and the Clarity ECL solution (BioRad, Munich, Germany) was used. The signals were recorded using the ChemiDoc MP System (BioRad, Munich, Germany). For details about antibodies see Supplementary Table S4.
</p>
