<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mtz interacts with oxidoreductase enzymes in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic>, which include glycolytic and antioxidant enzymes, but is also influenced by enzymes that contribute to the reduction potentials through electron transport, cofactor abundance, and flavin metabolism. Changed activity or expression of these enzymes correlates with resistance, with changes leading to decreased activation or increased detoxification of Mtz, known as passive and active resistance mechanisms, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In 
 <italic>Giardia</italic>, the downregulation or reduced activity of pyruvate:ferredoxin oxidoreductase (PFOR) is a centrally recognized passive resistance mechanism [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10–14</xref>]. However, transcriptional studies suggest that exposure to Mtz elicits genome-wide changes in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], including within wider glycolytic and redox systems. Notably, downregulation of thioredoxin reductase [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], which links thiol metabolism to thioredoxins and peroxiredoxins in the antioxidant system, is a passive resistance mechanism that can limit activation of Mtz, albeit at presumed costs to collateral antioxidant systems. Furthermore, the role of the 2 nitroreductases (NRs) in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> have been implicated in Mtz resistance, with NR-1 and NR-2 activating and detoxifying MtzR, respectively, and are active (NR-2) and passive (NR-1) resistance mechanisms. NR-1 transcript levels are reduced in Mtz-resistant lines [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref>], and the enzyme is increasingly recognized as a PFOR-independent mechanism of passive resistance. Drug-resistant lines also exhibit differential transcription protein chaperones, thiol-cycling, and stress response genes [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], as well as DNA repair mechanism transcriptional regulators [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
</p>
