<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Collectively, evidence suggests that Mtz resistance is a complex polygenic phenotype (reviewed by Ansell et al. [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]). Namely, divergent changes in transcript abundance between genetically similar Mtz-resistant 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and laboratory lines [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] suggest multiple Mtz-resistant molecular phenotypes. Further, the interactions of transcriptional expression, enzyme activity, and, recently, nonsynonymous mutations [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] remain to be understood in key enzymes. Phenotypic aspects including infectivity and fitness also differ in lines of different genetic background selected for Mtz resistance 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Plasticity in the resistance phenotype during encystation [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] or when drug selection is discontinued [
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] further suggests reversible or inducible transcriptional regulation. Transcriptional plasticity has been linked to Sir2 nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD)-dependent protein deacetylases (sirtuins) [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and may indicate a role for reversible protein modifications in resistance phenotypes. RNA transcription and control of gene expression in 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22–24</xref>] suggest an important role for post-transcriptional and post-translation regulation, and a global description of protein expression is a key, missing link in Mtz-resistance research. In light of this, we undertook detailed, quantitative proteomic analyses in Mtz-resistant and -susceptible 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> lines to identify differentially expressed proteins. To our knowledge, this marks the first such analysis of Mtz resistance in any parasitic pathogen. This work was conducted in 3 genetically distinct 
 <italic>Giardia</italic> cell culture isolates that each have been heavily characterized in the literature [
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25–27</xref>] and have shaped the foundational understanding of Mtz resistance in the genus [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Moreover, we examined dynamic changes in a wide range of post-translational protein modifications in Mtz-resistant and -susceptible and isogenic isolates and, in the latter, after several months of drug-free passage.
</p>
