<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f020">Figure 20</xref> schematically illustrates some potential applications of this basic idea. In 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f020">Figure 20</xref>A, an enthalpy change Δh
 <sub>sc</sub> due to quench-induced precipitation during slow cooling is assumed. Since the reheating step ends in an enthalpy state h
 <sub>0</sub> = 0, the same magnitude of enthalpy change (with an opposite algebraic sign compared to cooling) must be exchanged during reheating. Reheating can therefore reveal the enthalpy change caused by precipitation during slow cooling. Reheating experiments after variations of the “slow” cooling rate thus allow for the determination of precipitation enthalpy as a function of the cooling rate [
 <xref rid="B117-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Since “slow” cooling in this case refers to the capability of the calorimeter used, reheating can be applied to extend the cooling rate range in both directions, i.e., both slower and faster experiments. In both cases, quantitative statements of the enthalpy changes are possible [
 <xref rid="B117-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. We performed slow cooling in a controlled air furnace with rates down to 3 × 10
 <sup>−5</sup> K/s, corresponding to a cooling duration (540 to 20 °C) of more than half a year [
 <xref rid="B132-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. On the other side of the spectrum, using the chip-sensor based DFSC, “slow” cooling may be as fast as several hundreds of K/s [
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. These DFSC devices commonly require scanning rates above 1,000 K/s to obtain a sufficient signal to noise ratio [
 <xref rid="B134-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Thus, reheating in a DFSC is typically carried out at rates above 1,000 K/s [
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B162-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. The reheating approach can be extended to a temperature-dependent determination of the precipitation enthalpy by interrupting the precipitation process during “slow” cooling at a certain temperature T
 <sub>i</sub> (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f020">Figure 20</xref>C) [
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>].
</p>
