<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our finding that both GluN2B and GluN2D are preferentially expressed in the male SDH is consistent with previous reports demonstrating predominant localization of both subtypes to the SDH [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The high expression of both isoforms in the SDH is also consistent with functional evidence. Unlike the majority of mature CNS synapses where GluN2A dominates excitatory NMDAR-mediated responses [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], both GluN2B- and GluN2D-containing receptors mediate a significant fraction of synaptic responses in laminae I and II neurons of male rats [
 <xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. As observed in other CNS regions [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], there is also evidence for the contributions of GluN2B- and GluN2D-containing receptors to extrasynaptic glutamate-evoked NMDAR responses in SDH neurons [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In agreement with single-channel recordings demonstrating GluN2B- and GluN2D-like currents on SDH somatic membranes [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], our results here show significant localization of both GluN2B and GluN2D protein to the soma of SDH neurons. Previous studies have reported a pronounced contribution for GluN2A-containing NMDARs to the afferent-evoked synaptic responses of SDH neurons [
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], which is consistent with our finding of robust expression of GluN2A protein that is mainly confined to synaptic neuropil across the dorsal horn. Taken together, our experimental results on the relative cellular and subcellular localization of GluN2A, GluN2B, and GluN2D proteins across the dorsal horn of male rats align well with the available functional and immunohistochemical data from male and unspecified sex rodents.
</p>
