<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the prevalence of chronic pain syndromes is higher in females [
 <xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], the vast majority of preclinical basic science research into molecular mechanisms of pain processing have been conducted in male rodents. This study highlights the urgent need to systematically characterize all elements of pain processing in female animal models, as even fundamental mediators of synaptic transmission and plasticity – NMDAR subunits – are differentially expressed at baseline between males and females. We found that the overall expression and subcellular localization pattern of GluN2A, GluN2B, and GluN2D in the dorsal horn were relatively conserved between males and females. However, unlike males, only GluN2B (and not GluN2D) was preferentially localized to the SDH in female spinal cord. Moreover, the preferential localization of GluN2B to the medial SDH was observed in males and not females (see below for importance). The underlying mechanisms that mediate this differential NMDAR subunit expression between sexes remain to be explored and could be due to hormonal, genetic, and/or epigenetic factors. For example, both estrogen receptor α (ERα) and estrogen receptor β (ERβ) are expressed in laminae I and II from an early embryonic stage and are involved in dorsal horn morphogenesis, such as the differentiation of specific neuronal subpopulations [
 <xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Interestingly, both ERα and ERβ are expressed within glial cells of the developing spinal cord [
 <xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and thus, 17-β-estradiol (E2) may act on ER receptors within neurons or glia to directly or indirectly mediate transcriptional changes and differentiation within dorsal horn neurons. To further investigate this, it will be important to examine the potential differential expression of NMDAR subunits and their regulators within specific spinal subpopulations of neurons and glia in males versus females using single-cell sequencing approaches [
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Given that this study was conducted in juvenile rats, future studies should also investigate NMDAR subunit expression in adult rats to determine whether puberty further enhances (or diminishes) the differential expression of NMDAR subunits between sexes.
</p>
