<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many studies have used LCA techniques and confirmed that the impact of EV manufacturing on the environment and depletion of mineral resources is higher than that of fossil fuel-powered vehicle manufacturing [
 <xref rid="B13-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This difference is mainly attributed to the battery manufacturing processes, which could account for approximately 20% of the total energy consumed for manufacturing EVs and approximately 40% of the CO
 <sub>2</sub> released by EVs during their entire life [
 <xref rid="B35-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. More specifically, the production of cathodic materials, particularly for Ni- and Co-based cathodes, is the most impactful step during the manufacturing of LIBs [
 <xref rid="B36-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="materials-13-00801-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the global warming potential associated with the production of 1 kg LFP active material calculated using LCA data provided in the listed references. The energy impact of cathodic material manufacturing has been reported to range from 19 to 56 MJ per kg of LFP [
 <xref rid="B38-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The charts in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-00801-f003">Figure 3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-13-00801-f004">Figure 4</xref>, which were reproduced from Dunn et al. (2015), compare the process costs and greenhouse emissions of several cathode materials [
 <xref rid="B38-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Therefore, post-consumption LIB recycling could reduce the life cycle impact of EVs by up to 51% [
 <xref rid="B14-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and deviate a significant amount of waste from MSW facilities [
 <xref rid="B40-materials-13-00801" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. This could also represent a great opportunity for boosting local economies as long as circular economy principles are applied.
</p>
