<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">Although 
 <italic>ZNF131</italic> acts as a transcriptional activator, Kaiso, a transcriptional regulator, was implicated in its repression, and together they fine-tune the transcription of Kaiso targets
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. Muscle structure development and skeletal muscle tissue growth were among the BP over-represented by the 34 co-regulated genes between 
 <italic>ZNF131</italic> and 
 <italic>ZBTB33</italic>. The myogenic regulatory factors 
 <italic>MYOD1</italic>, 
 <italic>MYF5</italic>, and 
 <italic>MYOG</italic> were negatively and differentially correlated with 
 <italic>ZBTB33</italic> and/or 
 <italic>ZNF131</italic> in RES fetuses. The 
 <italic>CDKN1A</italic> gene was negatively correlated with these TFs in the RES group and also DEG
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. The protein encoded by the 
 <italic>ZNF131</italic> gene has been associated with skeletal muscle atrophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, 
 <italic>CDKN1A</italic> gene expression is synergistically activated by 
 <italic>SMAD4</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup> that was identified here as DK and negatively co-expressed with 
 <italic>MYOG</italic> and 
 <italic>MYOD1</italic>. The protein encoded by 
 <italic>SMAD4</italic> has an inhibitory effect on protein synthesis and muscle growth
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. Genes encoding proteins involved in muscle contraction, such as those from the troponin and myosin families, were also negatively regulated in the RES group. We collected the fetal tissues on day 50 of pregnancy, which coincides with the beginning of primary myogenesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, our findings show the potential mechanism by which maternal nutrient restriction negatively modulates myogenic developmental programming in cattle.
</p>
