<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">Like the muscle, our findings evidenced a severe impact of a moderate maternal nutrient restriction in the day 50 fetal brain genes involved with development and metabolism. First, we found a large number of DC genes between CON and RES, and several DK TFs. Second, pathways such as PI3K/AKT and mTOR seem to be differentially regulated between the CON and RES groups. The brain plays a central role in the body’s energy homeostasis by integrating metabolic signals from other tissues and coordinating adaptive changes under nutrient deficiency
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. These signals are integrated by the mTOR pathway that together with the PI3K/Akt signaling pathway governs neuronal fate by regulating protein synthesis and energy homeostasis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, insulin signaling plays a role in neuronal differentiation by activating mTOR
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. Nutrient restriction has been associated with reduced transcription rate modulated by mTOR
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. We found the ribosome pathway over-represented by the DC genes encoding ribosomal proteins, and intriguingly these genes were mainly negatively correlated in the RES group. Impaired ribosome biogenesis has been associated with neurodevelopmental disorders and reduced protein synthesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup>. The 
 <italic>PAK5</italic>, 
 <italic>ELAVL4</italic>, and 
 <italic>ZNF207</italic> genes were DC with the ribosomal genes identified in the current study. The 
 <italic>ELAVL4</italic> gene encodes an RNA-binding protein (HuD) important for neuronal development and plasticity, acting on mRNA stability, translation, and alternative polyadenylation of target genes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. The 
 <italic>PAK5</italic> gene encodes a brain-specific protein involved with neurite development
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, the PAK family members are regulators of PI3K and via the PI3K/Akt pathway modulate HuD abundance post-transcriptionally
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. The ZNF207 TF plays a role in cell pluripotency by regulating neuronal TFs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
