<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">Metabolic stress resulting from energy restriction can activate the transcription of inflammatory genes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. The TGF-β family is pivotal for organogenesis, and it was shown to negatively affect brain development by inhibiting neurite elongation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>. We identified 
 <italic>TGFB1</italic> and 
 <italic>TGFB3</italic> DC and negatively correlated with 
 <italic>NKX2</italic>-1, 
 <italic>ELAVL4</italic>, and 
 <italic>SLC17A6</italic> in the RES group. The 
 <italic>SLC17A6</italic> gene encodes a glutamate transporter protein
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
 </sup>, while 
 <italic>NKX2</italic>-1 encodes a TF that regulates target genes involved with the development of interneurons
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>. In response to inflammatory processes, hypoxia-inducible factors (HIFs) modulate metabolic homeostasis by activating hypoxia-induced genes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, these genes underlie cell differentiation and vascular development in the fetal brain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>. We identified the HIF pathway over-represented from the DC genes. Among them, the 
 <italic>ZNF395</italic> TF was positively correlated with most of the gene pairs DC in the RES fetuses. 
 <italic>ZNF395</italic> is targeted by the HIF-1α TF activating hypoxia-induced pro-inflammatory genes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. On the other hand, the 
 <italic>ETS2</italic> and 
 <italic>NFKB2</italic> TFs that were both DC and DK showed mainly negative correlations in the RES group. The ETS2 protein has been associated with neuronal apoptosis and neurodegeneration in neurons of Down syndrome
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. However, in macrophages, it had a negative effect on the inflammatory response
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. Regarding the NFKB2 protein, it has a pleiotropic effect and acts in processes such as synaptic plasticity under normal physiology; however, in disease, it is involved with neuroinflammation as well as neuronal cell death
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup>. Considering the findings, the moderate maternal dietary restriction induced changes in gene wiring and expression in the brain may have altered BP related to neuronal development and energy homeostasis. Although the effects of these changes in animal health and performance are still unknown, they could affect animal reactivity, stress responses, and feeding behavior
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
