<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">Maternal nutritional insults may have more dramatic effects on muscle development as it has low priority in nutrient partitioning, resulting in greater concern due to the economic importance of muscle tissue
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Offspring of nutrient-restricted dams showed a reduced number of muscle fibers and muscle mass, as well as altered muscle function and gene regulation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. Among the TS genes, well known upstream regulators of myogenesis, such as 
 <italic>MYOG, MYOD1, PAX1,</italic> and 
 <italic>MYF5</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>,</italic> were found by our approach. Interestingly, some of these TS regulators along with DEGs were negatively correlated with the 
 <italic>ZBTB33</italic> and 
 <italic>ZNF131</italic> TFs in the RES group. The 
 <italic>ZBTB33</italic> gene encodes a methyl-CpG-binding protein (Kaiso) that recognizes both unmethylated and methylated CpGs, acting as a transcriptional repressor
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. The role of Kaiso in regulating myogenic genes is still to be examined; however, Ruzov et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> showed that Kaiso is necessary during early 
 <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> development. Moreover, CIBZ, a Kaiso-like family member, represses 
 <italic>MYOG</italic> in a methylation-dependent manner
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Although we do not have the methylation profile for these animals, Crouse et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup> reported reduced methionine and increased homocysteine concentrations in amniotic fluid and serum, respectively, in RES heifers. The imbalance in one-carbon metabolism would likely affect the gene transcription by altering chromatin remodeling and DNA methylation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
