<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nucleases are important pathogenic factors for certain mycoplasmas, which degrade host nucleic acids, and are used as a source of nucleotide precursors, thereby playing a pivotal role in growth, survival, persistence, and pathogenicity. The first nuclease was identified approximately 20 years ago. Since then, a number of similar enzymes or homologous genes have also been reported in 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae, M. genitalium, M. hominis, M. penetrans, M. bovis, M. agalactiae, M. meleagridis, M. gallisepticum, M. hyopneumoniae, M. hyorhinis, M. pulmonis, U. diversum, U. urealyticum</italic>, and 
 <italic>U. parvum</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0120" ref-type="bibr">120–129</xref>]. Some of the characterized nucleases are listed in 
 <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Certain nucleases contain distinct functional domains, such as the TNASE_3 domain or glutamic acid-, lysine-, and serine-rich (EKS) regions. For example, both 
 <italic>M. gallisepticum</italic> MGA_0676 and 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> MbovNase contain a TNASE_3 domain, which is essential for nuclease activity, cytotoxicity, apoptosis, and nuclear translocation [
 <xref rid="cit0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. In contrast, the EKS region of 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> Mpn133 is essential for binding and internalization in A549 cells and nuclear localization of mycoplasma proteins within the host cells, but it is not involved in the enzymatic activity of Mpn133 [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. Mycoplasma nucleases are not only considered to perform a metabolic function in the generation of nucleotide precursors from host or bacterial nucleic acids released by normal and death cell, but also serve as a significant immune evasion factor for certain mycoplasmas [
 <xref rid="cit0133" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. The nucleases-mediated invasiveness is predominantly reflected in the following aspects: (I) degradation of neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs), thereby promoting evasion of innate immunity (e.g. 
 <italic>M. agalactiae</italic> MAG_5040, 
 <italic>M. hominis</italic> MHO_0730, 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> Mpn491, and 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> MnuA) [
 <xref rid="cit0134" ref-type="bibr">134–137</xref>]; (II) modulation of the expression of certain proinflammatory cytokines, such as, 
 <italic>M. hyopneumoniae</italic> Mhp597 that upregulates the expression of inflammatory genes and downregulates the expression of type I IFN [
 <xref rid="cit0125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. 
</p>
