<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.4.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art540.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.4.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_JGR277 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ginseng Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ginseng Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Ginseng Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1226-8453</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2093-4947</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6026366</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1226-8453(16)30330-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgr.2017.04.006</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A proteomic approach reveals the differential protein expression in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> treated with red ginseng extract (<italic>Panax ginseng</italic>)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Qing-Xiu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><email>jilinhouwei@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Ying-Ping</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Institute of Special Animal and Plant Sciences, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Changchun, Jilin, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>State Key Laboratory for Molecular Biology of Special Economic Animals, Changchun, Jilin, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Institute of Special Animal and Plant Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Science, Changchun 130112, Jilin, China. <email>jilinhouwei@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>42</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2017 The Korean Society of Ginseng, Published by Elsevier Korea LLC.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Red ginseng is a popularly used traditional medicine with antiaging effects in Asian countries. The present study aimed to explore the changes in protein expression underlying the mechanisms of life span extension and antiaging caused by red ginseng extract (RGE) in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A proteomic approach of two-dimensional polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (2-DE) was used to identify the differential abundance of possible target proteins of RGE in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>. The reliability of the 2-DE results was confirmed via Western blotting to measure the expression levels of selected proteins. Proteins altered at the expression level after RGE treatment (1&#x000a0;mg/mL) were identified by matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization-time of flight tandem mass spectrometry and by searching against the National Center for Biotechnology nonredundant and Uniprot protein databases. The differentially expressed proteins were analyzed using bioinformatics methods.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The average survival life span of <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> was significantly extended by 12.60% with RGE treatment (1&#x000a0;mg/mL) compared to untreated flies. This followed increased superoxide dismutase level and decreased methane dicarboxylic aldehyde content. Based on the searching strategy, 23 differentially expressed proteins were identified (16 up-regulated and 7 down-regulated) in the RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>. Transduction pathways were identified using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes database, and included the hippo and oxidative phosphorylation pathways that play important roles in life span extension and antiaging process of <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Treatment with RGE in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> demonstrated that mechanisms of life span extension and antiaging are regulated by multiple factors and complicated signal pathways.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>antiaging</kwd><kwd>life span extension</kwd><kwd>proteome</kwd><kwd>red ginseng extract</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Aging, a spontaneous and complex process with the passage of time, is one of the most important risk factors for increasing susceptibility to multiple diseases <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. It involves much morphological and functional deterioration in biological systems, which are associated with various molecular, cellular, and organic changes <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Aging features a progressive accumulation of oxidative agents associated with decreased efficiency of antioxidant defense mechanisms. Related to this is a progressive decrease in immune activity or immune senescence. As animals age, their mitochondrial function and thus cellular metabolism systematically decline, leading to a loss of cellular homeostasis and the occurrence of multiple disorders <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Thus, a number of efforts have been made to elucidate the mechanisms of the processes of aging and to discover new compounds that retain antiaging activities.</p><p id="p0015">Ginseng (<italic>Panax ginseng</italic> Meyer, Araliaceous) is an important medicinal herb that has long been used to treat various diseases in Asian countries (i.e., Korea, China, and Japan) <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Among several kinds of <italic>P.&#x000a0;ginseng</italic> products, red ginseng, produced by steaming and drying fresh ginseng, is a main active ginseng. During this process, ginsenosides undergo chemical changes that have the potential to create special physiologic activities <italic>in&#x000a0;vivo</italic>
<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. This is known to have various physiological activities, including&#x02014;but not limited to&#x02014;antioxidant, anticancer, tonic, and antiaging effects. Red ginseng improved learning and memory of the mice <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, and Korean Red Ginseng tonic extended the life span of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>
<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. However, there is very limited information on the proteomic mechanisms underlying the antiaging effect and life span extension of red ginseng on <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> or other animal models, because existing studies have primarily focused on pharmacology and/or pharmacodynamics association studies <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p><p id="p0020">In this study, <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>, an internationally recognized model for studying life span that is widely used in antiaging medical research, was used to elucidate this issue <italic>in&#x000a0;vivo</italic>. A proteomic approach of two-dimensional polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (2-DE) was used to investigate changes in age-related specific indicators and relative abundance of proteins in expression caused by feeding with red ginseng extract (RGE). Our findings could be helpful in revealing the mechanisms and addressing biological questions underlying the effects of red ginseng on life span and antiaging.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Plant materials and reagents</title><p id="p0025">Fresh ginseng (6&#x000a0;yr) was obtained from Jilin City, Jilin Province, China. Red ginseng and its extract (RGE) were processed and provided by the Medicinal Plant Analysis laboratory of the Institute of Special Animal and Plant Sciences, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences (Jilin, China), according to the national standard of China (Technical specifications for red ginseng processing, NO. NY/T 2784-2015). The panaxoside content (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>, <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref>) in the RGE was determined as previously described <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, using high-performance liquid chromatography, as follows (all in mg/g): Rb1 30.13, Rb2 14.67, Rb3 8.23, Rc 20.45, Rd 15.57, Re 16.44, Rf 1.83, Rg1 4.47, Rg2(s) 1.96, Rg2(r) 0.42, Rg3(s) 2.06, Rg3(r) 1.18, Rg5 3.31, Rk1 1.07, and Ro 4.09.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Panaxoside content of red ginseng extract (RGE) determined by high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). (A) HPLC chromatogram of ginseng saponin standard. (B) HPLC chromatogram of RGE.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig.&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0030">Urea, 3-[(3-cholamidopropyl)dimethylammonio]propanesulfonate (CHAPS), Pharmalyte, dithiothreitol (DTT), and iodoacetamide were obtained from AMRESCO (Solon, OH, USA). ReadyPrep 2-D cleanup kit and reagents used for 2 DE and Western blotting were purchased from Bio-Rad (Richmond, CA, USA). The primary antibodies for Western blotting included rabbit anti-14-3-3 zeta (1433Z) polyclonal antibody, rabbit antivacuolar-type H(+)-ATPase (VATA) polyclonal antibody, rabbit antiheat-shock protein 70 (HSP70) polyclonal antibody, rabbit antiglycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GPDA) polyclonal antibody, mouse antiubiquitin carboxyl-terminal hydrolase isozyme L1 (UCHL1) monoclonal antibody mouse antifructose-bisphosphate aldolase (ALF) monoclonal antibody, and mouse antiglyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) monoclonal antibody (dilution 1:1000; Proteintech, Chicago, IL, USA). The secondary antibody used in this study was horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat antirabbit/mouse IgG (dilution 1:2,000; Proteintech).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Life span analysis of <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic></title><p id="p0035">Wild type <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> (Oregon K) was a gift from Jilin Agricultural University and was used throughout the experiment. Single populations (200 flies each) of males were housed in a biochemical incubator with 12-h dark/light cycle at 25&#x000b0;C, 60% humidity, and with free access to basal food (water, 1.2% agar, 2.2% sucrose, 1.8% yeast extra powder, 8% corn extract, and 6.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L/L propionic acid). For RGE treatment, basal food was supplemented with RGE at a final w/v concentration of 1&#x000a0;mg/mL optimized by&#x000a0;our previous study (unpublished). The food was changed every 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;d.</p><p id="p0040">To examine the effects of RGE on the life span of flies, survival was observed and documented at 8:00 <sc>p.m</sc>. when transferring to fresh basal food or basal food supplemented with RGE every 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;d. Survivorships were scored regularly and eliminated the unnatural death flies, and death flies were removed out of the cage when possible. Prism 5 (GraphPad Software Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) was used for data analysis, and statistical significance was tested with log-rank statistical methods. Mean (average value of all values) and maximum (average values of the last 20 dead flies) values were presented to compare results.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Methane dicarboxylic aldehyde and superoxide dismutase assessment in whole tissue</title><p id="p0045">Flies of wild type and RGE-treated groups were anesthetized and collected at the age of 21&#x000a0;d. Flies (whole tissue) were homogenized and centrifuged at 4,000<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x000a0;min. Supernatants were collected gently and kept at&#x000a0;&#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until analysis measurements.</p><p id="p0050">The extent of lipid peroxidation in whole tissue was estimated by measurement of methane dicarboxylic aldehyde (MDA) formation <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The MDA assay was performed using an MDA kit (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, Nanjing, China) following the manufacturer's instructions. In brief, 0.2&#x000a0;mL thiobarbituric acid and antioxidant reagents were respectively pipetted into a microcentrifuge tube containing 0.1&#x000a0;mL of wild type or RGE-treated homogenate and MDA standard solution. Tubes were vortexed and then incubated at 95&#x000b0;C for 40&#x000a0;min and centrifuged at 4,000<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x000a0;min. Then, 0.3&#x000a0;mL of the supernatant from each of the tubes was transferred to the quartz sampling cell, and the absorbance was measured at 532&#x000a0;nm using a spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Lite; Thermo-Fisher, Waltham, MA, USA). The content of MDA was expressed as nmol MDA/mg homogenate protein. The total protein concentration was determined by the Bradford method, using bovine serum albumin as the standard.</p><p id="p0055">Whole tissue total superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity was measured using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kits (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, China) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, 0.1&#x000a0;mL of whole tissue homogenate was mixed with 0.9&#x000a0;mL of physiological saline (0.9% NaCl), and then 0.1&#x000a0;mL of 15mM pyrogallic acid was added. The activity was measured at 420&#x000a0;nm for 3&#x000a0;min using a multidetection microplate reader (Infinite 200; Tecan, M&#x000e4;nnedorf, Switzerland) and expressed as U/mg protein. One unit was determined as the amount of enzyme that inhibited the oxidation of pyrogallic acid by 50%. Experiments for MDA content and SOD activity were performed in triplicate in this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Sample preparation and protein extraction</title><p id="p0060">Both wild type and RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> (21&#x000a0;d old, about 20 flies each) were resuspended in 600&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L lysis buffer (7M Urea, 2M Thiourea, 4% CHAPS, and 1% phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF)). Bullet Blender (Next Advance, Averill Park, NY, USA) was used to break the tissue as described previously <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Supernatants were collected after sharking in ice for 2&#x000a0;h and centrifugation at 12,000<italic>g</italic> at 4&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min. Concentrations of proteins were detected using the <italic>RC DC</italic> Protein Assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). The protein samples were purified using the 2D Cleanup kit (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) following the manufacturer's instructions. Experiments in this study were performed in triplicate gels (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Two-dimensional gel electrophoresis</title><p id="p0065">Proteins (both wild type and RGE-treated) were first separated with isoelectric focusing using linear precast immobilized pH gradient (IPG) strips (17&#x000a0;cm, 3&#x02013;10 linear pH gradients; Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). IPG strips with 1.2&#x000a0;mg of proteins were rehydrated for 12&#x000a0;h and focused at 15,000 Vhs (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). First-dimension strips were stored at&#x000a0;&#x02212;80&#x000b0;C or equilibrated immediately in first equilibration solution [75nM Tris&#x02013;HCL, pH 8.8, 6M urea, 2M thiourea, 30% glycerol, 2% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS), and 0.002% bromophenol blue] with 100mM DTT for 15&#x000a0;min, followed by the second equilibration with 250mM iodoacetamide for 15&#x000a0;min. 2-DE was performed using 12.5% polyacrylamide gels at 90&#x000a0;V for 30&#x000a0;min and 140&#x000a0;V for 4&#x02013;5&#x000a0;h at 20&#x000b0;C in Bio-Rad systems (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Staining and image analysis</title><p id="p0070">Gels (six in total) were stained using Pierce Silver Stain Kit (Thermo Fisher, MA, USA) as per the manufacturer's instructions. The stained gels were scanned using an image scanner (UMAX, Dallas, TX, USA) at 600 dpi. All detected spots were automatically matched by gel-to-gel comparison using the PDquest software version 8.0 (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). Areas of all detected spots were normalized. Those protein spots with reproducible and statistically significant changes in abundance were considered to be differentially expressed. Only those spots with quantitative changes &#x0003e;1.5-fold in abundance, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;value &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, were considered for subsequent analyses.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Mass spectrometry and database search</title><p id="p0075">Protein spots were manually excised from the preparative gel, digested with trypsin, and analyzed using matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization-time of flight tandem mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS/MS) with a 4700 Proteomics Analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). The peptide mass fingerprint was analyzed with GPS (Applied Biosystems) MASCOT (Matrix Science, London, UK). The identified proteins were named according to the corresponding annotations in the National Center for Biotechnology (NCBI, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" id="intref0010">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) and/or Universal Protein Resource (Uniprot, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/" id="intref0015">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>). For proteins without functional annotation in the databases, homologs of these proteins were searched against the NCBI nonredundant protein database with BLASTP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" id="intref0020">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) to annotate these identities. The experimental molecular mass of each protein spot was estimated by comparison with molecular weight standards, whereas the experimental isoelectric point (p<italic>I</italic>) was determined by the migration of protein spots on linear IPG strips.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Bioinformatics analysis</title><p id="p0080">Functional annotation analysis was performed for up-regulated and down-regulated differentially expressed proteins using STRING (version 10.0) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://string-db.org/" id="interref0010">http://string-db.org/</ext-link>). The associated Gene Ontology (GO) terms (i.e., molecular function, biological process, and cell component) were annotated based on the database. Additionally, to further investigate the signaling pathways of the identified proteins, protein&#x02013;protein interactions analyzed by available experimental evidence, and statistical enrichment tests were carried out for Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway annotations.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Validation by Western blotting</title><p id="p0085">Six differentially expressed proteins (VATA, GPDA, HSP70, 1433Z, ALF, and UCHL1) were randomly selected for further verification using Western blotting. Total protein from both wild type and RGE-treated flies were extracted using lysis buffer and concentrations determined (as described above). Equal amounts of proteins (40&#x02013;50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g) were resolved on 12% polyacrylamide&#x02013;SDS gels and transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride membranes (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA) using standard methods blocked with 5% (w/v) nonfat dry milk (NFDM; BD Biosciences, San Diego, CA, USA) freshly made in TBS-T [Tween-Tris buffered saline: 0.1% Tween-20 in 100mM Tris&#x02013;HCL (pH 7.5), 0.9% NaCl], rock on a rotating shaker for 2&#x000a0;h at room temperature or overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. The membranes were probed with specific primary antibodies (dilution 1:1,000 in TBS-T/1% NFDM) for 2&#x000a0;h at room temperature or overnight at 4&#x000b0;C, washed three times of 15&#x000a0;min each with TBS-T, and then incubated for an additional 1.5&#x000a0;h with horseradish-peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibodies (dilution 1:2000 in TBS-T/1% NFDM) at 37&#x000b0;C. The levels of selected proteins were visualized using an ECL system (GE Healthcare, Waukesha, WI, USA). The Western blots were performed in triplicate, and the target protein bands were quantified by scanning densitometry using Image J (version 1.50) (National Institutes of Health, MD, USA) processing software and normalized to the signal intensity of GAPDH.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0090">Values in the figures are expressed as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation. Statistical analysis was carried out with three replicates for proteomic and biochemical analyses. The results of the spot intensities and physiological data were analyzed using Student <italic>t</italic> test to determine the significant difference between group means. A <italic>p</italic> value &#x0003c;0.05 was considered statistically significant (SPSS for Windows, version 12.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Effects of life span extension and antioxidant index induced by RGE in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic></title><p id="p0095">In this study, 200 males (20 flies per cage) of wild type and RGE-treated flies were used for longevity screening. RGE extended <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> life span and generated significantly lower mortality in older population groups (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>A). All wild type flies had died by Day 84, whereas the RGE-treated flies survived until Day 94 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>A). RGE-treated flies showed significantly higher mean and maximum longevities compared with wild type flies (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01). In comparison to the wild type, RGE-treated flies had a 12.60% and 11.90% increase in mean and maximum life span, respectively.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Effects on life span, superoxide dismutase (SOD) level and methane dicarboxylic aldehyde (MDA) content in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> treated with or without red ginseng extract (RGE). (A) Life span curves of male flies feed with RGE. Wild type (circles): mean survival life span, 71.67&#x000a0;d; maximum life span, 79.8&#x000a0;d; RGE-treated (squares): mean survival life span, 80.7&#x000a0;d; maximum life span 93.8&#x000a0;d. In comparison to the wild type, RGE-treated flies had a 12.60% and 11.90% increase in mean and maximum life span, respectively. Life span curve was constructed with Prism 5 software and statistical significance was determined with log-rank test. Bar graphs of average level of SOD and average content of MDA were repeated three times and analyzed by Student <italic>t</italic> test. (B) Average level of SOD. (C) Average content of MDA. Data in this figure are shown as mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation. Statistical significance: **<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01 (RGE-treated vs. wild type).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig.&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0100">In addition, the SOD level and the MDA content were highly significantly changed by RGE treatment. Total SOD enzyme activity (U/mg protein) was significantly increased in RGE-treated flies (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) compared to the wild type (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>B), whereas the MDA content (nmol/mg protein) was significantly lower in RGE-treated flies (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) compared to wild type flies (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>C).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Proteomic analysis of wild type and RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic></title><p id="p0105">A 2-DE-based comparative proteomics analysis was performed to investigate the possible target-related proteins of RGE in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>. Extracted proteins were separated by using SDS polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS&#x02013;PAGE) to detect the quality of protein extraction (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>A). The proteins were further separated by using 2-DE and silver stained to evaluate their relative abundance levels by analyzing all protein spots from three independent replicates using an imaging software (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>B and C). Among the 65 differentially abundant protein spots on the 2-DE gels, 38 spots were successfully identified by using MALDI-TOF MS/MS (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table&#x000a0;S2</xref>). Based on the information found in the NCBI, Uniprot, and GO protein databases, 23 (16 up-regulated and 7 down-regulated) differentially accumulated protein spots were identified as related to RGE treatment (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>D; <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Proteome maps (two-dimensional polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis images; representative of six gels) of wild type and red ginseng extract (RGE)-treated <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>. (A) Coomassie Brilliant Blue-stained gels of protein extracts from wild type (left) and RGE-treated (right) flies. Proteins (40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g in total) were separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) to detect the quality of extracted protein. Silver stained gels (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3) of extracted protein: (B) Wild type flies. (C) RGE-treated flies. Proteins (1.2&#x000a0;mg) were resolved in 17&#x000a0;cm linear, immobilized pH (3&#x02013;10) gradient gels and then separated by 12.5% SDS&#x02013;PAGE. All spots were matched and normalized by gel-to-gel comparison using the PDquest software version 8.0 (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA), and only those spots with reproducible changes (quantitative changes&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;1.5-fold in abundance, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) were considered for subsequent analyses. (D) Spot numbers indicated on the master gel are differentially expressed proteins related to RGE treatment that were subjected to matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization-time of flight/time of flight mass spectrometry. IEF, isoelectrofocusing.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig.&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Protein identifications of differentially expressed proteins using MALDI-TOF MS/MS</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Entry</th><th>Accession no.</th><th>Protein name</th><th>Score</th><th>Mass ku/p<italic>I</italic></th><th>Molecular function</th><th>Change</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:Q9VN95" id="intref0030">Q9VN95</ext-link></td><td>Enolase-phosphatase E1 (ENOPH)</td><td>159</td><td>54.6/8.68</td><td>Acireductone synthase activity</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P29310" id="intref0035">P29310</ext-link></td><td>14-3-3 protein zeta (1433Z)</td><td>100</td><td>28.3/4.77</td><td>Protein heterodimerization activity</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P07764" id="intref0040">P07764</ext-link></td><td>Fructose-bisphosphate aldolase (ALF)</td><td>245</td><td>45.8/7.08</td><td>Fructose-bisphosphate aldolase activity</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P35122" id="intref0045">P35122</ext-link></td><td>Ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal hydrolase (Uch; also named UCHL1)</td><td>80</td><td>100.0/9.37</td><td>Thiol-dependent ubiquitin-specific protease activity</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P13395" id="intref0050">P13395</ext-link></td><td>Spectrin alpha chain (SPTCA)</td><td>85</td><td>481.2/6.02</td><td>Actin binding</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P84029" id="intref0055">P84029</ext-link></td><td>Cytochrome c-2 (CYC2)</td><td>715</td><td>45.6/9.47</td><td>Electron carrier activity</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P83967" id="intref0060">P83967</ext-link></td><td>Actin, indirect flight muscle (ACT6)</td><td>628</td><td>42.1/5.29</td><td>Structural constituent of cytoskeleton</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P02574" id="intref0065">P02574</ext-link></td><td>Actin, larval muscle (ACT4)</td><td>580</td><td>42.2/5.3</td><td>Structural constituent of cytoskeleton</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P48610" id="intref0070">P48610</ext-link></td><td>Arginine kinase (KARG)</td><td>122</td><td>40.1/6.04</td><td>Arginine kinase activity</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P48611" id="intref0075">P48611</ext-link></td><td>6-Pyruvoyl tetrahydrobiopterin synthase (PTPS)</td><td>81</td><td>20.1/6.07</td><td>6-Pyruvoyltetrahydropterin synthase activity</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P29844" id="intref0080">P29844</ext-link></td><td>Heat shock 70&#x000a0;kDa protein (HSP70)</td><td>586</td><td>72.3/5.22</td><td>ATP binding</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:Q27331" id="intref0085">Q27331</ext-link></td><td>V-type proton ATPase catalytic subunit A (VATA)</td><td>464</td><td>68.5/5.23</td><td>Proton-transporting ATPase activity</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:Q94511" id="intref0090">Q94511</ext-link></td><td>NADH-ubiquinone oxidoreductase 75&#x000a0;kDa subunit, mitochondrial (NDUS1)</td><td>135</td><td>79.5/6.43</td><td>Metal ion binding</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P53501" id="intref0095">P53501</ext-link></td><td>Actin-57B (ACT3)</td><td>128</td><td>42.2/5.23</td><td>Structural constituent of cytoskeleton</td><td>Increase</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P13706" id="intref0100">P13706</ext-link></td><td>Glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase [NAD(+)], cytoplasmic (GPDA)</td><td>396</td><td>39.2/6.17</td><td>NAD binding</td><td>Decrease</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:Q9VWH4" id="intref0105">Q9VWH4</ext-link></td><td>Probable isocitrate dehydrogenase [NAD] subunit alpha, mitochondrial (IDH3A)</td><td>202</td><td>38.9/6.96</td><td>Isocitrate dehydrogenase (NAD+) activity</td><td>Decrease</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:Q9W0T1" id="intref0110">Q9W0T1</ext-link></td><td>Nucleosome-remodeling factor subunit NURF301 (NU301) gene E(bx)</td><td>291</td><td>32.7/5.58</td><td>Ligand-dependent nuclear receptor binding</td><td>Decrease</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P10981" id="intref0115">P10981</ext-link></td><td>Actin-87E (ACT5)</td><td>163</td><td>38.2/5.36</td><td>ATP binding</td><td>Decrease</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P00334" id="intref0120">P00334</ext-link></td><td>Alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH)</td><td>187</td><td>57.3/6.37</td><td>Protein homodimerization activity</td><td>Decrease</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:Q9VPH2" id="intref0125">Q9VPH2</ext-link></td><td>DNA primase large subunit (PRI2)</td><td>78</td><td>65.5/6.38</td><td>DNA primase activity</td><td>Decrease</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:Q9V3R1" id="intref0130">Q9V3R1</ext-link></td><td>Accessory gland protein Acp36DE (A36DE)</td><td>676</td><td>84.5/9.18</td><td>Hormone activity</td><td>Decrease</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P08171" id="intref0135">P08171</ext-link></td><td>Esterase-6 (EST6)</td><td>88</td><td>61.9/5.78</td><td>Carboxylic ester hydrolase activity</td><td>Decrease</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:Q9VA73" id="intref0140">Q9VA73</ext-link></td><td>Calcium binding protein 1 (CABP1)</td><td>217</td><td>21.5/4.71</td><td>Calcium ion binding</td><td>Decrease</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0015"><p>Mass ku (kDa)/p<italic>I</italic>, molecular mass and isoelectric point; score corresponding with two-dimensional gel electrophoresis gel as shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref> or calculated by mass spectrum identification or PDquest software. In the table, increase means up-regulation in RGE-treated, compared to the wild type; decrease means down-regulation in RGE-treated, compared to the wild type</p></fn><fn id="tspara0020"><p>RGE, red ginseng extract; MALDI-TOF MS/MS, matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization-time of flight tandem mass spectrometry</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Functional classification of the differentially expressed proteins</title><p id="p0110">To investigate the function roles of RGE in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>, the altered proteins were subjected to GO-based enrichment analysis using STRING version 10.0 (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table&#x000a0;S3</xref>). The most significantly enriched terms in each GO category were included for &#x0201c;biological process,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;cell component,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;molecular function&#x0201d; (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). The biological process category showed that most proteins were associated with small molecule metabolic process (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.56&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>), nucleotide metabolic process (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.69&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>), and cytoskeleton organization (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.98&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>). In addition, most of the differentially expressed metabolic related-proteins (such as CYC2, 1433Z, GPDH, VATA, and ND75) were found to be up-regulated in RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>. The &#x0201c;cell component&#x0201d; annotation revealed a major spectrum of organelle part (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.53&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>), actin filament (5.14&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>), and cytoskeletal part (2.21&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>). Proteins that participated in the &#x0201c;molecular function&#x0201d; were related to the structural constituent of cytoskeleton (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.72&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>), oxidoreductase activity (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.51&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>), and catalytic activity (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.25&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>). Most proteins enriched within these GO terms were up-regulated in the RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> compared to the wild type.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Gene Ontology (GO) term annotation analysis of the proteins altered by red ginseng extract. The differentially expressed proteins are categorized into molecular function, biological process, and cell component by using GO annotation software (STRING version 10.0). ATP, adenosine triphosphate; NAD, nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig.&#x000a0;4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Enrichment of pathways in which the differentially expressed proteins participated</title><p id="p0115">Nine KEGG pathways (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) were enriched from the dataset using STRING software (version 10.0) (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>). The most significant pathways for the differentially expressed proteins were metabolic pathways (10 proteins, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.11&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>) and hippo signaling pathway (3 proteins, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.36&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>), which are involved in potentiation of the antiaging process in flies. As to the &#x0201c;metabolic&#x0201d; pathways, six of 10 enriched proteins (ALF, CYC2, PTPS, VATA, ND75, and ENPD) were found to be up-regulated in RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>, whereas EST6, IDH3A, PRI2, and ADH were down-regulated. Regarding the &#x0201c;hippo&#x0201d; signaling pathway, most of the enriched proteins (1433Z and ACT6) were up-regulated in RGE-treated flies.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Distribution of KEGG (Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes) pathways in which the differentially expressed proteins participate. KEGG pathways are arranged in ascending order according to the <italic>p</italic> values. Dash line represents <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.01 or <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig.&#x000a0;5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Validation of the selected differentially expressed proteins</title><p id="p0120">Expression levels of VATA, GPDA, HSP70, 1433Z, UCHL1, and ALF were confirmed using Western blotting (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;6</xref>). Expression levels of VATA, HSP70, 1433Z, UCHL1, and ALF were significantly up-regulated in RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> versus wild type. Although GPDA expression appeared to be lower in RGE-treated flies, this was not significant. These results of Western blotting are consistent with those of the 2-DE MALDI-TOF MS/MS analysis.<fig id="fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Relative expression levels of VATA, GPDA, HSP70, 1433Z, UCHL1, and ALF by Western blot analysis. (A) Western blotting in this study was performed in triplicate and the target protein bands were quantified by scanning densitometry using Image J processing software and normalized to the signal intensity of glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH). (B) The data are expressed as mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation and analyzed using Student <italic>t</italic> test. Statistical significance: *<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; **<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01 (RGE-treated vs. wild type). 1433Z, 14-3-3 zeta; ALF, fructose-bisphosphate aldolase; GPDA, glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; HSP70, heat shock 70&#x000a0;kDa protein; UCHL1, ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal hydrolase; VATA, V-type proton ATPase catalytic subunit A.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Fig.&#x000a0;6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0125">Proteomic technology has become an indispensable and efficient tool in modern bioscience research, and this technology has been successfully used to study the mechanisms of traditional medicines by comparing the protein expression profiles. To our knowledge, this study is the first proteomic analysis for revealing the mechanisms of life span extension and antiaging on <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> treated with RGE.</p><p id="p0130">In this study, <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> treated with RGE (1&#x000a0;mg/mL) extended the life span significantly compared to the wild type (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01). Further results demonstrated that the effects of life span extension of RGE on <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> might be attributed to elevation of SOD levels, reduction in lipid peroxidation of MDA content, and a range of differently expressed proteins. Proteomic analysis detected 23 differentially expressed proteins in the RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> versus wild type: 16 up-regulated and 7 down-regulated. These&#x000a0;proteins were found to involved in multiple biological processes and signaling pathways, such as hippo and oxidative&#x000a0;phosphorylation signaling. Taken together, the results provided&#x000a0;a scientific basis for the further exploitation of mechanisms of longer life span and/or antiaging altered by RGE in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>.</p><p id="p0135">Age-associated neurodegenerative disorders including Alzheimer's disease (AD) and Parkinson's disease (PD) are associated with multifactorial etiology <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. In this study, UCHL1, a ubiquitin ligase exclusively expressed in neurons, is up-regulated in RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> versus wild type. UCHL1 was shown to be involved in the pathophysiology of PD and AD <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> and is elevated in AD patients <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, AD mice <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, and senescent C57BL/6J mouse pituitaries <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> compared to controls. However, UCHL1 overexpression has been shown to delay AD progression <italic>in&#x000a0;vivo</italic>
<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, and low levels have also been reported in <italic>postmortem</italic> brain tissue from AD patients <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. The increased expression level of UCHL1 protein by RGE treatment suggested that it may play important roles in antiaging and life span extension, and potentially neurodegenerative disorders. HSP70, which also showed increased expression in RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>, plays important protective roles in various neurodegenerative disorders <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. HSP70 is up-regulated in AD model mice compared to normal mice <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Further studies are required to explore these mechanisms during the process of neurodegeneration, and RGE may offer new avenues for novel therapeutic approaches for the treatment of chronic neurodegenerative disorders that currently have no effective medication.</p><p id="p0140">Oxidation impairs protein function as the proteins are unfolded leading to an increase in protein hydrophobicity. This often leads to the formation of toxic aggregates that interfere with normal cellular functions, which is a sign of the aging process and many age-related diseases. In this study, changes in the expression levels of HSP70 and UCHL1 (both up-regulated in RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>) could be a response to general age-derived cellular alterations, such as increasing oxidative burden, accumulation of damaged proteins, and elevated protein synthesis. At the molecular level, to ensure survival, cells have developed antioxidants to counteract this oxidative damage accumulation <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. It is wildly believed that HSP70 and UCHL1, which are responsible for the removal of damaged proteins, counteract the oxidative stress damage of proteins <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. HSP70 has also been shown to confer protection against the harmful effects of oxidative stress, as well as modulate the inflammatory status <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Furthermore, the overexpression of HSP70 in mice muscle eliminated the age-related increase in posttranslational modifications of proteins <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>.</p><p id="p0145">Ginseng can increase long-term resistance to stress and disease and therefore affects life span <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Our study demonstrated an elevation of SOD and a reduction in lipid peroxidation of MDA content in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> treated with RGE. In addition, three antioxidant-related proteins&#x02014;HSP70, UCHL1, and ALF <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>&#x02014;in 2-DE results were identified by Western blotting and elevated in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> induced by RGE. Previous studies reported that Korean Red Ginseng ameliorated oxidative tissue injury, provided an antiaging effect, and suppressed age-related renal injury <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. In addition, ginsenoside Rg1 improved cognitive ability and promoted neurogenesis by enhancing the antioxidant and anti-inflammatory capacity in the hippocampus <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Therefore, the higher expression of the antioxidants HSP70 and UCHL1 in RGE-treated flies may facilitate slower aging progression and prolong life span.</p><p id="p0150">HSP70 is an important molecular chaperone, which plays a key role in cell protection by assisting with protein homeostasis or protein quality control <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In addition, aging has been related to impairment in activity and availability of HSP70 induction. Previous reports revealed that exogenous HSP70 protein can significantly enhance mouse life span <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> and stimulate the growth of aged mesenchymal stem cells <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic>
<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Ginseng treatment increased expression of HSP70 in rats, which showed protected functions of neurological responses and memory ability <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. In the present study, we found an increased level of HSP70 in RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>, suggesting a protective role in aging and life span extension. Therefore, RGE might be considered a potential source to identify compounds that delay aging.</p><p id="p0155">The hippo pathway is a signaling cascade that plays an evolutionarily conserved role in organ size control from Drosophila to humans by regulating cell proliferation, apoptosis, stem cell/progenitor cell fate determination, self-renewal control, and tissue architecture and renewal <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Mutations of these genes lead to a common phenotype of tissue overgrowth and enlarged organ size in Drosophila eyes and wings <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Hippo pathway components also mediated crosstalk with other pathways, for example, Wnt, TGF, and BMP pathways <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. In the present study, the differentially expressed proteins, 1433Z and ACT6, of the hippo pathway were up-regulated in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> treated by RGE versus wild type. This may indicate a role in maintaining cellular health and tissue turnover, induced by RGE treatment.</p><p id="p0160">V-type ATPase (VATA), an up-regulated protein in RGE-treated <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic>, is categorized as a rotary ATP synthase/ATPase complex <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. ATP synthase is a key enzyme of mitochondrial energy conversion, and inhibition of ATP synthase may cause energy deprivation and increased reactive oxygen species production. A high reactive oxygen species content induces cellular necrosis and/or apoptosis <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Because the oxidative phosphorylation pathway is induced (via both VATA and ND75 up-regulation) by RGE treatment, this may provide the energy for the antiaging process and life span extension.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0165">This is the first comprehensive study of <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> treated with RGE using a 2-DE-based quantitative proteomic approach. In this study, we found that RGE had longevity-enhancing effects on <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic> by altering the expression of antioxidants and regulating by multiple pathways. Further studies are warranted to explore the novel molecular mechanisms underlying the antiaging effects and life span extension by treatment with red ginseng.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p id="p0170">The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghimire</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Jujube (<italic>Ziziphus Jujuba</italic> Mill.) fruit feeding extends lifespan and increases tolerance to environmental stresses by regulating aging-associated gene expression in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Biogerontology</source><volume>18</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28251407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahangarpour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamoochi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathi Moghaddam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic>Portulaca oleracea</italic> ethanolic extract on reproductive system of aging female mice</article-title><source>Int J Reprod Biomed (Yazd)</source><volume>14</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27294220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peleg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forne</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e9;vin</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Regnard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Straub</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prestel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klima</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life span extension by targeting a link between metabolism and histone acetylation in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><volume>17</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26781291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghimire</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defensive behavior against noxious heat stimuli is declined with aging due to decreased pain-associated gene expression in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Biomol Ther (Seoul)</source><volume>23</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25995829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>W.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farooqui</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farooqui</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effects of ginseng on neurological disorders</article-title><source>Front Aging Neurosci</source><volume>7</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26236231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>G.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Y.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heat processing decreases Amadori products and increases total phenolic content and antioxidant activity of Korean Red Ginseng</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Med Food</source><volume>13</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1478</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Administration of red ginseng ameliorates memory decline in aged mice</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Ginseng Res</source><volume>39</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26199557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Korean Red Ginseng tonic extends lifespan in <italic>D.&#x000a0;melanogaster</italic></article-title><source>Biomol Ther (Seoul)</source><volume>21</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24265871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;high-fat diet increases oxidative renal injury and protein glycation in <sc>d</sc>-galactose-induced aging rats and its prevention by Korea red ginseng</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Nutr Sci Vitaminol (Tokyo)</source><volume>60</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25078371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of red ginseng extract on UVB irradiation-induced skin aging in hairless mice</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>123</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19501277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast determination of ginsenosides in ginseng by high-performance liquid chromatography with chemometric resolution</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Sep Sci</source><volume>37</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>2126</fpage><lpage>2130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24854551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protection effect of kallistatin on carbon tetrachloride-induced liver fibrosis in rats via antioxidative stress</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>e88498</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24558397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ba</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>iTRAQ-based quantitative proteomic analysis of the potentiated and dormant antler stem cells</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><volume>17</volume><year>2016</year><comment>pii: E1778</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erd&#x00151;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Denes</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lange</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-associated physiological and pathological changes at the blood&#x02013;brain barrier: a review</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source><year>2016</year><comment>pii: 0271678X16679420</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plenzig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gispert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Korf</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Gall</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disturbed sleep/wake rhythms and neuronal cell loss in lateral hypothalamus and retina of mice with a spontaneous deletion in the ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal hydrolase L1 gene</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><volume>33</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20363052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;hrfelt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreasson</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zetterberg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blennow</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased cerebrospinal fluid levels of ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal hydrolase L1 in patients with Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Dement Geriatr Cogn Dis Extra</source><volume>6</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27504117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sattlecker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiddle</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alzheimer's disease: are blood and brain markers related? A systematic review</article-title><source>Ann Clin Transl Neurol</source><volume>3</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27547773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marzban</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grillari</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reisinger</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemetsberger</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katinger</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related alterations in the protein expression profile of C57BL/6J mouse pituitaries</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><volume>37</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal hydrolase L1 (UCHL1) delays Alzheimer's progression in&#x000a0;vivo</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>7298</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25466238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levey</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gearing</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative modifications and down-regulation of ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal hydrolase L1 associated with idiopathic Parkinson's and Alzheimer's diseases</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>13256</fpage><lpage>13264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14722078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>P.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of heat shock protein 70 in the protective effect of YC-1 on &#x003b2;-amyloid-induced toxicity in differentiated PC12 cells</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>e69320</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23922702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis of protein expression throughout disease progression in a mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Alzheimers Dis</source><volume>47</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>915</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26401771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez de Toda</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>De la Fuente</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of Hsp70 in oxi-inflamm-aging and its use as a potential biomarker of lifespan</article-title><source>Biogerontology</source><volume>16</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>721</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26386684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Domenico</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coccia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cocciolo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cenini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Head</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butterfield</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schinina</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancuso</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impairment of proteostasis network in Down syndrome prior to the development of Alzheimer's disease neuropathology: redox proteomics analysis of human brain</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1832</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1249</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23603808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broome</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kayani</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomero</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillmann</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mestril</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mc Ardle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of lifelong overexpression of HSP70 in skeletal muscle on age-related oxidative stress and adaptation after nondamaging contractile activity</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><volume>20</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1549</fpage><lpage>1551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16723383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bittles</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulder</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of ginseng on lifespan and stress responses in mice</article-title><source>Gerontology</source><volume>25</volume><year>1979</year><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">571386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goren</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reznick</surname><given-names>A.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isoelectric properties of nematode aldolase and rat liver superoxide dismutase from young and old animals</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>84</volume><year>1977</year><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">590530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of Cu/Zn SOD protein is suppressed in hsp 70.1 knockout mice</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Biochem Mol Biol</source><volume>38</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15715955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coulombe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamage</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woulfe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saffrey</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of UCHL1 promotes age-related degenerative changes in the enteric nervous system</article-title><source>Front Aging Neurosci</source><volume>6</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24994982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ginsenoside Rg1 prevents cognitive impairment and hippocampus senescence in a rat model of <sc>d</sc>-galactose-induced aging</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>e101291</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24979747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ing</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelsang</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heat shock protein 70 gene expression in equine blastocysts after exposure of oocytes to high temperatures in&#x000a0;vitro or in&#x000a0;vivo after exercise of donor mares</article-title><source>Theriogenology</source><volume>74</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>374</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20416934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reeg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henze</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grune</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular chaperone Hsp70 promotes the proteolytic removal of oxidatively damaged proteins by the proteasome</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><volume>99</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27498116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobkova</surname><given-names>N.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evgen'ev</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garbuz</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulikov</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morozov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samokhin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Velmeshev</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medvinskaya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesterova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exogenous Hsp70 delays senescence and improves cognitive function in aging mice</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>112</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>16006</fpage><lpage>16011</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26668376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>N.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatsepina</surname><given-names>O.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garbuz</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evgen'ev</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belyavsky</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recombinant HSP70 and mild heat shock stimulate growth of aged mesenchymal stem cells</article-title><source>Cell Stress Chaperones</source><volume>21</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27091568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>San</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Panax ginseng</italic> ginsenoside-Rg2 protects memory impairment via anti-apoptosis in a rat model with vascular dementia</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>115</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18083315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pesce</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chimenti</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltrami</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiac mechano-perception: a life-long story from early beats to aging and failure</article-title><source>Stem Cells Dev</source><volume>26</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27736363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>K.-L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hippo pathway in organ size control, tissue homeostasis, and cancer</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>163</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26544935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halder</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of the Hippo pathway by cell architecture and mechanical signals</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><volume>23</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22750148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Hippo pathway in heart development, regeneration, and diseases</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><volume>116</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1431</fpage><lpage>1447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25858067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lnc RNA mediated regulation of aging pathways in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> during dietary restriction</article-title><source>Aging (Albany NY)</source><volume>8</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>2182</fpage><lpage>2203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27687893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forgac</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vacuolar ATPases: rotary protonpumps in physiology and pathophysiology</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>8</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>929</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Numoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inter-subunit interaction and quaternary rearrangement defined by the central stalk of prokaryotic V1-ATPase</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><volume>10</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1228</fpage><lpage>1234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19779483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skorokhod</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davalos-Schafler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulliers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Notarpietro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandili</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Novelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Persico</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taglialatela-Scafati</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress-mediated antimalarial activity of plakortin, a natural endoperoxide from the tropical sponge Plakortis simplex</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><volume>89</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>624</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26459031</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0180">The following are the supplementary data related to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec1"><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1">Project of the National Science Foundation for Youths of China</funding-source> (No. 31401606), <funding-source id="gs2">Jilin Science &#x00026; Technology Development Plan</funding-source> (20140101125JC and 201627), the special fund for <funding-source id="gs3">agro-scientific research in the public interest</funding-source> (201303111), and <funding-source id="gs4">the International Science &#x00026; Technology Cooperation Program of China</funding-source> (2015DFA31290). The authors also thank Dr. Eric Arthur Lord (University of Otago) and Dr. Yali Li for kindly reading and revising through the manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0185">Supplementary data related to this article can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.jgr.2017.04.006" id="intref0025">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jgr.2017.04.006</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>