<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Rats (<italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>) and mice (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>) were the first vertebrates found to each have two insulin proteins, which were subsequently found to be encoded by a pair of genes (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). While the insulin 2 genes (<italic>Ins2</italic>) have a gene structure similar to that of the human gene (three exons and two introns), the insulin 1 gene (<italic>Ins1</italic>) was found to be composed of only 2 exons, with all of the coding sequence contained in the second exon (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). These two genes have a relatively recent origin (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figure 1B</bold>
</xref>), in the common ancestor of mice and rats (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Further study of these genes indicated that the <italic>Ins1</italic> gene originated from an aberrant mRNA transcript that was initiated about 500 bases upstream of the normal mRNA start site and partially processed to remove only intron 2 sequences before being reverse transcribed and inserted into the genome (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Despite the differences in the structures of these two genes, both are equally expressed (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Since the mouse and rat <italic>Ins1</italic> genes only have ~500 bases of 5&#8217; flanking sequence homologous to the <italic>Ins</italic> genes of other mammals, this indicates that only a limited amount of sequence is needed for efficient beta-cell-specific expression of the insulin gene. But why do mice and rats have two insulin genes that have identical expression patterns, while other species can survive with a single gene? This might suggest that the two genes differ in function, perhaps specializing function at different sites or times, thus generating a need to retain both genes. While some evidence for differences in the selective constraints acting on the two insulin genes has been detected (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), no evidence for different functions have been found, thus a convincing explanation has not been reached. Intriguingly, duplicated insulin genes that originated by retroposition, like the rodent <italic>Ins1</italic> gene, have also been described in several species of bony fish through three independent origins (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). While most of the retroposed insulin-like sequences in fish appeared to be pseudogenes, the gene sequence of a potentially retroprocessed insulin gene in the Northern pike (<italic>Esox lucius</italic>) has an intact coding sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figure 1C</bold>
</xref>) that is potentially functional (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Further study is needed to determine whether this retroposed Northern pike insulin gene is expressed and if its encoded protein has a physiological function. These observations also indicate that the vertebrate insulin gene is expressed in the germ cells of a number of species, thus allowing it to be retroprocessed and integrated into the genome allowing to be passed on to the next generation, raising questions about the possible function of insulin in germ line cells.</p>