<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Duplicated copies of the insulin gene have also been found in several other vertebrate species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figures 1C, D</bold>
</xref>), where these genes retain the three exon and two intron gene structure and potentially have large amounts of flanking sequences that would allow their continued expression. The frog <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic>, which experienced a recent genome duplication (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figure 1D</bold>
</xref>), was the first published example (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Unlike the duplicated rodent insulin genes, the two <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> insulin genes were found to display differing developmental gene expression patterns that might suggest diverging functions (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), and a reason why both are retained, however they also had overlapping gene expression in the adult pancreas (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). A genome duplication, the fish-specific whole genome duplication (3R), was experienced by an ancestor of teleost fish (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), thus the discovery of a second insulin gene in several fish genome sequences (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) was not a surprise. Characterization of the two zebrafish (<italic>Danio rerio</italic>) insulin genes (<italic>insa</italic> and <italic>insb</italic>) provided evidence that the two genes had distinct expression patterns and potentially differing functions (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), supporting a hypothesis that fish genes have diverged in function, potentially subfunctionalizing so that each now is responsible for a subset of the ancestral functions of insulin. More recently, a third insulin gene (<italic>insc</italic>) has been found in some, but not all, fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figure 1C</bold>
</xref>), with all three of these genes originating in an early teleost, thus it is unclear which, if any, originated through the fish-specific whole genome duplication (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). The role of this third insulin gene in fish physiology is unknown. Does it also possess a subset of ancestral insulin functions, or has it gained new function? In addition to these three types of insulin genes found in fish, additional lineage-specific duplications of insulin genes were found, including some species [e.g., carp (<italic>Cyprinus carpio</italic>)] that are associated with additional genome duplications on these lineages (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). In addition to these lineage-specific duplications due to genome duplications, a duplication of the <italic>insa</italic> insulin gene, resulting in the <italic>insaa</italic> and <italic>insab</italic> genes, occurred early in the diversification of teleost fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">
<bold>Figure 1C</bold>
</xref>) yielding a large number of species with these gene duplicate. Intriguingly, most of the proteins encoded by the <italic>insab</italic> genes have amino acid substitutions that are predicted to impair proteolytically processing that generates the typical two-chain insulin hormone (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). While these sequences retain signal peptides, which would allow secretion, and cysteine residues that allow disulphide bridge formation, this raises the possibility that they yield an unprocessed inulin-like protein that retains an insulin-like protein structure and has an unknown function (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p>