<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f055">Figure 55</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f056">Figure 56</xref>, it also becomes obvious that in several cases, a substantial amount of enthalpy change caused by quench-induced precipitates is detected. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f055">Figure 55</xref> includes experimental findings from DFSC obtained on 7049A in a range of cooling rates up to some hundreds of K/s [
 <xref rid="B130-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B162-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. As outlined in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot1dot3-materials-12-04083">Section 3.1.3</xref>, DFSC allows us to obtain the specific precipitation enthalpies of highly concentrated alloys via a differential reheating measurement [
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B162-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. This is demonstrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f057">Figure 57</xref>A, which shows raw DFSC data for the first reheating (after relatively “slow” cooling with 10 K/s) and a second reheating after overcritical fast cooling (100,000 K/s, baseline). During the first reheating at 1000 K/s, endothermic dissolution reactions of phases precipitated during the preceding “slow” cooling are clearly seen. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f057">Figure 57</xref>B shows DFSC data for cooling rates of up to 500 K/s. Normalisation by sample mass and scanning rate and subsequent integration of the curves, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f057">Figure 57</xref>B, allows us to obtain the specific precipitation enthalpies as a function of cooling rate [
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f058">Figure 58</xref>A shows precipitation enthalpies for six samples of 7150 [
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. In 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f058">Figure 58</xref>B, the averaged DFSC values from [
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>] and data from DSC [
 <xref rid="B133-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>] are plotted, and these fit together smoothly. The UCCR of 7150 was determined to be about 300 K/s for 7150 [
 <xref rid="B129-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. In 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f058">Figure 58</xref>, the solid lines for the specific precipitation enthalpy Δh and for the hardness after ageing are the model predictions from [
 <xref rid="B119-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. The model predictions were created without knowledge of the DFSC data, as the DFSC experiments had not yet been done. Very good agreement between the measured and predicted values is seen, and this further confirms the high accuracy of the derived model for quench-induced precipitation of AlZnMg(Cu) alloys.
</p>
