<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ten variants of the alloying system AlZnMg(Cu) are considered in this work. Due to the multiple potential combinations of alloying elements, the 7xxx alloying system can be considered a very complex system in terms of precipitation. It is often a quarternary system, as in addition to Al, Zn and Mg, Cu and other elements such as Si are often incorporated. Cu and Si may add additional precipitation sequences, for instance those of S-Al
 <sub>2</sub>CuMg and/or β-Mg
 <sub>2</sub>Si [
 <xref rid="B35-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B189-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>]. Moreover, the Zn- and Mg-containing phases do not have a fixed composition, and isostructure variants are known for the η-Mg(Zn,Al,Cu)
 <sub>2</sub> phase [
 <xref rid="B190-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>,
 <xref rid="B191-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>]. For most of the 10 AlZnMg(Cu) alloys analysed here, DSC indicates the presence of three or four different main reaction intervals during cooling. DSC cooling curves for 7020 (an AlZnMgSi alloy) and 7150 (an AlZnMgCu alloy) can be seen in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f048">Figure 48</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f049">Figure 49</xref>, respectively. Although these two alloys have substantially different alloy compositions, they both show at least three main reaction intervals, which are HTRs (typically ≈450–350 °C), medium-temperature-reactions (MTRs, ≈350–250 °C) and LTRs, (≈250–150 °C). This holds for the majority of the 10 AlZnMg(Cu) alloys investigated, as can be seen from 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f0A3">Figure A3</xref> in the 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-12-04083">Appendix A</xref>. In some cases, a fourth reaction was detected at an even lower temperature of about 150–50 °C, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f050">Figure 50</xref>. For the 7xxx alloys with highest concentration of alloying elements such as 7075, 7049A (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="materials-12-04083-f0A3">Figure A3</xref> in the 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-materials-12-04083">Appendix A</xref> and Refs. [
 <xref rid="B161-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>,
 <xref rid="B162-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]) and 7068 [
 <xref rid="B192-materials-12-04083" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>], cooling DSC appears to show only one very broad peak, which ranges from about 450 to 150 °C. It can be assumed that this very broad heat effect is caused by the sum of numerous reactions.
</p>
