<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <p>Many thanks to Dr. Roberto Sacco (Laboratory of Molecular Psychiatry and Neurogenetics, UCBM, Rome, Italy) for microarray statistical support and Dr. Roberta Pastorelli (Protein and Gene Biomarkers Unit, Department of Environmental Health Sciences, IRCCS-Istituto di Ricerche Farmacologiche “Mario Negri”, Milan, Italy) for protein array critical suggestions. The study was partially supported by the Fondazione Roma, the Italian Ministry of Health and the “National 5xMille 2010 tax donation to IRCCS-G.B. Bietti Foundation”. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. This work is dedicated to the memory of our colleague and friend Prof. Marco Centofanti (M.C.; IRCCS- G.B. Bietti and Tor Vergata University) who recently passed away.</p>
 <p>All named authors meet the International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) criteria for authorship for this manuscript, take responsibility for the integrity of the work as a whole, and have given final approval for the version to be published.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1">
  <title>Disclosures</title>
  <p>A. Micera, L. Quaranta, G. Esposito, I. Floriani, A. Pocobelli, S. C. Saccà, I. Riva, G. Manni, F. Oddone have nothing to disclose.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2">
  <title>Compliance with Ethics Guidelines</title>
  <p>All procedures followed were in accordance with the ethical standards of the responsible committee on human experimentation (institutional and national), with the Helsinki Declaration of 1964, as revised in 2013, and was reviewed/approved by the institutional Ethic Committee (IRCCS IFO—Fondazione Bietti). A written informed consent was signed by patients joining the study and undergoing surgical therapy.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="d30e1886">
  <title>Open Access</title>
  <p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.
  </p>
 </sec>
</ack>
