<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The main mechanisms that contribute to mRNA isoform diversity are alternative splicing and alternative polyadenylation (APA). Alternative splicing produces different combinations of coding sequences in mature mRNA and protein. APA occurs at genes that have more than one polyadenylation site (PAS) and can result in mRNAs with different coding sequences or variable 3' UTR lengths. Like alternative splicing, APA that occurs within the gene body can affect protein sequence and function. (
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Sandberg et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Tian and Manley, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Vasudevan et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2018</xref>). Unlike with alternative splicing, a PAS in a coding region will lead to a truncated isoform rather than a different combination of included exons. APA that occurs outside of the coding sequence, in the 3' UTRs, can lead to differential inclusion of protein-binding motifs that can affect translational efficiency, mRNA stability, and mRNA localization (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Mayr, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Tian and Manley, 2017</xref>). Yet, despite its potential to produce tremendous variation in mRNA and protein regulation, few studies have explored the contribution of APA to regulatory divergence between species. Indeed, our current understanding of APA conservation in mammals comes from few comparative studies of humans and rodents (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ara et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018a</xref>). However, these studies used sequence conservation rather than direct measurements of PAS usage to characterize APA (
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018a</xref>). Thus, it remains possible that many mammalian PAS are functionally divergent despite having similar sequences.
</p>
