<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">The mammalian transcriptome harbors a myriad of coding and non-coding RNA transcripts, with biogenesis, abundance and subcellular localization tightly regulated to match the physiology and function of the cell. Genome-wide technologies such as RNA sequencing have been instrumental in characterizing the transcriptome architecture. However, transcriptome analysis using RNA sequencing has primarily been performed on total or polyA + RNA from whole cells, overlooking the spatial dimension of gene expression at the subcellular level. Nevertheless, an increasing number of reports are pointing to the importance of investigating the subcellular repertoire of RNA molecules and understanding the mechanisms that govern their distribution inside the cell
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. Subcellular RNA localization is widespread and conserved from bacteria to mammals, and it is becoming evident that this process plays crucial roles in regulating gene expression
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. For mRNA, subcellular localization provides a means to spatially control protein production and target proteins to their site of function
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, the differential distribution of mature mRNA between the nucleus and the cytoplasm may have a direct impact on protein expression levels. In fact, it has been recently shown that nuclear retention of mature mRNA is a mechanism that involves a wide range of protein-coding transcripts. This nuclear retention is believed to ultimately fine-tune mRNA translation in the cytoplasm
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, identifying the subcellular localization of non-coding RNA such as long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) can provide substantial insights into their biology and function. Based on the link between localization, function, and regulation it is important to map the subcellular localization of coding and non-coding RNA in different cells and tissues to obtain a more comprehensive understanding of RNA’s biological functions.
</p>
