<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The biogeography of 
 <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> shows it is widely distributed all over the world. The RDP (Ribosomal Database Project) and GenBank databases contain 16S rRNA gene sequences of 54 
 <italic>Thalassolituus-</italic>like bacteria from microbial communities inhabiting both marine (Baltic, Barents, Mediterranean, North, Okhotsk and South China seas, and the Atlantic, Pacific, and Polar Oceans) and terrestrial environments (caves and ground waters) (
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">Yakimov et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Mou et al., 2008</xref>). Previous reports have shown that 
 <italic>Thalassolituus</italic>-related species were among the most dominant members of hydrocarbon/petroleum enriched consortia and can outcompete other OHCB such as 
 <italic>Alcanivorax</italic>, which is often the most dominant alkane degrader in marine oil spills (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Harayama et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Kostka et al., 2011</xref>). For example, 
 <italic>Thalassolituus</italic> outcompeted 
 <italic>Alcanivorax</italic> in 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>14</sub> enriched microcosms even though tetradecane was shown to be the preferred substrate of 
 <italic>Alcanivorax</italic> (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Yakimov et al., 2005</xref>). 
 <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> became abundant in crude oil-amended North Sea microcosms at both 4°C and 20°C and was in fact the most dominant bacterium at 20°C, with total extractable hydrocarbons 15% their original value, confirming the important role this species plays in crude oil degradation in seawater (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Coulon et al., 2007</xref>). 
 <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> has also been shown to be the most dominant alkane degrader in both single and mixed alkane seawater microcosms over a range of different length 
 <italic>n</italic>-alkanes from 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>12</sub> up to 
 <italic>n</italic>-C
 <sub>32</sub> (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">McKew et al., 2007b</xref>). Also, in contrast to previous studies, 
 <italic>Thalassolituus</italic>, rather than 
 <italic>Alcanivorax</italic>, was shown to be dominant in crude oil-amended microcosms, suggesting that they are less affected by potentially stressful compounds within crude oil (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Hara et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Brakstad and Lødeng, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Yakimov et al., 2005</xref>). 
 <italic>T. oleivorans</italic> was also one of the dominant species within bacterial communities in deep water samples taken near the oil plume from the Deepwater Horizon oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Camilli et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Hazen et al., 2010</xref>). 
 <italic>Thalassolituus</italic> spp. also dominated the microbial communities present in water samples collected from oil production wells in Canada (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Kryachko et al., 2012</xref>).
</p>
