<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Capsular polysaccharide plays an important role in the pathogenesis of mycoplasma. For example, 
 <italic>M. ovipneumoniae</italic> CPS exerts a cytotoxic effect and induces apoptosis of sheep airway epithelial cells through a ROS-dependent JNK/P38 MAPK mechanism [
 <xref rid="cit0108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]; meanwhile, it can activate the TLR4-MyD88-NF-кB and TLR4-TRIF-IRF3 pathways to trigger overexpression of pro- and anti-inflammatory cytokines, such as IL-10 and TGF-β [
 <xref rid="cit0106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. This anti-inflammatory cytokine-inducing activity is also observed in 
 <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> CPS and Mmm-derived free exopolysaccharide (EPS), which negatively regulates the immune system [
 <xref rid="cit0109" ref-type="bibr">109–111</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>M. pulmonis</italic> secretes EPS-I, which is composed of galactose and glucose (ratio 1:1) and can be recognized by the lectin Griffonia simplicifolia I [
 <xref rid="cit0105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Like Mmm-derived polysaccharides, EPS-I can also offset the effects of the complement system [
 <xref rid="cit0110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0112" ref-type="bibr">112–114</xref>]. Mutation of EPS-I results in decreased adherence to A549 and MLE-12 cells, an increased tendency for 
 <italic>M. pulmonis</italic> to form biofilms on glass surfaces, and effective colonization of mouse lungs and trachea by overexpression of EPS-II [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>], indicating that certain types of EPS may function in invasiveness. Moreover, certain capsules and polysaccharides are instrumental in facilitating the dissemination of mycoplasmas and in sustaining a chronic infection either by anti-phagocytosis or by downregulating the functions of macrophages [
 <xref rid="cit0110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0115" ref-type="bibr">115–117</xref>]. Galactan, the galactofuranose homopolymer, serves as CPS and EPS in Mmm strains [
 <xref rid="cit0117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Similarly, the galactofuranose of CPS components is also a virulence factor in 
 <italic>M. mycoides subsp. capri</italic> (Mmc) [
 <xref rid="cit0110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. Furthermore, the galactofuranose in Mmm and Mmc is essential for membrane integrity and concealing adhesins but does not contribute to serum resistance [
 <xref rid="cit0114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>].
</p>
