<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Simple Summary</title>
  <p>MiRNAs are small noncoding RNAs that regulate a variety of developmental and physiological processes, with many having well-defined developmental and cell-type specific expression patterns. Aspects of the cell cycle such as cell differentiation, proliferation and apoptosis can be regulated by miRNA, underscoring an unexplored link between arginine supply and mammary tissue function during lactation. The specific objective of the present study was to determine miRNA profiles in mammary tissue at the end of lactation in response to enhanced dietary supply of arginine. Our results indicate that arginine may potentially be involved in the development of rat mammary glands through miRNA.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>This study was designed to determine the effects of dietary arginine on development and proliferation in rat mammary tissue through changes in miRNA profiles. Twelve pregnant Wistar rats were allocated randomly to two groups. A basal diet containing arginine or the control diet containing glutamate on an equal nitrogen basis as the arginine supplemented diet were used. The experiment included a pre-experimental period of four days before parturition and an experimental period of 17 days after parturition. Mammary tissue was collected for histology, RNA extraction and high-throughput sequencing analysis. The greater mammary acinar area indicated that arginine supplementation enhanced mammary tissue development (
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). MicroRNA profiling indicated that seven miRNA (miR-206-3p, miR-133a-5p, miR-133b-3p, miR-1-3p, miR-133a-3p, miR-1b and miR-486) were differentially expressed in response to Arginine when compared with the glutamate-based control group. In silico gene ontology enrichment and KEGG pathway analysis revealed between 240 and 535 putative target genes among the miRNA. Further verification by qPCR revealed concordance with the differential expression from the sequencing results: 17 of 28 target genes were differentially expressed (15 were highly expressed in arginine and 2 in control) and 11 target genes did not have significant difference in expression. In conclusion, our study suggests that arginine may potentially regulate the development of rat mammary glands through regulating miRNAs.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
