<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In heterocyst-forming cyanobacteria, thylakoid membranes in vegetative cells contain photosystem I (PS-I) and PS-II, which use water as the electron donor and produce oxygen. Whether heterocysts have both PS-I and PS-II remains controversial [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Thylakoid membranes in vegetative cells have been suggested to contain PS-I and PS-II, whereas those in heterocysts predominantly contain PS-I [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The water-oxidizing activity of PS-II, as well as fluorescence emission at 685 nm associated with PS-II, has been reported to be absent in intact heterocysts from several filamentous strains [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The reaction center proteins of PS-II were suggested to be degraded during heterocyst differentiation, although PS-II proteins can still be found in mature heterocysts [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In our study, KEGG enrichment analysis showed that carbon fixation in the photosynthetic pathway (ko00710) was significantly enriched in the NV vs. NDV comparison, suggesting that nitrogen deprivation alters the photosynthetic capability of 
 <italic>Anabaena</italic> sp. strain PCC 7120 (
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). We also detected the expression of 13 and 19 genes encoding PS-I and PS-II proteins, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0248155.s005">S3 Table</xref>), including two DEGs encoding PS-I and five DEGs encoding PS-II. Comparison of NV vs. NDV suggested that nitrogen deprivation inhibited the expression of both genes encoding PS-I and PS-II, as shown by downregulation of 
 <italic>psaB</italic>/
 <italic>K</italic> in PS-I and 
 <italic>psbN</italic> in PS-II. Under nitrogen deprivation conditions, the expression of PS-I and PS-II genes was more active in heterocysts than in vegetative cells, shown by upregulation of 
 <italic>isiA</italic> (PS-II), 
 <italic>psbAII</italic> (PS-II), 
 <italic>psbAIII</italic> (PS-II), 
 <italic>psbAIV</italic> (PS-II), and 
 <italic>psbN</italic> (PS-II). Thus, both PS-I- and PS-II-related genes were expressed in heterocysts, which is not consistent with the results of a previous study reporting that heterocysts lack PS-II [
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0248155.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
