<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The functional differences we and others have observed between FLp53 protein and its splice variant, p53β, could conceivably result from at least two different general mechanisms: (1) differential transcriptional target gene expression, either resulting from: (a) differential binding of FLp53 vs. p53β to cis-regulatory sequences for regulating gene expression, (b) competition between FLp53 and p53β proteins for the same DNA regulatory sequences (with tetrameric FLp53 being the more potent transcriptional activator as p53β as a competitor could reduce transactivation by FLp53 by binding to the same sites), and/or (c) differential binding of FLp53 vs. p53β to transcriptional co-factors, regulating strength of transactivation or even whether transcriptional activation vs. transcriptional repression is induced; or (2) differential functions of FLp53 vs. p53β in regulating non-transcriptional events, such as differential interactions with cell-cycle or apoptosis-regulating proteins. Whether the functional differences between FLp53 and p53β are a result of differential DNA binding or differential protein–protein interactions, such functional differences could result from differential post-translational modifications of FLp53 vs. p53β, the lack of the C-terminal tail in p53β, or from distinct activities gained from the presence of the unique C terminal tail or its post-translational modifications. Data from our lab and others have shown that differential transcriptional target gene expression does occur [
 <xref rid="B8-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Global mapping of FLp53 and p53β binding sites compared to differential transcriptome regulation will begin to elucidate the differential regulation put forth by either protein. Finally, we presented evidence that differential cofactor binding does occur. In all, p53β promotes pro-senescent phenotypes, thus promoting differential molecular and biological outcomes compared with FL-p53.
</p>
