<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">As indicated by the high MCC
achieved (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jproteome.0c00717/suppl_file/pr0c00717_si_001.pdf">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>), structure-based binding energy assessment was more
accurate than sequence identity for distinguishing experimentally
confirmed species, provided that high-quality structure models were
used. Critically, the structure models are highly likely to be very
reliable given the high sequence similarity between hACE2 and the
ACE2 orthologs and the application of advanced structure modeling
tools.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref></sup> Moreover, we argued that it is critical
to model binding energy using structure ensembles rather than a single
model. We found that the binding scores that were calculated for different
models of the same ACE2/S-RBD complex fluctuated considerably (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jproteome.0c00717/suppl_file/pr0c00717_si_001.pdf">Supplementary Figure S4</ext-link>). The maximum MCC of
the classification by the binding energy derived from the first model
was only about 0.63 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jproteome.0c00717/suppl_file/pr0c00717_si_001.pdf">Supplementary Figure S5</ext-link>), suggesting a single model was not sufficiently accurate for the
classification even if a perfect scoring function was available. To
circumvent the randomness of binding energy from a single model, we
evaluated a large ensemble of structure models (e.g., 500 models in
this work) for each complex and took the lowest binding score as the
binding energy for ACE2 usage analysis. With a proper threshold (i.e.,
&#8722;47 EEU), the binding energy calculated in this manner correlated
well with experimental data, perfectly distinguishing the experimentally
determined effective ACE2 receptors from the less effective ones with
a maximum MCC of 1.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.jproteome.0c00717/suppl_file/pr0c00717_si_001.pdf">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>). Nevertheless, it should be mentioned that biochemical and biophysical
approaches, such as fluorescence resonance energy transfer experiments,
are important for verifying the interaction between S and the ACE2
protein (or any other candidate receptors) from different species.</p>