<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The proteomic profile of BALF from I.P. LPS treated mice revealed by the current study identified several immune pathways in the lung that were suppressed by systemic inflammation including the LXR/RXR activation pathway, the production of NO and ROS in macrophages, IL-7 signaling, and the expression of the neutrophil chemoattractant Cxcl15. The above findings were consistent with the so-called “immunoparalysis” observed in sepsis patients [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Severe sepsis is typically characterized by an initial cytokine-mediated hyper-inflammation or “cytokine storm”, and a subsequent hypo-inflammatory state with significant immunosuppression due to hypo-responsiveness, exhaustion, apoptotic depletion of immune cells and an increase in T regulatory and myeloid-derived suppressor cells [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Patients who survived early sepsis often develop nosocomial infections with organisms not typically pathogenic in immunocompetent hosts (opportunistic pathogens). A frequent site of nosocomial infection is the lung [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Our study suggests that LPS-induced systemic inflammation impairs lipid metabolism and inflammatory responses in macrophages in the lung. In addition, apolipoproteins, which participate in both LXR/RXR activation and the production of NO and ROS in macrophages, have been shown to regulate host immune responses by direct endotoxin binding and neutralization, inhibition of adhesion molecule expression, or stimulation of NO synthase production [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-20-03401" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
