<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">In contrast to the rarer juvenile Granulosa Cell tumors, the bulk of granulosa cell tumors are the adult type (aGCT), which occur peri to post-menopausally [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Patients characteristically present elevated estrogen levels and postmenopausal bleeding [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Almost all aGCTs bear the unique somatic mutation FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], which appears essential to the aGCT development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. However, its pathogenic role in the aGCTs has been investigated only recently and the FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> transcriptional action in aGCTs is still currently studied. These investigations are not trivial, as transcriptomic studies on rare tumors—like aGCTs—face difficulties in the procurement good quality RNA samples. Control samples from healthy human granulosa cells without any previous treatment (HGC or hormones) are similarly limited. Accordingly, only few transcriptomic explorations based on aGCTs samples are present in the literature [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Carles et al
 <italic>.</italic> developed an inducible FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> stable luteinized cell line (SVOG3e) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] showing FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> can precisely modify DNA binding specificity. More recently Weis-Banke et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] characterized the genome-wide binding of overexpressed FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> and transcriptomic consequences, in presence of TGFβ on the same non-luteinized GC cell line (HGrC1) used in our study. They showed that mutant FOXL2 has an important partner not only in SMAD3, but also in SMAD4. This corroborates our previous hypothesis that the partnership between the FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> and TGFβ-pathway SMADs mediators is essential and specifically orchestrates the aGCT gene expression hallmarks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].
</p>
