<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par45">Interestingly, 11 genes–of which 3 (TGFB2, GLI2, POLQ) are direct FOXL2 targets according previous ChIP-seq studies—were observed to be common between the FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> and FOXL2
 <sup>WT</sup> DEGs (717 genes) and the transcriptomic data from aGTC patients published by Benayon et al
 <italic>.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>f). 90 genes have been identified in common between our study and that of Carles et al
 <italic>.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S8, FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> vs Vectors condition). 29 common genes were also identified in common with the Weis-Banke et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Fig. S9, FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> vs FOXL2
 <sup>WT</sup>). It was remarkable that the TGBF2 gene emerges as the strongest FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> modulated candidate since was present as target and upregulated genes in all the analysis carried out. This is consistent with the molecular relationship between FOXL2 and TGFβ family [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Indeed, FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> can trigger neoplastic events in granulosa cells by altering the TGFβ pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Importantly, this finding implies that FOXL2 mutant may drive the steady induction of its key molecular SMAD partners by via a direct TGFB2 positive feedback loop. aGCT therapeutic approaches based on the inhibition of the TGFβ family member Activin showed limited antitumoral activity. However, potentially clinically meaningful dose-related metabolic effects, including treatment of cancer cachexia, were observed that support further exploration of activin A inhibitors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Treatments based on the Activin inhibition and other novel TGFβ pathway targeting approaches–as strongly advocated by Weis-Banke et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] and currently optimized for other indication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]—will be necessary to better determine their clinical meaning in aGCT [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Interestingly, the chromatin remodeler SMARCA4 (BSGR1)–already recognized as an important player in cellular tumorigenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>] and expressed in all aGCT samples [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]–has been directly associated with TGFβ pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>] supporting the assumption of FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> as main pathognomic orchestrator of aGCT. Our overall data are a novel contribution in deciphering how FOXL2
 <sup>C134W</sup> coordinates aGCT tumorigenesis.
</p>
