<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">Cell culture and RNA preparation were performed as described in
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. HUMEC and MCF7 cells were grown to 60–70% confluence in 6-well plates and the media were exchanged with the fresh complete media including AS6 at final concentration of 0.5 µM or H
 <sub>2</sub>O only as an untreated control. After 50 h incubation, the cells were washed with cold PBS once and scraped. The cells were washed again with cold PBS twice before extracting total RNA molecules using Qiagen RNeasy Kit (Qiagen, Germany). The cDNA construction and RNA sequencing were commercially performed by Omega Bioservices (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://omegabioservices.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://omegabioservices.com</ext-link>, USA) using the manufacturer’s typical procedure as previously reported (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSM471292" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSM471292</ext-link>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. The RNA concentration and integrity were assessed using Nanodrop 2000c (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) and Agilent 2200 Tapestation instrument (Agilent Technologies, USA). One microgram of total RNA was used to prepare Ribo-Zero RNA-Sequencing (RNA-Seq) libraries. Briefly, ribosomal RNA (rRNA) is removed using biotinylated, target-specific oligos combined with Ribo-Zero rRNA removal kit (Illumina, USA). After purification, the RNA is fragmented into small pieces using divalent cations under elevated temperature. First-strand cDNA syntheses were performed at 25 °C for 10 min, 42 °C for 15 min and 70 °C for 15 min, using random hexamers and ProtoScript II Reverse Transcriptase (New England BioLabs, USA). In a second strand cDNA synthesis the RNA templates were removed, and a second replacement strand was generated by incorporation dUTP (in place of dTTP, to keep strand information) to generate ds cDNA. The blunt-ended cDNA was cleaned up from the second strand reaction mix with beads. The 3`ends of the cDNA were then adenylated and followed by the ligation of indexing adaptors. PCR (15 cycles of 98 °C for 10 s, 60 °C for 30 s and 72 °C for 30 s) were used to selectively enrich those DNA fragments that have adapter molecules on both ends and to amplify the amount of DNA in the library. The libraries were quantified and qualified using the Agilent D1000 ScreenTape on a 2200 TapeStation instrument. The libraries were normalized, pooled and subjected to cluster and pair-read sequencing was performed for 150 cycles on a HiSeqX10 instrument (Illumina, USA), according to the manufacturer's instructions.
</p>
