<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par81">Raw reads were de-multiplexed and checked for quality using the FastQC software (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link>). Adaptors, duplicated sequences, ambiguous reads, and low-quality reads were removed by using Trim Galore (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/</ext-link>). The high-quality reads (QC &gt; 30) were used for assembling the transcriptomes with Trinity v2.0.2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. The available Roche 454/FLX + 
 <italic>P. notatum</italic> reproductive transcriptome generated by Ortiz et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] was initially used for a reference-guided assembly with the parameters:“--SS_lib_type RF --normalize_by_read_set --min_contig_length 400”, and --genome_guided_bam. Then, a second de novo assembly (without a reference) was carried out using the default parameters. The four assemblies (apo_over reference, sex_over reference, apo_without reference and sex_without reference) were combined in one file and the non-redundant transcripts were selected using CD-HIT [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. The quality of the assemblies was measured using QUAST [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]. The raw reads were mapped to the global assembly using Bowtie2 (v 2.3.2.0) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>] and TopHat (v2.1.1) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]. The transcriptome coverage was evaluated using Benchmarking Universal Single-Copy Orthologs (BUSCO, version 3.0.2) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>] with the following commands: “Python run_BUSCO.py –i sequence_file –o output_name –l lineage –m tran”, “Python generate_plot.py –wd working directory” and the “liliopsida_odb10” dataset. The coding competence for all expressed transcript sequences was predicted using the TransDecoder software (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/TransDecoder/TransDecoder.wiki.git" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/TransDecoder/TransDecoder.wiki.git</ext-link>) with the default parameters (−m 100). For differential expression analysis, RNA-seq reads were analyzed with the Kallisto v.0.44.0 software to determine transcript counts and abundances. The libraries were normalized by size and low-count transcripts were filtered out (&lt; 3 in the three replicas of each library). Differential expression analysis and the corresponding 
 <italic>p</italic>-values were estimated using the Bioconductor software package DESeq2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]. The 
 <italic>p</italic>-values attained by the Wald test were corrected for multiple testing using the Benjamini-Hochberg method. The adjusted 
 <italic>p</italic>-values (DESeq2 padj or FDR) thresholds for considering transcripts as DETs/DEATs were &lt; 0.001 and &lt; 0.05 for sense and antisense transcripts, respectively. Moreover, analyses of DETs were restricted to those showing an absolute value of Log
 <sub>2</sub>FC &gt; |3|. Comparisons of gene expression between modes of reproduction were carried out considering all stages of development (global comparison) or each developmental stage (stage-specific comparison). Venn diagrams were created by using the jvenn online tool/software (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jvenn.toulouse.inra.fr/app/example.html)%5B92" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://jvenn.toulouse.inra.fr/app/example.html</ext-link>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. The transcriptome dynamics was analyzed with R: normalized counts were used to execute a hierarchical clustering using a simple euclidean distance metric and a complete linkage method.
</p>
