<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The initial hydroxylation reaction converting pristane to pristanol could be catalysed by the AlmA homologue (ABO_0282), P450‐1/2 (ABO_0201/2288) and/or P450‐3 (ABO_2384) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="emi14620-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). AlmA expression was significantly higher on pristane compared to pyruvate, but the expression was highest on 
 <italic>n</italic>‐C
 <sub>14</sub>. The expression of P450‐1/2 was at least 2‐fold higher on both 
 <italic>n</italic>‐C
 <sub>14</sub> and pristane compared to pyruvate. P450‐3 was exclusively expressed on pristane. AlmA has previously been implicated in pristane degradation in other 
 <italic>Alcanivorax</italic> strains. In 
 <italic>A. dieselolei</italic> B‐5 pristane activated the expression of AlmA (Liu 
 <italic>et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Enzymatic assays showed it converted pristane to its corresponding primary alcohol (Wang and Shao, 
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0077" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). In 
 <italic>A. hongdengensis</italic> A‐11‐3 pristane selectively activated the expression 
 <italic>almA</italic> (Wang and Shao, 
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2012b</xref>). In other OHCB expression of AlmA was enhanced in four 
 <italic>Marinobacter</italic> strains (
 <italic>M. koreensis</italic> L53‐1‐2, 
 <italic>M. alkaliphilus</italic> L53‐10‐4, 
 <italic>M. alkaliphlius</italic> L52‐11‐18 and 
 <italic>M. lipolyticus</italic> 342‐2) when grown in the presence of pristane (Wang and Shao, 
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0075" ref-type="ref">2012a</xref>). P450‐1 from 
 <italic>A. borkumensis</italic> is expressed from the promoter of the upstream gene (ABO_0199), and this promoter was more active when 
 <italic>n‐</italic>C
 <sub>8</sub>‐
 <italic>n</italic>‐C
 <sub>18</sub> or pristane were assimilated than when pyruvate was available (Sevilla 
 <italic>et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). This is consistent with our results as P450‐1 is differentially expressed in 
 <italic>n</italic>‐C
 <sub>14</sub> and pristane compared to pyruvate suggesting it can use either linear or branched alkanes as substrates. P450‐3 is phylogenetically distant from the other two cytochromes in 
 <italic>A. borkumensis</italic> suggesting it may have a different substrate specificity, that is, branched alkanes (Wang and Shao 
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2012b</xref>; Sevilla 
 <italic>et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Further evidence of this has been shown by Schneiker 
 <italic>et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>), who confirmed that the branched alkane phytane strongly induce the expression of P450‐3 in 
 <italic>A. borkumensis</italic> SK2
 <sup>T</sup>. In 
 <italic>A. hongdengensis</italic> A‐11‐3 pristane selectively activates the expression of P450‐3 (Wang and Shao, 
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2012b</xref>), and the expression of P450‐3 in 
 <italic>A. borkumensis</italic> was much higher when cells assimilated pristane in contrast to when 
 <italic>n</italic>‐alkanes or pyruvate were available (Sevilla 
 <italic>et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="emi14620-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). This was confirmed in our study as P450‐3 was exclusively expressed on pristane.
</p>
