<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Virulence</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Virulence</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Virulence</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2150-5594</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2150-5608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7834096</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33356871</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21505594.2020.1868841</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1868841</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" vocab-term="Version of Record" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Superior Adherence Phenotype of E. coli O104:H4 is Directly Mediated by the Aggregative Adherence Fimbriae Type I</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">P. SCHILLER ET AL.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">VIRULENCE</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>Philipp</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="an0002"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kn&#x000f6;dler</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="an0002"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0760-7177</contrib-id><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Petya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Greune</surname><given-names>Lilo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9486-8358</contrib-id><name><surname>Fruth</surname><given-names>Angelika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mellmann</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8177-3280</contrib-id><name><surname>Dersch</surname><given-names>Petra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9949-1898</contrib-id><name><surname>Dobrindt</surname><given-names>Ulrich</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Institute of Hygiene, <institution-wrap><institution>University of M&#x000fc;nster</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>M&#x000fc;nster</city>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Institute for Infectiology, <institution-wrap><institution>University of M&#x000fc;nster</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>M&#x000fc;nster</city>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>Division of Enteropathogenic Bacteria and Legionella, <institution-wrap><institution>Robert Koch Institute</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Wernigerode</city>, <country>Germany</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">CONTACT Ulrich Dobrindt <email xlink:href="mailto:dobrindt@uni-muenster.de">dobrindt@uni-muenster.de</email></corresp><fn id="an0002"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage seq="26">346</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" start_date="2021-01-14">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="KVIR_12_1868841.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Whereas the O104:H4 enterohemorrhagic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (EHEC) outbreak strain from 2011 expresses aggregative adherence fimbriae of subtype I (AAF/I), its close relative, the O104:H4 enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (EAEC) strain 55989, encodes AAF of subtype III. Tight adherence mediated by AAF/I in combination with Shiga toxin 2 production has been suggested to result in the outbreak strain&#x02019;s exceptional pathogenicity. Furthermore, the O104:H4 outbreak strain adheres significantly better to cultured epithelial cells than archetypal EAEC strains expressing different AAF subtypes. To test whether AAF/I expression is associated with the different virulence phenotypes of the outbreak strain, we heterologously expressed AAF subtypes I, III, IV, and V in an AAF-negative EAEC 55989 mutant and compared AAF-mediated phenotypes, incl. autoaggregation, biofilm formation, as well as bacterial adherence to HEp-2 cells. We observed that the expression of all four AAF subtypes promoted bacterial autoaggregation, though with different kinetics. Disturbance of AAF interaction on the bacterial surface via addition of &#x003b1;-AAF antibodies impeded autoaggregation. Biofilm formation was enhanced upon heterologous expression of AAF variants and inversely correlated with the autoaggregation phenotype. Co-cultivation of bacteria expressing different AAF subtypes resulted in mixed bacterial aggregates. Interestingly, bacteria expressing AAF/I formed the largest bacterial clusters on HEp-2 cells, indicating a stronger host cell adherence similar to the EHEC O104:H4 outbreak strain. Our findings show that, compared to the closely related O104:H4 EAEC strain 55989, not only the acquisition of the Shiga toxin phage, but also the acquisition of the AAF/I subtype might have contributed to the increased EHEC O104:H4 pathogenicity.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>Enteroaggregative <italic>E. coli</italic></kwd><kwd>enterohemorrhagic <italic>E. coli</italic></kwd><kwd>AAF</kwd><kwd>adherence</kwd><kwd>biofilm</kwd><kwd>autoaggregation</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><ref-count count="44"/><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The outbreak of enterohemorrhagic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (EHEC) O104:H4 in 2011 in Germany was one of the largest and most severe EHEC outbreaks in recent history with almost 4000 infections resulting in more than 50 fatalities [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Since then, research was focused on the strain that caused this unprecedented rate of infection, especially as it affected mainly healthy adults, which is not common for EHEC epidemics [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The severity of symptoms and the high percentage of patients developing hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) were attributed to the unusual combination of virulence factors of different <italic>E. coli</italic> pathotypes found in this strain [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Typical EHEC markers include the Shiga toxin (Stx)- and the IrgA homologue adhesin-encoding determinants <italic>stx2</italic> and <italic>iha</italic>, respectively, whereas the most prominent virulence markers of enteroaggregative <italic>E. coli</italic> (EAEC) include the global virulence regulator AggR-encoding and aggregative adherence fimbriae (AAF)-encoding determinants <italic>aggR</italic> and <italic>aggDCBA</italic> [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Whole genome analysis revealed a very close relationship of the EHEC O104:H4 outbreak strain with the prototypic EAEC isolate 55989, which was originally isolated from an HIV-positive patient in the Central African Republic with persistent diarrhea [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5&#x02013;8</xref>]. However, the subtype of the main virulence factor of EAEC, the AAF adhesin, was different in EHEC O104:H4 (AAF/I) when compared to EAEC strain 55989 (AAF/III) [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>AAF were proposed to have significantly contributed to the exceptional pathogenicity of the outbreak strain, e.g. by increasing the amount of Stx2 molecules absorbed through the colon epithelial cells by the tight adherence of a high number of bacterial cells [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Up to date, five different AAF subtypes are known. In addition to the EHEC outbreak strain [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and a recently discovered EAEC/EHEC hybrid strain [<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], AAF are limited almost exclusively to EAEC. They are typically encoded on the large EAEC virulence plasmid pAA [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12&#x02013;15</xref>] and are activated by AggR [<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], which is a central virulence regulator in EAEC [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. AAF have been described as surface structures that mediate aggregative adherence to eukaryotic cells, other bacteria, and abiotic surfaces in a characteristic &#x0201c;stacked-brick&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;honeycomb&#x0201d; adherence pattern [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>The genes encoding AAF are usually organized in one operon that encodes four distinct proteins (schematically depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1(a</xref>)). The gene <italic>aggD</italic> encodes a chaperone protein, <italic>aggC</italic> encodes an usher protein, whereas the structural genes <italic>aggA</italic> and <italic>aggB</italic> encode the major and the minor fimbrial subunit, respectively [<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], with AggB sitting at the tip of a polymer body formed by AggA subunits [<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. AAF are assembled using the chaperone-usher (CU) pathway, similar to various other types of fimbriae in Gram-negative bacteria [<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. We have recently performed a comparative characterization of virulence relevant properties of the Stx2-encoding phage-cured EHEC O104:H4 with other prototypical EAEC, including the very close relative EAEC 55989. Overall, EHEC O104:H4 displayed similar phenotypic characteristics to the other EAEC, with the notable exception that significantly more bacteria were found to be attached to cultured epithelial cells [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, it was not clear, if the increased numbers of bacteria attached to cultured epithelial cells were due to other factors that are specifically encoded in EHEC O104:H4, differences in regulation and-/or expression of the AAF fimbriae, or if this phenotype could be attributed directly to different AAF/I properties. In order to phenotypically characterize AAF/III in comparison with AAF/I, we heterologously expressed AAF/I and AAF/III in AAF-negative EAEC 55989 derivative (EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) as well as AAF/IV and AAF/V, which are more distantly and more closely related to AAF/III than AAF/I, respectively. Expression of the AAF subtypes on the bacterial cell surface was confirmed by Western blot analysis and electron microscopy (EM). This further showed that the expression of all four AAF clusters resulted in autoaggregation and sedimentation of the aggregates in liquid culture, albeit at different kinetics. When incubated together, mixed aggregates were formed, but AAF-negative variants were not included, indicating that all tested AAF subtypes do not interact with other EAEC surface structures. Moreover, AAF-promoted biofilm formation by the different AAF subtypes was found to be temperature-dependent and correlated inversely with the observed autoaggregation phenotype. Finally, we show that AAF/I expressing EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> formed larger bacterial clusters on HEp-2 cells, similar to what we have previously shown for the outbreak strain EHEC O104:H4 [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Genetic organization of the <italic>aaf</italic>/I, III, IV and V operons and amino acid identities of the AggDCBA subunits. (a) Schematic representation of the genetic organization of <italic>aaf</italic>/I, III, IV and V operons (not to scale). (b) Amino acid identities of the AggDCBA subunits of AAF/I, IV and V in respect to the subunits of AAF/III in percent. Overall, AAF/V is more closely and AAF/IV more distantly related to AAF/III than AAF/I is to AAF/III</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0001_B"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0002" disp-level="1"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001" disp-level="2"><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p>All bacterial strains used in this study are listed in Supplementary Table S1. All experiments were performed in lysogeny broth (LB) medium (tryptone: 10&#x000a0;g/L, yeast extract: 5&#x000a0;g/L, NaCl: 5&#x000a0;g/L). Where applicable, the growth medium was supplemented with ampicillin (100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) and/or chloramphenicol (25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml).</p><sec id="s0002-s2001-s3001" disp-level="3"><title><italic>Construction of EAEC strain 55989</italic> agg<italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic></title><p>In EAEC isolate 55,989 the gene cluster coding for AAF/III (<italic>agg</italic>3<italic>DCBA</italic>) was replaced by the chloramphenicol resistance cassette of pKD3 using the lambda Red recombination system [<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The resulting strain <italic>E. coli</italic> 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3::<italic>cat</italic> was hereafter named EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002" disp-level="2"><title>Plasmids</title><p>All plasmids used in this study are listed in Supplementary Table S2 and all primers used in this study are listed in Supplementary Table S3. The structural genes coding for the different AAF allelic variants were amplified from clinical isolates (see Supplementary Table S1) by PCR using the primers listed in Supplementary Table S3 and cloned into the expression vector pBAD24 [<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The integrity of all cloned AAF encoding gene clusters was afterward confirmed by Sanger sequencing of overlapping segments.</p><sec id="s0002-s2002-s3001" disp-level="3"><title>Construction of pAAFI</title><p>The gene cluster coding for AAF/I (<italic>aggDCBA</italic>) was amplified by PCR using EHEC strain LB226692 plasmid DNA as template and primer pair agg_for/agg_rev. The PCR product was digested with <italic>Kpn</italic>I and cloned into the <italic>Sma</italic>I/<italic>Kpn</italic>I-digested pBAD24.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002-s3002" disp-level="3"><title>Construction of pAAFIII</title><p>The AAF/III determinant (<italic>agg</italic>3<italic>DCBA</italic>) was amplified by PCR using EAEC strain 55989 plasmid DNA as template and primer pair agg3_for/agg3_rev. The PCR product was digested with <italic>Xba</italic>I and <italic>Hind</italic>III and cloned into the <italic>Hind</italic>III/<italic>Xba</italic>I-digested pBAD24.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002-s3003" disp-level="3"><title>Construction of pAAFIV</title><p>The gene cluster coding for AAF/IV (<italic>hdaDCBA</italic>) was amplified by PCR using primer pair hda_for/hda_rev and plasmid DNA of EAEC isolate 13&#x02013;00093 (O73:H18) as template. The PCR product was digested with <italic>Nhe</italic>I and <italic>Hind</italic>III and cloned the <italic>Nhe</italic>I/<italic>Hind</italic>III-digested pBAD24.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002-s3004" disp-level="3"><title>Construction of pAAFV</title><p>The AAF/V encoding genes (<italic>agg5DCBA</italic>) were amplified by PCR using plasmid DNA of the aUPEC isolate 147/06 (alternative designation 1352) as template and primer pair agg5_for/agg5_rev. The resulting PCR product was cut with <italic>Xba</italic>I and ligated into pBAD24 that had been digested with <italic>Sma</italic>I/<italic>Xba</italic>I.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002-s3005" disp-level="3"><title>Construction of pPS1 and pPS2</title><p>pUC<italic>r-yfp</italic> and pUC<italic>r-cfp</italic> were constructed as described previously, except that primers MBPD 82/83 were used for the amplification of the kanamycin resistance cassette from pACYC177 [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. pUC<italic>r-yfp</italic> and pUC<italic>r-cfp</italic> were used as templates to generate linear PCR products to generate chromosomal P<italic>dps-cfp</italic> and P<italic>dps-yfp</italic> transcriptional fusions in <italic>E. coli</italic> K-12 strain MG1655 as described previously [<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The P<italic>dps-cfp</italic> and P<italic>dps-yfp</italic> fusion constructs were amplified from chromosomal DNA with primers MBP 140 and MBPD 156, digested with <italic>Kpn</italic>I and cloned into pWKS30 [<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], digested with <italic>Fsp</italic>I and <italic>Kpn</italic>I to create pPS1 (dpsP-<italic>cfp</italic>) and pPS2 (dpsP-<italic>yfp</italic>), respectively, for the differential fluorescent labeling of stationary phase <italic>E. coli</italic> cells.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003" disp-level="2"><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>10&#x000a0;ml of induced overnight cultures (LB medium supplemented with arabinose 1% (w/v)) was harvested by centrifugation (10&#x000a0;min, 3000 x g, 4&#x000b0;C). The supernatant was discarded, and the bacterial pellets were washed by re-suspending in sterile PBS followed by centrifugation for 10&#x000a0;min at 3000 x g and 4&#x000b0;C. The washing step was repeated twice. Pellets were frozen for 30&#x000a0;min at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C and then resuspended in 1.1&#x000a0;ml protein resuspension buffer (1045&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l PBS, 11&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l PMSF solution (100&#x000a0;mM), 44&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l protein inhibitor complete (25x) (Roche, Mannheim, Germany). The samples were transferred to Lysing Matrix E tubes (MP Biomedicals, Eschwege, Germany) and processed with the Precellys24 tissue homogenizer (Bertin Technologies, Montigny-le-Bretonneux, France). The supernatants were transferred to new tubes and stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C until further use. The protein concentrations of the whole cell extracts were determined using the Protein Assay Dye Reagent Concentrate (BioRad, Munich, Germany) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions in a Tecan Infinite F200 plate reader (Tecan, Crailsheim, Germany).&#x02009;10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g, 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g, and 2.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g of total protein extracts of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg3<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> harboring one of the plasmids pAAF/I, pAAF/III, pAAF/IV or pAAF/V, as well as 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (pBAD24) were subjected to SDS-PAGE and Western blotting according to the standard protocols described elsewhere [<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Polyclonal antibodies used for detection of AAF variant major subunits AggA to Agg5A expression were generated by Davids Biotechnologie GmbH (Regensburg, Germany). Primary antibodies were used in a 1:2000 dilution. For the detection of the primary antibodies an anti-rabbit antibody coupled with horseradish peroxidase (HRP) (Dianova, Hamburg, Germany) (1:15,000) and the Clarity ECL solution (BioRad, Munich, Germany) was used. The signals were recorded using the ChemiDoc MP System (BioRad, Munich, Germany). For details about antibodies see Supplementary Table S4.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004" disp-level="2"><title>Autoaggregation assay</title><p>EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells containing either pBAD24 or the plasmids encoding the different AAF subtypes were plated on LB agar containing the suitable antibiotics and incubated overnight at 37&#x000b0;C. Afterward, a single colony was inoculated in 2&#x000a0;ml LB medium containing the suitable antibiotics and grown overnight at 37&#x000b0;C and 180 rpm. The next day, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of these pre-cultures were used to inoculate 20&#x000a0;ml fresh LB medium and the cultures were grown at 37&#x000b0;C and 180 rpm. The OD<sub>600</sub> was determined using the Ultraspec 2100pro spectrophotometer (Amersham Biosciences, Freiburg, Germany) in regular intervals until an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.4&#x02013;0.6 had been reached. 600&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of a 10% arabinose solution were added and incubation continued for another 60&#x000a0;min. Sterile glass tubes were filled with 5&#x000a0;ml bacterial culture and kept static at room temperature. For the measurements, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l samples were taken approximately 1 cm below the liquid surface in duplicates and the OD<sub>600</sub> was determined. Samples were taken every 10&#x000a0;min in the first 60&#x000a0;min after the beginning of the experiment and afterward every 60&#x000a0;min for a total assay time of 3&#x000a0;h.</p><p>To test if the addition of purified specific AAF antibodies to the bacterial suspension disturbs AAF interaction and thus bacterial autoaggregation, we prepared the autoaggregation assays with EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing the different AAF subtypes as described above. We then added 25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of purified antibodies raised against the individual AAF subtype per ml of bacterial suspension and measured the optical density of the bacterial suspension in the absence and presence of the antibodies at time point 0&#x000a0;min and 60&#x000a0;min, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005" disp-level="2"><title>Mixed Aggregation Assay</title><p>EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells containing either pBAD24 or the plasmids encoding the different AAF gene clusters, as well as pPS1 or pPS2 (encoding <italic>cfp</italic> and <italic>yfp</italic>, respectively) were inoculated in 2&#x000a0;ml LB medium with glucose (0.4% w/v) from a previously plated glycerol stock and grown overnight at 37&#x000b0;C and 180 rpm. For this culture, we used LB medium with glucose in order to avoid premature aggregation of bacteria encoding the same fimbriae. The following day 5&#x000a0;ml of fresh LB medium were inoculated with 12.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of two different overnight cultures (overall dilution factor of 1:200). The OD<sub>600</sub> was determined in regular time intervals until an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.4&#x02013;0.6 had been reached, 150&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of a 10% arabinose solution was added, incubation continued for another 60&#x000a0;min and afterward samples were kept static at room temperature to allow the cells to sediment before microscopic inspection. Samples for microscopy using the inverted microscope Leica DMi8 were taken from the bottom of the tubes. The Leica Application Suite X (LAS X) was used to take and pre-process the images. For further processing, we used ImageJ 1.51&#x000a0;n.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006" disp-level="2"><title>Biofilm assay</title><p>The biofilm-forming capabilities of <italic>E. coli</italic> strains DH5&#x003b1; and 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing the different AAF variants were tested as described by Reisner and colleagues [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] with the following modifications: the bacterial strains plated on LB agar containing the suitable antibiotics and incubated overnight at 37&#x000b0;C. A single colony was inoculated in 2&#x000a0;ml LB medium containing the suitable antibiotics and grown overnight at 37&#x000b0;C and 180 rpm for 7&#x000a0;h. Afterward, the starter cultures were diluted 1:100 in 3&#x000a0;ml LB medium containing the suitable antibiotics and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C and 180 rpm for 16&#x000a0;h. The cultures were diluted to OD<sub>600</sub> 0.05 using fresh medium supplemented with arabinose 1% (w/v). Per 96-well plate (clear U-bottom, PVC; Corning, New York, USA), eight wells per strain were filled with 140&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l each, and plates were kept static at 37&#x000b0;C (or 30&#x000b0;C or 20&#x000b0;C, respectively) for 48&#x000a0;h. In order to minimize evaporation, plates were kept in a metal box lined with moist paper towels. Afterward, the wells were washed three times with 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l PBS and the plate was dried at 80&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;h. Staining of biofilm was done by incubation with 175&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l crystal violet (CV) (0.1%) per well for 1&#x000a0;h at room temperature. The CV solution was removed, and the wells were washed three times with double distilled H<sub>2</sub>O (ddH2O) and dried for 1&#x000a0;h. For the quantification of biofilm production, each well was treated with 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l destaining solution (80% ethanol, 20% acetone) for 30&#x000a0;min. Afterward, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l were transferred to a new 96-well plate and the OD was measured using a Tecan Infinite F200 plate reader at 595&#x000a0;nm. For each strain and condition, we tested three independent biological replicates with six technical repeats each. Data evaluation was done as described by Stepanovi&#x00107; and colleagues. The cutoff OD (ODc) was defined as three standard deviations above the mean OD of the negative control values [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Therefore, all tested samples shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6</xref>, except for the bacteria expressing AAF/III and AAF/V, produced significantly more biofilm than the negative control.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007" disp-level="2"><title>Cell adhesion assay</title><p>The cell adhesion assay was done as described by [<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], variations summarized by [<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], with the following alterations: HEp-2 cells were grown for 48&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> until 70&#x02013;90% confluence in EMEM (Biochrom, Berlin, Germany) in 4-well glass chamber slides (Merck Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany). On the day of the experiment, the cells were washed twice with 1&#x000a0;ml fetal calf serum-free EMEM (FCS-free) and incubated for 3&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> with &#x0201c;infection mixture.&#x0201d; The &#x0201c;infection mixture&#x0201d; was produced as follows: five fresh colonies per strain were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 16&#x000a0;h under static conditions in EMEM, supplemented with arabinose (final concentration 1%) for induction of AAF expression. OD<sub>600</sub> was measured the following day and the infection mixture was prepared consisting of 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of 10% mannose (final concentration 0.5%) for blocking type 1 fimbriae [<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], the calculated amount of bacterial cells (final concentration 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/ml) and cell culture medium up to 1&#x000a0;ml. After incubation of HEp-2 cells for 3&#x000a0;h with the infection mixture, the cells were washed thrice with PBS and fixed for 1&#x000a0;min with 1&#x000a0;ml methanol. The methanol was replaced with 1&#x000a0;ml of Giemsa staining solution (freshly diluted 1:20 in ddH<sub>2</sub>O) per well and incubated for 30&#x000a0;min at room temperature. The staining solution was discarded, and the cells were washed carefully with ddH<sub>2</sub>O until the water was clear. The slides were dried at room temperature and cell adherence was evaluated using 40x and 100x oil-immersion light microscopy (Zeiss Axiostar, Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany). Classification of adherence patterns was done as described in other publications [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2008" disp-level="2"><title>Electron microscopy</title><p>Overnight cultures of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg3<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> carrying one of the plasmids pAAF/I, pAAUF/III, pAAF/IV, pAAF/V, and pBAD24 were diluted in fresh LB medium containing ampicillin (100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) and cultivated at 37&#x000b0;C until an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.4&#x02013;0.6 had been reached. Then, 10% arabinose solution was added to a final concentration of 0.3% for the induction of AAF fimbrial expression, and the incubation was continued for another 60&#x000a0;minutes at 37&#x000b0;C. A drop of bacterial culture of each sample was sedimented on a Formvar-coated, carbon-sputtered grid. After negative-staining with 1% phosphotungstic acid, the samples were analyzed at 80 kV with a Tecnai 12 electron microscope (FEI, Eindhoven, The Netherlands). Images of selected areas were documented with Veleta 4k CCD camera (emsis, M&#x000fc;nster, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2009" disp-level="2"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical comparisons were done by performing a one-way ANOVA with Tukey&#x02019;s posttest using the software IBM SPSS Statistics Version 25. We set our significance level at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001" disp-level="2"><title>Comparison of the gene clusters encoding AAF variants I, III, IV and V</title><p>We have previously shown that EAEC strain 55989 expressing AAF/III fimbriae forms smaller aggregates on cultured cells than a Stx2 phage-cured <italic>E. coli</italic> O104:H4 strain expressing AAF/I [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This raised the question whether the different types of fimbriae confer phenotypically distinguishable traits that may have added to the exceptionally high virulence of EHEC O104:H4. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref> shows a schematic representation of the genetic organization of the AAF-encoding gene clusters I, III, IV, and V (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1(a</xref>)) and a comparison of the amino acid sequence identities of the subunits of AAF/I, IV, and V in respect to the subunits of AAF/III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1(b</xref>)). The amino acid sequences of the chaperones, ushers, and minor subunits showed medium to high amino acid sequence similarity, whereas the major fimbrial subunits were apparently highly variable and showed low to very low similarities. The subunits of the AAF/II fimbriae of prototypic EAEC strain 042 were like the AAF/I subunits of EHEC O104:H4 isolate LB226692 less similar to AAF/III than AAF/V and more similar to AAF/III than AAF/IV with respect to amino acid sequence. They were, however, not encoded in a single operon (data not shown). We therefore decided to focus on AAF variants&#x02009;/I,&#x02009;/III,&#x02009;/IV, and/V and investigated whether AAF/I fimbriae expressed by the EHEC O104:H4 outbreak strain possess different adhesive properties than closely and more distantly related AAF fimbriae of EAEC isolates.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002" disp-level="2"><title>Cloning and controlled heterologous expression of AAF/I, III, IV, and V in EAEC strain 55989</title><p>Several surface-exposed factors, such as type 1 fimbriae, long polar fimbriae, curli, and cellulose have been described to contribute to biofilm formation and adherence to eukaryotic cells of EAEC strain 55989 [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In order to be able to directly compare the properties of the AAF fimbriae in a homogeneous genetic background, we first deleted <italic>agg</italic>3<italic>DCBA</italic> from the pAA plasmid of EAEC strain 55989 by Red/ET recombination and cloned the encoding gene clusters for AAF/I, III, IV, and V into the expression vector pBAD24. Afterward, we transformed the plasmids into EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<bold><sup>&#x02212;</sup></bold>, induced the expression of the AAF fimbriae with arabinose, and confirmed their expression by Western blot analysis with polyclonal antisera raised against major fimbrial subunits of AAF/I, AAF/III, AAF/IV, and AAF/V (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>). A protein concentration-dependent signal of expected size was observed in total protein extracts of EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<bold><sup>&#x02212;</sup></bold> containing the AAF/I-, III-, IV- and V encoding expression vectors, but not if EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<bold><sup>&#x02212;</sup></bold> contained the empty expression vector (negative control, NC). This indicated that the controlled heterologous expression of the subunits of AAF/I, III, IV, and V in EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<bold><sup>&#x02212;</sup></bold> was successful. As the different AAF allelic variants were heterologously expressed in the isogenic strain background (EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3-), expression of the aforementioned bacterial factors (type 1 fimbriae, long polar fimbriae, curli and cellulose), that may be involved in bacterial adherence and biofilm formation, is unchanged.<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Western blot analysis of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> heterologously expressing AAF/I, III, IV and V. Shown is a Western blot analysis of the pBAD24-based expression of the <italic>aaf</italic>/I, III, IV and V determinants. Decreasing amounts of total protein (10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g, 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g and 2.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g) of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> carrying plasmid pAAF/I (a), pAAF/III (b), pAAF/IV (c) or pAAF/V (d) were used for semi-quantitative Western blot analysis using antibodies raised against each major fimbrial subunit. EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> carrying the empty vector pBAD24 was used as negative control (NC). Corresponding sizes of immunoreactive bands are given on the right (size marker; M)</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0002_B"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003" disp-level="2"><title>Confirmation of AAF expression by electron microscopy</title><p>In order to check if the heterologous expression of the AAF subunits also resulted in the expected cell surface structures of host strain EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<bold><sup>&#x02212;</sup></bold>, we subjected the bacteria to EM analysis. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>, thin surface structures resembling the previously described fimbriae of the corresponding wild type cells could be detected when EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<bold><sup>&#x02212;</sup></bold> was heterologously expressing AAF/I, III, IV, and V, but not when containing the empty plasmid (NC). Irrespective of the plasmid, strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<bold><sup>&#x02212;</sup></bold> was expressing flagella that were substantially longer and thicker than the fimbriae, which were readily distinguishable from the flagella, as expected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>).<fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Electron microscopic images of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing different AAF variants. Shown are negatively stained EM images of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> heterologously expressing AAF/I, III, IV and V (black arrows), as well as EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> containing the empty expression vector (NC)</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0003_B"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2004" disp-level="2"><title>Sedimentation speed depends on AAF cluster and strain background</title><p>We determined the sedimentation kinetics following autoaggregation of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells expressing the different AAF variants. We induced the expression of AAF/I, III, IV, and V as described above for the preparation of EM samples. Afterward, glass tubes were filled with 5&#x000a0;ml of culture, kept static at room temperature and the cell density was determined directly under the surface of the culture in regular time intervals.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4(a</xref>) shows the results of a typical assay. The bacterial autoaggregation was strictly dependent on the expression of the AAF-encoding gene clusters as judged by complete absence of sedimentation for the negative control, for which the OD<sub>600</sub> slightly increased, as expected (compare AAF/I, AAF/III, AAF/IV, and AAF/V to vector control in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4(a</xref>)). Amongst the AAF variants, AAF/I and AAF/V mediated reproducibly the fastest sedimentation with a comparable rate, followed by AAF/III, which lagged until t =&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4(b</xref>)). Of all tested fimbrial variants, expression of AAF/IV resulted in the slowest bacterial sedimentation and did so significantly until t =&#x000a0;30&#x000a0;min (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001). After 60&#x000a0;min, no further significant drop in OD<sub>600</sub> was observable.<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Impact of different AAF variants on bacterial autoaggregation. Shown is the relative decrease in OD<sub>600</sub> when compared to the OD<sub>600</sub> at the start of the experiment. Autoaggregation was tested for <italic>E. coli</italic> strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> carrying one of the plasmids pBAD24<italic>aaf</italic>I, pBAD24<italic>aaf</italic>III, pBAD24<italic>aaf</italic>IV and pBAD24<italic>aaf</italic>V or pBAD24 (NC). Samples were taken in ten min intervals until reaching a plateau. (a) Representative results of an autoaggregation assay. Except for <italic>E. coli</italic> strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/IV, the bacterial culture sedimented completely at t =&#x000a0;60&#x000a0;min. (b) Shown are average values for each time point and standard deviations of three biological replicates. Whereas the sedimentation of AAF/I-, AAF/III- and AAF/V-expressing cells differed significantly (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) from the negative control already after 10&#x000a0;min, AAF/IV-expressing cells differed only after 30&#x000a0;min significantly from the negative control (the first time point at which the sedimentation speed is significantly different from the negative control is indicated with an * for each AAF variant). The sedimentation speed of AAF/IV-expressing cells was significantly different from AAF/I-, AAF/III- and AAF/V-expressing bacteria until t =&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;min (indicated with **)</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0004_B"/></fig></p><p>To test if antibodies raised against the different AAF variants inhibit the sedimentation phenotype, we added suspensions of purified antibodies raised against the different AAF subtypes to EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing one of the AAF/I, AAF/III, AAF/IV, or AAF/V fimbriae (Figure S1). The antibodies completely prevented sedimentation of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/I and AAF/IV. For EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/III, sedimentation was markedly impeded. For EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/V, the sedimentation was not affected upon addition of the &#x003b1;-AAF/V antibody. However, as the antibody for AAF/V was also requiring substantially more time for the detection of the AAF/V signal in the Western blot analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2d</xref>) we assume that the concentration of the antibody stock solution was in this case too low for a complete block. In summary, the different heterologously expressed AAF variants promote bacterial aggregation and sedimentation to varying degrees. If the interaction of the AAF among each other is disturbed, e.g. by adding AAF-specific antibodies, sedimentation is inhibited.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2005" disp-level="2"><title>Mixed autoaggregation assay</title><p>The well-known AAF-dependent stacked-brick adherence pattern formed by EAEC on epithelial cells suggested that the fimbriae do not only interact with receptors on eukaryotic cells, but also with each other. However, it was unclear, if these are specific interactions in between the same AAF fimbrial subtype, in between AAF fimbriae in general, or if the fimbriae can also bind to non-AAF surfaces on the bacterial cell wall. In order to analyze the composition of the bacterial aggregates when <italic>E. coli</italic> strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressed different AAF subtypes, we mixed two strains marked with otherwise identical plasmids that either expressed the yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) or the cyan fluorescent protein (CFP). Afterward, we induced the expression of the different AAF variants as described above. This allowed us to microscopically analyze the resulting EAEC aggregates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref>). As expected, EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> containing the empty vector did not form any aggregates whereas homogeneously mixed aggregates were formed when the bacteria were expressing the same AAF subtype with different fluorophores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref> right bottom to left top). The combination of EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/I, AAF/III, AAF/IV, and AAF/V with the identical host strain containing the empty expression vector did not result in the systematic inclusion of planktonic bacteria into the aggregates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref>, far right panels). When bacteria expressing the different AAF subtypes were mixed together, less homogenously mixed aggregates were formed with rather patchy characteristics, in which cells expressing one AAF subtype appeared to cluster within the aggregates, e.g. for AAF/I and AAF/III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref>). Interestingly, EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/V was often found to form dense spherical aggregates that were not observed when the same host strain expressed the other AAF subtypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref>).<fig id="f0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Autoaggregation of mixed EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> populations expressing different AAF variants. Shown are fluorescence microscopic images of aggregates formed by EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> heterologously expressing the same, different or no AAF operon. In order to be able to distinguish the bacteria expressing the different AAF subtypes, the bacteria carried an additional identical plasmid, except for the encoded fluorophore (YFP, yellow/CFP, cyan). The bacterial cells formed more or less homogeneous aggregates, but only upon expression of AAF</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0005_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0005_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2006" disp-level="2"><title>Impact of individual AAF variants on bacterial biofilm formation</title><p>Due to the genetic heterogeneity of EAEC and potential differences in the regulation and expression strength of the different AAF-encoding gene clusters, it was not possible to directly test whether the specific AAF subtype of wild-type isolates affects biofilm formation. We therefore compared biofilm formation upon heterologous expression of the different AAF constructs in an isogenic EAEC 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> background at 37&#x000b0;C, 30&#x000b0;C, and 20&#x000b0;C in a standard biofilm assay.</p><p>Interestingly, EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/I was not able to form biofilms at any tested temperature. AAF/IV-expressing EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> produced the most biofilm at 37&#x000b0;C, followed by AAF/V- and AAF/III-expressing strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6</xref>, black bars). Biofilm formation by AAF/III and AAF/V was generally reduced at lower temperature (compare light gray bars in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0006">Figure 6</xref>). Expression of AAF/IV fimbriae resulted in the highest levels of biofilm formation at all tested conditions.<fig id="f0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Biofilm formation by EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3- expressing AAF/I, AAF/III, AAF/IV and AAF/V depends on the AAF subtype and temperature. Shown is the biofilm formation in LB medium at 20&#x000b0;C, 30&#x000b0;C and 37&#x000b0;C. For details see text</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0006_B"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2007" disp-level="2"><title>Cell adhesion</title><p>Adhesive properties of the different AAF variants were tested on HEp-2 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7</xref>), which is the current gold standard for testing cell adhesion patterns of EAEC [<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/I, AAF/III, or AAF/V formed a similar pattern. The bacteria piled up to stacked bricks, which resembled the aggregative adherence (AA) pattern as previously described [<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Notably, expression of the AAF/I variant also led to rudiments of honeycomb formations and resulted in the formation of the largest aggregates on the cells, very similar to what has been described for EHEC O104:H4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7</xref>, 40x magnification) [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].<fig id="f0007" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Impact of AAF subtype expression on the aggregative adherence phenotype. Shown are bacterial aggregates formed by EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> heterologously expressing AAF/I, AAF/III, AAF/IV and AAF/V on HEp2 cells as indicated. NC: negative control (pBAD24); Medium: uninfected HEp2 cells; Scale bar: 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m; Upper panels: 10x magnification, Lower panels: 40x magnification. White arrows indicate rudimentary honey comb formation</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0007_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_F0007_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>The EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/IV displayed a variation in its adherence pattern. Especially noticeable in less densely occupied areas of the eukaryotic cells the bacteria formed a serpentine line pattern, which occasionally branched off or less frequently run parallel to one another. Overall, EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<sup>&#x02212;</sup> expressing AAF/IV formed stacked-brick like patterns only when higher local concentrations of bacteria had been reached.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>The hypervirulent German outbreak strain EHEC O104:H4 encoded AAF/I, whereas EAEC strain 55989, one of its closest known relatives, encoded AAF/III [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The combination of a Stx2-encoding prophage with typical EAEC virulence markers was proposed to have resulted in the unusually aggressive phenotype and we had previously observed that Stx2 phage-cured EHEC O104:H4 formed larger aggregates than other tested EAEC strains on eukaryotic cells <italic>in vitro</italic> [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Against this background, we wanted to gain insights into phenotypic differences mediated by AAF/I and AAF/III. In order to assess potential differences, we decided to use closely and more distantly related reference fimbriae for a phenotypic comparison (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>). The heterologous expression of the AAF gene clusters in comparable amounts in EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> was successful, and surface-exposed fimbrial structures were detected resembling equivalent AAF fimbriae of previous studies [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13&#x02013;15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Due to a heavily stained matrix around the cells, the imaging of AAF expression in the EAEC 55989 strain background was very challenging. We anticipate that capsular polysaccharide or colanic acid is the main component of this matrix as large amounts of shedded &#x0201c;slime&#x0201d; blebs can be seen on the bacterial cell surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>As the ability to aggregate is considered to be an important trait for bacterial survival during host infection [<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], we compared the aggregative behavior between the different AAF-expressing strains. Bacterial cells expressing AAF/I autoaggregated and showed a very fast sedimentation behavior. Although faster than the AAF/IV expressing strain it was comparable to AAF/III- and IV-expressing isogenic strains, indicating no special aggregation property. Less efficient sedimentation by AAF/IV-expressing bacteria may not necessarily be due to a faster formation of the aggregates, but could as well be due to differences in shape and size of the aggregates. The disturbance of the interaction between AAF on the bacterial surface abolished or decreased bacterial sedimentation.</p><p>We further investigated the composition of the bacterial aggregates that are formed when the same, different, or no AAF fimbriae were expressed by EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref>). It might appear obvious that only bacterial cells that express AAF are integrated into the aggregates. However, the interactions of the highly positively charged major fimbrial subunits with known receptors, e.g. fibronectin and the transmembrane mucin MUC1, were proposed to be solely based on electrostatic interactions and therefore rather unspecific [<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Furthermore, dispersin was originally suggested to counteract the hyperaggregative phenotype of <italic>aap</italic>-negative bacteria by preventing the collapse of the positively charged fimbriae on the negatively charged bacterial surface [<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Such electrostatic interactions of the heterologously expressed fimbriae with the cell surface of the AAF-negative isogenic strain were therefore anticipated. In this context, we further observed that bacteria formed mixed aggregates when combinations of different AAF were expressed, albeit generally less homogeneous as bacteria expressing the same AAF subtype. This suggests that AAF mediate specific bacteria&#x02013;bacteria interactions, which may be mediated by the minor fimbrial subunit. This assumption is supported by the very well mixed aggregates formed by AAF/III and AAF/V that possess identical minor subunits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>) as opposed to rather patchy types of aggregates formed by, e.g., AAF/III- and AAF/I-expressing bacteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref>). In order to clarify this question, it will be necessary to analyze the aggregates formed by bacteria that express hybrid AAF operons.</p><p>With respect to the biofilm formation capacities, bacteria expressing AAF/I were not or much less efficient in biofilm formation on PVC (especially prominent at 37&#x000b0;C), compared to the closely related AAF/III and AAF/V-expressing strains, which formed intermediate biofilms in a temperature-dependent manner. In contrast, high biofilm formation was observed with bacteria expressing AAF/IV, which is supported by the fact that also wild type EAEC isolates encoding this cluster were described to adhere quite strongly to glass surfaces and to form strong biofilms [<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Overall we found that the sedimentation speed following autoaggregation of bacteria expressing different AAF variants was apparently anti-correlated with the capacity to form biofilms on PVC (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004 f0005 f0006">Figures 4 and 6</xref>). This might appear paradox at first sight, but if, e.g., the affinities of the fimbriae toward each other are higher than the affinity toward the surface, the bacterial aggregates might simply form too fast and sediment before an effective attachment to the surface can occur.</p><p>AAF/IV also appeared phenotypically distinct on HEp-2 cells when compared to the adherence phenotype of EAEC strain 55989 <italic>agg</italic>3<italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> expressing the other AAF variants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7</xref>). AAF/IV expression resulted in a chain-like bacterial adherence pattern to HEp-2 cells. This head-to-tail like bacterial interaction was apparently not dependent on contact with eukaryotic cells, as it could be also observed for AAF/IV-expressing EAEC strain 55,989 <italic>agg</italic>3<italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> in the mixed autoaggregation assay (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0005">Figure 5</xref>, AAF/IV in combination with negative control). This suggests that AAF/IV may differ functionally from the other AAF subtypes and may have a function outside of the human host. AAF/IV was also referred to as Hda (<underline>H</underline>US-associated <underline>d</underline>iffusely <underline>a</underline>dherent) originating from the plasmid pO86A1 of clinical isolate DIJ1 (GenBank accession no. AB255435.1). Although this chain-like adherence phenotype of some EAEC variants, especially in correlation with AAF/IV expression, has been reported before [<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], the exact phenotype mediated by this particular subtype of AAF still deserves further investigation. Nonetheless, it is interesting to note, that in a study on the impact of EAEC infection on childhood malnutrition and inflammation the presence of the AAF/IV, in contrast to the other AAF subtypes, was significantly associated with nourished children [<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p><p>In contrast to that, AAF/I, AAF/III, and AAF/V showed aggregates that were partially reminiscent of the strictly two-dimensional &#x0201c;stacked-brick&#x0201d; pattern described for the corresponding wild type cells [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7</xref>, note loci with less dense bacterial aggregates). However, most of the formed bacterial aggregates were rather three-dimensional, which may have disturbed the formation of a regular two-dimensional arrangement. Notably, the bacteria expressing AAF/I formed the largest aggregates on HEp-2 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0007">Figure 7</xref>), as previously observed for the corresponding EHEC O104:H4 outbreak strain [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Thus, this appears to be a trait that is mediated directly by this specific AAF subtype.</p><p>The aggregative adherence phenotype can also be conferred by another adhesin designated aggregate-forming pilus (AFP). AFP is more similar to the bundle-forming pilus (BFP), which is usually expressed in enteropathogenic <italic>E. coli</italic> (EPEC), in terms of their operon structure and relatedness of their protein subunits. Expression of the <italic>afp</italic> operon in AAF-negative EAEC/EHEC hybrids has been correlated with aggregative adherence [<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. It will thus be interesting to compare AAF and AFP with regard to their individual contribution to aggregative adherence and biofilm formation.</p><p>Our comparative analysis of AAF/I, III, IV, and V-expressing EAEC strains confirmed that the adherence and aggregation phenotype mediated by AAF/V is more similar to that of AAF/III than that of AAF/I. We show for the first time that these AAF subtypes mediate bacteria&#x02013;bacteria interactions, which exclusively affect bacterial cells expressing AAF. This raises questions about the exact role of AAF in aggregative adherence to epithelial cells, in particular its primary involvement in bacterial autoaggregation and interaction with host factors. Moreover, our work indicates that the strong aggregative adherence phenotype conferred by AAF/I compared to other AAF subtypes is very likely less dependent on differences in expression and/or regulation of AAF, but rather on the structural fimbrial proteins themselves [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Hence, the combination of AAF/I of EAEC with a <italic>stx</italic>2-encoding prophage from EHEC in one single <italic>E. coli</italic> bacterium might truly have been the &#x0201c;worst of both worlds&#x0201d; that we have so far experienced.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6035"><caption><title>Supplemental Material</title></caption><media xlink:href="KVIR_A_1868841_SM6035.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Support by the Medical Faculty of the University of M&#x000fc;nster (Medizinerkolleg MedK) to P.S. is gratefully acknowledged.</p></ack><sec id="s0005" disp-level="1" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="s0006" disp-level="1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/21505594.2020.1868841">here</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denamur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrindt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>The enemy within us: lessons from the 2011 European <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4 outbreak</article-title>. <source>EMBO Mol Med</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>848</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22927122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Epidemic profile of Shiga-toxin-producing <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4 outbreak in Germany</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>365</volume>:<fpage>1771</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1780</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21696328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kampmeier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mellmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>The 2011 German enterohemorrhagic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4 outbreak-the danger is still out there</article-title>. <source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>416</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30062592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bielaszewska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mellmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Characterisation of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain associated with an outbreak of haemolytic uraemic syndrome in Germany, 2011: a microbiological study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>676</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21703928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gounon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bougu&#x000e9;nec</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Identification of an aggregative adhesion fimbria (AAF) type III-encoding operon in enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> as a sensitive probe for detecting the AAF-encoding operon family</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>4302</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4311</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12117939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brzuszkiewicz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Th&#x000fc;rmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schuldes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Genome sequence analyses of two isolates from the recent <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> outbreak in Germany reveal the emergence of a new pathotype: Entero-Aggregative-Haemorrhagic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (EAHEC)</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>193</volume>:<fpage>883</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>891</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21713444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mossoro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Glaziou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yassibanda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Chronic diarrhea, hemorrhagic colitis, and hemolytic-uremic syndrome associated with HEp-2 adherent <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in adults infected with human immunodeficiency virus in Bangui, Central African Republic</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>3086</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3088</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12149388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro-Garcia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4&#x02009;pathogenesis: an enteroaggregative <italic>E. coli</italic>/Shiga toxin-producing <italic>E. coli</italic> explosive cocktail of high virulence</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<page-range>EHEC-0008-2013</page-range>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mellmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harmsen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Prospective genomic characterization of the German enterohemorrhagic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4&#x02009;outbreak by rapid next generation sequencing technology</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e22751</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21799941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The worst of both worlds: examining the hypervirulence of the shigatoxigenic/enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>210</volume>:<fpage>1860</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1862</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prager</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aurass</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Two novel EHEC/EAEC hybrid strains isolated from human infections</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e95379</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24752200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boisen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Struve</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheutz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>New adhesin of enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> related to the Afa/Dr/AAF family</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>3281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3292</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18443096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Czeczulin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balepur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Aggregative adherence fimbria II, a second fimbrial antigen mediating aggregative adherence in enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>4135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9317019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#x000f8;nsson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Struve</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boisen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Novel aggregative adherence fimbria variant of enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>1396</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1405</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25624357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nataro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maneval</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Aggregative adherence fimbriae I of enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> mediate adherence to HEp-2 cells and hemagglutination of human erythrocytes</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>2297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2304</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1350273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nataro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yikang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yingkang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>AggR, a transcriptional activator of aggregative adherence fimbria I expression in enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>4691</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4699</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7913930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Czeczulin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>A novel dispersin protein in enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>1329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1337</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12417572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kn&#x000f6;dler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>F&#x000f6;rstner</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>The primary transcriptome of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4 pAA plasmid and novel insights into its virulence gene expression and regulation</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>35307</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27748404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nataro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pathogenesis of enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>254</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16451173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savarino</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Identification and characterization of a gene cluster mediating enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> aggregative adherence fimbria I biogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>4949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4957</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7914189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pakharukova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Structural insight into host recognition by aggregative adherence fimbriae of enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e1004404</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25232738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waksman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Chaperone-usher pathways: diversity and pilus assembly mechanism</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>367</volume>:<fpage>1112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22411982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuccio</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>B&#x000e4;umler</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evolution of the chaperone/usher assembly pathway: fimbrial classification goes Greek</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>575</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18063717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haarmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kouzel</surname><given-names>IU</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Comparative virulence characterization of the Shiga toxin phage-cured <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4 and enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Med Microbiol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>308</volume>:<fpage>912</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>920</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29941383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Datsenko</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>One-step inactivation of chromosomal genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 using PCR products</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>6640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6645</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10829079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Tight regulation, modulation, and high-level expression by vectors containing the arabinose PBAD promoter</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>177</volume>:<fpage>4121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4130</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7608087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Construction of versatile low-copy-number vectors for cloning, sequencing and gene expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Gene</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>199</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2055470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Molecular cloning: A laboratory manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reisner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krogfelt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> biofilm formation of commensal and pathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains: impact of environmental and genetic factors</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>188</volume>:<fpage>3572</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3581</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16672611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stepanovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vukovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hola</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Quantification of biofilm in microtiter plates: overview of testing conditions and practical recommendations for assessment of biofilm production by staphylococci</article-title>. <source>Apmis</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>115</volume>:<fpage>891</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>899</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17696944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cravioto</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scotland</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>An adhesive factor found in strains of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> belonging to the traditional infantile enteropathogenic serotypes</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toval</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>K&#x000f6;hler</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> isolates from hospital inpatients or outpatients with urinary tract infection</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24478469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas-Lopez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cieza</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>The role of long polar fimbriae in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O104:H4 adhesion and colonization</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0141845</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26517878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiebel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nitschke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Genotypic and phenotypic characteristics associated with biofilm formation by human clinical <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> isolates of different pathotypes</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<fpage>83:e01660-17</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nataro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaper</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robins-Browne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Patterns of adherence of diarrheagenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to HEp-2 cells</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>831</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3313248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trabulsi</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tardelli Gomes</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Typical and atypical enteropathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>513</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11996687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzart</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guth</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedroso</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Diversity of surface structures and virulence genetic markers among enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (EAEC) strains with and without the EAEC DNA probe sequence</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>201</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collado</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meriluoto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salminen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Adhesion and aggregation properties of probiotic and pathogen strains</article-title>. <source>European Food Res and Tech</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>226</volume> DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00217-007-0632-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boll</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayala-Lujan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Szabady</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> adherence fimbriae drive inflammatory cell recruitment via interactions with epithelial MUC1</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<comment>e00717-17</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanton</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Aggregative adherence and intestinal colonization by enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> are produced by interactions among multiple surface factors</article-title>. <source>mSphere</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e00078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29577084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>RCB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>RHS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Analysis of the virulence profile and phenotypic features of typical and atypical enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (EAEC) isolated from diarrheal patients in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32391284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gioppo</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>WP</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vidotto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of HEp-2 cell-adherent <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and characterisation of enteroaggregative <italic>E. coli</italic> and chain-like adherent <italic>E. coli</italic> isolated from children with and without diarrhoea, in Londrina, Brazil</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11034294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>[43]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Havt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Prevalence and virulence gene profiling of enteroaggregative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> in malnourished and nourished Brazilian children</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28780245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>[44]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fruth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Novel type of pilus associated with a Shiga-toxigenic <italic>E. coli</italic> hybrid pathovar conveys aggregative adherence and bacterial virulence</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30514915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>