<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the mRNA–lncRNA expression co-expression network, we identified PRKAA2, one of the most important differentially regulated genes in endothelial cells with PC-3M adhesion. PRKAA2 is a catalytic subunit of the AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK). AMPK is an important energy-sensing enzyme that monitors cellular energy status. Once AMPK is switched on by increases in cellular AMP:ATP ratios, it acts to restore energy homeostasis by switching on catabolic pathways while switching off cell growth and proliferation (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Vara-Ciruelos et al., 2019</xref>). In cancer cells, studies have shown that AMPK could promote epithelial–mesenchymal transition (EMT) by upregulating Twist 1 and thus promote tumor metastasis (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Saxena et al., 2018</xref>), and PRKAA2 has been shown to be involved in cell energy metabolism in various cancers. In bladder cancer, loss of PRKAA2 resulted in increased tumor proliferation and larger xenografts (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). AMPK acts downstream of the tumor-suppressor LKB1. The canonical AMP-dependent mechanism of activation has suggested that AMPK might also suppress tumorigenesis. However, once tumorigenesis has occurred, AMPK switches from tumor suppression to tumor promotion (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Diana Vara-Ciruelos and Hardie, 2020</xref>). We found that PRKAA2 mRNA expression was significantly higher in HUVECs adhered by PC-3M than that in endothelial cells alone. Studies have reported that AMPK can also be switched on by increases in intracellular Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>, by glucose starvation, and by DNA damage via non-canonical, AMP-independent pathways. In our previous study, we found that the endothelial intracellular Ca
 <sup>2</sup> level increased as PC-3M cells were added and contacted to the endothelium, then returned to the original calcium level (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Yan Pan et al., 2011</xref>). Also, other researchers found that the absence of PRKAA2 could cause aberrant expression and activation of NADPH and consequently cause dysfunction in endothelial cells (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2010)</xref> found that PRKAA2 could protect vascular endothelial cells from oxidative stress by suppressing the NF-κB-mediated expression of NAD(P)H oxidase. Moreover, it has been reported that PRKAA2 could suppress endothelial angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) expression via the phosphorylation of p53 and upregulation of miR-143/145 (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Kohlstedt et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
