<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">To determine if gene duplications were enriched in particular biological pathways, we used the WEB-based Gene SeT AnaLysis Toolkit (WebGestalt) (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Liao et al., 2019</xref>) to perform Over-Representation Analysis (ORA) using the Reactome database (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Jassal et al., 2020</xref>). Gene duplicates in each lineage were used as the foreground gene set, and the initial query set was used as the background gene set. WebGestalt uses a hypergeometric test for statistical significance of pathway over-representation, which we refined using two methods: a False Discovery Rate (FDR)-based approach and an empirical p-value approach (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>). The Benjamini&#8211;Hochberg FDR multiple-testing correction was generated by WebGestalt. In order to correct p-values based on an empirical distribution, we modified the approach used by Chen et al. in Enrichr (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>) to generate a 'combined score' for each pathway based on the hypergeometric p-value from WebGestalt, and a correction for expected rank for each pathway. In order to generate the table of expected ranks and variances for this approach, we randomly sampled foreground sets of 10&#8211;5000 genes from our background set 5000 times, and used WebGestalt ORA to obtain a list of enriched terms and P-values for each run; we then compiled a table of Reactome terms with their expected frequencies and standard deviation. These data were used to calculate a Z-score for terms in an ORA run, and the combined score was calculated using the formula <inline-formula><mml:math id="inf11"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#8901;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#8203;</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>