<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To further verify the effects of these MVs, renal tubular cells were treated with TGF-β1, the culture medium was obtained by ultracentrifugation, and MVs were applied to cardiomyocytes. The results showed that MVs could induce cardiomyocyte hypertrophy, while the culture medium without MVs had no such effect, suggesting that MVs produced by renal tubular cells treated with TGF-β1 were the cause of cardiomyocyte hypertrophy (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>). Although MVs are important vectors for intercellular communication, the substances contained in MVs indeed mediate the interaction between cells. Circulating miRNAs are very stable, which can avoid the degradation of RNase by the protection of MVs, thus attracting a wide range of interests [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. MiR-21 has been reported to be related to pathological cardiac remodeling and fibrosis [
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. It has been found that MVs from endothelial progenitor cells can antagonize angiotensin II-induced cardial hypertrophy and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], suggesting the participation of MVs in myocardial hypertrophy. Moreover, miR-21 has also been shown to play an important role in renal fibrosis [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It has been confirmed that miR-21 regulates peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor alpha, a molecular mechanism of cardiac pathology in CRS type 4 [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Suppression of miR-21 protects rats with 5/6 nephrectomy from development of left ventricle hypertrophy and impairment of left ventricle function [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. It has been also reported that the level of miR-21 in blood circulation is correlated with the severity of renal fibrosis, suggesting that the miR-21 delivered by MVs may enter the blood circulation [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Therefore, it is reasonable to speculate that MVs are the inner mechanisms, which form an interaction between heart and kidney diseases. In this study, we observed that myocardial hypertrophy was stimulated by the incubation of MVs. However, such effect could be eliminated by miR-21 inhibitor (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>). Therefore, MVs mediated the delivery of miR-21 into recipient cardiomyocytes, thereafter contributing to the hypertrophy of cardiomyocytes.
</p>
