<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Celiac disease (CeD) is a prevalent disorder that severely affects the upper part of the small intestine and impairs health and quality of life of many children and adults. The disease occurs in genetically susceptible individuals when they mount a harmful, adaptive immune response towards dietary gluten proteins. The only current treatment is a life‐long gluten‐free diet. All CeD patients have in their intestine proinflammatory CD4+ T cells that recognize posttranslationally modified gluten peptides in context of the disease associated MHC class II molecules HLA‐DQ2.5, DQ8, or DQ2.2.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> Even on a gluten‐free diet, low numbers of gluten specific CD4+ T‐cells remain in the memory T‐cell compartment.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> These cells are rapidly reactivated when CeD patients eat gluten again.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> CeD is therefore a life‐long condition that requires strict dietary measures. The proinflammatory T‐cell response to gluten results in small intestinal inflammation and mucosal destruction that causes clinical features such as diarrhea and nutrient deficiency. Mucosal affection is assessed from histological evaluation of small intestinal biopsies, where the morphology often is graded according to the categorical Marsh score.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> Marsh 0 represents normal morphology. Marsh 1 reflects normal morphology but with increased number of intraepithelial lymphocytes (IELs). Marsh 2 is similar to Marsh 1 but with addition of crypt hyperplasia. Marsh 3 has in addition blunting of the villi. Upon treatment with a gluten‐free diet, most patients recover with normalization of the intestinal mucosa to Marsh 0 or 1. Reintroduction of dietary gluten to treated patients can be done in the clinical contexts to confirm the diagnosis of CeD, and is used in clinical trials to evaluate drug efficacy where changes in intestinal morphology serve as read‐out. However, well‐treated CeD patients can respond very different to the same gluten challenge regime. This points to differences between patients that are not captured from routine clinical evaluation. Quantitative proteomic analysis of biopsy tissues allows for in‐depth and unbiased characterization, and can reveal differences that may be not be visible from histological evaluation. Here we have performed spatially resolved proteome analysis of intestinal biopsies collected before and after short‐term gluten challenge of 19 well‐treated CeD patients.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> Only some of the patients developed a strong mucosal response to gluten on day 14. We demonstrate that these patients have in their gut signs of ongoing, low‐grade antigluten immunity already before gluten challenge. These patients may therefore have a “head start” upon gluten challenge initiation. Our findings raise the question whether a standard gluten‐free diet is sufficient to fully curb the gluten‐specific immune response in all CeD patients.
</p>
