<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We analyzed global protein expression in total tissue and laser capture microdissected epithelium from formalin fixed paraffin embedded biopsies collected before and after gluten challenge (
 <bold>Figure</bold> 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>1</bold>A
 </xref>).
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> All study participants were adults (&gt;20 years old) with biopsy‐confirmed CeD that had followed a gluten‐free diet for more than 24 months (Table S1, Experimental Section, Supporting Information).
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> Patients that participated in the trial were considered to be in complete remission with Marsh scores 0 or 1 and negative serum anti‐TG2 IgA.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> Nineteen of 20 enrolled patients completed the challenge, consuming one müsli bar with 5.7 g gluten protein per day for 14 days. Small intestinal biopsies were collected before challenge and on day 14. Biopsies collected from one patient before challenge was in a blinded reevaluation reclassified to Marsh 3.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> We collected tissue from the biopsy blocks for protein extraction and digestion followed by liquid chromatography and mass spectrometry for protein identification and label‐free quantification.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> From total tissue protein digests we quantified 4301 proteins (Figure S1, Supporting Information). Unsupervised clustering segregated samples from 8 biopsies of which seven were collected after challenge (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). For the remaining patients, no clear separation was seen for biopsies collected before and after challenge (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). Based on tissue proteome expression, we classified the patients as “responders” (
 <italic>n</italic> = 7) or “non‐responders” (
 <italic>n</italic> = 12) to the gluten challenge (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>; Table S1, Supporting Information). All five patients that developed Marsh 3 after challenge were “responders.” Gluten induced differential expression of 258 proteins (115 up, 143 down) in “responders” compared to 38 proteins in “non‐responders” (23 up, 15 down) (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>; Table S2, Supporting Information). Neutrophil‐derived and inflammatory proteins increased significantly in “responders,” while the majority of proteins with reduced expression were of presumed enterocyte origin. We therefore addressed how gluten challenge affected the intestinal epithelial compartment specifically. Epithelial cell layer samples spanning the entire crypt‐villus‐axis (≈2000 cells/sample) were isolated from tissue sections by laser capture microdissection followed by mass spectrometry‐based proteome analysis (Figures S2 and S3, Supporting Information). Based on the expression of 2404 proteins, epithelial samples separated as “responders” and “non‐responders” similar to total tissue samples (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1D</xref>; Figure S3, Supporting Information). Baseline samples from “responders” also displayed skewing along principle component 1 (PC1) (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1D</xref>). Gluten induced differential expression of 441 proteins in the “responder” epithelium (233 down, 208 up) compared to only 8 proteins in the epithelium of “non‐responders” (3 up, 5 down) (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1E</xref>; Table S2, Supporting Information).
</p>
