<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The small intestinal lesion in CeD is characterized by epithelial changes such as increased frequency of IELs, crypt hyperplasia, and villous blunting. Villous height to crypt depth (Vh:Cd) ratio is a continuous morphometric variable that, similar to the Marsh score, can reflect gluten‐induced pathology.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> The majority of cells in the epithelium are absorptive enterocytes that come from stem cells in the proliferative crypts that divide and mature as they migrate up to the villi tips. Inflammation, increased epithelial turnover, and crypt hyperplasia as occurs in CeD results in fewer mature enterocytes which affects intestinal function. We mapped our proteome data to single cell RNA‐sequencing‐derived gene‐sets for “mature enterocytes” and “goblet cells” to compare cell‐type protein expression with histological measures (Table S4, Supporting Information).
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> “Mature enterocyte” proteins showed lowest expression in biopsies from “responders” after challenge, with an opposite expression pattern for “goblet cell” proteins (
 <bold>Figure</bold> 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>3</bold>A
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">B</xref>; Figure S8, Supporting Information). Median expression of “mature enterocyte” proteins showed a positive correlation with Vh:Cd ratio previously measured on the same biopsies while “goblet cell” protein expression showed negative correlation Vh:Cd ratio (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3C</xref>,
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). These plots show clearly that “responders” differ from “non‐responders” already at baseline. These baseline differences were captured by the Vh:Cd ratio (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3E</xref>), but not by the categorical Marsh score (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3F</xref>) or IEL frequency (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3G</xref>). Thus, the patients that respond strongly to gluten have altered epithelial protein expression at baseline, with activation of crypt cells in the absence of IEL infiltration.
</p>
