<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We next asked whether available blood parameters measured at baseline before the gluten challenge reflected this low‐level of mucosal inflammation. Serum ALAT, ALP, ASAT, CRP, ferritin, GT, Hb, and plasma TNF‐
 <italic>α</italic> were all slightly higher in “responders” compared to “non‐responders” while serum transferrin was lower in “responders” (
 <bold>Figure</bold> 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>4</bold>A
 </xref>; Table S1 and Figure S9, Supporting Information). Although modest, this clinical biochemistry profile supports the notion of low‐level inflammation in “responders.” The mucosal damage in CeD is considered to be a direct consequence of the adaptive immune response to gluten. Gluten specific CD4+ T cells as detected with HLA‐DQ:gluten peptide tetramers have previously been quantified in blood, and in intestinal biopsies from a subset of patients from this gluten challenge study (Table S1, Supporting Information).
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> “Responders” had higher frequency of gluten specific CD4+ T cells in the gut and in the blood at baseline compared to “non‐responders” (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). This difference was not explained by the duration of gluten‐free diet prior to gluten challenge (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>). Frequency of gluten specific CD4+ T cells in the gut at baseline correlated with “mature enterocyte” protein expression, with separation of “responders” and “non‐responders” (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4D</xref>, top left panel). Weaker correlation was observed between “mature enterocyte” protein expression and blood T‐cell frequency at baseline, and between Vh:Cd ratio and gut or blood T‐cell frequencies (Figure 
 <xref rid="advs2293-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4D</xref>). These data indicate that “responder” patients with ongoing low‐level inflammation at baseline also have more gluten‐specific CD4+ T cells in particular in the gut at baseline, despite long‐term treatment with gluten‐free diet.
</p>
