<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study we show that quantitative proteome analysis of routine histology biopsies reveals differential presence of low‐level inflammation in the intestine of CeD patients considered to be well‐treated by gluten‐free diet. An RNASeq study of treated CeD patients undergoing gluten challenge also found differences between patients before and after gluten challenge.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> The patients in our study that developed clear mucosal response by day 14 of the gluten challenge had ongoing low‐level inflammation at already at baseline. Gluten specific CD4+ T cells peak in blood on day 6 after gluten intake.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> From the current gluten challenge, 12 of the 15 patients that were analyzed on day 6 of challenge showed more than twofold increase in gluten specific CD4+ T‐cells.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> However this relative increase hides differences in baseline cell numbers, which is likely to be a more crucial variable for development of mucosal pathology. The T‐cell autocrine cytokine IL‐2 is secreted by gluten specific CD4+ T cells upon intake of gluten and is now considered the major driver of immediate gastrointestinal symptoms to gluten in CeD patients.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> Also in patients from the current study, mean fold increase in plasma IL‐2 within &lt;6 h after gluten intake correlated with baseline frequency of gluten‐specific CD4+ T cells in blood.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="advs2293-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> Thus, development of symptoms and mucosal pathology in response to gluten is linked to the magnitude of antigluten immunity present at the time of gluten consumption. Conceivably, mucosal pathology may develop more uniformly in response to longer gluten challenge regimes (e.g., ten weeks), where the gluten specific CD4+ T‐cells have time to expand sufficiently in all patients.
</p>
