<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group>
 <app id="app1-molecules-26-00305">
  <title>Supplementary Materials</title>
  <p>The following are available online, Figure S1: The workflow of our gel spot refining strategy. Three filters (two automated and one manual) were used for refining Progenesis SameSpot selected spots. F1 is a spot volume intensity filter to identify spots different by ≥2-fold. F2 is statistical ANOVA filter to identify spots significantly different at 
   <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.05. F3 is manual filtering to eliminate suspected background and noise spots. Visualization was achieved by silver staining before spot picking and was followed by LC-MS/MS analysis of spots, Figure S2: Gel spot comparison for two representatives differentially expressed proteins between the exponential and the stationary growth phases of MAH 104 using Progenesis SameSpots software; Upper line for spot number 63 (Glucose methanol choline) that is up regulated in the stationary phase and lower line for spot number 17 (Universal stress protein) that is down regulated in the stationary phase. Intensities of the two spots differentially expressed in the exponential and the stationary growth phases were shown in the representative gel image (A). 3D views of the intensities of the targeted spots blotted by SameSpots in both phases are shown (B). The logarithmic normalized volume between the 2 phases was blotted for each spot by SameSpots (C). Spot numbers are corresponding to those listed in 
   <xref rid="molecules-26-00305-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. (D) The standard expression profiles of the twelve differentially expressed proteins between the exponential and the stationary growth phases of MAH 104, Figure S3: Agarose gel electrophoresis of 12 PCR products of genes responsible for the expression of the 12 differentially expressed proteins between the exponential and the stationary growth phases of 
   <italic>Mycobacteriun avium</italic> 104. Low molecular weight markers are used. Band sizes for each gene product of the 12 genes are summarized in 
   <xref rid="molecules-26-00305-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, Figure S4: 
   <italic>M. avium</italic> RNA in exponential and in stationary growth phases quality on the gel (A), purity and concentrations using eppendorf Bio-spectrometer (B) and integrity; electropherogram profiles for 
   <italic>M. avium</italic> RNA resolved on a Pico Chip of Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer, Agilent Technologies (C). (D) Gel image formed for 
   <italic>M. avium</italic> RNA using Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer, Agilent Technologies, Figure S5: Correlation between the gene expression of each gene and the average normalized volume for each protein of the differentially expressed hits between the two growth phases. Numbers shown here indicating the number of genes and proteins as displayed in 
   <xref rid="molecules-26-00305-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Red circles; up-regulated, Green circles; down-regulated, Black circles; differ in/between the transcriptomic and the proteomic analysis, Table S1: List of primer sequences used in this study for 12 genes that were designed with the publicly available Primer3 software.
  </p>
 </app>
</app-group>
