<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Measurements based on the detection of X-ray fluorescence photons corresponding only to a certain decay transitions (HERFD-XAS) can serve to remove the background contribution from elastic and Compton scattering, which is important for studies of very dilute samples and samples in strongly scattering environments such as electrocatalysts in an electrolyte.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref191">191</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref192">192</xref>
 </sup> The HERFD-XAS approach also allows one to separate the XAS spectra of elements that are neighbors in the Periodic Table (so-called “range-extended” XAS), and thus, the collection of good quality Pt L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge XAS is possible in the presence of Au atoms, while in the conventional XAS analysis the length of the Pt EXAFS spectrum is limited by the onset of the Au L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge. Thus, measurements in HERFD-XAS mode are beneficial for studies of bimetallic catalysts.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref385">385</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref386">386</xref>
 </sup> One can also focus on a fluorescence channel with a particularly long lifetime, and thus improve significantly the energy resolution of the XAS method, which normally is limited by the finite lifetime of the created excitation. For example, HERFD-XAS was recently used by Friebel et al. at the Ni K-edge and Fe K-edge to detect changes in the structure and oxidation state of Ni–Fe catalysts under applied potential during the electrochemical water splitting,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref245">245</xref>
 </sup> and at the Cu K-edge HERFD to study the structure of monolayer and multilayer Cu on Au catalysts for CO
 <sub>2</sub>RR.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref191">191</xref>
 </sup> Similarly, Merte et al. used Pt L
 <sub>3</sub>-edge HERFD XAS to distinguish between chemisorbed oxygen species and different Pt oxides (PtO vs PtO
 <sub>2</sub>).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref362">362</xref>
 </sup> Complementary applications of XAS and XES in the field of biological catalysis were recently reviewed by DeBeer et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref387">387</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref388">388</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
