<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Analysis of rare functional SNVs showed that the 
 <italic>FTSJ3</italic> gene was most significantly associated with severe influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 disease. FTSJ3 protein is an RNA 2’-O-methyltransferase recruited by HIV-1 to evade innate immune recognition [
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In addition, Ribose 2’-O-methylation provides a molecular signature by which the cellular innate immune system distinguishes self from non-self mRNA [
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In the rare SNVs analysis that only considered LOF SNVs, we found that the 
 <italic>CPVL</italic> gene may contribute to the emergence of severe influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 disease. CPVL protein has been found to be involved in an inflammatory protease cascade, and trimming of peptides for antigen presentation [
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The results of the candidate genes priority analysis suggested that 
 <italic>NOD2</italic> was the most significant risk gene, followed by 
 <italic>ULK1</italic>, 
 <italic>IL10</italic> and 
 <italic>BST2</italic> etc. In the protein interaction analysis, we further analysed these candidate genes mutual relationship and discovered that 
 <italic>NOD2</italic> and 
 <italic>MAVS</italic> were most valuable hub genes. From the perspective of virus life cycle, we further investigated the role of these candidate genes in the antiviral process. The ULK1 complex initiates autophagosome formation, linking cellular nutrient status to downstream events in autophagy [
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. An earlier study suggested that SNPs in the 
 <italic>IL10</italic> gene might be associated with disease severity in influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 infected patients [
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. BST2 protein has been described to inhibit the virus replication by tethering the virus release from the cell surface [
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] or by inducing the NF-κB dependent antiviral immune response [
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] or by targeting and degrading virus nucleocapsid protein [
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. As a cytosolic sensor, NOD2 contribute to host defense against microbial infection in human through an IL-32-dependent dendritic cells differentiation pathway [
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. A recent study has shown that influenza A M2 protein colocalized and interacted with MAVS on mitochondria, and positively regulated MAVS-mediated innate immunity [
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Taken together, we successfully identified several novel candidate genes might confer risk for severe influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 infection through changing the activity of host immunity or interfering the survival of influenza viruses. Functional experiments are worthy to validate these findings in the future.
</p>
