<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">We will discuss our results in light with the trigger, facilitator and aggravator hypothesis for PD, recently proposed and extending this premise to AD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Indeed, this innovative hypothesis postulates that PD pathogenesis can be divided into three temporal phases. The first phase assumes that microbial infection, gut dysbiosis or environmental toxins ‘trigger’ the initiation of the disease process and are most prominent during the “prodromal PD” phase. Nevertheless, pathology progression needs ‘facilitators’ such peripheral inflammation or mitochondrial dysfunction. Indeed, it has been postulated that facilitators may promote the formation and/or seeding of pathogenic SNCA in the midbrain. After clinical onset we reach the third phase where ‘aggravators’ boost neurodegeneration and exacerbate symptoms. Johnson et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> proposed that impaired autophagy and cell-to-cell propagation of aggregated proteins (SNCA or eventually Aβ for AD) are the aggravators that lead to disease neurodegenerative progression in the brain. The human brain samples selected for this study with their Braak stage correspondence, IV–VI for PD cases and III–IV for AD cases, tell us that we are studying the aggravator phase of both disorders. Accordingly, we see an altered proteome in the SNpc of PD cases presenting a dysfunctional autophagic process, due to microtubule disassembly, altered levels of ER stress sensors and a decrease in post-synaptic markers. Our group previous work showed, in different PD models, that mitochondrial deficits lead to deficient intracellular traffic which results in incomplete autophagosome degradation and reduced autophagosome and mitochondrial movements culminating in a poor SNCA aggregate clearance
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Accordingly, we found that tau and tubulin acetylation are decreased resulting in microtubule disassembly and as consequence deficits in macroautophagy, seen by an accumulation of LC3II, which may potentiate SNCA accumulation in the SNpc. Indeed, PD cellular models show microtubule disassembly, due to tubulin depolymerization and deacetylation and tau hyperphosphorylation, postulating a direct involvement of tau in PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. It was previously reported in sPD cybrids, in mtDNA-depleted cells and in cultured cells exposed to mitochondrial toxins such as 1-methyl-4-phenylpyridinium (MPP+), rotenone and 6-hydroxydopamine (6-OHDA) an augment in the number of autophagosomes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, electron microscopy analysis revealed the autophagic vacuoles build-up in myelinized neurons of SNpc in PD patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. Arduíno et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> also showed that induction of autophagy is not primarily affected since Beclin1 levels, a principal regulator in autophagosome formation, remained unaltered in sPD transmitochondrial cybrids relatively to CT cybrids. Likewise, we do not see any difference regarding Beclin1 levels. We posit that mitochondrial dysfunction could have played a role as disease facilitators, which contributed to the observed microtubule disassembly and impaired autophagy, a disease aggravator. It is widely known that SNCA enriched protein aggregates (LBs) are one of the main pathological hallmarks of PD. Interestingly, we did not found SNCA aggregates in the hippocampus or cortex of PD patients, which excludes the spread of SNCA pathology hypothesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Importantly, we observed that SNCA oligomerization is contained in SNpc, while we see lysosomal alterations, specifically LAMP2A levels reduction in the cortex and in the hippocampus and no changes in the SNpc indicating chaperone mediated autophagy alterations in these brain areas. Since in PD patients SNpc LAMP1 and LAMP2A levels are not altered but there is an increase in LC3II levels, we hypothesize that SNCA accumulation might be due to a deficient mobilization of autophagosomes from their site of formation toward lysosomes due to disruption in microtubule-dependent trafficking or due to an impairment of autophagosome–lysosome fusion. Remarkably LAMP2A expression decreased in other 
 <italic>post-mortem</italic> PD brain samples
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>, which can be explained due to different Braak stages. Moreover, LAMP2A expression reduction was also observed in rats with targeted viral over-expression of SNCA
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. Indeed, we found alteration in autophagic markers and Aβ oligomers build-up in the hippocampus of PD patients, which indicates progression of the neurodegenerative process that is not due to SNCA spreading. Several data collected from in vitro and in vivo models found evidence of a synergistic action between SNCA and Aβ
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. In PD patients it was reported Aβ levels reduction in cerebrospinal fluid suggesting a possible contribution of Aβ not only on cognition but also on locomotor function
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, ER demise was found not only the SNpc but also in the hippocampus. Converging evidence reported the involvement of ER stress and the UPR in the pathophysiology of PD in in vivo and in vitro models of PD and in dopaminergic neurons in the SNpc of PD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. Our results lend strong support for ER and chaperone mediated autophagy demise in the hippocampus supporting hippocampus is also affected in PD late Braak stages.
</p>
