<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">With regard to the AD brain areas analysed in this study, and assuming that Braak stage III–IV fits on the aggravator phase of the disease, we observe relevant alterations in key autophagic proteins, such as increase in LC3II and p62 levels in the hippocampus and cortex, indicating that autophagosomes are being formed but accumulate probably due to a failure in lysosomal function, since we also saw a decrease in Lamp1 levels. In fact, the involvement of macroautophagy in AD neurodegenerative process was shown in neocortical biopsies from AD brain where immature autophagic vacuoles were abundant within dystrophic neurites
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, work from our group showed that in differentiated sAD patient-driven cells, autophagosomes transport velocity is decreased, therefore will not reach lysosomes for degradation of their contents contributing to a compromised autophagic flux
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. We found a decrease in CatD levels in cortical samples but an increase in the hippocampus. There is some controversy regarding lysosomal enzymes levels in association with AD. Whereas CatD has been reported to be decreased in skin fibroblasts from patients with AD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup> and in the hippocampus of the PS1M146L/APP751sl mouse model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>, this lysosomal enzyme has been shown to be elevated in the CSF in patients with AD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Chai et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> also found in neocortical regions of well characterized AD brains elevated CatD immunoreactivity. Additionally, the observed decrease in Lamp1 levels in the hippocampus and cortex of AD patients, corroborates our hypothesis that the lysosomal function may be affected. Nevertheless, Lamp1 was shown to be elevated in brain-derived blood exosomes of patients with AD compared with controls
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. We also observed a reduction in Beclin1 levels in AD susceptible areas, namely the hippocampus and cortex. Indeed, Beclin1 expression was found to be reduced in AD cybrids, as well as, in AD brain samples indicating that the initial steps of this pathway may be compromised
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. These alterations in autophagic markers correlate with the increase in Aβ oligomer levels, which is a key histopathologic feature of AD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. In this context, we also see alterations in PTMs in microtubule proteins, namely an increase in phospho-tau levels. In transgenic AD mice cytoskeletal defects were shown to be correlated with the build-up of filled autophagic vacuoles in dystrophic neurites
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, in AD cellular models tubulin acetylation was found to be reduced together with an increase of phospho and acetylated-tau. This pathway leads to microtubule disassembly which compromises autophagic vacuoles transport as observed by a decrease in the rate of LC3II degradation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. Also, confirmation from AD brain homogenates point to microtubule disassembly related with mitochondrial abnormalities before detectable NFT
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. Neuronal microtubules were found to be lessened in number and length
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>, acetylated-tubulin levels were diminished and tau phosphorylation was significantly increased
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. The selected AD cases were in mild-moderate phase (Braak stage III–IV) of the disease and so, we still detect a tendency for an activation of ER UPR. Cortical neurons exposed to Aβ show ER Ca2+ stores depletion and increased levels of ER stress markers such as GRP78 leading to the activation of an ER-mediated apoptotic cell death
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, GRP78 has been shown to be increased in AD 
 <italic>post-mortem</italic> brain tissues, demonstrating that sustained ER stress is involved in neurodegeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. In AD transgenic mice ER stress-related genes are differentially regulated during Aβ deposition in the hippocampus and cortex
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. On the other hand, in 5xFAD AD mouse model that displays aggressive amyloid pathology no elevation in the ER stress markers was found
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup>. Again, our results do not support a relevant role for the propagation of Aβ oligomers to other brain areas
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> since we show alteration in autophagy in SNpc of AD patients, proposed to be involved in the aggravator phase, but no increase in Aβ aggregates. Nonetheless, we do observe that SNCA oligomers are present in the hippocampus of AD cases, which may indicate that this event is neuronal specific. Indeed, in a mouse model of tauopathy immunohistochemistry studies showed accumulation of not only hyperphosphorylated tau but also aggregates of phosphorylated SNCA
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, SNCA is also implicated in AD pathogenesis. SNCA staining was found to be elevated in AD brain when compared to controls and as well in Tg2576 AD mice brain model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, it has been conjectured that SNCA is involved in the abnormal synapse formation in AD brain patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
