<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">As a control we used the same brain areas of VD cases to determine the specificity of the pathways altered in AD and PD. Accumulating evidence show that a large proportion of patients with dementia who have significant cerebral vascular lesions also exhibit more severe concomitant AD pathology
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>, such as deposits of hyperphosphorylated-tau and Aβ, and thus fulfil the neuropathological criteria for AD. Indeed, we found an increase in tau levels in the SNpc and in acetylated tau in the hippocampus. A report from 2015 showed a selective loss of total tau in the temporal cortex of VD patients relative to controls whereas phosphorylated tau levels remained unchanged in VD patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, VD brain blood barrier dysfunction and altered cerebrovascular permeability can result in overproduction of Aβ and oxidative stress
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>. Although elevated vascular risk may influence tau burden when coupled with high Aβ burden we do not see Aβ accumulation in VD patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>. Remarkably, we observed SNCA over-production in SNpc VD samples. Indeed, a clinicopathological study found no evidence for increased SNCA deposition in subjects with brain vascular pathological changes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. We did not see any conclusive or consistent alteration in protein expression related to autophagic-lysosomal pathway. Still, autophagy enhancement was found in animal models of VD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. It is also worth noting that this study indicates that ER stress may be a key event in VD neurodegenerative process. In fact, in a neuronal model of VD low concentrations of copper potentiate zinc-induced ER stress pathways
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, DL-3-n-butylphthalide was shown to protect against cognitive deficits in a rat model of VD by regulating ER stress-related markers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>
 </sup>. This work highlights a new conceptual model for AD and PD pathogenesis. Taking this into account we analyzed the aggravator phase in AD and PD 
 <italic>post-mortem</italic> samples and provided an updated summary of the cellular pathways and proteins involved in the pathophysiology of these neurodegenerative disorders. Of particular importance is the fact that the aggravator phase in the development of these diseases also includes microtubule-dependent transport defects that result from mitochondrial dysfunction and contribute to autophagic alterations culminating in protein aggregation. Another focus of potential significance is that Aβ accumulation was found in 
 <italic>post-mortem</italic> PD hippocampus and SNCA accumulation was found in 
 <italic>post-mortem</italic> AD hippocampus and SNpc. These results indicate an involvement of SNCA in AD and of Aβ in PD, at least in the moderate to late Braak stages. Consistently, a common feature in these disorders is protein aggregation, but our results clearly contest the prion “like” propagation hypothesis (revised in
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>), since SNCA oligomers are contained to SNpc in PD samples and Aβ aggregates only occur in the cortex and hippocampus in AD samples (revised in
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>). In summary, the aforementioned results raise the possibility that the hypothesis “triggers, facilitators and aggravators” proposed by Johnson et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> can be partially applied to both PD and AD pathogenesis (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig">16</xref>). Overall, we posit that future studies need to focus on the fact that effective treatments must be disease stage specific. 
</p>
