<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">The Flux high-performance computer cluster at the University of Michigan was used for computational analysis. Sequencing read quality was assessed using FastQC (Andrews 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2010</xref>). Reads were aligned to the human genome using STAR (Dobin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2013</xref>), with the options “outFilterMultimapNmax 10” and “sjdbScore 2”. Aligned reads were assigned to GRCh37 genes using featureCounts (Liao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2014</xref>). HTR-8/SVneo had 85.38% uniquely mapped reads. Villous explants had 82.46% uniquely mapped reads. Prior to differential gene expression testing, genes with mean read counts-per-million less than four (HTR-8/SVneo) or five (explants) across all samples were filtered out and excluded from the analysis to reduce dispersion due to low expression levels. After filtering, 12,855 (HTR-8/SVneo) or 13,972 (explants) genes were included in the analyses. Data were normalized using the trimmed mean of M values (TMM) method (Robinson and Oshlack 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2010</xref>). Differential gene expression testing was performed using the edgeR package (version 3.1) for R statistical computing (Robinson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2010</xref>). Quasi-likelihood general linear modeling was used for differential gene expression testing (Lun et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2016</xref>). For HTR-8/SVneo cells, comparisons were made within each time point between 0 (control) and 10 or 20 µM DCVC, respectively, adjusting for experiment day as a covariate using the glmQLFit function in edgeR. For villous explants, comparisons were made between 0 (control) and 20 µM DCVC, adjusting for a placental donor as a covariate. The log
 <sub>2</sub>fold change/fold change values reported for each gene were calculated from normalized (TMM method) gene expression counts averaged from each matching treatment/exposure replicate and directly compared to the average normalized gene expression counts of time-matched controls. Genes were considered differentially expressed between non-treated and treated samples with an adjusted 
 <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 using the Benjamini–Hochberg false discovery rate (FDR) method (Benjamini and Hochberg 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1995</xref>). DCVC-induced upregulation &gt; 1.3-fold or downregulation &lt; − 1.3-fold are denoted throughout the results section. These fold-change (FC) values equate to log
 <sub>2</sub> fold-change (logFC) &gt; 0.35 (upregulation) or &lt; − 0.35 (downregulation). We selected a relatively inclusive log
 <sub>2</sub> fold change threshold to facilitate discussion of our genome-wide discovery results. This selection was a balance of prioritizing genes with larger comparative gene expression changes, while still conducting a thorough evaluation of differential gene expression. Moreover, we conducted sensitive analyses to demonstrate that using a more conservative logFC cutoff does not change the overall conclusions of the paper (Suppl. Table 7).
</p>
