<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RP-LC-MS/MS/MS was performed using a nanoACQUITY UPLC system (Waters Corporation, Milford, MA, USA) connected to an Orbitrap Fusion Tribrid (ThermoFisher Scientific, San Jose, CA, USA) mass spectrometer in the MS &amp; Proteomics Resource of the Keck Foundation Biotechnology Resource Laboratory at Yale University. After injection, the samples were loaded into a trapping column (nanoACQUITY UPLC Symmetry C18 TRAP column, 180 µm × 20 mm) at a flowrate of 5 µL/min and then separated with a C18 column (nanoACQUITY column Peptide BEH C18, 75 µm × 250 mm). The compositions of mobile phases A and B were 0.1% formic acid in water and 0.1% formic acid in acetonitrile, respectively. Peptides were eluted with a gradient extending from 6% to 20% mobile phase B over 120 min and then to 40% mobile phase B for another 50 min at a flow rate of 300 nL/min and a column temperature of 37 °C. The data were acquired with the mass spectrometer operating in a top speed data-dependent mode with multinotch synchronous precursor selection (SPS)-MS3 scanning for TMT tags [
 <xref rid="B27-proteomes-08-00027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The full scan was performed over the range extending from 380–1580 m/z at an Orbitrap resolution of 120,000 at 200 m/z and automatic gain control (AGC) target value of 2 × 10
 <sup>5</sup>, with the maximum injection time set at 60 msec. Dynamic exclusion was enabled for a duration of 30 s. The most intense ions were selected above an intensity threshold of 5000 for collision-induced dissociation (CID)-MS fragmentation in the linear ion trap with collision energy of 35%. The isolation mode was set to quadrupole, and the isolation width was set to 1.6 m/z. The top 10 fragment ions for each peptide MS2 were notched out with an isolation width of 2 m/z and co-fragmented with higher-energy collision dissociation (HCD) at a collision energy of 65% to produce MS3 scans that were analyzed in the Orbitrap at a resolution of 60,000. The maximum injection time was set to 120 ms, and the AGC target value was set to 1 × 10
 <sup>5</sup>. 
</p>
