<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The DNA damage induction of the FLp53 protein results in either the arrest of cells in the G1 phase of the cell cycle [
 <xref rid="B19-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] or the induction of apoptotic cell death [
 <xref rid="B20-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], depending on cell type and other factors. In the limited studies on p53 isoforms, p53β was observed to increase in senescent cells, and induction was shown to decrease proliferation and increase cellular senescence [
 <xref rid="B8-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Thus, in order to further explore the biological outcomes related specifically to p53β expression, FLp53 or p53β was transiently or inducibly overexpressed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cancers-13-00251-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). Doxycycline-induced expression of p53β decreased cell growth compared with the induced expression of FLp53 in the absence of insult as well as in an IR dose-dependent manner (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cancers-13-00251-f002">Figure 2</xref>B). In the absence of insult, p53β expression caused a cellular senescent phenotype as indicated by G0/G1-phase growth arrest, SA-β-galactosidase (β-gal) positivity, senescence-associated secretory phenotype (SASP) induction, and p16INK4A induction, but there was no evidence of cell death (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cancers-13-00251-f002">Figure 2</xref>C). In contrast, induction of FLp53 induced signs of both apoptotic cell death and senescence (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cancers-13-00251-f002">Figure 2</xref>A,C). Since overexpression phenotypes can be misleading, we also generated cells in which p53β was specifically deleted by CRISPR-Cas9 mutagenesis; while these cells retained FLp53 expression and function, they were unable to produce p53β RNA and protein. Using these p53β-knockout cells, or by modulation of other pathway regulators (e.g., SMG1, SRSF7), we demonstrated that p53β was required for IR-induced cellular senescence in a manner dependent on SMG1, SRSF7, and p53β [
 <xref rid="B8-cancers-13-00251" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cancers-13-00251-f001">Figure 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cancers-13-00251-f002">Figure 2</xref>). 
</p>
