<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5915450</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">24344</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-24344-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Erythromycin leads to differential protein expression through differences in electrostatic and dispersion interactions with nascent proteins</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4141-1642</contrib-id><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>Hoang Linh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>Dang Lan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>Edward P.</given-names></name><address><email>epo2@psu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Mai Suan</given-names></name><address><email>masli@ifpan.edu.pl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Institute for Computational Sciences and Technology, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2097 4281</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.29857.31</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemistry, </institution><institution>Pennsylvania State University, University Park, </institution></institution-wrap>Pennsylvania, 16802 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1958 0162</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413454.3</institution-id><institution>Institute of Physics, </institution><institution>Polish Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Al. Lotnikow 32/46, 02-668 Warsaw, Poland </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>6460</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The antibiotic activity of erythromycin, which reversibly binds to a site within the bacterial ribosome exit tunnel,&#x000a0;against many gram positive microorganisms indicates that it effectively inhibits the production of proteins. Similar to other macrolides, the activity of erythromycin is far from universal, as some peptides can bypass the macrolide-obstructed exit tunnel and become partially or fully synthesized. It is unclear why, at the molecular level, some proteins can be synthesized while others cannot. Here, we use steered molecular dynamics simulations to&#x000a0;examine how erythromycin inhibits synthesis of the peptide ErmCL but not the peptide H-NS. By pulling these peptides through the exit tunnel of the <italic>E.coli</italic> ribosome with and without erythromycin present, we find that erythromycin directly interacts with both nascent peptides, but the force required for ErmCL to bypass erythromycin is greater than that of H-NS. The largest forces arise three to six residues from their N-terminus as they start to bypass Erythromycin. Decomposing the interaction energies between erythromycin and the peptides at this point, we find that there are stronger electrostatic and dispersion interactions with the more C-terminal residues of ErmCL than with H-NS. These results suggest that erythromycin slows or stalls synthesis of ErmCL compared to H-NS due to stronger interactions with particular residue positions along the nascent protein.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Antibiotics are a type of antimicrobial that kills bacteria by inhibiting their growth and replication. Antibiotics target a diverse range of molecules and processes including DNA gyrase, RNA polymerase, cell wall synthesis, metabolic pathways and protein synthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Due to the central nature of protein synthesis to life, many different antibiotics target and disrupt this process. Protein production occurs via the action of the ribosome, which covalently links amino acids together through the catalytic action of the peptidyl transferase center (PTC). Newly synthesized protein segments leave the ribosome through the exit tunnel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, a 10&#x02009;nm long, irregularly-shaped tunnel that is on average 1.5&#x02009;nm in diameter. The passage of a newly synthesized protein through the exit tunnel can be dramatically slowed due to interactions between the exit tunnel wall and sequence motifs within the primary structure of nascent proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Additionally, the binding of ligands, including antibiotics, in the exit tunnel can also inhibit protein synthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">The strong activity of ribosome-targeting macrolides against many gram-positive microorganisms indicates that they effectively inhibit protein production. Like the antibiotics chloramphenicol and puromycin, macrolides stop protein synthesis in the elongation phase of translation. However, instead of directly binding to the PTC and disrupting its structure, macrolides bind in the exit tunnel one or more nanometers from the PTC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. These macrolides decrease the diameter of the exit tunnel, leading to steric clashes with nascent peptides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. For instance, the <sup>64</sup>KVE<sup>62</sup> segment of the MarR peptide clashes with the cladinose and lactone moieties of both erythromycin (ERY) and Azithromycin (AZ) causing ribosome stalling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. In the case of the EngD peptide, only AZ induces ribosome stalling while ERY does not. The mechanism of ribosome stalling by macrolides is not limited to a narrowing of the exit tunnel. V&#x000e1;zquez-Laslop and coworkers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> showed that when the cladinose sugar group of ERY is replaced by substituents that are as bulky as cladinose, the resulting macrolide cannot stall protein synthesis. While V&#x000e1;zquez-Laslop<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, Johansson<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, and Arenz<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> and their coworkers observed that mutating amino acids in the region <sup>6</sup>IFVI<sup>9</sup> of the peptide ErmCL can relieve stalling and allow synthesis of the nascent protein. These results demonstrate that the ability of macrolides to inhibit protein synthesis involves a combination of excluded volume interactions and attractive inter-molecular interactions between the nascent protein and antibiotic.</p><p id="Par4">Although macrolides do not directly contact the PTC, the interaction between the peptide and macrolide can alter the PTC&#x02019;s structure. By hindering the movement of the peptide through the exit tunnel, the nascent chain can compress and push back on the P-site, altering the structure of nucleotides within the PTC and thereby suppress catalysis of peptide bond formation. For example, in the presence of ERY, rRNA nucleotide U2585&#x02019;s position is shifted within the tunnel, which could sterically conflict with the ErmCL nascent chain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Ramu and coworkers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> demonstrated that the presence of ERY and ErmAL1 peptide in the exit tunnel alters the properties of the A-site, preventing particular tRNA&#x02019;s from binding. The binding of macrolides in the exit tunnel can even alter the conformation of the PTC before the sequence of peptide has reached the macrolide through an allosteric mechanism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The exit tunnel can act synergistically with macrolides to inhibit protein synthesis, and altering the ribosomal nucleotides and residues that line the tunnel can lead to macrolide-resistant bacteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Mutations of the 23S ribosomal RNA (a component of the 50S ribosomal subunit) can confer macrolide resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. The mutations at A2058 and A2059, which are located on the surface of the tunnel mediate ERY resistance in multiple species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The C2610U mutation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>&#x02019;s (<italic>E. coli</italic>) ribosome reduces ERY-dependent ribosome stalling of ErmCL peptide twofold<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, implying that the interaction between the exit tunnel and macrolide plays an important role in inhibition. Mutations in other components of 50S subunit can also contribute to macrolide resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The mutation &#x00394;<sup>82</sup>MKR<sup>84</sup> in ribosomal protein L22, for example, confers antibiotic resistance in <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>Thermus thermophilus</italic> and <italic>Haloarcula marismortui</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Distinct amino acids and peptides attached to macrolide derivatives can establish interactions with components of the ribosomal tunnel that enhance the ribosome binding and inhibitory properties of macrolides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. For example, attaching Ala-Ala to the C20 aldehyde position of tylosin prevents covalent bonding between tylosin and A2062 of the ribosomal tunnel, but establishes a new interaction with the tunnel that improves inhibitory properties of tylosin.</p><p id="Par6">A fascinating characteristic of macrolides is that even when they can tightly bind to wild-type bacterial ribosomes, they cannot block the synthesis of all proteins. Kannan and coworkers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> have identified protein sequences in <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>S. aureas</italic> that can bypass the drug-obstructed tunnel to become partially or fully synthesized. A key finding is that the ability to bypass macrolides does not depend on the entire sequence of the synthesized protein, but rather on its N-terminal sequence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. The N-terminal segment of H-NS can be synthesized even when erythromycin is bound in the exit tunnel, although its movement is slowed down<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Furthermore, while the synthesis of a protein known as OsmC is inhibited by erythromycin, this inhibition is overcome when various lengths of H-NS&#x02019;s N-terminal residues are covalently attached to the N-terminus of OsmC, saturating at 12 H-NS residues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Erythromycin is still bound in the tunnel after translation of the entire H-NS protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, indicating that H-NS peptide bypasses erythromycin. Despite the important role of macrolide resistance in antibiotic development, motifs of peptides that are stalled by erythromycin, telithromycin and azithromycin have been extensively studied<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> while the identification of motifs that can bypass macrolides has received less focus.</p><p id="Par7">Here, we examine the molecular interactions that allow H-NS to&#x000a0;bypass erythromycin and prevent ErmCL from progressing through the exit tunnel using steered molecular dynamics (SMD) simulations. In SMD simulations, segments from these two proteins are pulled along the ribosome exit tunnel using an artificially imposed force at a constant velocity in the presence and absence of ERY. We find that while ERY makes it harder to pull either peptide through the tunnel exit, a much larger force and work is required to move ErmCL compared to H-NS. Decomposing the energetic components, we find the interaction energy of ErmCL with ERY is more favorable than that of H-NS. These results indicate that the differential impact of ERY on these two protein&#x02019;s arises from stronger intermolecular interactions between ERY and C-terminal residues of ErmCL than H-NS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Starting structures</title><p id="Par8">The structure of ERY bound to the <italic>E. coli</italic> ribosome was obtained from protein data bank (PDB) file with id 4V7U. Because this system is very large, ribosomal residues and bases were deleted that were more than 40&#x02009;&#x000c5; away from the center of mass of ERY. Initial structures of ErmCL (sequence: MGIFSIFVI) and H-NS (MSEALKILNNIR) peptides off of the ribosome were created using the RaptorX webserver<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and equilibrated in bulk solution using molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. Specifically, the peptides were solvated in a cubic box with TIP3P water molecules and the AMBER99SB-ILDN force field was utilized. GROMACS version 5.1.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> was used to perform the simulations. The structures were equilibrated for 200&#x02009;ps in the NVT ensemble followed by 5&#x02009;ns in the NPT ensemble at 330&#x02009;K and 1&#x02009;bar. The system was then simulated for another 100&#x02009;ns per trajectory at 330&#x02009;K in the NPT ensemble. Peptide structures that had no secondary structure were identified in the simulations and selected for later insertion into the ribosome exit tunnel. A ribosome without ERY was created by deleting ERY from the ribosome-ERY crystal structure.</p><p id="Par9">To insert the ErmCL and H-NS peptides into the truncated ribosome we used a home-made program based on an optimization algorithm named Differential Evolution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The input parameters for this program were set to a scaling factor F&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.5 and crossover probability of P<sub>c</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.9, and were&#x000a0;chosen based on trial and error attempts. The space occupied by the nascent peptide was divided into 60&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;60&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;60 discrete mesh points and the objective function defined as the number of mesh points that overlap with the ribosome. We used the additional constraint that the N-termini of the peptides be located near the base 2602 of the ribosome. As expected, after insertion the N-termini of the peptides was found to be closer to ERY than their C-termini (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The exit tunnel was aligned along the z-axis of the local coordinate system. The ribosome-peptide systems were then neutralized by adding 129 Mg<sup>2+</sup> and 186 Na<sup>+</sup> ions. Na<sup>+</sup> ions were used instead of K<sup>+</sup> ions because K<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>-</sup> can erroneously form salt crystals when using the AMBER force field. We then performed MD simulations in the gas phase for 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> integration steps, which allowed the ions to rapidly diffuse to their binding sites&#x000a0;on the ribosome. The heavy atoms of the peptide, ribosome and ERY were harmonically restrained during these simulations. The system was then solvated with TIP3P water molecules with an additional 0.1&#x02009;M Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl- ions. In total, about 30,000 water molecules were used in the simulations.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>An illustration of a starting simulation structure. The ribosome (transparent cartoon), ERY (red), and nascent chain (cyan) are shown. The black arrow indicates the pulling direction applied to the N-terminal residue of the nascent chain in the SMD simulations. The arrow also lies along the long axis of the ribosome exit tunnel. &#x0201c;Exit&#x0201d; denotes the exit side of the tunnel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e503"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>SMD simulations</title><p id="Par10">Following the conventional SMD approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, the truncated ribosome was split into three regions. Bases and residues containing one or more atoms within 28&#x02009;&#x000c5; of ERY comprised the dynamic region. The buffer region is between 28 and 34&#x02009;&#x000c5;, while the remaining portion belongs to the outer region. Atoms within the dynamic region were not subject to any restraints during the SMD simulation course, but harmonic restraints were applied to non-hydrogen atoms within the buffer and outer regions with spring constants of 5 and 10&#x02009;kcal&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> &#x000c5;<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, respectively. The ribosomes were solvated in a rectangular box with distances between the system and box edge of 12&#x02009;&#x000c5;, 12&#x02009;&#x000c5; and 28&#x02009;&#x000c5; along the <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$y$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$z$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> axes, respectively. The AMBER99SB-ILDN force field was used in the SMD simulations, whereas force-field parameters for ERY were taken from the work of Solthiselvam and coworkers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. The constant velocity and the cantilever spring constant were set to 5&#x02009;m/s in the <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$z$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>-direction and 1,000&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> nm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>. The cantilever was connected to the center of mass of the N-terminal residue of the nascent peptide. Because there is no experimental evidence that ERY diffuses out the tunnel during protein synthesis, a harmonic restraint, with a force constant of 1000&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> nm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, was applied to the heavy atom closest to the center of mass of ERY. The PME method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> was applied to calculate electrostatic interactions using a 1&#x02009;nm cutoff. We used only one starting structure for each peptide. In each SMD run, the system was first minimized by the steepest descent algorithm and equilibrated in the NVT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> ensemble for 200&#x02009;ps and then in the NPT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> ensemble for 10&#x02009;ns. The final structures from this NPT equilibration were used as starting structures for the production SMD simulations. A total of 30 and 34 SMD trajectories were performed for ErmCL and H-NS, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Mimicking nascent peptide elongation</title><p id="Par11">In order to mimic the real situation in which a new amino acid is added to a nascent peptide we first generated five different starting structures of the nascent peptide&#x000a0;using the Differential Evolution program. At the start of the simulation, only the non-bonded parameters of the first nascent peptide residue was turned on. Then, once the nascent peptide had been pulled a distance of 4&#x02009;&#x000c5; into the tunnel, the non-bonded interactions of the next residue were turned on. The structure of the system with the newly added residue was minimized by the steepest descent algorithm and equilibrated in the NVT ensemble for 20&#x02009;ps and then in the NPT ensemble for 100&#x02009;ps. This procedure was repeated until the interactions of the most C-terminal residue were turned on. After this, we continued the SMD simulations. A total of 10 trajectories were performed in this manner&#x000a0;for ErmCL and H-NS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Definitions of computed quantities</title><p id="Par12">A hydrogen bond is considered to be formed when the distance between a donor atom and acceptor is within 3.5&#x02009;&#x000c5; and the angle of the acceptor, hydrogen and donor is greater than or equal to 135 degrees. A contact between bases of the ribosome and residues of the nascent peptide is present when the distance between their respective centers of mass is less than 6.5&#x02009;&#x000c5;. The average non-bonded interaction force at a time point is calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\langle {F}_{I}\rangle }_{J}=\frac{1}{{N}_{traj}}\sum _{n=1}^{{N}_{traj}}{|\sum _{j}\overrightarrow{{F}_{IJ}}|}_{n}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02329;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x0232a;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\langle {F}_{I}\rangle }_{J}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02329;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x0232a;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the average of the magnitude of the force for all trajectories that system <italic>J</italic> acts on system <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$I$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\sum _{j}\overrightarrow{{F}_{IJ}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the force that system <italic>J</italic> acts on system <italic>I</italic> of one trajectory. <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overrightarrow{{F}_{IJ}}=\sum _{i}\overrightarrow{{F}_{ij}},$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> where <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overrightarrow{{F}_{ij}}={\overrightarrow{F}}_{electrostatic}(i,j)+{\overrightarrow{F}}_{vanderWaals}(i,j)\,\,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mspace width=".25em"/></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>is the force that atom <italic>j</italic> of system <italic>J</italic> acts on all atoms <italic>i</italic> of system <italic>I</italic>. The self non-bonded interaction force is the total force, per residue, acted on by the others. The charges and van der Waals parameters of the atoms for calculating forces are the same as in the MD simulation. The work associated with pulling the nascent chain through the tunnel was calculated by the Trapezoid Rule <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$W={\int }^{}Fdx\approx \sum _{i=1}^{N}({F}_{i+1}+{F}_{i})({x}_{i+1}-{x}_{i})/2,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-.25em"/></mml:msup><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> where <italic>i</italic> represents simulation step, <italic>F</italic> is the pulling force and <italic>x</italic> is the pulling coordinate.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>In the absence of ERY, H-NS is harder to translocate through the tunnel than ErmCL</title><p id="Par13">We used SMD simulations to calculate the pulling force versus time profiles of pulling ErmCL and H-NS through the exit tunnel in the absence of ERY (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). ErmCL has a mean rupture force, denoted <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub>, of 468.6 pN (95% CI: [442.6, 494.6]), which is lower than the 599.9 pN (95% CI: [585.2, 614.6]) value associated with H-NS (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This result is perhaps surprising because in the presence of ERY, ErmCL&#x02019;s synthesis is stalled but not that of H-NS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. The distribution of rupture forces of ErmCL are statistically different from those of H-NS (Student&#x02019;s t-test, <italic>p</italic>-value 0.007). Integrating the force profiles in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> yields the non-equilibrium work, <italic>W</italic><sub>pull</sub>, of translating these peptides whose values are 305 and 507&#x02009;kcal/mol for ErmCL and H-NS, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Therefore, there is a statistically significant difference between the distributions of <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>W</italic><sub>pull</sub> for these two peptides, indicating that H-NS interacts more strongly with the ribosome exit tunnel than ErmCL. Nevertheless, in the absence of ERY both peptides are completely synthesized<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Rupture force in the absence and presence of ERY in the exit tunnel.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Rupture force (pN)</th><th>ErmCL</th><th>H-NS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Without ERY</td><td>468.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;26.0</td><td>599.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.7</td></tr><tr><td>With ERY</td><td>2639.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;119.8</td><td>1394.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;88.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Nonequilibrium work in the absence and presence of ERY in the exit tunnel.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><italic>W</italic><sub>pull</sub> (kcal/mol)</th><th>ErmCL</th><th>H-NS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Without ERY</td><td>305.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;24.0</td><td>507.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20.1</td></tr><tr><td>With ERY</td><td>2009.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;122.7</td><td>1267.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;106.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>In the presence of ERY, ErmCL is harder to translocate through the tunnel than H-NS</title><p id="Par14">The presence of ERY changes not only the magnitude of rupture force but also the shape of the force versus time profile. For ErmCL, the mean-maximum-rupture force is increased dramatically from 469 pN to 2,640 pN. Moreover, sharp peaks in the force profiles appear in the presence of ERY (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). These results indicate that the presence of ERY in the exit tunnel impedes the movement of ErmCL through the tunnel. In the case of H-NS, the presence of ERY also increases its mean-maximum-rupture force from 599.9 to 1,394 pN, however, the rupture force is nearly half that of ErmCL. Additionally, the distribution of rupture forces is statistically different between the two peptides in the presence of ERY (Student&#x02019;s t-test, <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.43&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>). Thus, ERY has a greater impact on the translocation of ErmCL than H-NS.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Pulling force versus time from the SMD simulations of (<bold>A</bold>) ErmCL and (<bold>B</bold>) H-NS with ERY bound in the exit tunnel. Black lines represent the average force across trajectories, while gray lines are the force traces for each individual trajectory.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1229"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">The non-equilibrium work of translocating these peptides also leads to similar conclusions (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), as <italic>W</italic><sub>pull</sub> equals 2,009.6 (95% CI: [1886.9, 2132.3]) and 1,267.8 (95% CI: [1161.4, 1374.2]) kcal/mol for ErmCL and H-NS, respectively. The difference between the work distributions is statistically significant (Student&#x02019;s t-test test, <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$p$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.62&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>). Thus, ErmCL needs more energy to translocate through the exit tunnel than H-NS. Because <italic>W</italic><sub>pull</sub> correlates with binding affinity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, ErmCL is expected to interact with ERY and the ribosome more strongly than H-NS. Therefore, the results from <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>W</italic><sub>pull</sub> are consistent with the experiments showing that the translation of ErmCL is stalled by ERY, while H-NS can bypass it.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Robustness of results to changes in pulling speed</title><p id="Par16">To determine whether these conclusions are sensitive to the pulling speed used in the SMD simulations we have performed simulations in which the pulling speed is&#x000a0;5-fold larger, <italic>i.e. v</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;25&#x02009;m/s. Compared to the 5&#x02009;m/s case, the rupture force and non-equilibrium work are higher for both ErmCL and H-NS. However, ErmCL still has a larger <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>W</italic><sub>pull</sub> than H-NS (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>) indicating that, consistent with the&#x000a0;slower pulling speed, ErmCL is harder to pull through the tunnel than H-NS. Thus, our conclusions&#x000a0;do not depend on pulling speed. In the rest of this study we report results in which v&#x02009;=&#x02009;5&#x02009;m/s in the SMD simulations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>N-terminal residues bypassing ERY experience the largest forces</title><p id="Par17">To determine why ErmCL&#x02019;s maximum pulling force is higher than that of H-NS&#x02019;s we first calculated the average force acting on each residue along the nascent chain when <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> occurs in the individual trajectories, because at this point there is the greatest opposition to protein movement through the tunnel. We find that for both peptides, their N-terminal residues have larger forces acting on them than their C-terminal residues (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). And that ErmCL&#x02019;s first two N-terminal residues experience around a 70% greater force than in H-NS (compare Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A,B</xref>). This suggests that the differential behavior of ErmCL and H-NS in the presence of ERY originates at their N-terminal residues.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Average force per atom experienced by nascent chain residues at <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${F}_{{\max }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for (<bold>A</bold>) ErmCL and (<bold>B</bold>) H-NS. Above each data point the &#x02018;+/&#x02212;&#x02019; signs indicate&#x000a0;whether, on average, the force was attractive or repulsive, respectively. Error bars represent the 95% confidence interval about the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1343"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">We hypothesized that structurally, the largest forces in the force profiles (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) are generated when the peptides are passing through the constricted space formed between ERY and the exit tunnel wall. To test this, we determined the average distance between the center of mass (COM) of each nascent chain residue and ERY (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) when <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> occurred in the individual trajectories. We find that for both peptides the N-terminal residue is closest to ERY at <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub>, and the C-terminal residues are increasingly further away. Thus, for both peptides, the largest forces arise as the N-terminal residues attempt to bypass ERY.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Average distance (&#x000c5;) between COMs of residues of nascent peptides and COM of ERY at <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Residue</th><th>ErmCL</th><th>H-NS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td>10.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>8.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td>9.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>11.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td>9.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>15.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td>11.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>18.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td>13.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>21.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td>15.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>25.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td>18.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>28.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td>21.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>32.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td>24.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>N/A</td><td>27.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.8</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>N/A</td><td>31.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>N/A</td><td>33.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par19">As follows from Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, the residues at the N-terminus appear to play a decisive role in ribosome stalling, but this contradicts experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> which have found that more C-terminal residues of ErmCL are important. In the next section we show that this discrepancy can be resolved by taking into account the fact that amino acids are added one&#x000a0;at a time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Gradual addition of amino acids to a&#x000a0;growing nascent peptide</title><p id="Par20">The results presented thus far are from simulations in which the entire nascent peptide is present at all times during the simulation, which does not reflect what happens during protein synthesis. It is therefore possible that our results are affected by interactions between residues that would not normally be present at a given point during synthesis, and the rest of the system. To address this issue we more accurately modeled the synthesis process by only turning on non-bonded interactions of nascent peptide residues as they pass 4&#x02009;&#x000c5;&#x02019;s into the exit tunnel, which is the approximate distance between successive amino acids.</p><p id="Par21">Using five different starting structures, ten simulation trajectories were simulated to obtain the force-time profiles shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. The mean rupture forces of ErmCL and H-NS are 2,242 and 1,359 pN, respectively, indicating that ErmCL is harder to pull through the tunnel (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The non-equilibrium work also leads to a similar conclusion (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Thus, these results are in agreement with our earlier simulations.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Pulling force versus time from the SMD simulations in which the non-bonded parameters are turned on gradually as nascent chain residues enter the exit tunnel for ErmCL (<bold>A</bold>) and H-NS (<bold>B</bold>) with ERY bound in the exit tunnel. Black lines represent the average force across trajectories, while gray lines are the force traces for each individual trajectory.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1557"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Nonequilibrium work and rupture force in the presence of ERY in the exit tunnel when the non-bonded parameters of residues of nascent peptides are turned on by sequence.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>ErmCL</th><th>H-NS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>W</italic><sub>pull</sub> (kcal/mol)</td><td>1441.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;286.8</td><td>957.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;192.0</td></tr><tr><td>Rupture force (pN)</td><td>2242.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;374.8</td><td>1358.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;278.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par22">As done before, we computed the force experienced at each residue position when the maximum force occurs. We find different results (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>)&#x000a0;for these simulations. For ErmCL, residue 1 seems to substantially contribute to stalling but the strong interaction with ERY is compensated by interaction with ribosome. Residues 6 and 8 experience the largest force, indicating that the C-terminus needs more energy for passage through the tunnel than the N-terminus. Furthermore, residue 4 is closest to ERY at <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>), and, within error, residues 3, 5 and 6 are also close to ERY suggesting that residues 3 through 6 are located near ERY when ErmCL attempts to bypass it. These findings are consistent with experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> showing that C-terminus of the ErmCL motif is critical for stalling and that residues 4&#x02013;6 are located next to ERY. Our results also indicate that turning on non-bonded interactions residue-by-residue, which better mimics the protein synthesis process, allows the nascent peptide to better adapt to the presence of ERY during equilibration. In the earlier simulations the nascent peptide apparently did not have enough time to adapt to the presence of ERY, leading to a strong interaction of the N-terminal residues with ERY.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Average force per atom experienced by nascent chain residues at <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${F}_{{\max }}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for (<bold>A</bold>) ErmCL and (<bold>B</bold>) H-NS with non-bonded interactions are turned on one by one. The &#x02018;+/&#x02212;&#x02019; signs refer to attractive or repulsive forces, respectively. Error bars represent the 95% confidence interval about the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1655"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Average distance (&#x000c5;) between COMs of residues of nascent peptides and COM of ERY at <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> with non-bonded parameters turned on one by one residue.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Residue</th><th>ErmCL</th><th>H-NS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>16.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.2</td><td>19.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.6</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>12.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.2</td><td>16.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.8</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>11.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8</td><td>15.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>9.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1</td><td>15.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>11.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8</td><td>14.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>11.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7</td><td>17.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>13.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.5</td><td>18.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>14.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.3</td><td>19.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.4</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>16.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.4</td><td>21.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.7</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>N/A</td><td>22.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.0</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>N/A</td><td>25.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.5</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>N/A</td><td>29.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par23">For H-NS, the N-terminus has stronger interactions with ERY than its C-terminus (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), as found in the earlier simulations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). However, because H-NS has more time to adapt to the presence of ERY in this SMD setup, the rupture force becomes weaker. At <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> the COM distance between ERY and residue 5 is minimal (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>), but in contrast to ErmCL, the weak interaction between the C-terminus of H-NS and ERY (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>, note the ~5-fold smaller interaction force in this figure compared to Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>) allows H-NS to bypass ERY easier. The importance of the C-terminus in H-NS&#x02019;s ability to evade inhibition by ERY was also confirmed experimentally by Kannan <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Therefore, in the analyses that follow, we focus on these simulations as they better mimic protein synthesis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>The contribution of erythromycin to the forces the nascent chain experiences</title><p id="Par24">To identify the molecular origins of the differential behavior of ErmCL and H-NS in our simulations we need to decompose the interactions of their residues with the ribosome and ERY. To determine the relative contribution of the ERY-Ribosome complex to the forces acting on ErmCL and H-NS, we calculated the forces arising from interactions of the&#x000a0;nascent chain with the tunnel wall, and&#x000a0;with ERY. These forces were calculated as a time series and normalized by the number of atoms in each component, with all of the trajectories post-processed to align the occurrence of their <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> value at <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0. We observe that when <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> occurs (at <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0), ErmCL experiences a higher interaction force with ERY than H-NS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6A</xref>) as well as a 2-fold larger interaction force with the ribosome tunnel (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6B</xref>). This indicates that both ERY and the tunnel play a role in the force difference experienced by ErmCL and H-NS as they move through the exit tunnel, with the tunnel and ERY impinging more on ErmCL than H-NS.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Average interaction force experienced by nascent chain atoms with ERY and the ribosome when we turned on non-bonded parameters one by one residue. (<bold>A</bold>) Average non-bonded interaction force, per nascent chain atom, between the nascent chain and Erythromycin. (<bold>B</bold>) Average non-bonded interaction force, per nascent chain atom, between the nascent chains and the ribosome. Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals. Line is to guide the eye and does not represent a model. Note well, the individual trajectory force traces were first aligned such that <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> occurs at time equal to zero, and then the average across trajectories was calculated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1900"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Electrostatic and dispersion interactions drive ERY&#x02019;s differential impact on ErmCL</title><p id="Par25">To determine which non-bonded interaction energies contribute the most to <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub>, we calculated the electrostatic and dispersion interaction force components between each nascent-chain residue and the tunnel wall and erythromycin at <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub>. We observe in both peptides the N-terminal residue exhibits electrostatic repulsion with ERY and attractive dispersion interactions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The stronger interaction with ERY of the C-terminus compared to N-terminus of ErmCL come from dispersion interactions of residues 6 and 8 and the electrostatic interaction of residue 9 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7A</xref>). The strong dispersion force between residue 6 and ERY implies that this residue is important in ribosome stalling. This result is consistent with Arenz <italic>et al</italic>.&#x02019;s report that hydrophobic amino acids at position 6 maintain the stalling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. In the case of H-NS, the N-terminal interactions of residues 1, 3 and 6 with ERY are dominant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7B</xref>). Furthermore, the non-bonded forces between ERY and ErmCL&#x02019;s C-terminus are mainly attractive while in H-NS residues 1 and 6 exhibit repulsive electrostatic forces. This suggests that the differential impact that ERY has on ErmCL and H-NS&#x02019;s motion through the tunnel arises from the larger electrostatic and dispersion forces their C-terminal residues experience.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Force decomposition into electrostatic and van der Waals interactions between the nascent chains and ERY or the ribosome in the simulations in which non-bonded interactions are turned on as residues enter the exit tunnel. (<bold>A</bold>) Non-bonded interaction force at <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> between ErmCL&#x02019;s residues ERY or the ribosome. (<bold>B</bold>) Non-bonded interaction force at <italic>F</italic><sub>max</sub> between H-NS&#x02019;s residues and ERY or the ribosome. Above each data point the &#x02018;+/&#x02212;&#x02019; signs indicate, on average, whether the force was attractive or repulsive, respectively. Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1957"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Discussion and Conclusions</title><p id="Par26">We have performed two sets of SMD simulations. In the first set, protein synthesis was not been taken into account, <italic>i.e</italic>., the nascent peptide was treated as a preformed chain. In the second set each amino acid was added onto the peptide by gradually turning on its non-bonded interactions as it moved into the exit tunnel. We observed that in both sets of simulations it is harder to move ErmCL through the tunnel than H-NS (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). However, the interactions of individual nascent chain residues with ERY are different between the two sets of simulations. In the first set, the differential impact of ERY on ErmCL compared to H-NS arises in part from stronger intermolecular interactions between the N-terminal residues of ErmCL and ERY (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), at which point the N-terminal nascent-chain residues are sandwiched between ERY and the ribosome exit tunnel (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). In the second set of simulations, however, residues that were more C-terminal (residues 3 through 6) in ErmCL experienced the largest forces and therefore are more likely to contribute stalling. The interaction forces between ErmCL and ERY and the ribosome were about two-fold higher than the interaction forces of H-NS with these components (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Decomposing the pair-wise interactions, we observed that when the maximum force occurs, ErmCL experiences larger electrostatic and dispersion interaction forces with ERY than H-NS does (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Thus, ERY opposes the movement of both peptides through the tunnel, but the interactions with more C-terminal residues of ErmCL lead to even greater opposition than H-NS.</p><p id="Par27">Other sequence features might also contribute to the differential impact of ERY. In ErmCL, residues 6I, 8&#x02009;V and 9I of ErmCL are highly hydrophobic (with hydropathy indices for V and I of 4.5 and 4.2, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>) suggesting hydrophobic interactions might be important to ERY-driven ribosome stalling. Moreover, the average per-residue hydropathy index of ErmCL (25.2/9&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.8) is larger compared to H-NS (20.3/12&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.7). This suggests the possibility that the higher the hydrophobicity of the nascent peptide the greater the likelihood of arrest by ERY. This notion is supported by experimental data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> showing that the mutation F7A in ErmCL, which reduces the hydropathy index by 1.0 (hydropathy index of F and A is equal 2.8 and 1.8, respectively), promotes translocation of ErmCL through the tunnel exit.</p><p id="Par28">Another sequence difference that might be important is that H-NS contains a positively charged residue K at position 6 that experiences a repulsive interaction with ERY which also carries a positive charge&#x02009;+1e (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). This repulsive electrostatic interaction might facilitate H-NS bypassing of ERY. Thus, a nascent peptide containing residues that have a charge opposite to that of the macrolide might be more likely to be arrested. Taken together, the results and implications of this study could be tested by making mutations in the nascent chain that alter its hydrophobic or charge characteristics at residue positions that experience the largest force in our simulations.</p><p id="Par29">In these simulations we applied a pulling force to the N-terminus of the nascent chain. In contrast, a transient pushing force may be experienced on the C-terminus of the nascent peptide as the A-site tRNA moves from the classical (A/A) to hybrid (P/A) to translocated (P/P) state. Once the tRNA has translocated to the P-site there should be little to no pushing force present (as the C-terminus is no longer moving), and the nascent chain can relax under the new conditions. Thus, provided quasi-equilibrium conditions are achieved under these conditions, and in the simulation conditions, the two situations should yield similar results. While the SMD simulations are clearly out-of-equilibrium, the robustness of our conclusions to varying the pulling speed suggests our results are independent of the irreversible pulling force.</p><p id="Par30">Other molecular mechanisms have been identified or suggested to be the cause of ERY&#x02019;s differential impact, such as the perturbed conformation of A76 in the P-site, which can lead to a decrease in translation rate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, or the reorientation of A2062 and A2503 that might allosterically affect the A-site crevice nucleotides thereby preventing peptide bond formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. However, the mechanism we have identified is not mutually exclusive with these other mechanisms. The delay of nascent peptide movement past ERY, which our results suggest occurs, could change the PTC configuration due to a pile up of residues near the PTC.</p><p id="Par31">Limitations of this study include the perennial issue of the accuracy of the all-atom force field employed and the rapid translocation of the peptide through the exit tunnel in the simulations. The all-atom force field we used is among one of the most accurate and successful in terms of ribosome simulations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The rapid translocation of the peptide was necessary so as to obtain results in a realistic time frame. It is possible that the forces experienced by the peptide could change as the translocation speed is decreased. However, we have shown that even if this is the case, the qualitative differences we observed between ErmCL and H-NS (larger forces for ErmCL as compared to H-NS) are likely to persist. Thus, while the exact numbers may change, the trends and conclusions are not likely to.</p><p id="Par32">More generally, this study illustrates the utility of using Steered Molecular Dynamics simulations to understand the mechanisms by which an antibiotic can act on a biological process. The 100-fold speed up of SMD simulations over conventional MD methods suggests that it may be possible to utilize a similar approach to screen potential antibiotics for their ability to inhibit protein synthesis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec16"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_24344_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supporting information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-24344-9.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are indebted to Dr. Bo Liu for providing us the topology file of ERY. This work was supported by Department of Science and Technology at Ho Chi Minh city, Vietnam (grant 179/2016/HD-SKHCN), and the Polish NCN grant 2015/19/B/ST4/02721, Poland (to MSL), and by NSF grant 1553291 (to EPO). Allocation of CPU time at the supercomputer center TASK in Gdansk (Poland) is highly appreciated.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>N.L., E.P.O. and M.L. designed the project. N.L. and P.L. carried out the simulations and analysis. N.L., E.P.O. and M.L. wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par33">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribosome-targeting antibiotics and mechanisms of bacterial resistance</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3155</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24336183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nissen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structural basis of ribosome activity in peptide bond synthesis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>920</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.289.5481.920</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10937990?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10937990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Puglisi</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Dynamics of SecM-Induced Translational Stalling</article-title><source>Cell Rep.</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1521</fpage><lpage>1533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.04.033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24836001?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mankin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vazquez-Laslop</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Programmed drug-dependent ribosome stalling</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2008.06576.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19170872?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19170872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinct XPPX sequence motifs induce ribosome stalling, which is rescued by the translation elongation factor EF-P</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>15265</fpage><lpage>15270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1310642110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24003132?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24003132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez-Laslop</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of antibiotic ligand in nascent peptide-dependent ribosome stalling</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>10496</fpage><lpage>10501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1103474108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21670252?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21670252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arenz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blast from the Past: Reassessing Forgotten Translation Inhibitors, Antibiotic Selectivity, and Resistance Mechanisms to Aid Drug Development</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2015.10.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26585390?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26585390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohara</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>M-NF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence selectivity of macrolide-induced translational attenuation</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>15379</fpage><lpage>15384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1410356111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25313041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25313041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vazquez-Laslop</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mankin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Mechanism of Drug-Dependent Ribosome Stalling</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.02.026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18439898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18439898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Puglisi</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence-Dependent Elongation Dynamics on Macrolide-Bound Ribosomes</article-title><source>Cell Rep.</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1534</fpage><lpage>1546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.04.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24836000?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arenz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drug Sensing by the ribosome induces translational arrest via active site perturbation</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2014.09.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25306253?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25306253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nascent peptide in the ribosome exit tunnel affects functional properties of the A-site of the peptidyl transferase center</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.12.031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21292164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21292164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sothiselvam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Macrolide antibiotics allosterically predispose the ribosome for translation arrest</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>9804</fpage><lpage>9809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1403586111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24961372?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24961372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Va&#x02019;zquez-Laslop</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mankin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective protein synthesis by ribosomes with a drug-obstructed exit tunnel</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.09.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23101624?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23101624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Va&#x000b4;zquez-Laslop</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Klepacki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mankin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The key function of a conserved and modified rRNA residue in the ribosomal response to the nascent peptide</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>3108</fpage><lpage>3117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2010.180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20676057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weisblum</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Erythromycin resistance by ribosome modification</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>1995</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>577</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.39.3.577</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7793855?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7793855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vester</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Douthwaite</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macrolide resistance conferred by base substitutions in 23S rRNA</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>2001</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.45.1.1-12.2001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11120937?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlberg</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Erythromycin resistance mutations in ribosomal proteins L22 and L4 perturb the higher order structure of 23 S ribosomal RNA</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1999.2839</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10369764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10369764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revisiting the mechanism of macrolide-antibiotic resistance mediated by ribosomal protein L22</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>18261</fpage><lpage>18266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0810357105</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19015512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starosta</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interplay between the ribosomal tunnel, nascent chain, and macrolides influences drug inhibition</article-title><source>Cell Chem. Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>514</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The general mode of translation inhibition by macrolide antibiotics</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>15958</fpage><lpage>15963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1417334111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25349425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25349425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Template-based protein structure modeling using the RaptorX web server</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2012.085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22814390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GROMACS: High performance molecular simulations through multi-level parallelism from laptops to supercomputers</article-title><source>SoftwareX</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.softx.2015.06.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential evolution&#x02013;a simple and efficient heuristic for global optimization over continuous spaces</article-title><source>Journal of Global Optimization</source><year>1997</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008202821328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sergei</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepaniants</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Balsera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oono</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular dynamics study of unbinding of the avidin-biotin complex</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>1997</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1568</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(97)78804-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9083662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Essmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A smooth particle mesh Ewald method</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1995</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>8577</fpage><lpage>8593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.470117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bussi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Donadio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canonical sampling through velocity rescaling</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2007</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>014101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.2408420</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17212484?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17212484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphic transitions in single crystals: A new molecular dynamics method</article-title><source>J. Appl. Phys.</source><year>1981</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>7182</fpage><lpage>7190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.328693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vuong</surname><given-names>QV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A New Method for Navigating Optimal Direction for Pulling Ligand from Binding Pocket: Application to Ranking Binding Affinity by Steered Molecular Dynamics</article-title><source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source><year>2015</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>2731</fpage><lpage>2738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jcim.5b00386</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26595261?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26595261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method for displaying the hydropathic character of a protein</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1982</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2836(82)90515-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7108955?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7108955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arenz, S. <italic>et al</italic>. A combined cryo-EM and molecular dynamics approach reveals the mechanism of ErmBL-mediated translation arrest. <italic>Nat. Commun</italic>. <bold>7</bold> (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>N-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cieplak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free energy profile of RNA hairpins: a molecular dynamics simulation study</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2009.10.040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20159159?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20159159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spasic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Serafini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Amber ff99 force field predicts relative free energy changes for RNA helix formation</article-title><source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2497</fpage><lpage>2505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct300240k</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23112748?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindorff-Larsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How robust are protein folding simulations with respect to force field parameterization?</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>L47</fpage><lpage>L49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2011.03.051</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21539772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21539772</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>