<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>In the past 10 to 15 years, the dynamic range of in situ DSC on age-hardening alloys has been substantially extended, particularly in terms of continuous cooling experiments. A range of cooling rates from about 3 × 10
   <sup>−4</sup> to 3 K/s can now be applied in a reliable analysis method using direct, in situ DSC experiments. Based on a typical temperature interval for the cooling of light metal alloys from solution treatment, this is equivalent to cooling durations ranging from several weeks up to a few minutes.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>By combining direct, in situ DSC measurements with indirect DSC measurements where no direct measurement is possible, the accessible cooling rate range is extended to 10 orders of magnitude, from about 10
   <sup>−5</sup> to 10
   <sup>5</sup> K/s. When applied to the cooling of aluminium alloys from solution annealing, this corresponds to cooling over several months down to cooling within several hundredths of a second.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The key features which make these in situ DSC analyses of solid-solid phase transformation possible are as follows: 
   <list list-type="simple">
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Measurement and evaluation of the specific excess heat capacity;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Taking great care with the accuracy of the DSC zero level; and</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <label>○</label>
     <p>Consideration of a large dynamic range of heating or cooling rates as well as the analysed scales of microstructural changes.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>DSC provide crucial information for choosing appropriate heat treatment parameters for age-hardening alloys based on in situ experiments. This holds for the solution treatment (heating rates, solution temperature and soaking duration) and particularly for quenching.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The new DSC methods have also been successfully adapted and applied to the analysis of solid-solid phase transformations in other precipitation hardening alloy systems, including Mg alloys, precipitation-hardening martensitic steels and Ni-based alloys.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
