<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Available evidence demonstrates that the level of amino acids especially arginine uptake by mammary is much higher than the level secreted in milk [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Further meta-analysis by Lapierre proved that the average uptake: output ratio averages 2.45 no matter the protein sources or levels [
 <xref rid="B25-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], which might indicate that the arginine that had been taken basically does not participate in the formation of structural protein of the mammary gland. Similarly, Mezl and Knox (1977) [
 <xref rid="B26-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] observed a significant conversion of arginine to proline and glutamate in lactating rat mammary gland, with conversion increasing as milk production rose suggesting a dominant disposition of excess arginine in the gland. O’Quinn et al. (2002) [
 <xref rid="B27-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] pointed out that proline, ornithine and urea were the major products of arginine catabolism in lactating porcine mammary tissue. Together, data suggested that most arginine from plasma to mammary cannot participate in milk synthesis or tissue accretion directly. However, the present study showed positively larger alveolar cells in mammary tissue in response to dietary arginine we hypothesized. Thus, this effect probably was not only caused directly by increased concentration of arginine but also indirectly through its metabolism. Arginine is the precursor of NO and polyamines which are bioactive molecules stimulating cell proliferation and migration, cell recombination, angiogenesis, dilatation and increased blood flow in mammary thereby increasing the uptake of nutrients [
 <xref rid="B28-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Mateo et al. (2008) [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] found that supplementing L-arginine to the diets of primiparous sows could enhance milk production. Arginine-enriched or citrulline-abundant foods are supposed to have great potential to enhance NO production and cell proliferation in mammary tissue [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
