<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present study, by means of predicting target genes of the five miRNAs via different web-based tools, we further observed 15 target genes upregulated significantly including Mkrn2, Slfn3, Mex3c, Rnf185, Ndrg3, Tgoln2, Dhx15, Slc22a5, Casp3, Tmem178a, E1td1 (Adgrl4), Hsp90b1, Tmem30a, Ppp1r2 and Agt and two genes, Atp51 and 15-Seq, downregulated by arginine supplementation. This further indicated the direction in which arginine affects specific genes based on miRNAs. These target genes represent various functions regulating the biological processes involved in growth, energy, immunity, nervous system and tumor development. Among these genes, some particular upregulated genes whose expression is associated with hematopoiesis and angiogenesis, for example, Eltd1 (Adgrl4) which was highly expressed in microvascular endothelium has been reported to contribute to the development and homeostasis of the vascular system [
 <xref rid="B43-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Angiotensinogen (Agt) is a precursor of angiotensin II (Ang II), an octapeptide pressor hormone that has a key role in mediating vascular constriction and regulating salt and fluid homeostasis [
 <xref rid="B44-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Other target genes else also have similar biological function including Makrin2 [
 <xref rid="B45-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and Ndrg3 [
 <xref rid="B46-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Based on the upregulation of target genes, we propose that the physiological phenomenon of hematopoiesis and angiogenesis is a significant part of mammary tissue activated by metabolism of arginine. However, we also acknowledge that the prediction of miRNA target genes is based on several classical tools. Recently, new prediction tools like AmiRNA designer [
 <xref rid="B47-animals-11-00535" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] based on the thermodynamic analysis of the native miRNA/miRNA* and miRNA/target duplexes that allow researchers to perform analysis of natural miRNAs is worthy to try in the future study.
</p>
