<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">One of the most interesting findings is that most DETFs share one common characteristic: they have been associated with developmental processes involving mesodermal derivatives. Many of them have been shown to activate or inhibit processes leading to muscle, cartilage, or bone formation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. In many cases they are involved in keeping cells in an immature state or inhibiting their differentiation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, some are directly associated with the formation of digestive system organs, such as the liver, pancreas, cloaca, stomach and even with enterocyte identity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup>. Among these factors we found various transcripts associated with developmental-related homeobox family of genes. Our results show activation of MKX, HMX, TAP26 and DLX5 at day 1, while inhibition of HLX, EMX1 and CDX1 is observed for the same day. This contrasting expression trend is particular of homeobox genes, which are characterized by their dynamic expression pattern as shown by members of the Hox family during sea urchin development
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>. Although homeobox TFs appear to be involved in countless mechanisms, functions associated with MKX, HLX and CDX1 are worth mentioning. MKX has been shown to have a role as a regulator of collagen production
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>, a structural protein previously shown to have important implications during intestine regeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. As for HLX and CDX1, their implication in enteric nervous system and intestine development
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup> makes them interesting study targets. This activity could also be associated with downregulation of neurogenic associated transcripts observed when comparing day 3 versus 1 (see Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S8</xref> online). Previous studies from our group have shown that an important plexus made up of nerves and fibers is present in the intestinal mesentery
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Following evisceration, the plexus connection to the intestinal tissues is lost, since the latter have been eliminated. Thus, many of the axons connecting the mesentery to the intestine would have been severed. Morphological changes induced by the evisceration have been documented including the disorganization of the fiber tracts and their retraction at the regenerating end
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, it can be hypothesized that significant changes in nervous system gene expression are taking place during early regeneration stages.
</p>
