<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">In the present study, using RNA-seq, we have constructed a large-scale differential gene expression profile of the regenerating intestine in 
 <italic>H. glaberrima</italic>. We validated our results by comparing the expression of genes between our database and expression trends using different methods in previous studies. Results showed an identical expression pattern in the early, 1- and 3-days post evisceration (dpe) stages. Among the genes showing parallel upregulated expression between RNA-seq and previous methods, we found genes encoding proteins involved in cell differentiation and proliferation as in the case of Myc and Mtf
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, β-catenin showed no considerable change of expression in early stages from previous studies using RT-qPCR, and no changes were observed in our RNA-Seq results
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Other methods to detect gene expression were also found to give consistent results with our data. For instance, northern blot analysis of Serum amyloid A expression showed upregulation during day 3 of regeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. We found an increase in the expression of its mRNA at the same stage with RNA-seq. Furthermore, in situ hybridization studies, although not quantitative, do show differences in mRNA expression that coincide with our data. In this case, WNT9, BMP and mortalin showed considerable increased labeling in the early regenerate, while survivin appeared to have scarce and dispersed labeling in the regenerating mesenteric region
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. Finally, we applied the RT-qPCR method to validate the expression of 7 genes with 12 expression values from day 1 and 3 of regeneration. The analysis showed a high correlation using both methods, thus reassuring the reliability of the analysis obtained in our experimental approach to study early stages of intestinal regeneration in 
 <italic>H. glaberrima</italic>.
</p>
