<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">Both functional and signal pathway analyses point out to certain activities that are central to the regeneration process. Overall upregulated transcripts were mostly involved with transcriptional processes, translation, and protein transport. This was expected as the regenerative process requires expression of abundant components for reconstitution of lost tissues. Post-translational protein processing and proteasome related pathways were also represented in the results. Both mechanisms appear to be evidently important for cell renewal especially the former which is needed for enzymatic modifications following synthesis. Proteasome-related transcripts have been previously observed to be upregulated during intestinal regeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup> and activity of the proteasome complex has been classified as indispensable for stem cell maintenance
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Proteasome activity is also important in cell signaling as the degradation of particular proteins can cause large shifts in cell processes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. Downregulated GO terms include cell adhesion, which comprise proteins with diverse expression patterns such as the cadherins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. A possible reduction in cell adhesion is consistent with mesenterial cell migration toward the forming blastema and with EMT events. In this respect it is interesting to highlight the observed correlation of certain TFs expression with genes associated with cell adhesion. Immune system at day 1 appears surprising given the fact that this activity is believed to be activated during regeneration and previous studies have shown representation of inflammatory response terms at day 3
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. However, there are no studies analyzing expression patterns as early as day 1, which could indicate a late immune response in the beginning of the process. There is also evidence of positive regeneration response by suppression of the immune response in tadpole tail regeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>, which highlights the puzzling role of this complex network in regeneration. The term peroxisome pathway in this downregulated group, suggests a decreased activity towards removal of reactive oxygen species (ROS). The importance of ROS has been documented in various regeneration model organisms for its positive effect during regeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Finally, and worth highlighting, the phagosome related pathway was represented in upregulated and downregulated transcripts for day 3. This tendency results from similar DEGs of actin and tubulin involved in phagosome motility and structure
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. However, transcripts grouped in both expression trends were different, e.g. tubulin alpha-1A in downregulated and tubulin beta-4B in upregulated. Additionally, there were a greater number of transcripts promoting the phagocytic process in upregulated transcripts such as calnexin and calreticulin, two pro-phagocytic proteins with chaperone activity in endoplasmic reticulum
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
