<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a recent study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], multiple molecular profile data of LUAD for the CAMDA 2014 lung adenocarcinoma challenge data provided by ICGC is analyzed and it is noted that EGFR signaling pathway plays a significant role among the patients. Besides, it is known that EGFR activation initiates RAS signaling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and EGFR induces rapid increase in number of epithelial cells by activating a network of signaling elements, including members of the RAS and PI3K [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Thus, it is common for lung cancer patients to have active EGFR mutation. Moreover, the RTK/RAS/RAF pathway, identified as the main route in causing adenocarcinoma, is shown to be activated in patients with “common” pathway mutations, e.g., in KRAS, BRAF, and EGFR [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Although the EGFR kinase inhibitor Gefitinib is an effective treatment for lung cancers with EGFR activating mutations, amplification of MET causes Gefitinib resistance by driving ERBB3 (HER3)–dependent activation of PI3K [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], a pathway thought to be specific to EGFR/ERBB family receptors. This fact, along with the fact that MET has been found in the module of the “progression” group but not in that of the “complete remission” group in PI3K signaling pathway of LUAD (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) in our current study, suggest that the patients under study might have been treated with Gefitinib, but the presence of MET in some of these patients (those in the “progression” group) may have led to the resistance to this drug. However, this is subject to verification as we don’t have the information regarding the treatment regime for any of these patients. This highlights the potential role of MET in lung cancer progression.
</p>
