<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f3">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Schematic illustrations of the two-phase quasi-equilibrium.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>a</bold>) Schematic binary phase diagram. The green solid lines represent the equilibrium liquidus line, the solution limit of β-Ti and the eutectic line. The left two red dashed lines describe the beginning stage at which β-Ti or other crystalline phases begin to precipitate in the undercooled melt at the cooling rate representing the ingot with a weight of 100 g. β-Ti begins to precipitate as the melt is cooled down and intersects the red dashed lines, and the composition of β-Ti is 
   <inline-formula id="d33e1594">
    <inline-graphic id="d33e1595" xlink:href="srep19235-m56.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>. It is slightly richer in solute (Cu and Co) than its equilibrium composition (the far right green line). For higher cooling rates, the degree of undercooling increases
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref> and thus the red dashed lines shift to lower temperatures. As the fraction of β-Ti increase, the compositions of both phases change from 
   <inline-formula id="d33e1599">
    <inline-graphic id="d33e1600" xlink:href="srep19235-m57.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> to 
   <inline-formula id="d33e1602">
    <inline-graphic id="d33e1603" xlink:href="srep19235-m58.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>. When the quasi-equilibrium is established between the (undercooled) liquid and β-Ti, the compositions of both phases change along the liquidus and the solution limit of β-Ti (green lines) from 
   <inline-formula id="d33e1606">
    <inline-graphic id="d33e1607" xlink:href="srep19235-m59.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> to 
   <inline-formula id="d33e1609">
    <inline-graphic id="d33e1610" xlink:href="srep19235-m60.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>. (
   <bold>b</bold>) Schematic continuous cooling transformation curves (CCT) for BT48. The β-Ti begin curve (
   <italic>T</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>n</italic>
   </sub>–line), the two-phase quasi-equilibrium curve (
   <italic>T</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>e</italic>
   </sub>–line), and the crystallization TTT curve of BT0 are drawn between their 
   <italic>T</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>l</italic>
   </sub> and 
   <italic>T</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>g</italic>
   </sub>, respectively. (
   <inline-formula id="d33e1640">
    <inline-graphic id="d33e1641" xlink:href="srep19235-m70.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>) are DSC measured times before crystallization of BT0 plus (2000 K-990 K)/(1 K s
   <sup>−1</sup>). The cooling curves starting from 2000 K are indicated by the different sample diameters (calculated from equation 
   <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq21">(2)</xref>). Phases in regions with different colours are: I, liquid; II, liquid + β-Ti (non-equilibrium compositions, changeable microstructure); III, liquid + β-Ti (equilibrium compositions, changeable microstructure); IV, supercooled liquid + β-Ti (non-equilibrium compositions, unchangeable microstructure); V, supercooled liquid + β-Ti (quasi-equilibrium compositions, unchangeable microstructure); VI, non-equilibrium BMGCs; VII, quasi-equilibrium BMGCs; VIII, crystallized matrix + β-Ti. If cooling curves intersect 
   <italic>T</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>e</italic>
   </sub>–line (not crystallization curve of BT0), quasi-equilibrium BMGCs will be achieved, otherwise, non-equilibrium BMGCs will be obtained. The sketches of thermodynamic views are shown in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="srep19235-f3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
