<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">Using TargetFinder software, we identified 3268 potential target genes from 213 miRNAs. Among these target genes, the largest number were encoded TFs. Notably, among these miRNAs with target gene encoded TFs, some miRNAs such as miR156, miR160, miR396, and miR858 targeted the SBP, ARF, GRF, and MYB TFs, respectively. Interestingly, these miRNAs have been experimentally verified to target these corresponding TFs in other plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. This suggested that these miRNA targets were highly conserved in different plants and further confirmed the high reliability of target identification in our study. Based on a homologous search of the predicted target genes, 61 miRNAs have target genes were homologous genes of 47 known seed or organ size genes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Notably, among these miRNAs, most were first identified targeting the known seed or organ size genes, except for miR156 and miR396 targeting the known seed size SPL and GRF TFs, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. These showed that these miRNAs might play an important regulatory role in Tartary buckwheat seed size and most of these known seed or organ size regulatory genes might exist a post-transcription regulatory mechanism in regulating seed size. In plants, miRNAs have been reported to regulate flavonoid biosynthesis through target regulating the structural or regulatory genes of flavonoid biosynthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. In our study, 3 miRNAs (fta_novel_miR26, fta_novel_miR74, and fta-miR394a-5p) were identified to target the flavonoid biosynthesis structural genes 
 <italic>PAL</italic>, 
 <italic>4CL</italic>, and 
 <italic>FLS</italic>, respectively. Furthermore, 5 miRNAs (fta_novel_miR1, fta_novel_miR58, fta-miR858a-5p, fta-miR858a-5p, and fta-miR858b-3p) were found to target the orthologs of known flavonoid biosynthesis regulatory genes in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. These implied that these miRNAs could regulate flavonoid biosynthesis in Tartary buckwheat by regulating the expression of the structural or regulatory genes of flavonoid biosynthesis.
</p>
